<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Denmark</title>
         <author>Ernst Christainsen</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>4 January 1958</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.VIII, No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
   <body>
    <p>The Danish Social Democratic movement was founded in 1871. The Party was, from the time of its foundation, a member of the First International, until a judgment of the Supreme Court held the First International to be illegal in Denmark; but the first, quite stormy, period of the Party’s development in Denmark was predominantly shaped by French Socialism and the propaganda of Lassalle, and this applied particularly to the founder and first leader of the Party, Louis Pio. Throughout the growth of the Party up to the First World War, the influence of German Social Democracy was strong, even though the Danish Party was only to a very limited degree given to theorising, for the reason, among others, that it had in its leadership almost entirely men of the working class and few with academic education. While Lassalle’s influence was certainly the strongest in the first ten or fifteen years, Marxist theories gradually assumed greater importance. Kautsky’s presentation of Marxism became the theoretical basis of the Danish Party, largely as a result of the work of Gustav Bang, a prominent Danish Socialist scientist who stood very close to Kautsky. But, in actual fact, the Party took account to a considerable extent of what was practicable. In the controversies between Kautsky and Bernstein the Danish Party was in principle on the side of Kautsky, but a certain dualism existed because in its practical policy the Party was more often in agreement with Bernstein.</p><p>The Party’s programme was predominantly based on the Gotha Programme of the German Social Democratic Party. Until 1890 it contained the following statement on the relations with the other parties, following a general statement of Socialist principles:</p><p>"It is the task of Social Democracy to free labour from capitalist exploitation. All parties which do not recognise this task as the aim of the State, form, from the point of view of Social Democracy, a single reactionary mass."</p><p>In 1890 this last point was altered as follows:</p><p>"All parties which do not recognise this task as the air, of the State are in fundamental opposition to Social Democracy."</p><p>In 1894 this point was entirely deleted, and the Party Congress of that year adopted a version of the Party programme which resembled the Erfurt Programme of the Gorman Social Democratic Party.</p><p>The question of treating all other parties as a "single reactionary mass" was for Danish Social Democracy not only a theoretical, but also a highly practical problem. The answer to it was of practical importance in connection with the tactical problem whether the Party could enter into an electoral alliance with liberal bourgeois parties. Hardly any other question has given rise to such sharp and prolonged differences of opinion as this one. From the '80s until the turn of the century there was electoral co-operation between the Liberal Peasant Party (called "Venstre" - the Left) and the Social Democrats with the aim of bringing down the Conservative régime, which was able to remain in power - although it was supported by an ever-diminishing minority of the voters - with the help and assistance of the royal authority. Co-operation with the Peasant Party took the form of an electoral alliance, whereby each party withdrew its candidates in certain constituencies where it was weaker in favour of the other party. This was a struggle for parliamentary democracy. With the so-called "change of system" in 1901, this struggle ended in victory. The King was forced to entrust the Peasant Party, which had a large majority in the Second Chamber of Parliament, with the formation of a government, and the principle of parliamentary democracy has remained - with the exception of a single incident in 1920 - uncontested until this day.</p><p>The Danish Social Democratic movement has stressed from its earliest congresses in the late l870s its determination to use legal methods - not the least important, reason being the recollection of the events of 1872 when some strong comments in what was then the newspaper of the newly formed Party led to the intervention of the authorities and heavy sentences for the Party leaders. The Party aims - according to the formulation which was retained until 1890 - "at securing power in the State, in order to bring, by those legal methods, all the means of production into the common ownership of the people... The legislative method to be used by the people for achieving the great aim of social production is expropriation with compensation of the means of production". Both the will to advance by legal means and the declaration regarding compensation for expropriation constitute a firm line which has not been changed over the years.</p><p>The programme, on the other hand, has been amended in many respects as the Party achieved a higher degree of maturity. There can be no doubt that the expression “common ownership of the people” did not express any completely clear aim. Until 1894 the programme said: "Only by placing in the hands of the people the direct management and control of production which is today run by private capitalists, limited companies, the State and local government, i.e. by the abolition of the present wage system, can the yield of production be justly distributed." The introduction to the Party's short-term programme speaks, in similar unclear wording, of a "transition to common Socialist enterprise in agriculture, industry and transport". The following demand, which was somewhat more of a matter of principle, was included among the points described as being topical: "The State is to take over all the means of transport ay well as the industries which cater for the essential needs of the people."</p><p>At the Party congress in 1894 the whole paragraph quoted above, calling for the handing over of the direct management and control of production to the people was deleted. The immediate demand for the taking over of the means of transport arm: essential industries by the State was formulated as follows: "The State is to take over all the means of transport. Production will gradually be organised under the direct management and control of the State." On the other hand, the phrases about "common Socialist enterprise" were retained without amendment.</p><p>These years were for Social Democracy in Denmark the first period of a significant break-through. Its representation in Parliament, which had started with two members in 1884, increased to 14 by the turn of the century. In the capital, Copenhagen, the first representatives entered local government in 1893, and the Party obtained the majority at the turn of the century - albeit only with the co-operation of the representatives of Radical—Liberal groups. In 1903 the first Social Democratic burgomaster (the financial burgomaster) was elected in the capital. The Party also made good progress in other local authorities, although the franchise partly depended upon privilege. The trade unions made good progress; national unions were formed for the various trades and in 1898 the trades union congress was founded. The Party press developed rapidly. The industrialisation of the country advanced, even though this advance was not very rapid. Gradually the distribution of the population outside the capital was being affected, and in 1901 the "change of system" took place, as mentioned above, after which recognition was given to parliamentary democracy.</p><p>***</p><p>The period around the turn of the century produced a new situation in many respects for the working-class movement in Denmark.</p><p>Industrialisation brought about an increase in the numerical strength of the working class, which was particularly noticeable in the population figures for the capital and the smaller towns. The trade unions which, as already stated, had formed national federations and a Trades Union Congress, grew continuously in numbers and strength. But the employers organised themselves at the same time. Guerilla tactics, which had previously been employed by the trade unions, faded into the background and were replaced by mere extensive trade union campaigns in favour of closer regulation of the relations between workers and employers.</p><p>Politically the position of the Social Democratic movement was mainly altered by the fact that the "change of system" in 1901, which brought about the constitutional victory of the parliamentary system, gave governmental power to the Peasant Party, the former great Opposition party.</p><p>The latter party, in which the wealthier section of the peasants played the leading part, pursued a policy which soon brought it into conflict with Social Democracy, and which also, in the course of a few years, caused a split in the Peasant Party which shed a radical Liberal Party. Within the Social Democratic movement there existed in the ensuing years very varied views on the question whether one should enter into an alliance with this new radical Liberal Party. The majority of the Party leadership supported an alliance and pointed out that since the international Congress in Paris in 1900 electoral alliances were permitted, provided the party did not give up any part of its programme. They maintained : "Our watchword must be: no alliance which involves departure from our programme, but we cay help other democratic parties at the elections and may accept help from them." Politically the alliance was argued on the grounds that it would help to counter the influence exercised by the Upper Chamber of Parliament, which was elected on a very reactionary franchise, and also to attain a genuinely equal and universal suffrage in central and local government. The opposition to the electoral alliance was - in the case of a small group - entirely a matter of principle and directed against every form of closer co-operation with non-Socialist parties. For others it was a matter of tactics; they were reluctant to help to bring a new bourgeois party into existence, since it was thought that without such a party the Social Democrats would be more quickly in a position to win over certain groups of electors, in particular among the small peasants. Finally, the opposition was in some places purely local, being connected with particular candidatures and constituencies.</p><p>At every Party congress from 1906 to 1920, when a new voting system with proportional representation made electoral alliances superfluous, the question of electoral alliances played an important part. At one congress - in 1908 - when a great economic crisis accompanied by much unemployment was having a devastating effect on the country, the alliance was accepted by a more 143 votes against 142. But at the other congresses the majority was a safe one and, at times, very large.</p><p>Although the Social Democratic Party was new in alliance with the Radicals, there was nevertheless a significant difference in comparison with the situation before the turn of the century, the alliance had then been one between a largo party and a much smaller Social Democratic Party, but with regard to the new Radical Liberal Party, the situation was reversed. Although the latter party in one parliament attained a number of seats equal to the number of Social Democratic scats, the number of Social Democratic votes was growing rapidly while the number of votes for the Radicals remained unchanged or even declined. In fact, the Social Democratic Workers’ Party contested with the Peasant Party for the national political leadership. It made very little difference to this historical development that the Radical Party hold power in the years before and during the First World War. Its majority was dependent on the Social Democrats and there was close co-operation between the two parties, which had not been the case before the turn of the century between the Peasant Party and the Social Democratic Party. Co-operation was also very close in local government. This co-operation with the Radical government was an important precondition for securing a far-reaching democratisation of the constitution and other reforms. On the other hand, this co-operation resulted in an unavoidable blunting of the policy of the Social Democratic Party. The opponents of co-operation also attacked it on the ground that it prevented the Party from carrying out a policy more closely related to its principles.</p><p>In the course of the debates about alliances and cooperation with bourgeois democratic parties, the problem of "ministerial Socialism" - i.e. participation in a non-Social Democratic government - obviously reared its head, even though it had no practical significance. The question of participating in a bourgeois government was also discussed in connection with debates within the International. The Party congress of 1908 resolved unanimously that "the Social Democratic Party must reject any suggestion of participation in the formation of a government as long as the Party has not got an absolute majority, in the Folketing (the Second Chamber)." In spite of the unanimity of this resolution, and although it was not amended in subsequent years, it is doubtful whether it reflected the view of the Party; certainly this was hardly the case among the leadership. When, in 1916, a situation arose in which it appeared advisable for reasons of foreign policy to strengthen the Radical government with one representative from each of the other political parties, this was agreed to with a large majority at an extraordinary congress. During the debate on this first participation in the government by Social Democrats it was said that this was an exceptional situation which did not alter the Party's attitude in principle. The position was, in fact, quite different. Many people inside the Party considered it a victory for the Party to have a representative in the government, and this point of view was emphasised when the representatives of the other parties left the government somewhat later, during the war, and only the Social Democratic representative remained in office. His position was changed so that he became, in effect, the Minister for Social Affairs. But even during that time the view was widespread that participation in a bourgeois coalition government was not desirable.</p><p>In the period between the turn of the century and the First World War there was a noticeable rise in the influence of Social Democracy. At general elections the Party won a total of about 25 of the votes and seats. In a number of towns Social Democratic majorities were obtained, mainly owing to the democratisation of the local government franchise carried out in 1918. In the capital, Copenhagen, a Social Democratic majority was attained in 1917. Social Democracy, under the leadership of Borgbjerg and Stauning, was a driving force in favour of a democratisation of the Constitution, which led to an amendment of the Constitution in 1915 abolishing the voting privileges of the propertied classes and giving the vote to women and to younger people.</p><p>Simultaneously with the growth and increased influence of the Party, it was considered necessary to replace some of the vague points in the programme by more exact formulations. An expression of the prevailing tendency was to be seen in the fact that the Party congress of 1906 altered the sentence "transition to Social Democratic common enterprise" into "transition to a Socialist organisation of society". After discussion lasting for several years in committees charged with clearing up this question, a revision of the Party programme was carried out at a Party congress in 1913 ; as regards general principles it was very much influenced by the Marxist views of Gustav Bang, but for the rest it was drafted with an eye on the conditions and trends in Denmark. The programme was actually in tune with the policy of the Social Democrats, which was very opportunistic, with a view to assisting the achievement of a democratisation of the Constitution.</p><p>In the theoretical introduction to the programme attention was drawn to the increase in capitalist exploitation and the growing mass of property-less wage-earners and the unplanned nature of capitalism. The main aim of Social Democracy was stated to be the introduction of common Socialist ownership and Socialist production. As regards current political questions, land reform and the position of the army were of particular importance. On the subject of land reform, which was so important in an agricultural country like Denmark, the programme had previously stressed that collective farms should be set up as widely as possible. But the development of agriculture and its transition to intensive cultivation had made this formulation out of date. At the Congress in 1913 the new line was laid down that the division of estates was to be the aim and that collective farms would only be set up where this could be done with advantage.</p><p>* * *</p><p>At the Party congress of 1913 - as at previous and later congresses - the military question came very much to the fore. This is connected with the fact that the military question in Denmark has probably been a matter of more bitter controversy than in any other country. The reason is partly to be found in the history of the country and partly - and particularly - in its small size and geographical structure and situation. The attitude of the Social Democratic movement to military and defence questions was naturally influenced by the same factors, but on the important occasions it was Socialist and democratic principles which were decisive in determining the Party's attitude. In order to facilitate an understanding of the Party's attitude to these questions a general review is given below of its defence policy up to 1957.</p><p>Until 1906 the basic principle of the Social Democratic Party was that the standing army should be abolished and replaced by a general militia. On foreign policy the view of the Party was comprehended in the sentence of its programme which ran "international disputes must be settled by arbitration". During the first ten years of the century the state of the Danish defence forces was intensively debated. The Social Democrats took the view that the Danish State should disarm. The main reason for this very far-reaching proposal, which was put forward in 1909, was that Denmark, on account of its smallness and very difficult position from a technical military point of view - because, among other reasons, the country consists of many islands of different sizes - was actually not in a position to defend itself against the Great Powers of that time. As far as a war with other States of similar size was concerned, everyone was agreed that such a war was out of the question. In view of Denmark’s indefensibility the Social Democrats proposed that the Danish State should declare itself completely and permanently neutral and should have no military force, but only a kind of police force as a frontier guard. Accordingly, the Party programme was amended to incorporate the demand for disarmament and in place of a militia the Party demanded physical training for young people, their training in the use of arms and other physical exercises.</p><p>Proposals for disarmament certainly had no chance of obtaining the support of a majority in Parliament, but could count on a not inconsiderable amount of sympathy outside the Social Democratic movement. And inside the Party this was a point of view which aroused much enthusiasm. It appeared to be the logical conclusion of the position of the country in international affairs and a strong expression of the will to peace of the whole international Socialist movement. This point of view was not based on arguments involving the rejection of national defence on principle. That attitude was only defended by quite a small minority. It happened that certain extremist speakers would use the well-known phrase “the workers have no fatherland”, but officially and in the Party generally the argument was based on the special position of the country and general love of peace. Extreme pacifist sentiments against any participation in war played their part. This was expressed at the Party congress in 1913, which deleted the expression “use of arms” from the section of the programme dealing with the physical training of youth, in defiance of a large majority of the Party leadership. This alteration was also due to tactical difficulties which had arisen in the debate on the motion on disarmament, in which opponents had asked what young people were going to do with exercises in the use of arms in a disarmed State. It was further asked whether these were intended for use in a civil war. The Social Democratic answer was that they did not desire a civil war, but wanted to work by legal methods. Only if illegal methods were employed by their opponents would they use force. As an indication of the different views on this matter it may be mentioned that well-known leaders of the Party put forward the point of view on this question, in the debate on the deletion of the term “use of arms”, that it should be kept, in order that one might be able to use weapons if the necessity arose.</p><p>During the First World War pacifist sentiment grew among the Danish people in general and among Social Democrats in particular. As the Party now formed one half of the majority supporting the Radical Liberal Government, it now voted for both ordinary, and quite high extraordinary, military credits, although until 1913 it had refused to vote for the budget on the grounds that it contained military credits. But the reason for the new attitude was expressly stated to be the existing position and consideration of the general war situation.</p><p>After the war the agitation in favour of disarmament increased, and when in 1924 the Social Democrats formed a government for the first time, this Government proposed such an extensive reduction in armaments that it would, in fact, have amounted to complete disarmament. These proposals were accepted by the Folketing with the support of the Radical Liberals, but were defeated in the Landsting (Upper House),</p><p>When the Social Democrats took over the government for the second time, in 1929, another attempt was made to carry through the disarmament proposals, but without success. Therefore in 1932 a Defence Bill was passed, which certainly represented a reduction in armaments, but which in essentials bore the stamp of compromise with the Peasant Party.</p><p>With the victory of National Socialism in Germany a new situation arose. This found expression for the first time in 1934, when the Party, in a great manifesto dealing with the attitude of the Party towards disarmament, stated that there was "at the moment no sufficient basis for unilateral disarmament", but that efforts for peace and disarmament would be continuously supported in the international organisations (the League of Nations). In the following year this point of view was accepted by a Party congress and further expanded by a declaration that effective control of the frontiers and territorial waters was necessary and that army and navy regulations should be revised accordingly. In consequence, a Military Ordinance was issued two years later, which involved an increase in the armed forces.</p><p>In the course of these years the Danish Social Democratic movement swung over from an unequivocal and precise support of disarmament to an attitude which favoured defence. The reason was - as has already been stated - to be found in the victory of National Socialism in Germany. This new attitude was based on social and democratic, rather than national, arguments. Danish Social Democrats had seen how the German working-class movement had been crushed and that all other sections of the population in Germany had been deprived of their civil rights. If Hitler was thinking of producing similar situations in other countries the Danish workers would defend themselves. It is not possible to decide how deeply rooted was the new attitude on the arms question among Party members and in the working-class movement and its supporters. A large section of the Party and of the trade unions understood that a change had taken place in the attitude of the Party on this question and endorsed this change. But an important part of the working-class movement had either not understood the new policy at all clearly or had only done so to a very small extent. Nevertheless, the Party congress of 1939 was able to achieve virtual unanimity on this question, for a resolution was adopted with only two dissentient votes which stated that "defence measures of a different type from those previously required are new necessary" and that "the national interest requires that sufficient troops shall always be available". The Leader of the Party, Prime Minister Stauning, had not disguised in his speech the fact that a new policy was being discussed when he said that it would be "a continuation of the re-orientation which has begun, and which unfortunately appears to be necessary". The assessment of the country's basic position and its military potential remained unchanged, however, for Stauning stressed strongly that Denmark was not aiming at becoming a military power which had plans to attack other countries. He further said s "If violations of our neutrality should take place they must be resisted as long as they are of a type which it is possible to resist”.</p><p>This last phrase showed unequivocally that Denmark would be prepared to prevent any possible attempts at coups d'état on the part of National Socialist gangs which were not officially backed by the Third Reich, but that little Denmark with its unfavourable geographical position would be able to engage in battle against a real attack by a great power – in this case Nazi Germany.</p><p>In 9 April, 1940, the situation arose in which Denmark was unable to put up a fight<hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">. </hi>Nazi Germany attacked Denmark and occupied the country. During the five years of occupation which in followed the population was confirmed in its general sentiment that in future everything possible would have to be done to prevent a repetition of the occupation. Denmark's adherence to the Atlantic Pact must be seen from that point of view.</p><p>Immediately after the war the view was held in Denmark, as indeed in most other countries, that it would be possible to carry through an international reduction of armaments through the offices of the United Nations, and that Denmark's arms, like those of other countries, would be fixed on a certain scale. When this did not happen and the international situation came to a head – as in the 'thirties - even though the danger of aggression came from a different quarter, Denmark, and therefore also the Social Democratic movement in Denmark, had to resume the debate on the armaments question.</p><p>For the Social Democrats, as for the majority of the Danish people, the idea of national defence in isolation presented a hopeless prospect. It was new proposed from various quarters that a Northern Defence Union should be formed, embracing Denmark, Norway and Sweden. These three countries would establish a common defence system and declare themselves neutral towards all other States. The Social Democrats under their Leader, Prime Minister Hedtoft, were the decisive factor in the negotiations on this question which were, however, broken off without success in 1949. The Social Democrats were then of the view that Denmark could not be left in isolation and, as a consequence, she joined the Atlantic Pact.</p><p>This attitude was, in fact, the same as that which the Party had taken up since 1934, and which had been accepted by congresses of the Party and by other bodies between the two world wars. This point of view was that defence was necessary to maintain national independence and freedom, which in turn were necessary conditions for the maintenance of the achievements of the working-class movement. One difference did, however, emerge. In the period between the wars Denmark insisted on its unconditional neutrality and defence was planned as a defence of this neutrality, with the recognition that such defence could not be maintained in the event of an attack by a great power. Both in the planned but still-born Northern Defence Pact and in the Atlantic Pact neutrality was abandoned and the defence of national existence was made possible by an alliance - in the former case by alliance with the related Northern States, and in the latter case with the democratically ruled great powers.</p><p>In both cases high military expenditure was unavoidable. Denmark's adherence to the Atlantic Pact was certainly regarded in many quarters an something new that one was forced to accept. Anti-militarist and pacifist sentiments had always been stronger among Social Democrats in Denmark than in most other countries, and it is therefore a tribute to the strength of the new policy and to the effect of experience of the occupation, that the decisions in connection with the Atlantic Pact were taken practically without opposition in the Party. Nevertheless, this policy is felt by significant sections of the Party - particularly among the older members - to be an embarrassment. The recognition of the necessity of the Atlantic policy is, however, so strong that these view's primarily secure positive expression in the form that Denmark must use its influence in every sphere in favour of a reduction of international tension. No responsible sections of the Party dare to suggest an isolationist policy.</p><p>The Social Democratic point of view on defence is new, therefore, that the foreign and defence policy of the country is based on adherence to the United Nations and NATO. In those periods when the Party led the Government it carried out this policy with the support of the Peasant Party and of the Conservative Party, while the Radical Party, which in respect of home policy at always stands close to the Social Democrats, is against the association with NATO. Nevertheless, there is complete unanimity about the policy towards the United Nations, and the Social Democratic proposal in 1956, that the United Nations force in the Near East should be supplemented by Danish troops, was adopted with the support of the votes of all parties,</p><p>* * *</p><p>Throughout the First World War the policy of the Social Democrats was marked by the fact that the Party, although it was only represented by one member of the Government after 1916 - nevertheless, by reason of its support, had an important influence on the maintenance in office of the Government formed by the Radicals and the Peasant Party. In this political situation the Social Democrats provided important support for the implementation of constitutional reform already referred to. Participation in the coalition government had, however, the effect that the Party’s policy was influenced by consideration of the maintenance of the coalition. In the splits which took place in the international working-class movement as a result of the war, the Party took up the same position as the majority of the German Social Democrats and strongly opposed the opposition movements in the various countries and the so-called Zimmerwald movement.</p><p>Social Democratic policy during the First World War gave rise to an opposition movement - even though a limited one - particularly among certain sections of the Social Democratic youth movement. This opposition became stronger and more bitter after the Russian Revolution and particularly after the October Revolution of 1917. Developments in Russia had the effect, on the other hand, that the Danish Social Democrats stuck firmly to their democratic principles. Opposition groups then formed in 1919 a Left-Socialist (later Communist) Party, which shortly afterwards was amalgamated with the majority section of a syndicalist Trade Union Opposition, which had been able to make certain gains during the war. The Communist Party remained quite small, however, and did not succeed in achieving representation in Parliament at any election in the inter-war period, after which it was further weakened by internal divisions.</p><p>The wave of revolutions in the countries of Central Europe in 1918 was used by the Social Democratic Party find the trade unions in Denmark to achieve certain reforms, particularly the eight-hour day. A political crisis in 1920 in connection with the delineation of the new frontier between Denmark and Germany led to the formation of a new government, following which the Social Democrats became the leading Opposition party in the immediate post-war years. The ways and means by which the new government came to power, including the intervention of the King, gave rise to sharp counter-measures on the part of the working-class movement, including the proclamation of a general strike in defence of democracy and parliamentary government. In the resulting negotiations about the Constitution, the Social Democrats proposed an extensive democratisation of the Constitution, including the introduction of a republic. During the ensuing years the Social Democrats conducted a policy of very active opposition. The attitude of the Party to international questions was expressed in keen co-operation in the re-establishment of the Labour and Socialist International.</p><p>In 1924 the Social Democrats won a decisive electoral victory, which made them the largest party in the country. The question of participation of the Party in the government became one of urgency. Since the general view in the Party was that one should not take part in a coalition government, the Party formed a purely Social Democratic government, which did not have a majority in Parliament - although the Social Democrats were the largest party in the country - and which therefore had to count on the support of the Radical Left Party for its policy, to the extent that that party was ready to give it. This first period in office in the years 1924/26 provided, on the one hand, a useful demonstration of the plans of Social Democracy, but on the other provided the Party with a useful lesson on the difficulties which are involved in maintaining a minority government in such circumstances.</p><p>The experiences of this period of minority government in the years 1924/26 had a decisive effect on the decision which the Party took when, after an electoral victory in 1929, it was once again in a position to take over the government, and on that occasion it formed a coalition with the Radical Left Party. But within this coalition, which ensured a majority in Parliament, the Social Democrats, with their 61 seats - while the Radicals only had 16 - was the leading party, a fact which also found expression in the composition of the government, which was led by Th. Stauning. On the other hand it was obvious that this Government under Social Democratic leadership was extremely dependent on the support of its smaller coalition partner in carrying through its reforms.</p><p>In spite of the difficulties, which were a consequence of the fundamental differences between the two Government parties, and in spite of the extremely great difficulties arising out of the world economic crisis which started in 1929 and was particularly noticeable in Denmark with its extensive agriculture, the Stauning Government succeeded in carrying out a great deal of reform legislation. The great difficulties arising out of the world economic crisis were overcome and in this connection it was possible to carry out reforms, of which an extensive social reform should be particularly mentioned. The decade 1929/39 can be described as the hey-day of Danish Social Democracy so far. Extensive reforms ware carried out and the number of votes cast for the Party grew from election to election. In 1935 the Party obtained 46.1% of all votes cast; this is the highest percentage ever. In 1936 the Party succeeded in obtaining a majority in the Upper House, together with the Radicals, which enabled them to carry out further and yet more extensive reforms. During these ten years the Social Democratic Party developed into a broadly based people's party, in respect of the votes it obtained as well as its policy. One gets a good idea of the development of the Party’s general political attitude by reading the introduction to the manifesto, set out below, of the 1934 Party executive, which may well be described as one of the most significant publications of these years so far as the Party is concerned:</p><p>"In this manifesto the Social Democratic Party, basing itself on the Social Democratic programme which aims at gathering in the Party all sections of the working and exploited population so that they can attain power and abolish capitalist private ownership of the means of production, calls upon all those sections of the population who are suffering on account of the slump caused by capitalism - the workers in industry and agriculture, the small farmers, the crofters, fishermen, clerks and employees in commerce and trade; all the workers by hand and by brain - and urges them to work for a positive policy for the restitution of healthy and orderly economic conditions. There can be no doubt that the form of production which is the objective of Social Democracy will replace capitalism, but we realise that this requires a steady process of development and that no stages must be omitted. The immediate aim of the Social Democratic Party, therefore, is to ensure the planning and control of production and distribution in the process of transforming the economy."</p><p>The quite considerable degree of unemployment during that otherwise fruitful decade presented a serious difficulty which could only to a limited extent be countered by government action. It was partly due to this unemployment that the Communists succeeded in winning a few seats in the Folketing for the first time in 1932. The victory of National Socialism in Germany, which had the aforementioned effects on the defence policy of the Social Democratic Party, called forth some pre-Nazi trends in Denmark, but they were of no political significance, and their representatives obtained only a very few seats in Parliament in the 1939 elections.</p><p>Disputes about wages and conditions of work repeatedly placed the Government in the unfortunate position of having to settle these conflicts - strikes or lock-outs - by special decree. Naturally these measures were discussed within the Labour movement, but all the same they caused no estrangement between the trade unions and the Social Democratic Party. However, the key note of the whole period was set by the significant reform legislation.</p><p>***</p><p>The outbreak of the Second World War brought the period of reform to an end. The Third Reich’s attack on Denmark in April 1940, and the occupation of the country, produced an entirely new situation. The Government was transformed into a coalition of democratic parties under the leadership of Th. Stauning. After Stauning’s death, in the spring of 1942, the Social Democrat Vilh. Buhl took on the leadership of the government, but in response to the demand of the occupying power he had to resign at the end of that year. Hans Hedtoft had been elected chairman of the Party at the Social Democratic Party congress in 1939. In 1941 he had to relinquish this position following requests by the Germans, and so had the Party secretary, H.C. Hansen, but both remained in the Folketing, and furthermore they co-operated with the underground resistance movement during the years of occupation.</p><p>The position of the Social Democratic Party during the five years of occupation was a very difficult one. Naturally the Party and the Labour movement as a whole were the most bitter enemies of the National Socialists, who realised this fully. On the other hand, the Party had to take responsibility, at least in part, for official Danish policy which, until the autumn of 1943, aimed at avoiding open conflict with the occupying power, so that Hitler should have no excuse for breaking the promises which he himself had made, to the effect that the rights of the Danish authorities under Danish leadership would be respected.</p><p>In the Folketing elections in the spring of 1943, which strangely enough Hitler’s representatives allowed to be held, the Social Democratic Party polled more votes than ever before, but only 44.5 % of the total vote cast. The poll was much higher than normally. Within the Social Democratic Party - as indeed within the other democratic parties - there were divergent views about the policy to be adopted towards the occupying power, but it was possible to avoid any splits. There can be no doubt that the years of occupation resulted in a marked development of national sentiment in general and also within the Social Democratic movement. The relationship between the Party and the King, which had suffered badly on account of the events of 1920, became normal and correct between the two world wars. The occupation years led to a considerable increase in the personal popularity of the King among all sections of the population, which resulted in the earlier differences between King and Social Democratic Party being forgotten as a problem of no immediate importance.</p><p>Politically the most important fact was that rather close co-operation developed between the democratic parties, which continued even after the coalition government had come to an end in 1943.</p><p>* * *</p><p>On 5 May, 1945, a coalition government in which not only the democratic parties, but also the Communists and the Resistance Movement were represented, was formed under the former Prime Minister, Vilh. Buhl. In the summer of 1945 a Social Democratic congress unanimously approved the Party's war-time policy and at the same time agreed upon a constructive and progressive economic programme for the post-war period, entitled "The Denmark of the Future".</p><p>In this programme, the economic and social order of the present day was described in the following terns:</p><p>"Since 1939 the world has destroyed the menace of National Socialism, but an economic system is still in existence which is incapable of solving the problems of the pre-war years... Not until we have transformed this system can we claim to be master of the situation. The war and the war economy have shaken this system profoundly. Now it must never be allowed to return. It was unable to deal with pre-war slumps. It will be the source of new slumps, increased unemployment - and perhaps of new Nazi movements and wars. It is irrelevant what name this system bears. We Social Democrats generally refer to it as 'private capitalism'. It may be mere correct to call it monopoly capitalism at the present time, because it is ruled by monopolistic organisations."</p><p>There follow proposals regarding the reform of the economy in various aspects. These remarks are made, inter alia, about industry:</p><p>"In carrying cut the necessary reconstruction the opportunity will arise for society to exercise all kinds of control and influence. Undertakings under direct State control should be the exception. Joint stock companies are more likely to be suitable. These provide the greater measure of flexibility in the State's share in ownership and control. Collaboration with the co-operative movement should be as widespread as possible."</p><p>In the election in the autumn of 1945 the Social Democrats suffered a defeat unparalleled in their history. They only polled 32.8 % of the total vote and lost 18 of their 66 seats in Parliament. The cause of this defeat is to be found partly in the propaganda of the bourgeois parties against the Party's programme "The Denmark of the Future", and partly in the fact that the Party, having been pre-eminent in the coalition government, was held responsible for some of the events of that period. In spite of having defended the Hitler-Stalin Pact until Russia was attacked, the Communists’ popularity had increased during the resistance movement and it was thought that they were democratically inclined. Furthermore, a certain amount of confusion arose within the working class on account of negotiations between Social Democrats and Communists about combining in a Unity Party - in Denmark as in other countries - even though these fell through because the Communists did not accept the principles of democracy without reservation. The Communists obtained 12 % of the total vote in 1945 and 18 seats in Parliament, which corresponded to the number of seats lest by the Social Democrats.</p><p>Until 1947 the Social Democratic Party was in opposition, but in that year it was remarkably successful in the elections and halved the Communists’ strength. The Social Democratic Party formed a government under Hans Hedtoft as Prime Minister, but it was a minority government without the permanent cooperation of any other party. In the course of the following three years much was dene to restore the Danish economy after the ravages of the war. In the next elections, in 1950, the Party maintained its position, but after a few weeks the Government was overthrown by a coalition of the bourgeois parties. In the elections in the spring and autumn of 1953, after the abolition of the Upper House by a change in the Constitution, the Social Democratic Party again registered successes and polled 41.3 % of the total vote, while the Communists, whose strength had again been halved in 1950, were unable to recover any of their lost support.</p><p>In the autumn of 1953 Hans Hedtoft formed his second cabinet, this time as a purely Social Democratic government based on a minority in the Folketing. Hans Hedtoft suddenly died in January 1955. He was succeeded, both as Prime Minister and as Party Chairman, by H.C. Hansen who had been Foreign Minister since 1953.</p><p>Under the prevailing political conditions of recent years, all policies of reform were - and still are - very difficult. One of the factors in the situation was the currency problem, which greatly impaired Denmark’s financial relations with other countries. Denmark is a country without raw materials. Its most important economic activity is agriculture and a considerable part of its foreign trade is based on agricultural exports, which have had to contend with difficulties during certain periods with regard to both prices and markets. Partly for that reason and partly on account of the foreign currency situation caused by international price fluctuations, special laws for the restriction of consumption had to be passed, but such legislation is in itself unpopular.</p><p>In spite of all this the present government * [* This article was written before the General Election of May 1957 (for results of which see S.I.I., Vol.VII, No.22).] has succeeded in carrying out a certain measure of reform. In the first place the introduction of a national pensions scheme should be mentioned; all citizens of Denmark over 67 are new entitled to a pension. Until new the system in force was the payment of a certain annual sum to elderly people with low incomes. This has now been extended and a pensions system has been introduced which covers all citizens. In principle, this is a great advance, even though the actual payment to individual pensioners is still quite modest; but further improvements in the national pensions scheme in the years to come are to be expected.</p><p>In the spring of 1956 the political situation and the attitude of the trade unions became rather grave, since the employers’ resistance to wage claims created a serious wage dispute. After a short strike the State arbitrator suggested a compromise, but this was turned down. Nevertheless, the Government considered it necessary, for political and economic reasons, to give legal effect to this compromise. The leading trade unionists did not agree to this, and the Government’s decision led to resistance and demonstrations in some unions and places of work. The difference of opinion between the unions and the Government, which was backed by the Party leadership, did not, however, result in a cessation of the collaboration between the unions and the Party, nor has it produced tensions which hinder their close co-operation; they are, for example, represented in each other's leading bodies. The situation produced a lively, and in some ways useful, discussion within the Party and the unions. During the course of this debate the Party stated quite unequivocally that, generally speaking, an enforced settlement of trade disputes is not considered satisfactory. It is true that at the Social Democratic Party congress in January 1957 the Party's attitude during this industrial dispute came under fire, but its activities were unanimously approved. And this approval corresponds to the general view of the whole Labour movement.</p><p>The congress of the Social Democratic Party held in January 1957 adopted a programme containing guiding lines for the immediate future. It is stated inter alia:</p><p>"The aims which have guided the policy of Social Democracy have been given a new and enhanced topicality by the technical and economic developments of the past ten years.</p><p>"Our aims correspond to the ideals of democratic Socialism, which are to guarantee freedom for all men and to abolish want, injustice and insecurity. The living conditions of the people have been gradually improved in a long and tenacious battle... Our well-founded political democracy must be underpinned by further economic and cultural democratisation... The aim of Social Democracy is a society where there is work for all, combined with the greatest possible output and a just distribution. Ways and means must depend on changing conditions and possibilities. Public and private initiative must collaborate. Co-operative forms of enterprise constitute a natural element in a democratic economy... Social Democracy supports a positive production policy. New social and cultural advances which assist the development of the modem welfare state must be based on a continual increase in the supply of goods at the disposal of the community. Cultural progress, the importance of which will doubtless increase, must benefit all members of the community and strengthen our free democracy. The Social Democratic Party is open to all irrespective of whether they derive their Social Democratic outlook from economic, social, ethical or religious principles."</p><p>This programme, which indicates the outlines of the work of the next few years, is a sober programme in the true sense of the word, bearing the stamp of the events and developments of the post-war period. It is not designed for the distant future and is not in the real sense a party programme. Congress therefore decided to set up a special committee charged with working out a new programme to lay down the future directives and principles, as was the ease with the Party programme of 1913. The working programme adopted by the congress makes possible a satisfactory continuation of the practical and sober work of reform which the Social Democratic Party in Denmark has been carrying cut for generations, in changing circumstances and with changing facilities, in order to achieve practical results, but always with a view to a steady improvement of conditions in society.</p>
   </body>
  </text>
</TEI>