<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The ideological development of Democratic Socialism in Norway</title>
         <author>Torolf Elster</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>5 November 1955</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol. V, No.45</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

<text>
  <body><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">I. Historical background</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Characteristics of the Norwegian Labour Movement</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the course of its history the Norwegian Labour movement has shown many traits which distinguish it from the Labour movements of the other West European countries. These differences, which have been gradually disappearing over the last twenty years, concern political and organisational activity rather than theory. In general they reflected special aspects of the historical framework within which the Norwegian movement developed; a review of them and of their effect on the movement will throw some light on the background to Socialist thought in Norway during the last ten or twenty years.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Norwegian industry and the Norwegian industrial working class are of comparatively recent growth. It was not until the turn of the century that industrialisation begun in earnest: then, however, it proceeded at an unusually fast tempo. The rapidity of the change created a strong radical movement among the new industrial workers who had been suddenly uprooted from farming and fishing communities.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Serfdom and feudalism never existed in Norway. The Norwegian farming community has always consisted of independent small farmers who are, by tradition individualistic and self-reliant. Their character has left its mark on the Norwegian Labour movement. Independence and self-reliance are, in fact, national characteristics and are attributable perhaps to the extremely low density of the population.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Because industry is young and because political consciousness is highly developed in the rural areas, there has been much less political difference between town and country than in most other lands. This has led to the unusual phenomenon that the Norwegian Labour movement is as firmly rooted in the countryside as in the industrial centres.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Until 1814 Norway was a part of the Kingdom of Denmark, with provincial status. It was then joined in a union under the Swedish crown which lasted until 1905. The country’s traditions of independent politics are therefore comparatively recent. During the 1880’s, when the parliamentary system emerged, when industry began to expand, when a strong independent bourgeoisie began to establish itself, and when the first beginnings of the Labour movement appeared, political life in Norway was dominated by the struggle for independence from Sweden. The opening of the long fight for economic and social emancipation thus coincided with the national struggle for independence and was affected by it. Since the first Labour organisations came into existence during a period of conflict in which the whole nation was involved, they were more radical, more conscious of their goals, and more directly political in outlook.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">However the theoretical development of political questions was handicapped by the lack of established political tradition, find by concentration on the struggle for national independence. In Norway, the tradition of philosophical inquiry is on the whole weak and did not provide fertile ground for Socialist one theory. The Labour movement, moreover had no special desire to delve into questions of theory.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Labour movement was strongly influenced by the active radical cultural life which flourished in Norway in the second half of the last century - particularly in the field of literature - and which related the country's national to the strong revolutionary developments on the continent.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian labour movement developed out of the bourgeois-liberal movement, which has exerted an unusually significant influence on Norwegian political life. Its strong tradition of struggle in the cause of social radicalism had an important impact on the Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The moneyed class in Norway has never been strong politically. Its political traditions have been wavering and, most important of all, it has never developed any conservative ideology worthy of the name. There was, therefore, no stimulus from the bourgeoisie to make the Labour movement engage in theoretical inquiries into social problems.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In general, until recently Norway was unaffected by world political upheavals. It was protected by its remoteness and insulated from then by its concentration on national problems. Its shipping and commerce, however, brought the country into constant contact with the whole world. This gave rise to widespread interest in international affairs ; it was not, however, strong enough to have a significant influence on the ideological development of the Norwegian labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Until the middle of the 1930’s the Norwegian bourgeoisie was westward-locking for that was where her most important economic interests lay ; its Labour movement looked to the politically more backward continental countries.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Norway is one of the smallest countries in the world and is the farthest north; it is the most thinly populated in Europe and has a more severe climate than any other. It is, perhaps, of all countries the most dependent on economic relations with the outside world. These are the hard realities which have to be taken into account by a constructive social movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">On the other hand, the country is small, conditions relatively easy to survey, the conflict of social classes limited, economic power still comparatively easy to acquire ; Norway's problems are therefore in many ways simpler than those of the typical industrial country or of the underdeveloped agricultural lands.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">For long there was a wide gap between revolutionary ideals and the practical solution of problems. This hindered the development of systematic Socialist thinking in the Norwegian Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">From Social Democracy to Communism, and back to Social Democracy</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian Federation of Trade Unions was established in 1899, twelve years after the creation of the Norwegian Labour Party. Relations between the industrial and the political movement were close from the start, and it was early established that political aims should take precedence over industrial ones. The close co-operation between party and trade unions has contributed to the characteristic organisational pattern of the Norwegian Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian movement received its ideological inspiration from Denmark which received it, in turn, from Germany. The basic programme was based on the German Gotha Programme, which continued to leave its mark on party programmes until 1939.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">However, until the First World War Socialism was rarely discussed. Political work was concentrated on more immediate objectives: universal franchise and a shorter working day.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">An important political task wa3 to exert pressure on the Liberal Party to enlarge its programme of social reforms.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Theoretical study played a subordinate role in the Party and the basic questions turned largely upon nationalism and defence. The fight in Germany between Revisionists and Marxists and in France on the question of “Ministerial Socialism" at first made little impression in Norway.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Agrarian policy was a fundamental issue. After the turn of the century the Norwegian Party freed itself from the orthodox Marxist position brought over from Germany and adopted its own agricultural programme which recognised the farmers’ right to private ownership of the land.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">About 1910 the struggle between reformists and revolutionaries reached Norway, too, and was more bitter and more violent than in many other countries. The strong syndicalist tendency in the revolutionary opposition, which was influenced by developments in Sweden and by the IWW in the United States, was a typical result. The intensity of this struggle was due partly to the radical tradition in Norwegian politics, partly to the unusually fast industrialisation which took place at this time. Later, as in other countries, the revolutionary feeling was strengthened by the failure of Social Democracy in 1914, by the war, by inflation and by the Russian Revolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The revolutionary opposition had its roots partly in intellectual groups in the youth movement, partly and more significantly in the trade union movement where it sought to make it the trade union movement's first task to work for Socialism. The fight against the capitalist system as such, not attempts to gain reforms and small improvements, was advanced an the decisive aim of the Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Immediately after the war the revolutionary wing succeed in winning power in both the Labour Party and the Federation of Trade Unions. The Party joined the Third International and accepted, with certain reservations, the 1920 basic programme of principles and aims. After internal strife, the Right wing left the party and in 1921 established the Norwegian Social Democratic Labour Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian Labour Party was the only one of the old big Social Democratic parties which joined the Third International. It differed in many ways, however, from the other Communist parties. First of all, it was a typical "mass party", based on the collective affiliation of the trade unions. Secondly, the change in political direction did not lead to any fundamental change in the practical activities of either the Party or the trade unions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The new Communist ideology did not penetrate the Party to any appreciable extent; it inclined rather to German Social Democratic ideals as expressed in the revolutionary period of the previous century. The political ideas which were bound up with Lenin's strategy and tactics exercised only a superficial influence.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Although the Norwegian Labour movement was then strongly influenced by intellectuals who called themselves Marxists, there was little chance of theoretical activity in this hectic period of struggle when many believed that world revolution was just around the corner. There were revolutionary demands for workers' councils, but few people concerned themselves with the problems which would arise with the assumption of power.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The question of socialisation was an exception; in this field fairly extensive research work was done. A Parliamentary commission was even established under revolutionary pressure but the drive for socialisation came to nothing. This failure strengthened the view that important results could not be achieved by parliamentary means.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The bitter struggle between reformists and revolutionaries expressed itself in disagreement on the attitude towards parliamentarism. The reformist wing held that respect for the will of the majority was a fundamental part of a Socialist philosophy, while the revolutionaries claimed that the existing democratic system was a tool for bourgeois exploitation and oppression.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The latter point of view, which was held by the majority, influence the practical activities of the Labour Party, but it continued to be an unsettling influence on political thinking in the Norwegian Labour movement for the next twenty years.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In 1923 the Labour Party left the Comintern because it should not submit to the latter's demands for military discipline. But it continued for several years to call itself a revolutionary Communist party, with the dictatorship of the proletariat in its programme.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In practice a party organised as was the Norwegian labour Party could not be revolutionary in the sense which the Russian Communists have given to the word. But among the town and agricultural workers there was a radical fighting spirit opposed to compromise arid cautious reformism. The leadership had strong sentimental ties with its revolutionary past.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The result was a gap between practical politics and revolutionary ideology which made it difficult to build a solid theoretical foundation for constructive Socialist activity. It was contrary to Communist ideology to develop a social plan which could be realised within the capitalist system. The Party's leading intellectual figure, Edvard Bull, who was a critical and sober historian, was, as a Socialist theoretician, hopelessly hampered by emotional attachment to Marxist dogma.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">All in all the 1920's were a period dominated by intellectual manoeuvring with few incursions into new Socialist thinking. After 1923 the Norwegian Labour Party took no part in the Socialist International but - unlike in Austria - no distinct theoretical school developed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A small group of independent intellectuals called “Mot Bag” (“Towards Day”) were exceptions to the general apathy on ideological questions. They carried on intensive theoretical work and made a significant effort to adjust Marxism to current problems and current sociology. The theoretical weakness of the group was that it clung determinedly to a revolutionary objective, which had no basis in the social and economic conditions of Norway and which tied its members to Marxist dogma. However, they later made their mark on the theoretical work of the Norwegian Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In 1927 the Labour Party and the Social Democratic Party amalgamated; at the same time the Communists were reduced to an insignificant party. Everything pointed to the closing of the revolutionary period in the Norwegian Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But the old revolutionary ideas continued to play an important role. Such expressions as “adherence to principles”, “no compromise”, “faith in ideals”, have always played a significant role in Norwegian political and cultural life, often at the expense of clear theoretical analysis and rational thinking.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">When in 1928 the Labour Party was charged with the responsibility of forming a government, it was still opposed to “ministerial Socialism”. However, a deep economic crisis had brought victory to the Party in the general elections of 1927 and the party leadership felt that people would not understand if it declined to accept the responsibility of government. The experiment lasted for twelve days only. The stale revolutionary language used by the Government in its inaugural declaration made it easy for the bourgeois parties to find a pretext for deposing it on a vote of no confidence.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">When the Labour Party adopted a new basic programme in 1930, it cut out the statement which had been introduced upon fusion with the Social Democrats in 1927, that the task of the Party was to win the majority of the nation for Socialism. Instead, it stressed once more that the role of the Labour Party was to be the party of the working class, and that it should not be transformed from a class party into a “people's party”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian Labour Party wag ill-prepared theoretically to face the great economic crisis of the 1930's. Social Democracy and revolutionary thinking had been kept running side by side only by neglecting further work on basic principles or constructive planning.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The economic crisis and mass unemployment forced a change. The Labour Party’s programme of action in 1933 had an obviously reformist, social democratic content. It called for the major stress to be put on parliamentary work and a positive economic policy to be followed, aimed at strengthening Norwegian economic life. In the following years the Party developed extensive plans for dealing with the economic crisis; they aimed at the gradual introduction of a planned economy without violent changes in the structure of society.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This policy change was not easy. Time after time the Party leadership maintained that the new programme did not mean a break with the earlier ideology. The Party was hampered by its lack of experience in constructive thinking, nevertheless, the Labour Party emerged from the 1933 elections as the strongest single party. It formed a government in 1935 and has been in power ever since.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Before the Second World War the Labour Government was dependent on support from the Farmers’ Party on economic questions and from the Liberal Party on social and cultural questions. This lack of independence made it difficult to carry out to the full the Labour Party's plans for combating the economic crisis. Nevertheless, the country made great strides forward, and faith in democracy was strengthened at a tine when Fascism was conquering Central Europe.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Large-scale theorising was still the object of suspicion within the Labour movement. This attitude influenced the debate both on basic Socialist principles and immediate practical policy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It was not until 1938 that the Norwegian Labour Party joined the Socialist International. With this act it adopted the basic platform which was common to all the other European Social Democratic parties. It had become a straightforward reformist party, supported by various groups in society, and seeking increasingly stronger support from the electorate. It now relied upon purely parliamentary means to implement its programme, and in this it had the full support of the trade unions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">International developments – the upsurge of Nazism and the civil war in Spain - had the effect, in Norway, of focusing attention on democracy. At this time the Party altered its traditional negative attitude towards national defence and advocated rearmament as a safeguard against possible anti-democratic aggression from the outside world. There was growing Labour interest in international problems, but this did not contribute to a clarification of Socialist principles. Anti-Nazi sentiment was strong in the nation as a whole, but only a handful of men, either in the Labour Party or in the other parties, sought a change in the traditional Norwegian policy of neutrality. Until the end of the 1930’s there was strong Labour sympathy for Soviet Russia.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Second World War marked a sharp break.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">II. The Basic Principles of the Norwegian Labour Party</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Defence of Democracy</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In 1939 the Norwegian Labour Party adopted a new programme setting out its basic principles. World War II had broken out. Earlier, the Finnish-Russian war had startled the Norwegian Labour movement and dissipated the old sympathy for Soviet Russia.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Against this background, democratic ideal were elevated to a central place in the new programme. It was clearly stated that the aim of the Labour Party was the democratic conquest of a majority of the nation. “The aim of the Norwegian Labour Party is democratic and peaceful development toward Socialism.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The section on international problems was dominated by the defence of democracy and of fundamental human rights, in place of the old call for international solidarity of the proletariat in the struggle against the class enemy. In contrast to the earlier ideology, it was now stated that there was a wide gap between the bourgeois parties and the totalitarian movements of the extreme Right. “Fascism and Nazism represent a threat to civilisation which all democratic forces must unite to avert.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The programme of 1939 was new in content, but it followed the pattern of older programmes. As a consequence old and new points of view, which were unrelated or even incompatible, appeared side by side.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">One section, for instance, stated that the working class must be prepared for the use of force by the bourgeoisie to defend its privileges, and that the Party would have to use all the power at its command to defeat such an attack upon the democratic rights of the people. There was another relic of previous lines of thought in the statement that militarism and war are inseparably tied up with the capitalist system.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The 1939 basic programme shows that the Party had liberated itself from its former revolutionary ideology but that it had not yet been able to formulate clearly a new set of principles. The introduction stated: "The Norwegian Labour Party, which is the political organ for the Norwegian working class, has as its goal the abolition of capitalist exploitation.” Now it was explained that Socialist society involved “... regulation and planning of the economic life on the basis of the interests of the community and in accordance with Socialist ideas”. And further :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“There is at the same time an urgent need for energetic attempts by society to create more openings for labour and to utilise the country's labour force and productive capacity more effectively, thereby creating the necessary economic basis for a lasting rise in the standard of living of the entire nation and for continuing social and cultural progress. But this can be accomplished only through organised cooperation, a planned economy and the gradual socialisation of big industry, foreign trade, the big private banks, and the means of communication."</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But in spite of progress towards a positive approach, the 1939 programme still gave much more space to criticism of the capitalist system than to formulation of the Party's own goals and principles.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The debate at the 1939 conference revolved round two criticisms. The first was that the Marxist foundation of the Party had not been more precisely expressed. The section on production and ownership stated : “This is in accordance with the Marxist conception of history”; but the opposition found this unsatisfactory. The second point was that the programme did not differentiate between “false bourgeois” and “real Socialist” democracy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Ideological Repercussions of the War</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In 1940, for the first time since the Napoleonic wars, Norway became involved in a big-power strategy. Invasion and occupation were a shaking experience which profoundly influenced the development of political thought and action. For the Labour movement the result was a definite break with many old traditions and, to some extent, a resumption of political modes of thought dating from before the First World War. Among the main results of the change were the following:</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">First of all, democracy, the rule of law and spiritual and cultural freedom – values created and developed in the bourgeois society – were fully accepted as fundamental ideals for the Labour movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Second, national unity during the occupation created a new relationship between the Labour Party and the bourgeois parties which made it natural to seek the solution of current problems as far as possible through co-operation and compromise.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Third, experience of war-time controls in allied countries and even, to some extent, in occupied Norway and produced a general attitude which made it easier to establish a planned economy after the war without provoking a sharp social struggle.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Fourth, the heightened interest in international problems led to an attitude which saw the nation’s task from an international point of view. For the Labour movement, co-operation between governments cane to overshadow international cooperation between Labour organisations.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Fifth, the Labour movement’s international ties developed along new lines. Contact with the continental movements had been very limited after Hitler’s victory, and during the war new and valuable contacts were established with the British and American Labour movements. The change brought a series of new influences and experiences which stimulated both Socialist action and Socialist thinking.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">“Principles and Directives”</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The revolution in outlook on both ends and mean, which took place in the Norwegian Labour movement in the 1940’s expressed itself in the new basic programme, “Principles and Directives”, which was adopted in 1949. The programme indicates clearly that the Party considered the period of violent struggle over, and the period of construction began. Words like “Marxism” and “class war” find no place in the programme. For the first time positive aims are dominant together with the means which the Party will use to attain them.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The new direction is clear from the opening statement :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“We are living in a period of transition; an old social order is being transformed into a new one.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It is again expressed somewhat later :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“But with this development the character of the Labour movement itself has changed. It is still a fighting movement which aims at the creation of a new society, but thanks to its own strength and to the support which it has among the people it is now direct the re-shaping of Norwegian society. In the execution of this task it no longer stands as the representative of a single class or group of the nation; it now represents all those who are willing to find their place in a society built upon the principles co-operation and community of interest.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">An attempt is made to formulate what the Party understands by Socialism :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“It is the a in of the Norwegian Labour Party to build a Socialist society in Norway.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“All activities useful to society must be organised with a view to the common good, so that the real needs of the people can be net. All human beings shall have the same opportunities of participating in the progress towards greater prosperity and a fuller life.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“This goal can only be achieved in a society where all branches of the life of that society join in organised co-operation, which is subject to the will and control of a majority of the people. Everybody must be secured the fundamental prerequisites for man's happiness in life, viz. work, rest, food, a home, family life, education, and development of the mind. No single human being or group of men shall have the right to promote their own interests to the detriment of the community.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Progress towards a society of this kind shall proceed in conformity with the traditions of Norwegian democracy. We will expand democracy so as to cover the whole of the life of the community, especially economic activity. For the latter, we need planning under the control of the nation. Pledged to mutual assistance we shall safeguard personal liberty and bring about security for every one by a systematic management of society.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Economic policy is examined at some length and with much more precision than in earlier programmes. The section is introduced as follows :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“In the field of economics, society must take the steps that are necessary to obtain the objective, viz. maximum production and fair distribution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“This calls for different solutions in the different branches. In a number of cases the State should take over the economic activity. In other cases it is natural to have undertakings run by local authorities, operating separately or in groups. In many spheres it is a sound policy to carry on production and trade on a co-operative basis. Finally, there are some cases where society will be best served by private enterprise. The problem of which solution to choose in a given case is a practical one...</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The Norwegian Labour Party desires to carry through its policy in an orderly way, so that every step may be carefully considered and well planned. All measures shall serve the interests of the country and accord with the will of the people.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The areas best suited to socialisation are enumerated :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The Labour Party will build on the traditions already established in our society, which allow central and local authorities to run vital industries in order to meet the needs of the people and to safeguard the country against exploitation and speculative business. Public enterprise ought to prevail in the following sections of industrial life - so far as it conforms with the country's interest : generation and distribution of electricity, communications, mining, large-scale industry, banking, insurance, and foreign trade. There are particularly strong reasons for taking over a) such branches of industry as are controlled by monopolies or by a few big firms, b) enterprises not running satisfactorily under private management, and c) natural resources not utilised in a proper way.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The economic policy calls also for private and local initiative. It emphasises the importance of expanding and developing democratic organs in industrial life. The section concludes as follows :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The Norwegian Labour Party is of the opinion that the State must give compensation in accordance with Constitutional Law when property or concerns are taken over by public authorities. Prevailing rules regarding capital and income must be adjusted gradually and in conformity with the interests and the will of the people. The means for such an adjustment are at hand, viz. in price and income control, levying of taxes, and social reforms. But, first, we must raise the general standard of living.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Entirely new is a long section dealing with the human side of Socialist aims. It is opened as follows :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Socialisation and planned economy are indispensable elements in the work of remodelling society. The goal may be said to be achieved when all human beings are able to satisfy their needs and to develop their personalities in harmonious contact with others. Consequently, the object of all economic progress must be the creation of a fuller life within the community.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It continues later :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Modern society has become a composite and intricate machine. The problem will be how to prevent it from stagnating in bureaucracy. We will meet this challenge by, affirming the inviolacy of democratic liberties and rights;</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">encouraging a cultural life, in the atmosphere of which are fostered thinking men and women with an active social conscience;</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">giving a fair chance to all useful initiative in town and country, in every place of work;</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">letting democracy expand through the people’s, own organisations.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There then follows a statement on the fundamental liberties which are to be guaranteed to all men in all sections of society without regard to race, religion, sex, social position or income - freedom of expression, assembly and organisation, religion and conscience ; equality before the law; equal access to education and cultural life ; equality for women and special advantages to mothers corresponding to their responsibility towards the young ; the free and secret vote. This statement on fundamental liberties also includes the following :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The authorities are subject to control by the people, who have a right to unbiased information. Everybody is to enjoy the same right to work and rest, to a good home, to an adequate diet, and to varied recreations during his periods of leisure. The expenses incurred in connection with illness, accidents and old age shall be borne by the community.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The section on human and social goals concludes as follows:</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The whole nation must participate actively in the work of the society. At the same time, society must encourage creative genius and ingenuity in the individual and must establish a connection between his daily work and his activity within the organisations and his work for society. There shall exist a lively contact between the people and its authorities.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The aim of Socialism is the creation of free men and women. Liberation of the mind is, therefore, also necessary. The injustice and the insecurity of the old class society stunted human beings, implanted fear in their mind and restrained free thought.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Intellectual life shall be free, no restraint being put upon it by public authorities. But it is, at the same time, the duty of society to support all free research, promote education of the people, and encourage the arts.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“We must, in full harmony with our traditions, establish a firm basis for a rich cultural life among the people. We must efface the social distinction between town and countryside so that rural districts may participate on equal terms in cultural life.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“We must, above all, take good care of our children. At home and at school, during hours of play and hours of work, we must offer them favourable conditions and a wholesome and free upbringing. We want healthy and happy children who will develop into thoughtful, spirited citizens, both able and willing to work together.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The concluding section of the 1949 basic programme deals with international problems. It is somewhat shorter and more superficial than the others. Here it is stated in part :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The world has become a single unit so that it is no longer possible for a nation to live in isolation. The great social problems can be completely solved only on an international basis...</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Democratic Socialism has as yet gained influence only among a minority of the peoples of the earth. But more than ever before, it stands as the exponent of the ideals and human rights which were conceived in Western Europe, and which have since demonstrated their vitality all over the world. Countries with an influential democratic Socialism are today called upon to stand as models for the world.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Norway can make its greatest contribution by developing a society in security, prosperity and freedom. In this way we can - together with other democratic nations - assist in showing the world a way out of chaos and insecurity. At the same time, we must work for effective international co-operation, and for a peaceful solution of international conflicts.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The programme supports disarmament and opposition to nationalism and militarism. But</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“So long as circumstances require it, we must maintain a defence force strong enough to protect our own country and to enable us to fulfil our international obligations.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">After stating that democracy and the gradual elimination of destitution and insecurity are essential to peace, it continues :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“Norway shall work for an international acknowledgement of the fundamental human rights, and we must support all efforts to establish an international law, which will be respected by all.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The principles of law that exist within a democratic society must also be practised in relations between nations. All peoples have the right to claim self-government. All nations and all races are equally entitled to benefit from progress. No one nation can be permitted to place its own interests above the rights of other nations to security and liberty.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“We must insist upon respect for a free international forum, where all views may obtain a hearing irrespective of powerful interests.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">The Norwegian Labour Governments Post-War Policy</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The fundamental outlook which emerges from the Labour Party's last basic programme corresponds to the main tendencies in Norwegian society.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A far-reaching equalisation of incomes has taken place there. Consumption by the wealthy has been cut considerably, and the standard of living of those groups which were formerly worst off - lumberjacks, farm hands, small farmers and fishermen - shows a significant rise. These and other aspects of economic policy have brought about a levelling of class differences and a re-distribution of economic power, without any significant change in the terms of ownership.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The trade union movement has won a central place in economic life, and no change in the political majority could now materially reduce its influence.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The machinery for public control created to handle post-war economic reconstruction and extended to cope with the continuing balance-of-payments crisis has become such an integral part of Norwegian society that no bourgeois government would think of reverting to free capitalism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian Labour Party has conserved and strengthened its position as the leading political party. In the 1949 elections the Party won 57% of the seats in Parliament. It received only 46% of the votes cast, but the second largest party, the Conservative, got only 18%.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Party and Government have not tried to launch a large-scale programme of socialisation. Numerous steps have been taken to implement the programme of socialisation outlined in the 1949 basic programme. All but a handful of the nation's mines are now owned by the government, The supply of electric power has been expanded tremendously through public enterprise. State ownership of banking been widened by the inclusion of a number of new public banks serving housing, the fishing industry, agriculture, etc. The Government has created great state-owned industrial enterprises, especially in steel and aluminium, which when in full operation will command key positions in the country’s economy. Nevertheless, the 1949 programme calls for more far-reaching socialisation than the party leadership wants to press for in the near future.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The economic policy of the Labour Party will continue, in general, to aim at more effective planning within an economy which is predominantly - at present almost 80 % - in private hands. This policy is becoming a basic principle of the Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Economic planning will be implemented primarily through expansion of the machinery of public control and regulation of prices, profits, investment, etc. The Government's power in these fields is at present based on temporary legislation subject to yearly extension by Parliament.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is under discussion a permanent price and rationalisation law which would give the Government greater authority vis-à-vis, private enterprise than exists in any other democratic<anchor xml:id="bookmark35"/> land.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Post-war economic policy has teen summarised each year in the “National Budget”, which surveys economic trends in the whole economy and in the various branches and serves as an instrument for measuring capabilities and setting goals in all parts of the economy. It is given wide publicity and has had the effect of encouraging the Norwegian people to think in terms of the real determinants of notional income.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Changes in International Outlook</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Immediately after the war there was a new and strong upsurge of sympathy for Soviet Russia called forth by its war effort. The Norwegian Labour Party took the initiative in proposing a fusion with the Communist Party, but this effort was wrecked by Communist sabotage.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the first post-war years Norway undertook a foreign policy aimed at remaining neutral and serving as a bridge of understanding between the great powers within the United Nations. On several international issues the Norwegian Labour Government took up positions different from those of the other West European countries.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This foreign policy accorded well with the traditions of the Norwegian Labour movement. It was perhaps also the expression of a certain lack of realism which has not infrequently characterised Norwegian policy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The charge in Norwegian foreign policy followed the coup in Czechoslovakia in 1948. This event had particularly strong repercussions in Norway because previous illusions with respect to Russian foreign policy were greater here than in most other countries.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">All the bourgeois parties favoured Norway’s affiliation to the North Atlantic Pact, but at first a certain opposition expressed itself within the labour Party. However, the arguments against affiliation were extremely varied and could not be united into a common opposition policy. At its convention in 1949 the Party voted unanimously to support Norway’s entry into the Pact.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Party's foreign policy. Such opposition as has appeared has been directed mainly against the economic consequences of the defence effort and against the rearmament of Germany - and has been combined with a certain general suspicion of American policy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Labour Government and the Party leadership have seen in the co-operation between the Atlantic rowers a desirable form for international co-operation on a democratic basis - even though it is not distinguished by a Socialist approach.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The issue of an Atlantic community has aroused scepticism in certain Socialist quarters on the ground that conservative and Catholic influences in France and Germany threaten to dominate. This attitude nay, however, also express an element of old-fashioned isolationism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In Scandinavian relationships the Norwegian Labour movement has found itself in a dilemma; it desires an increasingly intimate co-operation between the governments and Labour movements of all the Scandinavian countries, but the other countries follow a foreign policy which differs from the Norwegian in many important respects. There has been some discussion of a Scandinavian economic union. For the Norwegian economy - the least developed among the Scandinavian group - such a union would create serious problems, at least during a lengthy transitional period.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">On the whole it may be said that the Norwegian Labour movement has accepted the theory of the limitation of national sovereignty in the interests of binding international co-operation, but that it is not yet ready to undertake any special sacrifice for the cause of international solidarity except in the field of defence.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This is an important field for further Socialist thought.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">III. <hi rend="underline">Tendencies in Socialist Ideological Debate in Norway</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">What is Socialism ?</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It is new generally recognised in the non-Communist Labour movement in Norway that Marxism has very little to offer modern Socialists beyond what has already been absorbed by the modern social sciences. The importance of Marxism in the history of European thought is recognised, but the fact that there has been practically no theoretical development since the days of Marx himself is taken as a proof of its sterility today.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Reaction against Marxist dogma has created a certain antipathy to theories in general, but the lively debate on socialisation has raised the question of what the concept “Socialism” is to be taken to cover.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is a clear tendency away from the concept of the “Socialist society” as a precisely determined goal. Instead there is a tendency to seek a Socialist policy, determined not by a distant goal but by whatever is appropriate to the solution of practical problems of the day. Greater equality of income, economic security, effective planning, economic democracy, etc. - everything understood by the expression, “welfare policy” - are part of a steady advance towards Socialist shaping of society.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But because a Socialist policy presupposes long-range goals, and because in practice a number of fundamental issues arise - for example, the relationship between the<anchor xml:id="bookmark38"/> individual and society - a Socialist movement is inevitably led to debate the basic content of Socialism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Some efforts have been made to use the modern social sciences and their analytical methods. This approach has not been particularly fruitful, partly because of the weakness of the social sciences in Norway, partly because the formulation of a political ideology cannot proceed without subjective normative postulates.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In spite of the Norwegian Labour movement's revolutionary past, it is natural for it to see Socialism as part of a larger coherent historical development of political thought - as the natural continuation, development and clarification of “bourgeois liberalism”, as the modern expression of those thoughts and feelings which, in their time, shaped the Declaration of Human Rights. The centre of gravity in the conception of Socialism has moved in the direction of democratic and social humanism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Whereas last century's liberalism took as its point of departure the individual as distinct from society, Socialist thinking places greater stress on the individual as a part of a co-operative society. Both ways of thinking contain dangers which, given one-sided development, can lead to absurd results. The debate at present going on in Norway is an attempt to find the correct balance between freedom, security and equality.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This debate has not produced a complete definition of Socialism, but it has made it more generally understood that concern for happiness - that simple and unsatisfactorily vague concept - is fundamental to Socialism. Happiness is held to involve harmonious life together within the community such as to permit all people to attain to free and unhampered development. This, it is thought, can be realised within a completely democratic society which gives the individual the maximum freedom compatible with the common good.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Although this mode of thought deals in abstract analyses, it has felt the impact of political realities. The concept, “harmony in society”, which presents itself as a Socialist goal once direct need has been eliminated comes more or less in conflict with the demands of efficiency, which are of decisive significance for Norway's economic development. Again, this concept, may conflict with certain political tendencies which lie dormant in the Labour organisations and have their origin in the class war.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Meanwhile, the general view remains that Socialism is one, the most efficient of all economic systems and two, synonymous with socialisation. But there is a tendency to revise these views in the light of the practical experience which is gradually being reaped by Norwegian labour rule.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Questions of Principle in Economic Policy</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Norway's unusual dependence on the international economy limits the scope of Socialist economic policy. Nevertheless, and in spite of the unusual constraints imposed by foreign trade problems in the post-war years, it has been possible to introduce a more far-sighted policy obtains in most other countries. When formulating it the Labour Government has had to cope with many questions involving basic principles.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian Labour movement has passed the period of simple class war, when the major concern of the working class was to secure a steadily larger portion or the national income. Today an increase in the standard of living of the working class is dependent, on the whole, on an increase in production.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Whether the means of production should be socialised to obtain an increase in production (apart from other objectives of socialisation) becomes then a question of practicability. There has been no conclusive proof that socialisation means increased effort or more rational business methods but the question has not been examined adequately.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The debate on this issue has, however, undergone a change; the old problem concerning ownership of the means of production is acquiring new content in modern society. The major issue is no longer ownership, but management is how to secure that management of industry which will best serve the interests of existing society as a whole. The community's right to guide the use of the total productive apparatus is, to a certain extent, now recognised by all.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Because of practical and political considerations, the Norwegian attitude towards socialisation has been very cautious. The Norwegian Labour movement does not want to undertake more than it can manage ; and it in coming to believe that a Socialist economy can be realised to n large extent without disturbing the formal private ownership of the means of production.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">An economy which is publicly controlled and in part publicly run requires not only the preservation, but also the stimulation of certain forces in capitalism. The profit motive must be protected, the formation of private' capital rendered possible, free competition respected - but still subordinated to the basic interests of the community.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The extraordinary conditions which have existed in world economies since the war make it impossible to come to any firm conclusions as to the final form of a system of private enterprise under public direction. There are many signs, however, that it means a very slow transition to a fully socialised economy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In Norway, as in other countries, the struggle for economic efficiency causes discussion on the relative advantages of a liberal versus a publicly-owned centralised economy. This discussion is reflected within the Labour movement in the debate on such problems as bureaucracy and centralisation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is a growing inclination to see dangers in an economic life wholly subordinated to departmental bureaucracies which may lack both detailed knowledge and breadth of approach. It s relatively easy to organise public enterprises on an independent businesslike basis with personally responsible leadership; a more difficult problem is presented by an apparatus for direction and control with all its wide ramifications. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In principle the desideratum is economic decentralisation; economic life ought as far as possible to be organised on a municipal or regional basis, and the trade union movement, employers’ organisations, co-operatives, etc., ought gradually to assume a part of the business or control now handled by the State. But in practice decentralisation would meet with serious difficulties. It would intensify the already serious shortage of people qualified to give economic leadership. Secondly, it would not elicit from private enterprise that willingness to co-operate which is a prerequisite for self-discipline in the common good. Thirdly, the possibilities for decentralisation of economic policy, are limited by the fact that most important economic problems have a bearing on foreign trade, and foreign trade must by its nature be centralised.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In Norway a discussion has started on how to achieve smoother control of economic life by methods which would make planning possible without the stifling effect of an excessively complicated apparatus and a mass of regulations. It has been urged that voluntary control should be sought as far as possible, with positive incentives of one form or another replacing legal compulsion and prohibition as stimuli.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The award of marked economic advantages for increases in production, new trends in production, re-allocation of plant and labour, etc., would have to be given alike to employers, managers and workers. There are many signs, however, that such a policy would meet with opposition in both the trade union movement arid in private enterprise.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Possible conflicts between Socialist principles and the pursuit of a higher standard of living are becoming apparent. One is connected with the development of the country’s natural resources. Norway is in part economically underdeveloped and more than ordinarily dependent on imports. Its ability to hold its own, in international trade, and thereby to protect and raise its relatively high standard of living, is dependent on intense specialisation in a few export industries for which the country in naturally suited.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">First in importance are the hydro-electric industries - industries which require large initial capital investment. Since the internal supply of capital is limited, Norway is interested in attracting foreign capital. Thin means that its economic policy cannot be such as to frighten off the foreign investor. Although it in still hypothetical, the question may yet arise - whether the welfare of the Norwegian people is best served by an increase in the standard of living, even combined with an increase in capitalist influence, or by the pursuit of Socialist economic policies, even at the cost of slowing down further development. The answer may lie in finding a proper balance between the two.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The same problem of balancing economic progress and other Socialist objectives also arises in connection with agricultural policy and certain industries serving the hone market. It is a truism that Norway is not suited to agriculture. As many people are engaged in agriculture as in industry, but agriculture’s contribution to the national income is only one eighth of industry’s. Norway is not suited, either, for the local production of all its industrial needs; the market is too small and scattered to sustain an all-round home industry which can hold its own in competition with foreign industry.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Intensive specialisation in the most fruitful fields of economic activity would meet bitter political opposition, particularly from the farmers. But apart from this there is a real question of principle, namely, whether such specialisation is desirable from the Socialist point of view. The problem again involves harmony: the question is whether, or to what extent, a many-sided economic life should be maintained in order to create the conditions for varied and thriving human development, although such a life is admittedly inconsistent with a high degree of productive efficiency.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Socialist demands for justice, expressed in such slogans as “income according to effort” or “effort according to ability, income according to need”, must be adjusted - at least during a lengthy period of transition - to the forces that make an economy function. Two more immediate questions of principle, dealing with the distribution of income, are being discussed in Norway.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The first is whether it is desirable to introduce a wider graduation of wages (and other forms of income). The issue is not simply whether to make payment correspond to effort and thus put a premium on initiative and ideas, but whether to establish a system involving a more marked differentiation in wages for qualified and responsible work in order to stimulate vocational training and higher production. Action in the same sense could be taken over fiscal policy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It would be possible, as already mentioned, to use income graduation for other planning goals - for instance, to attract capital or manpower to certain areas or industries. This incentive has been used to a certain extent in development plans for the northernmost part of the country, but an extension of the practice would meet many objections. However, one may well ask how a planned economy can function unless it is possible to move, the labour force.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The second problem concerning the division of income arises from the fact that wages are paid for work without consideration being given to the worker's burden of dependents. Although fiscal and social legislation have brought about a certain levelling of incomes as between large and small families, it is generally agreed that the present situation is inconsistent with Socialist demands for justice. But there is no general agreement on how it should be corrected.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A Socialist outlook must attach decisive importance to providing conditions which promote the welfare of the young generation. Sound economic considerations lead to the same result. One might expect then that this problem would receive greater consideration all round.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There are, however, serious practical difficulties in the way of graduating income in accordance with the number of dependents. To name only two: a wage system so graduated (which would presumably entail the operation of some form of equalisation fund) would become extremely complicated; and regulation of family income through the State budget would require channelling through the government a large additional part of the total national income.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Arguments are heard for carrying the Socialist demand for justice still further: for instance, to use further increases in national income not for a general increase in the standard of living but for an increase in the standard of those groups now worst off - the sick, the old, the disabled, and to a certain extent, the children. Apart from the question of whether the majority would be willing to make this sacrifice in the interests of justice, it once more involves the channelling of a larger proportion of the national income through the State budget. It becomes increasingly difficult to reconcile such action with the retention of a predominantly private economic system. The fact is that already many wage earners are more aware of the burden of taxation due to income redistribution and for social services than of the compensating advantages.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">More indirect taxation might contribute to a solution in the sense that the burden of taxation would not be so obvious, but on the other hand would conflict with the Labour movement's traditional attitude on this point.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">The Socialist State</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The old dogma that the state would gradually disappear under Socialism is hardly confirmed by experience. On the contrary, within the foreseeable future Socialists can count on being faced with the problem that the extension of the State's area of jurisdiction creates certain dangers for democracy and justice which must not be underestimated.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It would be in accordance with Socialist philosophy to advocate administrative decentralisation - an increase in self-government by localities and organisations. But this would conflict with certain strong tendencies in the development of modern society.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The discussion on basic principles which has taken place in recent years has shown a tendency to add a new declaration to the citizen’s bill of democratic rights: “Interference in men’s lives by the State shall be as limited as possible.” This would mean in practice that the State’s task should be limited to hindering encroachment by one group in society at the expense of another, and to providing that co-ordination of individual activities which is necessary for the society to function to the advantage of all.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It has been emphasised that a clear distinction must be drawn between the State and the political party which is in power. Furthermore, it is recognised, as a corollary to the growing stress on basic democratic rights, that a government, regardless of the composition of its majority, has the obligation to safeguard the interests of the minority as well.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Thus moderation is becoming a basic Socialist virtue.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The relevance of those problems is due to the transformation of society, as a result of modern technical and economic development, into a complicated machine. Under a Socialist</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Or partly Socialist government important new areas are brought under public administration; co-ordination of economic activity becomes the moat important administrative task. The influence of the State is extended to touch almost all aspects of men’s lives.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In view of these developments, the need to reconcile a planned economy with the demands of democracy and justice gives rise to two fundamental issues. One concerns the connection between government and parliament in the formation and leadership of economic policy. The other concerns the legal protection of the individual against administrative decisions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It has been said that capitalism has given economic activity a disproportionately large place in men's lives; that instead of being a practical prerequisite for free human development, it has become synonymous with this development; and that control of production could quite possibly be reduced to a technical and administrative problem, thus freeing man's attention for more important aspects of life. But at least for the present, the economic management will continue to claim a largo share of man's attention ; and it will raise fundamental problems of justice and of constitutionality.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It would be impossible for a parliament to direct economic activity. It would be unable to exercise effective control or issue the necessary laws. Parliament therefore has to entrust the administration with far-reaching powers over the economic life of the country.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the course of the development of modern parliamentarianism parliament's controlling function has been much weakened by the close connection between government, parliament and party leadership. This development could easily create the feeling that there are no secure guarantees against administrative encroachment. This criticism is heard with most force from the bourgeois opposition, but it cannot be lightly set aside by Socialists ; the Labour movement has frequently emphasised that, parallel with growing State direction of economic life, new forms of democratic control and of the protection of the citizen’s legitimate economic interests must be created. Control and protection must cover both far-reaching economic enactments and administrative decisions affecting single individuals ; everyone must feel himself to be protected against bureaucratic arbitrariness.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is as yet no clear view of the form such controlling organs should take. It has been asserted that they must not be subordinate to the administration or parliament and that they must enjoy the same independence and status as the courts.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Economic planning has given rise to a growing mass of regulations and prohibitions which are not always well based in the traditional concept of justice; the consequence is that the general respect for law may be weakened and the relationship between State and people distorted. This development might lead a Socialist State into a dangerous situation; it must therefore find other positive methods of directing economic development.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Another danger involved in a planned economy is that planning may be influenced in an unfortunate way by considerations of political prestige and political tactics. A governing party may, for instance, be reluctant to change important economic decisions, even when proved wrong, because an clement of prestige is at stake. Or it may be reluctant to decide an issue on its merits because the decision would unfavourably affect that group in society which supports the governing party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In Norway all these considerations have been used as arguments against attempting to move too quickly towards a planned economy. The point of view is gradually gaining ground that administrative jurisdiction must not be allowed to extend more rapidly than the democratic maturity of the people, their degree of social responsibility and solidarity.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Internal Problems of the Norwegian Labour Movement</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Labour organisations were shaped and tempered in the period of class war, and it has not always been easy for then to adjust themselves to new situations and new tasks, when the struggle was over, unity and interest in the movement were put to a hard test; with better conditions, full employment and social security the life of the organisation has become less vigorous.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This is also due to the fact that the centre of gravity in Socialist policy has coved from the Labour organisations to the State. Trade unionists see that their wages and working conditions are not decided by local union activity, but on the political and administrative level.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Simple economic claims have had to make room for complicated evaluations of the economy such as an ordinary worker is not always able to deal with.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Decreased participation on the one hand and the growing complexity and technicality of the tasks on the other tend to create a gap between members and leadership, both in the party and in the trade union movement. But the fact that these organisations become increasingly stronger factors in the framework of society makes it especially important to fester a living internal democracy in them both. It is important to counteract the tendency towards “rule by the party machine”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Norwegian Labour movement has not solved the task of giving its organisations a new content which could release member activity. New emphasis on educational activities is not enough. The first requirement is probably to make the basic local organisation participate directly in the construction of a Socialist society. Socialist development must not be directed “from above”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Labour movement has long had Socialism on its programme but it is not easy to shake off the attitudes and practices which were formed during the period of struggle within the liberal society, and to adjust them to the demands of a planned economy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While the major task of the trade unions, now as before, is to defend the interests of their members, they can participate actively in further Socialist development only, if they find their place within a broader framework of national solidarity. In addition, they must change their approach to economic matters: they can now contribute to raising the real income of their members only by contributing to more effective production.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The trade union movement must ensure that its activities are in all cases consistent with economic democracy and Socialist reform. Wage negotiations present a basic problem The importance of preserving the trade unionists’ sense of self-reliance in taking care of their own material interests is self-evident. However, so basic an economic factor as wages is obviously a central point in economic planning, and union wage demands must be consistent with economic prospects. The distribution of the national income is an issue which concerns the whole people and which ought to be subject to democratic control.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Another question arises in connection with wages policy. Wage differentials have been considerably reduced in recent years through a series of flat, rather than proportionate, wage increases but a tendency in the opposite direction has just appeared. The question is how far wage differentiation should go towards increasing productivity and bringing about a new distribution of the labour force.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">So far production committees have in most instances produced no particularly significant results. Nevertheless, great possibilities ought to exist here - for increasing productivity, for promoting economic democracy and, not least, for giving new content to the trade union movement. It is perhaps precisely in the individual enterprise that the trade union movement can find new tasks which would arouse more enthusiasm and activity.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There has been some discussion of workers' participation in profits, by relating wages in the individual enterprise to total production in that enterprise, but this question has not yet received careful study.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Labour Party must never set out to be anything other than one party among many competing on an equal footing for the people's votes. It cannot say: “we are the State.” And now less than ever can it consider itself the representative of wage earners alone. The trade union movement should, on the contrary, represent a definite group in the community.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A major point in bourgeois propaganda against the Labour movement is the intimate organisational relationship between the Labour Party and the Federation of Trade Unions. This propaganda has been rejected sharply by the Socialists, but it is becoming clear nevertheless that this relationship presents certain fundamental problems. At one time or another it may become desirable to draw a sharper division between the political and industrial movements - in order to secure a planned and rational national policy on the one hand and trade union independence on the other.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Such a separation should in any case take place gradually. The close relationship between the political and the trade onion sectors of the Labour movement has a long historical background, and a violent break in continuity should he avoided. But it is clear, on Socialist principle , that a wage earners' organisation - even if it were to embrace all wage earners - cannot assume a privileged position in relation to other groups “who are willing to find their place in a society built upon the principles of co-operation and community of interests”. (From “Principles and Directives”.)</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This question has also a tactical aspect. While the trade union organisation must continue to be the organisational foundation for the Labour movement, it is considered most important to win the support of the numerous Norwegian middle class - if one wishes to attain a popular majority and lay a safe foundation for a planned economy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Individual and Community</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As the economic and social incongruities of capitalism are gradually abolished, the Norwegian Labour movement is approaching one of Socialism's major problems: the fact that mankind's intellectual development and ability to work co-operatively does not proceed as rapidly as economic, technical and political developments demand.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This raises the question of encouraging Socialist attitudes and, as a long-term aim a Socialist community morale for the efficient conduct of daily political and economic life is generally recognised. It has been thought that they can be influenced by appealing to the individual's sense of social responsibility by promoting “Socialist enthusiasm”, “pleasure in work”, etc. It is self-evident that they are not to be sought by dictation or regimentation. But no clear idea of how to proceed has so far emerged.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Probably a stable democracy simply does not give rise to a high pitch of “enthusiasm”. Perhaps it ought not to - in any case, not in such form as is soon in the peoples’ democracies or during a war, when “enthusiasm” is often connected with fear or regimentation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Undoubtedly much can he done to create greater pleasure in work, and the trade union movement perhaps has an especially big task here. But clearly work in mechanised mass production cannot and should not be enough to fill a man's life. It will probably become a steadily more important task for Socialist policy to create possibilities whereby life outside working hours can acquire a richer content - without public direction.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">All in all, in a democratic society the state will never be able to create a community spirit by decree. It must grow out of the community itself. The State can only create the conditions for growth. Here is a wide and virgin field for Socialist thinking, which demands all the more attention because of the shift in Socialist policy from concentration on raising the standard of living to a wider policy of promoting the full development of the individual man.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The steady increase in the complexity of the social machinery, which is the reverse side of the medal of economic development and social progress, creates a growing inner tension in the community. The multiplication of intermediate links between an individual man's activity and the satisfaction of his needs tends to obscure his sense of fellowship and solidarity with the community.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Men's feeling of fellowship does not embrace the whole nation today and can hardly be expected to do so. In ordinary daily life this fellow-feeling seldom extends beyond the framework of home, neighbourhood and place of work. The Socialist task must not be the unsolvable one of forcing an extension of fellow-feeling to embrace the whole country - that would be appropriate only in a "people's democracy" - but to promote participation in small democratic centres and to develop the connection between these small units and the whole community.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Democracy must be something active. The growing complexity of the community is a danger for both the spiritual harmony of the individual man and democratic community life. In the face of this danger there is a growing demand that community life be divided into small units in which a man can feel himself a part. Small centres like the workshop club, the neighbourhood club, the co-operative, the theatre group, can constitute such “manageable” units in which the individual can see his participation and control. These forms must be promoted and their democratic and Socialist content emphasised.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">At the same time there must be developed a more organic connection between the lower and the higher organisational units, so that “the top” will not stiffen into a power apparatus. The co-ordinating activity of the central leadership must be under the direct control of the people - through increasing contact and exchange between groups and regions, as well as through the more generally recognised means of elections, free press, etc.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The debate in the Norwegian Labour movement on how a free and harmonious community is to be created has also touched a number of other problems which can only be mentioned here:</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">With the mechanisation and commercialisation of those forces in the community which create public opinion and influence the cultural life, how are spiritually independent, self-thinking people to be formed?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">How are we to find the forms for political activity which suit a democracy - forms built on information and the factual exchange of opinion, free from the factors of power and blind faith?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">How are we to find the right balance in the conduct of public affairs between specialised knowledge and the people's common sense?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">How are we to ensure effective influence by women on the policy of the community - fully equal to men's - and proper attention to their special interests ? etc.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)"><hi rend="underline">Socialist Foreign Policy</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The profound significance of international developments on Socialist policy in Norway is coming to be more and more clearly recognised within the Norwegian Labour movement. Internationalism is gradually setting its mark on general outlook and way of thinking. But there have been few attempts at a thorough analysis of what a Socialist attitude towards world development must contain today.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A certain amount of attention has been given to the question of insuring full candour in foreign policy. The demand has been expressed that the formation of foreign policy be subjected to continuous democratic control, and that no decisive step be taken without certainty of the backing of a majority of the people.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Obviously, this demand cannot be fully realised. The Norwegian Government must have contacts with foreign governments, and it cannot maintain diplomatic relations with then without respecting international practices - even if they are in part undemocratic. The alternative would be a foreign policy for purposes of propaganda only, with consequences which would not be acceptable to the majority of the Norwegian people. However, Norway can undertake to contribute to a democratisation of international policy as far as circumstances allow and to advance Socialist points of view wherever Norway has a voice.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">To an unfortunate degree, the debate on foreign policy within the Norwegian Labour movement is influenced more by emotional or tactical motives than by rational Socialist thinking. There has been no clarification of even the basic problem whether foreign policy shell be guided by the short-term interests of its people, or by ideals and long-range ideological goals which nay demand immediate sacrifices for their attainment.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">An international Socialist foreign policy is obviously an impossibility today, when the Socialist parties in the individual lands often take incompatible points of view.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It is in line with fundamental Socialist views to welcome every act of democratic international co-operation, even those which take place on non-Socialist grounds. The misgivings which have here been expressed have often been of dogmatic nature.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">For instance, it has been said that North Atlantic co-operation increases dependence on the United States, but it is open to question whether the degree of dependence is in fact greater than it would be without such co-operation. Again, rejection of European co-operation on the ground that it can become dominated by French and German conservative elements can with certain right be labelled a reactionary point of view. In both cases the arguments which have been presented are superficial.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While it still lacks clarity and development, certain basic points of view are emerging in the foreign policy debate within the Norwegian Labour movement:</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A Socialist foreign policy must observe full freedom of speech in all fields of international co-operation, even where it may result in offending another party in the common undertaking.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A policy of collective security and balance of power must not be built on emotional evaluations, but on long-range analysis of the international development and of the underlying social forces, backed by all the available scientific knowledge.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A Socialist movement must not forget that Socialism means solidarity - with all the peoples of the earth. Today this means, above all, solidarity with the great underdeveloped areas of the world. National Labour movements have so far focused on claims; now in the Western countries they must be willing to give. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">World history is now entering the age of the underdeveloped countries; in the coming hundred years they will dominate world development. They have a deep suspicion of the white man’s world, but at the sane time they need to co-operate with it. Here the small democratic countries with a strong Labour movement - countries like Norway - can help to develop mutual understanding and make a contribution in the spirit of democratic Socialism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The struggle which small Socialist groups started a hundred years ago has created a series of social democracies in Western Europe which can serve as model for the world. But national welfare is only a partial goal, and a Socialist must not allow short-sighted national foreign policy to stand in the way of solidarity with the people who are reaching later than we for economic development, individual freedom, and political independence.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">A Socialist movement confronts difficulties here which are greater than it meets in its national policy. An easing of political tension in the underdeveloped parts of the world demands progress in raising the standard of living in these areas, and this calls for material assistance from the West. But it cannot be lightly assumed that any West European working class will accept the sacrifices which would be called for if the West is to make its maximum contribution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">During the period of world transformation which is new in process, the threat of warfare continues and the means have not yet been found to free the world of this danger. Here lies the most important task for Socialist thinking today. It calls for intense co-operation between all the Socialist movements of the world, in the true spirit of what was once proudly called “scientific Socialism”, an approach to the problems at hand with logical, critical, unprejudiced minds.</p></body></text></TEI>