<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Germany</title>
         <author>Richard Freyh</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>19 January 1957</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.VII, No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
  
  <body>
  <p>Like all Social Democratic parties the German Social Democratic Party was and is primarily the political expression of the rise and urge to rise of the working class which had grown in the process of industrialisation. The immediate objectives of this urge - participation in the political development of the State, in the first place through full equality of franchise, and participation in economic expansion, primarily by means of higher wages and shorter working hours - also constituted the immediate objectives of all Socialist parties. But these two basic demands did not exhaust all the distinguishing features of the incipient rise of the working classes. On the contrary, the growth of that class signified at the same time a general victory over prevailing injustice. Similarly, the demands of the Social Democratic parties were not limited to improving the conditions of the workers. They all, more or less explicitly, set as their goal a complete transformation of society.</p><p>This objective was most pronounced in German Social Democracy. For a variety of reasons Germany has, in many respects, undergone a distinctive development, in which many stages especially as regards economic and social developments occurred appreciably later than, say, in France or Britain and in a different form. Since the bourgeois revolution first made its appearance in European history this difference in development has been ever more strongly marked in the political and intellectual fields. The less successful Germany was in ever producing a victorious bourgeois revolution the more strongly its thought developed radical forms. The rise of the working class also found its most consistent ideological expression in Germany - in Marxism. Nowhere has the identity of the struggle of the workers for the improvement of their conditions with the struggle for the Socialist reconstruction of society been built up into a more highly developed theory than in the work of Marx. At the name time it is true that at first the actual results of Socialist policies in Germany remained, generally speaking, very slight, not least because of the way in which this form of theoretical expression was driven to its logical conclusion.</p><p>Marx saw the struggle of the working class as the point in world history at which, by the victory of the proletariat, class rule and the clans structure of society would be abolished once and for all. The capitalist economic system, indeed the whole of world history, he interpreted as a process at the end of which must necessarily lie the conquest of capitalism and the victory of Socialism, or barbarism. Who would not then choose the first alternative? The step by which the victorious proletariat was to set in motion the real history of mankind and leap from the realm of necessity to that of freedom, was the abolition of that which Marx regarded as the cause of all preceding, and particularly of capitalist, servitude and exploitation : the private ownership of the means of production, Up to that point, every other form of political activity appeared only as a preparation for this last decisive struggle.</p><p>However much Marxism may have regarded the day-to-day political and trade union struggle of the working class as a step on the road to a Socialist society, it still emphasised the wide gap between its final objective and what could be achieved at the present time. This gap had become all the greater since at the time when the Gorman Social Democratic Party came into existence the unification of Germany, in its "lesser German" form under Prussian aegis, was achieved under Bismarck's leadership, and Germany was thus even more strongly separated intellectually and politically from the West than before. In the same period in which Britain and France finally found their way to political democracy, the authoritarian state and its methods of thought received a new impetus in Germany. Indeed this authoritarian state survived the Weimar Republic to join forces with the new forms of totalitarian dictatorship, belonging to the age of the super-specialised industrial mass society, and formed one of the bases of the Third Reich.</p><p>This great gap between final objective and existing reality already found expression in the first Social Democratic programme, the Eisenach Programme of 1869, in which one part deals with principles and the shape of the distant future and another part deals with the present situation and the immediate objectives. As long as Bismarck's policy of suppression, during the period of the anti-Socialist law, allowed the Social Democratic Party no share in the state, this gap was hardly noticed. When, however, with the fall of Bismarck, the anti-Socialist law lapsed, it gradually became important and eventually found its theoretical expression in what was called "Revisionism".</p><p>Eduard Bernstein, the ideological leader of the movement for the revision of Marxism, had learnt in England and from England to see many things differently from the way in which they had previously appeared while he was still in Germany. And just as Marx's work had, to a great extent, been a synthesis, based on the fundamental tenets of Hegelian philosophy, of French Socialism with the British Chartist workers’ movement and classical political economy, so Bernstein attempted to find a similar synthesis between that which he had accepted as Marxism and that which he found in reality. A not insignificant factor in this attempt was the now appreciation of the philosophy of Kant. Revisionism found its most significant expression in Bernstein's dictum that for him the goal, whatever it might be, was nothing, the movement everything. It is true that by "movement" he did not in any way mean only the organisation, but as he said himself: "By 'movement' I understand the general movement of society, that is to say, social progress, as well as the political and economic agitation and organisation directed to the attainment of progress." (Eduard Bernstein, <hi rend="underline">On the History and Theory of Socialism</hi>, Berlin, 1901.) However much the theory of Revisionism had been foreshadowed by the later works of Engels, indeed even by Marx himself, nevertheless it suffered from the fact that Bernstein, to a considerable degree, lacked understanding for the philosophical foundations, or at least for the origins, of Marxism.</p><p>Independently of Bernstein, a practical reformism had developed in Germany by that time, a readiness and a desire to attain Socialism through reforms rather than through revolution. Bernstein, who rejected the term "Revisionism" for his point of view, called himself a Reformist. If at first Reformism was based on the altered political circumstances after the repeal of the anti-Socialist law, later the economic arguments in connection with the general upward trend of the economy came into the foreground of the debate, in which the so-called theory of increasing misery occupied a central place.</p><p>Revisionism obtained important assistance from the altered structure of the Social Democratic Party itself which developed into a mass party from the interests of the Social Democratic members of State legislatures and local authorities and from the attitude of the trade unions. In 1905 the number of Social Democratic members of State Parliaments was 151 ; in 1913 it was already 231, mostly from Württemberg, Baden and particularly Bavaria. The number of Social Democratic local councillors rose even more quickly, doubling itself in five years. In 1908 it was 5,931 and in 1313 as high as 11,681.</p><p>The dispute between Revisionism and officially supported Marxism dragged on for years. Time and again the decision wont in favour of Marxism, thanks to the influence of August Bebel and Karl Kautsky, at the Hanover Party Conference in 1899 and particularly at the Dresden Conference in 1903. It must, however, be admitted that Bebel, as the undisputed leader of the Party, and Kautsky, as its most prominent theoretician, had in fact already taken up a middle position in these struggles between the opposing sides which were developing on this and on ether issues. In 1910 the Magdeburg Conference condemned support for the Budget in Bader. In this way majority decisions prevented a theoretical clarification being achieved on the real issue in the conflict and it was precisely in this way that the foundations were laid of a deep-seated ideological crisis in the Social Democratic Party, because a contradiction, arose between its theoretical claims and its rational policy, which was only gradually resolved, generally speaking to the benefit of Reformism,</p><p>The practical policy of the Party was in most spheres fully at one with what the Reformists demanded and what the trade unions were in any case doing: the eight-hour day, higher wages and franchise reform in Prussia, where the Three-Class franchise still ensured vital privileges for the possessing classes. During this period both the SPD and the trade unions went through a stage of turbulent growth, which to a large extent concealed the contradiction between revolutionary theory and reformist practice. The voting strength of the SPD rose from 1,427,000 (19.7%) in the Reichstag elections of 1890, to 3,010,800 (31.7%) in 1903. In the Reichstag elections of 1912 it amounted to 4,250,000 (34.95%). It is no accident that the greatest practical success of Reformism was the 1912 agreement for the second ballot. The trade union federations organised in the General Council represented 277,659 members in 1891, 1,344,803 in 1905 and 2,548,763 in 1913.</p><p>After Revisionism had been condemned in theory and largely accepted in practice, a new controversy - also in connection with the Russian Revolution of 1905 - developed, this time on the problem of the general strike. The slogan of a general strike for equal and universal suffrage in Prussia had been put forward by the so-called Right in the Party, which was in favour of carrying on the struggle for political democracy by every means. The Left immediately took up the slogan hoping that they had found a suitable instrument to set a revolution in motion. It was true that Marx had always refuse: to provide "recipes for the soup kitchen of the future". But was not the strike of all the workers, the general strike, the means of putting power into the hands of the working class? Who would be able to resist such action? Were not all strikes by the trade unions for higher wages in fact rehearsals for this final strike? This was, the point over which the struggle raged between the Left wing of the Party led by Rosa Luxemburg and Franz Mehring, and the Centre, whose spokesman on theoretical questions, as in the controversy with Bernstein, was Karl Kautsky. They were united only in rejecting the general strike in its syndicalist sense as the infallible means of establishing the just society. The question of the general strike was eventually settled very soberly by the Party which decided that one could only judge from case to case whether it was am appropriate weapon and that one must continuously work for the expansion of political and trade union organisation in order to be prepared for anything.</p><p>Just as in the discussion on the problem of the general strike it was the difference between theory and what actually appeared to be possible which created the two opposing factions, so the gap between objective theoretical knowledge of the possibilities of capitalist development on the one hand and, on the other, Marxist economic theory, as it was taught in Party schools, was revealed in another controversy, namely, that about imperialism and the accumulation  of capital. Rudolf Hilferding’s <hi rend="underline">Finance Capital</hi> and Rosa Luxemburg’s <hi rend="underline">Accumulation of Capital</hi> still remain today by far the most significant contributions made by German Marxism since Marx and Engels to the development of Socialist theory. Both linked up with the second and third volumes of <hi rend="underline">Capital</hi>. Hilferding traced the development from industrial and bank capital to a new form, finance capital, while for Rosa Luxemburg the main point of interest was provided By the problem of the large-scale reproduction of capital.</p><p>The significant content of the work of both may perhaps be up is the following way. If the capitalist economy expands its production year by year, it can only dispose of this increased production if its market expands to the same extent. Since the desire for profit on the part of the bourgeoisie only permits a very limited increase in the purchasing power of the masses, and since the absorption of the surplus production by the capitalist productive process itself would only be possible given centralised capitalist planning without any competition, the only solution that remains is the conquest of ever greater spheres of economic influence both at home and abroad; at home by the formation of trusts and cartels, abroad by imperialist policies and imperialist wars. While Hilferding mainly developed the aspects of this problem which were concerned with the internal organisation of the capitalist system, Rosa Luxemburg was principally interested in the connection between capital accumulation and slumps on the one hand and imperialism on the other.</p><p>But at the same time that these questions arose in theory they presented themselves in a different and more decisive way in practical politics. For years there had been discussions at conferences about the problem of capitalist-imperialist war and resolutions had been passed in favour of international working-class solidarity and against war. When war actually broke out international solidarity and abstract pacifism did not stand up to the test. It was suddenly shown that there was an essential difference between what one wanted and what one could do. Opposition in principle to the war of the ruling classes could only have been sustained if the SPD, when faced with war, had issued a call for "revolutionary defeatism", and if the solidarity of the proletariat in the belligerent stales had beer, stronger than the feeling and realities of national solidarity. Certainly it was the struggle against Tsarism in Russia, which Rosa Luxemburg and Karl Liebknecht in particular had worked to prepare, which made possible in the first place the united attitude of the SPD. But the truce between the Government and Social Democracy after August, 1914, showed with disastrous clarity that the SPD was not the radical mass party which it had believed itself to be.</p><p>When the war went on longer than had been expected ever increasing groups began to oppose the war and call for a struggle against the class enemy at home. When the Imperial government had asked for now war credits in December, 1914, Karl Liebknecht had voted against them. As early as 1916 the opponents of the political truce separated themselves from the majority Socialists calling themselves the "Social Democratic Working Group", and in 1917 they formed their own Party, the Independent Social Democratic Party of Germany (USPD) in which both Marxists and Revisionists joined in their opposition to the war.</p><p>Even before this Socialists from the neutral countries had met together with the Russians and Italians and the German Independents in Switzerland at the conferences at Zimmerwald in September 1915 and at Kienthal in the following year, and attempted to revive the International. But a common objective was lacking. Lenin was striving for a new International which should serve as a weapon in the struggle for the world revolution which he foresaw as the sequel to the world war. But the majority of the participants in these conferences just wanted to restore the old International. In this way the Zimmerwald Left found very few supporters, apart from the Bolsheviks, and the whole movement petered out without any lasting results.</p><p>The controversy received a powerful new impetus as a result of the revolution in Russia in the sprint of 1917 and the victory of the Bolsheviks in November. It is difficult to say how large a part of the German working class may have been ready then and in 1918 to join the new movement, and later also the new International, to which attached none of the odium of 1914 and which could boast of the victory in Russia. But it was above all the Bolsheviks themselves who not only enabled but actually forced the SPD and then the old International to continue or rebuild themselves practically unchanged. The activities of the Bolsheviks were in no way based on the principle of voluntary international solidarity of the proletariat, for whose fulfilment so many people longed. They wished rather to achieve control over the workers’ parties in all other countries and simply equated the interests of the world proletariat with their own and then, to a rapidly increasing degree, with the interests of the leaders of the Soviet dictatorship. In this way opinions were sharply divided from the outset. The division arose over the problem of democracy, parliamentary democracy as well as party democracy.</p><p>When the military collapse occurred in November, 1918, it found Social Democracy completely unprepared for an immediate Socialist transformation of society. The Left inside the Social Democratic and Independent Social Democratic Party, faithful to the Marxist sneer at "recipes for the soup kitchens of the future", possessed nothing but general formulae and the belief in the spontaneity of the masses. But the firm organisation, decisive and clear about its objectives, which could have given expression to this spontaneity, did not exist. The majority could see no other course in this situation than to carry things on in some way or other under their own control. The leadership of the Party faced the choice of risking chaos without knowing what to do in that situation or simply continuing along the same way as they had pursued before, namely that of perfecting democracy. It soon became apparent that the decision in favour of parliamentary democracy meant the renunciation of power.</p><p>Through the whole history of German Social Democracy there runs a fundamental contradiction between two interpretations of the Party’s own task. On the one hand, there was the belief that Socialism would necessarily develop as a result of the immanent laws of historical development and that the role of the Party consisted merely in recognising those laws and furthering their operation, in short, in executing the iron will of history. On the other hand, there was the conviction that the Socialist movement existed to give political expression to the desire of the working class in particular for a better and just or future and to realise it as far as possible in a given set of circumstances. This contrast which in its extreme form existed between a fatalistic anticipation of the inevitable revolution end a purely ethically based aspiration has never actually been clear - even in Marx the second element is by no means absent - but to a considerable extent it has always been inherent in the ideological trends.</p><p>The situation after 1918 made possible - only temporarily, it is true - a resolution of the dilemma in the Görlitz Programme of the Majority Social Democrats of 1921. In this programme not only was reformism for the first time actually accepted, but it constituted also a conscious departure from the traditions of the "party waiting for the Revolution". To point the way for the aspirations of the working class movement and also, of course, to bring consciousness and unity to the necessary struggle of the working masses, was expressly proclaimed as the role of the Social Democratic Party. But just at this time the situation began to change once more.</p><p>The Communist Party of Germany which had been formed from the Spartacus League at the beginning of 1919 lost Rosa Luxemburg by assassination after only a few weeks, and thus lost the only personality whose high standing might perhaps have acted on a moral counterpoise to Lenin and his victorious party, although she had been unable to carry the day at the foundation conference of the Communist Party. Thus the new Party fell from the outset under the influence of the Bolshevists and quickly sank to the position of a dependency. It is true that in 1920 it succeeded in splitting the Independent Social Democratic Party at the latter’s Conference at Halle and in winning a section for the Communist Party, but in the second half of 1922 the Independent Social Democratic Party was reunited with the majority Socialists. With the Independent Social Democratic Party the two leading theoreticians of German Socialism, Hilferding and Kautsky, also returned and it goes without saying that presently their theoretical influence, and particularly that of Hilferding, made itself felt, and that the Marxist method, as he understood it, once more assumed a fundamental importance. This development then led, in the period of general stabilisation of the situation after 1923, to a new turn towards the Left in the Heidelberg Programme of 1925.</p><p>Even after the Kapp Putsch had been suppressed and the struggles of the year 1923 brought to a successful end, the reunited Social Democratic Party had still to carry on a war on two fronts. Their opponents were the Communists on the one side and the bourgeois parties on the other. This position was further complicated by the fact that the fight against the Right could not be carried on least a single united bloc, but that on the extreme Right stood open counter-revolution in the shape of Nazism, compared with which the democratic, and even the monarchist, bourgeois parties still represented the lesser evil, and were even allies.</p><p>In this atmosphere it was obviously not possible to keep up the theoretical, abstract radicalism of the pre-war period. Revisionism provided the guiding principle in nearly every attempt to construct a new theoretical and tactical foundation. The Social Democratic Party was more emphatic than ever about its determination to win power only by democratic means and to remain in power only by democratic means. This did not, of course, involve giving up the basic struggle against the capitalist order of society. However, the final objective remained as before the building of a Socialist, classless society. But it was now admitted that this objective was too to be achieved by the revolutionary dictatorship of the proletariat, but by means of reforms, and in the first place still within the scope of the bourgeois capitalist order, though increasingly going beyond this at a later stage.</p><p>It was no easy task to produce a programme which, in a simple form, would at the same time satisfy both requirements of the day-to-day political struggle - partly under conditions of governmental responsibility - and the need to mobilise one’s own Party members, as well as the mass of voters, for the struggle for the ultimate objective. Although the bourgeoisie, who at first disappeared from geopolitical scene in November 1918, within a few years once again held most of the power in its own hands. Social Democrats could not go beyond their almost unconditional support for the Republic, because they had their share of power in the Länder – and in Prussia in particular – and in numerous municipalities, because this form of government and the stability of democracy depended in the last resort on the Social Democrats and, particularly because they were able under the Republic to achieve a very extensive improvement in the position of the working classes.</p><p>To the SPD the establishment of the Republic and the social progress which was achieved rightly appeared as an enormous success. If it identified itself with this Republic, which – as far as power was concerned – was generally speaking fairly independent of it, so that eventually it increasingly lost its freedom of action, the policy of the Communist Party, which sank lower with each new changes of leadership, contributed decisively to this result.</p><p>For German Social Democracy the period of the Weimar Republic was above all a period of practical success in the field of social policy. The trade unions and the Party having achieved, in long years of struggle and by the continual development of the system of collective bargaining, a position where the working classes were able to confront the employers on equal terms and improve their standard of living, the Labour Exchange and Unemployment Insurance Law of July, 1927, provided the complementary factor needed to ensure the maintenance of these gains in times of crisis, assuming, of course, that the general structure of the Republic could withstand the crisis.</p><p>It was not only in the field of practical social policy, however, that continual progress was made, but also in the field of economic and general theory. Even though early in the inter-war period the j main achievements in the theoretical field were, generally speaking, undoubtedly In Britain and the Scandinavian countries, nevertheless the lull after 1923 also rendered possible a productive controversy in Germany. Formal versus social democracy, economic democracy and the sociological and ethical foundations of Socialism were problems on which discussion centred. It is significant that in this debate the Marxists who followed Hilferding and leading trade unionists like Fritz Tarnow were particularly concerned with Socialist economic policy, while the younger Marxists who in the traditional way considered themselves revolutionary began to divert their attention away from economic theory towards a philosophical understanding of the Marxist system.</p><p>This two-fold stream of development extended far beyond the Marxists in the narrow sense of the term. Not for the first time Social Democracy derived strength from the fact that the motive force of the capitalist system, as formulated by its own doctrinaire supporters, ran counter to all ethical principles. The realisation of this fact, which previously had often been concealed by the crude Marxist belief in inevitability, now began, for the first time, to become a driving force. The fact that Christianity and capitalism were absolutely incompatible became for the first time a recognised basis of Socialist conviction in the period of stabilisation under the Weimar Republic. The theoretical controversy was not inconsiderably influenced, especially among the Left-wing Socialists, by Austro-Marxism and particularly by the discussion which preceded the new programme adopted by the Austrian Socialists at their Conference at Linz in the late autumn of 1926. The problem of the State and of the struggle for power in the State occupied the foreground in this discussion.</p><p>As a representative summary of the generally prevailing view of Rudolf Hilferding’s report to the Party Conference of the Social Democratic Party in Kiel in 1927 on "The Tasks of Social Democracy in the Republic" may be extensively quoted here. Starting from the fact that, for the first time since the end of the war, a general improvement in the economic situation, particularly in Germany, had begun in 1927, Hilferding described the transition from a free market economy to an organised economic system. In this new system synthetic chemicals appeared as sources of productive power alongside steam and electricity, and these provided commodities in more suitable forms and more cheaply without dependence on the raw material producing areas. From the outset, he argued, these new potentialities would be organised and exploited by cartels and trusts. The result would be a high degree of internationalisation in the capitalist world. In this organised form of capitalism the profit motive would permit the introduction of a scientific form of competition instead of free competition. This would dispose of the last psychological objection to Socialism, because the capitalist principle of free competition would have been displaced even whilst capitalism still continued to exist by the Socialist principle of economic planning. The problem would then be to convert an economy managed and controlled by capitalists into one controlled by the democratic State. Previously, Social Democrats had fought for political rights and the beginnings and extension of a social policy. New, by the operation of economic development itself, the problem of Socialism had been put on the agenda.</p><p>Hilferding went on to show how the State had always intervened even in the free economy, that it had controlled the money market as well as fiscal and commercial policy. Through the medium of collective agreements and arbitration courts even the fixing of wages had be cone a political matter. The Socialist principle consisted in regarding the running and the economy as a matter which concerned society and society had no organ through which it could operate consciously other than the State, whose essential element, the political parties, like government and administration, were expressions of the class struggle. In this connection a change must also take place in the functions of the trade unions, which would no longer be fighting directly against the employers for shorter working hours and better wages, but concentrating increasingly on industrial and economic democracy.</p><p>After the privilege of ownership had been broken politically the whole thought and effort of the working class would be directed to breaking it economically. Democracy had always been the concern of the proletariat and not of the bourgeoisie. Socialists were no friends of violence, because there was no more serious obstacle to the achievement of Socialism than civil war. Therefore the maintenance of democracy and of the Republic was the most important interest of the Party. It was wrong to talk about "bourgeois" or "formal" democracy, because in this way the close connection between politics and their social efforts was obscured. In Italy Mussolini had been victorious, precisely because the Italian proletariat did not know what a prize freedom and democracy was. Democracy was only possible if it was backed by a strong and politically conscious working class. Whether Bolshevism had had a reactionary or a revolutionary effect history must decide, but in any case it was a great misfortune for the whole of Central Europe, and particularly for Germany, that the victory of the Bolshevists preceded the victory of the democratic revolution in Germany. It was not democratic illusions which were dangerous today, but anti-democratic illusions, all the more since all the reactionary forces in Germany were beginning to unite against democracy and for Fascism. The most important task in the class struggle in Germany at that time was to bring about the fall of the Right-wing Government. The whole working class needed to be built into a political party. With the development of the economy making Socialism increasingly an immediate problem for the working class, and with the interaction of the State and the economy becoming ever more intimate, the proletariat could not but eventually conquer power in the State in order to achieve Socialism.</p><p>The general election of the year 1928 gave the Social Democratic Party an increase of 1 1/2 million votes, mainly as a result of the years spent in opposition. A broad-based coalition with the Social Democrat Hermann Müller at its head took over the Government. Then trouble-over the so-called battle cruiser "A" plunged Social Democracy into a severe internal crisis. The building of this battle cruiser, decided on by the previous Reichstag, had been one of the main issues on which the Social Democrats fought the election. There now arose a threat that the Government coalition would fall apart if the Social Democratic Ministers insisted on its abandonment. The result was a violent controversy in the Party, first of all over the affair of the battle cruiser and finally over the whole military question. The real problem was that of breaking the reactionary power of the Reichswehr, but it was precisely on this that no solution could be found. Eventually, the Magdeburg Conference in 1929 adopted a defence programme which called for voluntary disarmament, but at the same time stressed the need to defend the Republic and its achievements. Whatever the merits of this decision it left untouched the central problem posed by the fact that in an emergency the Reichswehr was not on the side of the Social Democrats and therefore of the Republic but in opposition to it.</p><p>Then, in the same year, arose the greatest crisis which capitalism has ever experienced. This would have been the moment to mobilise the working masses both for the struggle against want and the struggle for power. But the world economic crisis found the Social Democratic Party without a convincing crisis programme. True, there were discussions over the Lederer Plan and the Woytinski-Tarnow-Baade Plan. The former was based on the idea that the unemployed should help one another by means of a direct exchange of their products and services with State assistance, while the latter contemplated the creation of additional purchasing power by government action to the extent of a milliard marks. Today it is common knowledge that the energetic application of a plan of this type would have made it possible to overcome, or at least to alleviate, unemployment. But there was no longer any real chance for an initiative.</p><p>The general situation was too unfavourable and the time too short for the Social Democrats to be able to abandon the defensive. These first attempts at a full employment policy, such as countries with firmly settled democracies were able to develop out of the measures to deal with the crisis, were in Germany either abandoned altogether or diverted into quite different channels. The Government of Hermann Müller did not fall because the Social Democrats went over to the attack against capitalism in the course of fighting the crisis; it fell in defending the social achievements of the Republic.</p><p>After the fall of Hermann Müller, bourgeois governments alone decided the fate of Germany. The Social Democratic Party had no choice but to support a succession of bourgeois governments and always to choose the lesser evil, while the evil became ever greater. Social Democracy had been compelled to identify itself with the Weimar Republic, without having any decisive share in the exercise of power. The fact that this Republic had not been able to achieve equality of status for Germany had already done great harm, particularly to the Social Democrats. That the Republic now failed when confronted with the economic crisis destroyed it and with it the Social Democratic Party. Parliamentary democracy, which alone could provide the soil for a progressive achievement of the Social Democratic programme, was not by any means firmly enough rooted in the masses to be able to withstand, in this emergency, the severe storms of economic crisis and the ceaseless barrage of anti-democratic propaganda from the Communists and the parties of the Right - not by any means only the Nazis. The fact that parliamentary democracy had been brought into being as a consequence of military surrender contributed to its relative weakness just as much as the short-sighted policy of the Western powers, who on security grounds refused democratic Germany those rather natural demands, which they then promptly granted to the Fascist terror regime, at a time when it really threatened their security. Certainly democracy, whose stability in Britain and the United States, and even in France, had been the result of prolonged development and struggles in which the whole nation had taken part, had not, in any case, had the chance in a bare decade to become as secure as it needed to be in those years. In January 1933, Hitler did not need to wrest power by force from the Social Democrats and Republicans, but was able just to step into the place of someone else as head of a bourgeois cabinet. The legal organisation of the Social Democratic Party was destroyed and its members forced into illegality. Those among them who were most in danger and could not carry on the struggle in other ways had to flee abroad.</p><p>Just as the movement towards reaction under the Weimar Republic and the meteoric rise of Hitler during the world economic crisis were not confronted by a united political representation of the working class, so the Social Democratic front after Hitler's victory was not cast in a single mould. The temporary co-operation and equally temporary independence of one part of the Left opposition in Central Germany achieved little more than a repetition of old formulae. More significant from a long-term point of view was the existence of three other groups. The oldest of them was the Militant International Socialist League, generally known as ISK, which had been founded by members of the International Youth League after they had been expelled from the Social Democratic Party in 1925. Leonard Nelson, whose development of the critical philosophy of Kant and Fries provided the theoretical basis of this League, had been the founder of the International Youth League. ISK rejected the crude Marxists conception of the inevitability of Socialism and saw the true foundations of Socialism in postulates based on a critique of knowledge and applied in a policy resting on sociological, economic and cultural foundations. For ISK the formation and training of a responsible leadership was the main problem of democracy.</p><p>The second group, the Socialist Workers’ Party of Germany (SAP), had been formed during the break-up of the Weimar Republic from sections of the Left wing of the Social Democratic Party and the Communist opposition to Stalinism. This group looked upon Marxism as developed by Lenin as its theoretical basis. Parliamentary democracy was to be replaced by the inner-party democracy of the proletariat and the dictatorship of the proletariat was supposed to lead to the achievement of Socialism. That the international solidarity of the working class was infinitely more important than any national bonds constituted a self-evident proposition for this group. The initially heterogeneous composition of this new party made itself felt in the attitude taken up to developments inside Russia and led in the end to a new split.</p><p>Finally, the Social Democratic group New Beginning developed a completely now orientation of the Social Democratic movement out of the criticism of the conduct of both the Social Democratic Party and the Communist Party during and before the great crisis. A reassessment of economic and political development based on the Marxist analysis and carried out by all the militant elements in both parties, but within the ranks of Social Democracy, was according to this group, to become the starting point for a new beginning for the working-class movement in a renewed Social Democratic Party.</p><p>The discussion of these three groups in particular, with – and inside – the Social Democratic Party, after the initially strong illegal movement in Germany had been broken up or driven into isolation by the Gestapo, was, to begin with, one of the most significant motive forces in the ideological development which took place during the Hitler period. The discussion centred at first on the causes of the catastrophe, the reasons for Fascism and for the failure of the Republic and of democracy, but the significance of experiences during the period of illegality and in exile soon became more important. Generally speaking, these experiences led to a rethinking and concretisation of the conceptions of Socialism, which nevertheless corresponded in essence to the general framework of the ideas for which the Party Executive had been trustee when it went into exile.</p><p>An initial radicalisation, which found expression in the Prague Manifesto of J934, and which was fairly general, although it arose from very different premises, rapidly gave way to a more sober frame of mind. Even though a reaction against the belief in democracy could be detected at first, experience of the dictatorship soon produced the conviction that democracy not only provided Mm most favourable basis for carrying on the struggle, but was also the essential precondition for Socialism. The victory of Nazism, for which the political split in the working class had been an essential precondition, posed afresh the problem of the attitude to be adopted towards Communism. Encouraged and strengthened by the Popular Front policy of the Comintern the desire for co-operation with the Communists grew among some Social Democrats. But the frightful waves of terror which swept the Soviet Union from 1934 to 1938, the reckless struggle for power by the Communists in the Spanish Civil War and, particularly, the Treaty between Hitler and Stalin in August 1939, eventually shattered all the illusions which had been nourished on the similarity between many of the traditional political formulations of the two parties.</p><p>The experiences with regard to the Soviet Union and its subsidiary organisations were strengthened by the experience of a functioning and firmly rooted democracy in the USA, and more especially in Britain which, after the collapse of France in the summer of 1940,withstood the storm completely alone, but completely unbowed. The importance of this experience was further reinforced by the fact that there existed in Britain a powerful Labour Party which, without being Marxist, possessed a clear sense of purpose and which, the longer it continued, was evidently more and more approaching the attainment of power. All these factors confirmed the traditional outlook of the Party. But for the further development of its programme the greatest significance lay in the fact that in the course of the world economic crisis economic methods had been devised which made it possible, in the first place, to stop the spread of unemployment and then to pursue a policy of full employment.</p><p>Illegality and emigration had, in the early years, still further deepened the split in the Socialist movement. In 1938 an attempt, under Austrian auspices, to unite the Social Democratic forces still failed. Not until the spring of 1941 was the "Union of German Socialist Organisations in Great Britain" formed in London where, owing to the experiences of the war, a considerable number of emigrés had congregated. This was a working group confined to Britain and composed of "Sopade", together with the ISK, SAP and New Beginning groups. Although emigrés in the rest of the world, and particularly in the United States and Sweden, made their contribution to the development of Socialist ideas, most of the developments took place in Britain where contact with the Labour Party, the Fabian Society and the trade unions had a fruitful effect. The fact that complete co-operation was quickly developed after the collapse of the Third Reich between the London "Union", under the leadership of Hans Vogel and then of Erich Ollenhauer, and the rebuilt Party organisation inside Germany under Kurt Schumacher, and the fact that all the old groups disappeared, had a decisive effect in determining the character of the new Social Democratic Party after 1945. Thus it was possible for the experiences of the period since 1933 to have an immediate effect on the newly formed Party. The consolidation of the guiding principles of democratic Socialism and the recognition of possibilities for their achievement, which were new in part, were decisive for the Party's policy.</p><p>The Social Democratic Party found its principal task: in the ideological field in meeting the challenge of Communism. The demand for the creation of a united working-class party, which found apparent justification in the tragic experience of the split in the working-class movement under the Weimar Republic, was taken up by the Communists when they became aware of their own hopeless unpopularity. Only the transfer of as many Social Democrats as possible to the Communist camp could give them, at any rate temporarily, the appearance of a mass party. But the democratic and anti-Communist traditions of Social Democracy were against this and they were still further strengthened by the barbarous object lesson provided by the Soviet occupying power and its German helpmates. In the Soviet Occupation Zone itself this refusal could not obtain a hearing, particularly because in the early stages there were still may illusions about the true character of Communist policy, which was welcomed by many as a liberation after the terror of the Hitler period. Thus the forced incorporation of the Social Democrats into the Communist Party apparatus, only thinly disguised as the Socialist Unity Party of Germany (SED), was carried out in the sphere of influence of the Red Army. In the Western zones of occupation and in Berlin the rejection of unification was practically unanimous. There, there were insufficient opportunities for interference by the Soviet representatives and the Social Democratic movement under the energetic and determined leadership of Kurt Schumacher had been rapidly organised on an independent basis. At the same time, however, the struggle against Bolshevism had from the beginning in Western Germany a complement of equal importance and of basically the same significance, in the struggle for the lightening and removal of the occupation regime, for the reconstruction and eventually the unification of Germany.</p><p>Schumacher had already played a part under the Weimar Republic, as a member first of the Württemberg Landtag and then of the Reichstag and was connected with the group of young Members of Parliament like Leber and Mierendorff, to whom a rethinking of the attitude towards the State and the nation appeared urgently necessary. His doctoral thesis entitled "The Struggle over the Attitude towards the State in German Social Democracy" in 1926 was devoted to this theme. Steeled by suffering in a decade of confinement in various concentration camps and grown to be a personality of exceptional force, Schumacher was the right person, in a way that no one else was, to give form and strength in the new situation to the main lesson of the Weimar Republic. The Republic, and with it Social Democracy, had foundered because they had not succeeded in becoming a convincing embodiment of the future of Germany. After 1945 it was essential to make the Social Democratic Party the recognised, powerful spokesman of the nation, not in a nationalistic, but in a humanistic and political sense of the word. Schumacher's basic belief and conviction was that the national, the democratic and the Socialist idea were one and the same. This has provided the central theme of Social Democratic policy since 1945, which, in this form and with this emphasis, was new.</p><p>Two factors, apart from defence against Bolshevism and full support for the independence and unity of Germany, characterised the struggle which raged around this central idea. The Western Allies Of the Second World War had also learnt from the past the lesson that it was worth while to make timely concessions. But because of the general situation, these concessions were mainly made to the conservative and reactionary forces. Secondly, experience with Fascism and Bolshevism, as well as economic developments, had placed on the agenda the necessity of a supra-national policy of European co-operation and the question arose as to how the struggle for the equality, unity and Socialist reconstruction of Germany was to be related to this.</p><p>It is not possible within the scope of this study to describe the controversy over these problems. It is sufficient to say that it absorbed to a considerable extent the attention of the Social Democratic forces which were simultaneously giving expression to newly consolidated and newly discovered beliefs. Two problems had been, prior to 1933, if not exactly controversial, at least not sufficiently clarified, namely the relationship to the State and nationalisation.</p><p>Experience of Soviet dictatorship has made it clear that Socialism cannot be achieved by means of any sort of dictatorship whatsoever. Modem means of domination, both military and in the realm of propaganda, enable a centralised dictatorship to attain a degree of hitherto unknown stability. The tremendous development of the means of production in recent decades has produced a society composed of many more different strata than would be compatible with the principle of the attainment of Socialism through a united party of those who possess none of the means of production. All types of function in society have become specialised to a degree which appears to render quite illusory the idea of a withering away of the State after a period of transition. It is, therefore, obvious that a Socialist order of society is inseparably bound up with the existence of a democratic political system containing several political parties independent of one another.</p><p>There has also been a considerable development with regard to the problem of socialisation since the debates on the State of the future and the discussions on socialisation under the Weimar Republic. It had become clear that it was not so much property relationships which would be decisive, as the power to control the economy. Here again the example of the Soviet Union had shown beyond doubt that the foundation of Socialism is not laid merely by the abolition of private ownership of the means of production, but that the problem of control is the crucial one. The transfer of the means of production from private to State ownership can bring about the democratisation of the economy only to the extent that the State itself is democratically organised. Just as the State-run war economy of the First World War had led to methods of economic planning which in the Soviet Union were then extended to a system of centralised total planning, so in connection with the world economic crisis of 1929 and in the Second World War there came into existence an instrument of democratic planning which made possible a more concrete conception of socialisation. The experiments in economic planning since the end of the First World War had shown that total planning involves dangerous frictional difficulties and a rapid loss of responsibility and initiative, because the complicated machinery consisting of countless highly specialised branches of production, with the unpredictable accidents which may occur in it, eludes centralised planning. But it had also proved that the requirements of detailed planning of all economic operations are, above all, at variance with the true aim of Socialism, namely, the freeing of society as a whole, equally with its individual members, from the fetters of economic dependence. It is also impossible under existing technical conditions to have regard in total planning to the changing requirements of consumers. The only possibility, therefore, is overall planning combined with the preservations of a market economy.</p><p>With the means at the disposal of modem economies it is possible to determine the general direction of the desired economic development with the aid of a Budget which sets out the economic premises as well as the quantitative relationships between the different objectives of the plan. According to whether it is desired to raise or lower the amount of purchasing power, the level of taxation and social service expenditure can be determined by State action and the amount of investment can be planned by means of credit policy, public investment and, if necessary, direct controls. Public ownership is necessary in those branches of the economy in which it is not otherwise possible to achieve the general aims of economic policy, either because of their unprofitability or because of resistance on the part of the owners; in those branches which, like the basic industries, represent a dangerous concentration of power in private hands; in those, like transport or atomic power, where, because of their structure, nothing other than public control is conceivable. Although it appeared at first as though a controversy would arise in connection with this policy of socialisation in the narrower sense between the supporters of nationalisation and the supporters of a co-operative economy, it rather seems to have become clear by now that, corresponding to the technical economic circumstances, national or co-operative or municipal ownership may be equally suitable.</p><p>This policy of economic planning and full employment requires, at least as long as there is no surplus of commodities, to be complemented by a social policy which aims at ensuring the health and maintenance, by the efforts of society as a whole, of those who are either wholly or partially disabled. Yet this alone does not achieve the true aim of socialisation, namely, the transfer of economic power from the hands of the few to the whole of society organised in the democratic State. Initially, it makes little difference to the wage and salary earners whether the managers of their places of work are private capitalists, directors of companies or officials, either of the State or of other organisations. A person who is ordered about at work cannot be a free and responsible citizen of the State. This raises the necessity of trade union participation both in the internal affairs and in the external relations of the enterprise. On this issue the trade unions have carried on and are still carrying on a bitter and still by now means wholly successful struggle. But all these measures can only have their full effect when everyone is given the opportunity fully to develop his own personality and to participate in public life. This requires the cessation of all cultural privilege and the reorganisation of the opportunities for education and culture in accordance with the enormous development of the intellectual and scientific basis of modern society.</p><p>The declaration issued by the reconstituted Socialist International, in Frankfort in July 1951, which contained a re-formulation of the aims of Social Democracy, reflected to the considerable extent the ideas of the German Party. The achievement of a social order based on social justice,, improved welfare, freedom and world peace is the aim. Political democracy and full employment are its indispensable preconditions. What was new in this declaration, besides the extremely sharp differentiation from Communism, lay in the importance now attached to the means by which Socialism is to be achieved and the explicit recognition of the differing personal convictions on which it can be based. For the first time, this last element, which had long been present in practice in German Social Democracy, attained, as it were, theoretical recognition, and the old question whether the Social Democratic Party was or was not "Marxist" began to be pointless. This gave expression to the fact that the basis of the Party was no longer to be found in a philosophical system which provided valid principles in every sphere. The Party had abandoned the escape from practice into theory, which was an inheritance of German history and especially of the absence of a bourgeois revolution, and had come to resemble the Anglo-Saxon type of party. This clearly also involved the abandonment of the traditional type of programme. If democratic Socialism is an international movement to which all Socialists belong, irrespective of whether they base their convictions on the results of Marxist analysis or any other form of social analysis or on religious or humanitarian grounds, it is obviously no longer possible to provide a basic programme in the old sense. The basic programme must then be replaced by something on which the representatives of all these trends are united. An all-embracing philosophically-based interpretation having been abandoned, the points of practical policy then emerge from these commonly accepted principles.</p><p>From the declaration of the Socialist International of 2 July, 1951, the road leads uninterruptedly to the Action Programme of the Social Democratic Party adopted at the Conference at Dortmund on 28 September, 1952. In the new situation it was natural that problems of foreign policy should be given a prominent place, and that passionate arguments were mainly confined to these questions, while everything else was dealt with in an unemotional and sober spirit. The experiences of the preceding two decades found full expression. Belief in democracy and a decisive rejection of Communism went without saying. Economic aims were no longer dealt with merely by general phrases, but by a discussion of increasing production as a means of raising the standard of living, a just distribution of income, a national investment programme and a policy of full employment. The Action Programme combined the demand for the socialisation of the basic industries with a demand for the maintenance and utilisation of the market mechanism and competition between individual enterprises. Special attention was directed to the part to be played by the co-operatives as self-help organisations of consumers or producers in restoring competition, particularly in agriculture and home crafts. There followed an outline of a social housing policy and a fiscal policy, including a consolidation and simplification of legislation and relief to smaller and middle incomes. The programme closed with a demand for strict unification of all branches of social welfare and their expansion into a full social plan, together with demands in the field of cultural policy.</p><p>Without the membership having had an opportunity for thorough discussions either before or after the launching of the new programme, the Social Democratic Party went straight into the Bundestag election of 1953. Its result seemed suddenly to reveal the fact that everything was not well. At first attempts were made to find the reasons solely in the German situation and particularly in the problems of foreign policy. Some expressed the view that the Party's rejection of rearmament had not been sufficiently clear and uncompromising, whilst others were of the opinion that the Party had behaved too radically and had, therefore, not been able to win the necessary confidence of the electors. Actually, when one looks at the development of other Socialist parties one sees that things are also going badly in countries where military problems and internal disputes about Marxism and with the Communists are of no practical significance. The causes cannot therefore be confined to Germany.</p><p>At the end of the Second World War, before the East-West conflict reached its full intensity, it appeared to many people as though all opponents of Socialism had disappeared with Nazism and Fascism, as though it would attain power at least in Europe and the British Commonwealth, after an irresistible victory march, as the crowning principle and panacea of an epoch. It seemed as though all the thinking had already been done, as though it was now only a matter of translating the demands of Socialism into practice. But it was soon shown - and in Germany first of all - how unfavourable the situation really was for Socialism.</p><p>An important element in Socialism is the belief in progress. Socialism is imbued with the conviction that it is possible and, indeed, necessary consciously to develop and to improve the condition of man. But the world today, in so far as it reflects at all on anything beyond the immediate things, is obsessed by a deep mistrust of the future of society, of mass society. It is true that the enormous and rapid progress of the natural sciences and of technology are undeniable, but every new discovery brings with it new methods of tyranny and destruction, and the very possibility, which clearly exists today, of consciously moulding even society itself, frightens many people away from trying to do so, because it seems to them to be impossible without a significant reduction in freedom.</p><p>Moreover, the world of today is held in suspense by the conflict between two non-Socialist powers. In the United States there is no politically significant Socialist Party, and nothing indicates that there will ever be one in the European sense. At the same time, many Americans regard Socialism as their enemy even in those matters in which the aims of American policy, both internal and external, coincide with those of Socialism. The Soviet Union on the other hand disgraces the true aims of Socialism by its brutal terror and its ruthless subordination of all its subjects to the interests of the ruling bureaucracy; it misuses and discredits the name of Socialism. To this must be added the fact that under the conditions of the present economic boom throughout the world, which is based on the one hand on enormous expenditure on armaments, particularly since the beginning of the Korean war, and on the other on the huge demand on the part of the former colonial countries to enable them to catch up with industrialisation, capitalism once again appears to many people to be a thoroughly satisfactory economic system. A whole generation has never known a capitalist economic crisis, but has, on the other hand, known the restrictions and compulsion of a war economy. To this must be added the fact that a considerable proportion of the points in the original programme - universal suffrage, improvement of working conditions, extensive interference by the State in economic life in the interest of society as a whole - have been accomplished, without the Socialist order of society appearing to have come appreciably nearer.</p><p>Many of these factors operate particularly strongly in Germany, especially the discredit cast upon Socialism by Communism and the sharp contrast between apparent capitalist prosperity and the scarcity economy of the rationing system, described by hostile propaganda as characteristic of a planned economy. The East-West conflict did not only have incomparably more far-reaching consequences for Germany than for any other country in Europe since it led to the country's division, it also led to interference by the American occupation forces to a degree unknown elsewhere. While the British Government in the early days treated Germany largely as a side-show in international politics, the occupation policy of the United States in many respects rendered a democratisation of the economy more difficult and encouraged the reactionary forces in many ways.</p><p>The Social Democratic Party, thrown entirely on its own resources for its effectiveness and its propaganda, would have required more than ever the full and effective activity of all its members in the common struggle. But the fight on two fronts made adequate theoretical development more difficult and simultaneously concealed for a long time the fact that in the last analysis the new knowledge only reached a small part of the membership. In the energetic struggle for power which the Party, under the dynamic leadership of Kurt Schumacher, waged anew since 1949 the basic principles laid down in 1946 remained generally unaltered and insufficient attention was paid to much that concerned the people of the post-war period in the new situation. Experiences gained, for example, by the Labour Party in Britain in carrying out its 1945 programme, and the disappointments which they suffered, were only seriously [considered] by a very small group. Scarcely had the Korean crisis placed in the foreground a new problem – that of military defence against Communism – and apparently brought the chance of the reunification of Germany enticingly near, though at the same time taking still further away than had already been the case the possibility of an independent Socialist policy based on Europe and the Commonwealth and standing between the great power blocs, when Schumacher’s death robbed the Party not only of its popular leader, but also of a personality whose strength and drive had partly made up for the inability of the membership since 1945 to recover ideological clarity, which was bound to express itself indirectly in a failure to inspire the general public.</p><p>The surprising victory of the Christian Democratic Party in the general election of 6 September, 1953, appeared at first to inaugurate attempts at fundamental clarification. A few months later, there was, in fact, launched a theoretical periodical under the tile “The New Society”. But it soon appeared that the old handicaps were still, to some extent, operative. In particular, the intense concentration of the Party’s forces and its efforts, especially among the rank and file on foreign policy, on the struggle against re-militarisation and for the reunification was not only the Party’s most important objective, but was really a condition sine qua non of a Socialist policy in Germany. Indeed, it seemed even as though a part of the new lessons learned since 1933 had vanished from the Party’s consciousness. Internal groupings on the “Left” and “Right”, which had been thought to be forgotten long ago, began once again to stand out in opposition to one another. This occurred at a time when the failures in foreign policy and sterility in internal policy of the ruling Christian Democrats provided the Party with wide openings for attack. Instead of making use of this situation criticism was largely directed against the Party itself, although the actual premises for the old opposition between Right and Left had really disappeared long ago.</p><p>It became apparent that in the existing circumstances the Social Democratic Party would not be in a position to take the seat of government by storm, but would need time, patience and constant single-mindedness. Under the level-headed and prudent leadership of Eric Ollehauer, a certain degree of clarity began to break through. The outward expression of this development was that the substance of the Action Programme adopted in 1952 at Dortmund, in spite of a number of additions and amendments, some of them important, remained unaltered at the next Party Conference in Berlin in 1954, and aroused no great discussion among the members. This was not the result of any intellectual inertia, but of the fact that people were agreed about the points laid down in the programme. How, however, there arose the necessity of focussing attention on new developments and of applying an order of priority to the problems which required solution. Although the latter question could clearly only be dealt with in the light of the circumstances prevailing in each particular case, attention was principally directed, apart from the primary problem of German unity, to those tasks which arose out of atomic energy, what is called “automation”, the rise of the former colonial peoples and the preservation of peace. It was largely with these quotations that the Conference in Munich in 1956 had to concern itself.</p><p>Human development and the opportunities open to man have acquired in our time the characteristic of moving with exceptionally rapid acceleration and even by leaps and bounds. Atomic energy and automation raise the productive potential of human society to an unheard of degree and at the same time threaten it, to an extent hitherto undreamt of, with dangers both to man’s very existence and to social freedom. Contact and conflicts with highly developed industrial countries have act in motion the peoples of Asia and Africa and created an international problem which is scarcely less serious than the East-West conflict. Co-operation with the underdeveloped countries which, on account of their experiences with capitalist imperialism and the need for rapid industrialisation, are in many ways moving in a Socialist direction, and the planning of the powerful new productive forces for the good of mankind, are tasks which Socialism cannot refuse to carry out, which indeed harmonise with its innermost nature. The same is also true of the task, which today, in the era of hydrogen bombs and inter-continental missiles, is necessarily of primary importance to all peoples, that of the preservation of peace.</p><p>Generally speaking, the basic aims of the Social Democratic Party, like those of international Socialism, have remained unchanged since the beginning: the attainment of freedom, welfare and security for all, and the "classless society", not only on a national, but also on an international scale. The decisive method of attaining this aim has also remained the same: the power to control the economy must be removed from the hands of a privileged minority and be entrusted to society as a whole. If a few decades ago the public ownership of the means of production appeared to some as a panacea, to others as an empty formula, practice, particularly since the last world economic crisis, has yielded and further developed methods of attaining Socialist aims. This process of developing techniques of economic planning and a policy of full employment naturally lacks the power of inspiration, particularly in the present situation which, from a power-political and psychological point of view, is unfavourable and admits the acute dangers which today threaten the existence of mankind from all sides. If formerly the way to a Socialist society seemed relatively simple, it has long been shown to be long and wearisome, and to require far more than the abolition of private ownership of the means of production. To advance in this situation demands time, patience and unflagging energy. The vital ideological task is to understand, apply and develop the means of attaining Socialism, while at the same time continually rediscovering its relevance to an ever more rapidly changing society and a continually shifting international situation. This task cannot be solved once and for all. The recognition that it must continuously be tackled afresh in order to provide purpose and direction to the political struggle as a whole and in detail, is in itself an ideological development which German Social Democracy shares with international Socialism.</p><p>It has found its expression in the Frankfort Declaration of the Socialist International adopted in July 1951.</p></body></text></TEI>