<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Great Britain</title>
         <author>Hugh Gaitskell</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>24 December 1955</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.V, No. 52-53</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
<p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The first half of the twentieth century was a period of more rapid and more extensive political, social and economic change than any previous fifty years in history. The collapse of three great dynasties - the Hapsburgs, the Romanoffs, and the Hohenzollerns, the rise of totalitarian Communism in Russia and China, the swift ascent of the United States to commercial and military pre-eminence, the transformation and relative decline in world influence of the British Empire, the outbreak of a new nationalism in Asia and the Middle East - these are only some of the developments which have completely altered the pattern of international relations since 1900. In the field of technology - electricity, aeronautics, the petrol engine, the new synthetic materials, electronics, and finally nuclear physics have revolutionised both the economies of nation states and the nature of the trade between them. And accompanying all this has been a significant if less sensational change in the structure of societies and in the status and power of the different groups within them.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In Russia and China the old feudal and bourgeois classes have either been destroyed or are on the way to extinction; in their place new ruling classes, or at least groups, enjoying new privileges, are emerging, which exercise in many respects a power oven more absolute and ruthless. In the democratic countries of the West a slower, more continuous and different process has taken place. The social barriers have crumbled; the old inequalities have greatly diminished, but this has resulted not from the extermination of the previous dominant classes, but through more gradual changes in the distribution of property and income, which in turn can be ascribed partly to war and inflation, partly to the crowing political power of the masses.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the face of such a remarkable transformation, one does not need to be a historical materialist to conclude that there must also have been major developments in the field of ideas. It would be astonishing if it were not so. But in the particular and quite small corner of that field with which I am concerned in this chapter - Socialist thought in Britain - there is a special reason for such a change. For one of the most outstanding developments in Britain in this period has been the rise to success and power of the Labour movement itself, in the course of which many immediate objectives put forward by the Socialists of fifty years ago have been achieved, and fair progress made on the road to other mom ultimate goals. This progress has itself called forth a more or less continual reappraisal. Moreover in Britain the course to be followed was never charted too far into the future, “We'll see how we go” - a favourite phrase of a highly influential Socialist, Mr Herbert Morrison - reflects the general view that you can always look a little way ahead, but not too far, and that only as you move on will the picture become sufficiently clear to make plans which are realistic enough to be of value. This approach acquired special importance when the Labour Party came to exercise the responsibility of government, and was thus compelled to face up to the detailed problems of making and administering laws.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The history of thought is a continuous process; it is never easy to pick on any one date and say of a particular theme, “This is when it began”. But looking back half a century to find a starting point for this essay, one can see that a little earlier - in the 1880’s and the 1890's - there was a quite exceptional blossoming of new Socialistic ideas and activities in Britain.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Karl Marx provided some, but by no means the most influential of those ideas. His only direct disciples in Britain were the members of the Social Democratic Federation - a body which never had more than a few thousand members, soon underwent internal schisms, never made much impact on the trade unions, and was overwhelmingly defeated in the political arena. Such influence us Marx had at this time was indirect, and extremely limited. The sociological theory of determinism and the role of the class conflict in history has never much appealed to the British. They are too shy of general ideas, too practical in their reforming zeal to appreciate the solace of an “inevitability” doctrine. As for the complex analysis of trade fluctuation, underconsumption, etc., set out in the second and third volumes of “Das Kapital”, this was beyond the comprehension of all but a handful of patient scholars, only some of whom found it convincing.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Undoubtedly the Marxian doctrine which had the greatest vogue both at that time and since was the theory of surplus value. Perhaps it was convenient that this was stated in Volume I, and before the reader was chocked by the turgidity of Marx’s style. Even so, one would not have found, outside a narrow circle, many to explain it in full.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Moreover, what stuck in people’s minds was not his scientific theory of how the prices of different goods were determined (the fallacies in which have been frequently exposed), but a moral principle often confused with it about the distribution of income. This was the essentially simple notion that the existence of income from property or “unearned” income was the root of all social evil, implying as it did that part of the workers’ reward was being filched from him in so-called surplus value. Beyond that there was no clear or widely accepted doctrine. The deduction from these premises, that the owners or property - the capitalist class - must be expropriated and that this could only be done by a revolution, was not acceptable in Britain except to a tiny minority.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">If one reason for the small impact Made by Marx was the impatience of the British with too much theory, another was the importance of Trade Unionism. In the first half of the 19th century, the Trade Unions, suppressed, persecuted, operating at a time of intense industrial depression and before the arrival of political democracy, took part from tine to time in revolutionary activities, but after the collapse of Chartism in the 1840’s, they settled down and became organisations for securing better working conditions and the highest wage rates they could squeeze from employers. They enhanced their value, when this was possible, by restricting entry; they developed the friendly society side of their work; they built up their funds.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Although in the last two decades of the century, now and more militant unions of unskilled workers were being formed, the dominant influence at this time was still that of the older and more cautious craft unions. Their members were far too absorbed by getting immediate practical results to be in the least accessible to revolutionary theories. Indeed the question at that time was not whether or not to “go revolutionary”, but whether to continue the policy of getting desirable changes by pressure upon and even alliance with the Liberal Party, or whether the Trade Unions should sot up a political party of their own.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There had already been formed an Independent Labour Party to run candidates for Parliament which was a long way to the left of most of the Trade Unions, both on the issue of tactics (as its existence and name implied), and also on policy. But it was an equally long way to the right of the SDF and the Marxists. Its Socialism - for it was a Socialist party - was derived far more from the Methodist Church and a Christian approach than from Continental revolutionaries. Its members shared, of course, the deep sense of social injustice which all Socialists have in common. But its conception of the good society was one in which, freed from the evil institutions of capitalism, the competitive system of private enterprise and the search for the maximum profit, men would work together for the good of all in Christian love and a true spirit of cooperation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The members of the ILP however were by no means wholly concerned with ultimate objectives. These came into the picture, but there was also the immediate programme.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Keir Hardie, their leader, himself a man of saintly character with an essentially Christian outlook, was absolutely clear that if the ILP, was to have any hope of support in the Unions and in the country generally, it must concentrate on bread and butter issues which mattered to people then and there.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In this he was completely at one with the third element in the new socialism of this time - the Fabians. For while the Trade Unions offered the solid and well-organised base of the British Labour Movement, and the ILF provided both the emotional inspiration and the driving force, the most important intellectual contribution came from the members of this Society. They were a group or middle-class men and women who, though especially interested in ideas, did not hold themselves aloof from political action, but on the contrary, under the guiding influence of Sydney and Beatrice Webb, worked closely both with the Unions and the ILP. Their influence upon Labour policy in Britain in the last fifty years has been substantial, and for that reason some account must be given of their point of view.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Full adult male suffrage had only just been conceded, and few people realised its profound significance. But the Fabians understood it very clearly; they saw from the start the now possibilities of getting results by democratic political action. They did not by any means limit this to national politics, but on the contrary were at pains to emphasise the importance of securing power and influence in local government - the structure of which had also only recently been modernised.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">They accepted as an inevitable feature of democratic methods the necessity of gradualism: votes could only be won by persuasion, and persuasion would take time. They were anxious to make it plain that their various reform projects, though valuable, were not in any way revolutionary. In his contribution to the Fabian Essays, Sydney Webb made great play with the argument that capitalism was already changing to Socialism, and that many Socialist institutions were already in existence - a conclusion he reached only by defining Socialism as almost any form of state intervention. This particular doctrine of “inevitability” was inspired less by historical determinism than by a desire to make Socialism seem “respectable”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">No doubt the special contribution of the Fabians lay in their acceptance of democratic gradualism, in their insistence on practical proposals, and in their detailed studies on a large number of social reforms. But something must also be said of their views on ultimate objectives. What sort of a Socialism did they preach?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Like so many contemporaries, including Liberals like Lloyd George and other much further to the left, they were greatly influenced by Henry George – the author of “Progress and Poverty” – who in turn had taken many of his ideas from the British classical economists, John Stuart Mill and David Ricardo. These earlier writers had argued that the payment of rent was a ‘surplus’ payment to the owners of land, which could be stopped without affecting the supply. It was not a payment for any active function at all. As John Stuart Mill put it, “They- the landlords - grow richer as it were in their sleep, without working, risking or economising. (1) [“Principles of Political Economy”, 1921 Edition, p.818”] Moreover, as the population increased, because of the scarcity of land, rents increased too - the capital value of land rising with them. Thus not only was something paid for no real service, but the ‘something’ went up in value all the time.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The conclusion which Henry George drew from this analysis was that the community should in effect appropriate the rents by means of a ‘single’ tax on land. The same idea appears in the pages of the Fabian Essays. But its application was extended. Other unearned incomes, it was claimed, were also really “rent” in the sense that a reduction in them would not affect the supply. This, it was suggested, was true of at least some high salaries which were the result of a differential between the more highly and the less highly skilled, analogous to the rent paid for better land. It was also true of capital equipment. Thus the Fabians persuaded themselves, on the basis of what they thought was sound economics, that Henry George’s argument about the nature of rent could be extended to other forms of unearned income. “What the achievement of Socialism involves economically,” wrote George Bernard Shaw, “is the transfer of rent from the class which now appropriates it to the whole people. Rent being that part of the product which is individually unearned, this is the only equitable method of disposing of it.” (2) [“Fabian Essays”, 1931 Edition, p.167]</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While the Fabian economic case for Socialism was largely based on doctrines which they took over from the classical economists, and which, as I shall later explain, would not be accepted to-day, it must be said that they had no very clear ideas of how the transfer of rent to the whole people must be carried out. The Fabians believed that there was very considerable scope for municipal ownership, and they saw in this the extension of something already familiar, which it would be easier for the electorate to accept. They favoured “the transfer to the community of such industrial capital as can be conveniently managed socially”. They were for nationalisation, but at this stage no detailed plans had been worked out.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">On compensation they were almost as vague. Some were against compensation for the former owners, except that there was to be “such relief to expropriated individuals as may seem fit to the community”. Others recognised that gradual transformation means that full compensation would have to be paid, but they expected to finance this out of a tax of rents à la Henry George. As for the problems of management in public enterprises, those, not surprisingly, were hardly envisaged at all.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It would be quite unreasonable to criticise the Fabian Socialists because their ideas on the practical problems of transition to public ownership were not always too precise. For at that time, after all, the prospect of achieving enough power to carry through such a programme was still very remote.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">More open to criticism are the economic arguments on which they based their case for Socialism. These really involved a confusion between three different questions - first whether not only rent but interest and profits too were ‘surplus’ incomes in the sense that if the payments in question were cut or abolished the supply of ‘land’, ‘capital’ and ‘risk-bearing’ would decline; secondly, whether the payment and receipt of rent, interest and profit as such was morally wrong, irrespective of the character and wealth of the recipient; and thirdly, whether the existing distribution of income and wealth among persons and classes was just.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It was a weakness of the Fabians that they tried to base their attack on inequality not so much on straightforward ethical principles, but on subtle sophisticated arguments about the supply of ‘land’ and ‘capital’, involved in the first question, which are only partly relevant to the second question, and scarcely at all to the third. Moreover the answers which they gave to the first of the three questions do not stand up very well to a critical examination. Modern economists would put the whole thing in far less absolute terms.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">For example, a distinction would be drawn between the rent of agricultural land on the one hand, which contains a large element of interest or profit (the return on the capital invested in the land to maintain or improve its productive quality - a return whose size certainly does affect the scale of investment) and ground rents in a built-up area on the other hand, which are no more than payments for space, with no element of invested capital at all.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Again, in the case of interest and profit, the differences between the short-run and the long-run effects of changes, differences between the effects which large as compared with small changes in the return have on the supply of capital, the differences between the effects of lower interest rates on saving on the one side and lower profits on risky investments on the other would all be brought out. While nobody would say that supply was everywhere responsive to changes in price, the conclusion would certainly be against building an argument for Socialism on the theory that all ‘unearned’ income were technically ‘surplus’.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Even where, as in the case of developed land, it would be accepted to-day that the rent can be regarded as a true ‘surplus’ payment in the sense that the supply of land cannot vary, modern writers would question whether this was sufficient justification for singling those particular property owners for exceptionally high taxation or even expropriation compared with other property owners. Here we encounter the confusion between ‘elasticity of supply’ and the coral justification for the income of particular individuals to which reference has already been made. No doubt if it could be assumed that all land owners were wealthy aristocrats who had inherited their property to tax them heavily might seem fair enough, but the justification would really be due to the scale of their wealth and the fact that they inherited it rather than to the type of property they owned. No such assumption can be made.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In a modern economy property is constantly changing hands.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is nothing to prevent a man switching the form in which he holds his wealth from land to bonds or securities and vice versa. The owners of developed land nowadays may include people of very different levels of wealth, insurance companies which invest the premiums paid by millions of individuals, building societies and other corporate bodies. It is impossible to justify picking on such a miscellaneous group of people for special attack.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">These are some of the logical reasons why to-day, half a century later, most British Labour writers find the idea of basing the case for taxation on the classical theory of Rent unconvincing and unsatisfactory. There is also another reason why land nationalisation - once in the forefront of the Socialist programme - has, for the time being at least, dropped out altogether. It is of course that the rent of land as a source of income is no longer anything like so important - in comparison with wages, interest and dividends - as it was once. The rapid rate of capital accumulation which has accompanied industrialisation in the twentieth century, the huge increase in the National Debt in two world wars, and finally the increase in the share of the product going to labour have between them dwarfed the significance of rent for land. At the same time the distribution of land ownership has changed. In agriculture there has been a shift from tenant farming to owner occupancy, and the very large estates have been broken up. In the towns, too, though there are still some large –‘ducal’ estates, there are fewer private and far more institutional holders.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There remains, however, one important element of truth in the Henry George-Fabian thesis. It is that most large fortunes have been accumulated not through the slow painful process of saving out of income, but by transactions involving capital profits of one kind or another. (1) [(1) The idea that there is something especially wrong about capital profits derived from land ownership compared with other capital profits cannot really be sustained. If in fact it was certain that the value of land would rise (excluding changes in the value of money), competition would drive up its price at the very start. The original owners would have had all the capital gain at the beginning. If such a rise in values is not certain, then there is a risk in holding land, as there is in holding wealth in other forms.]. This process is to some extent automatic, not only or so much because of the pressure of population on scarce resources as the classical economists conceived – but because of the slow, discontinuous but apparently inexorable tendency to inflation. Moreover the development over the years of the joint stock company and the increasing size of the business undertaking has meant that most corners of industrial shares are passive or functionless as Henry George’s landowners, and indeed far more so than the owners of agricultural land. We do not look on those who inherit a fortune criminally accumulated by their grandfathers and still invested in - say - steel shares as necessarily contributing to the economy of one country by virtue of their ownership of this sort, of inherited wealth any more than - say - the grandson of the Duke who inherits a similar fortune in the form of land in the City of London.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is another consequence of this. Those who hold that the great objection to Socialism is that the state cannot display the drive, initiative and flexibility of private business would find it hard to apply these arguments to the mere ownership of industrial shares by the state. Indeed, in the case of at least one very successful enterprise - the Anglo-Iranian, now British Petroleum Company - the British Government shareholding is simply taken for granted.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The implications of all this for Socialist policy were not really understood at the time, and have not yet worked out. All one can say of the early Fabians is that the germ of the idea was there. But there is no doubt that their main influence was felt not through their general Socialist theory, but through their work on she practical details of immediate reforms. It is for this, and for their general approach to politics, that they will be chiefly remembered.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the history of the British Trade Union and Labour Movement one can trace a certain oscillation between industrial and political action. For a period of years the greatest effort and activity is thrown into the struggle for political rights and legislative reforms; the emphasis then changes, a disillusionment with politics sets in, and the hopes of the workers become concentrated on the industrial front as trade unionism grows and becomes more militant in the fight for higher wages and bettor working conditions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Then again, perhaps after a series of strikes and lock-outs, the tempo in industry begins to flag and slowly the interest in political activity revives.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">At the end of the first decade of the twentieth century a swing of this kind took place towards industrial action. In 1906 a great advance had been achieved on the political side when no less than 29 Labour Members of Parliament were returned in the General Election. (1) [There were also 25 “Lib-Labs” who coul be expected to take the same view as the Labour Party on most things]. But although the Liberal Government of that time carried through a whole series of important social reforms, there was soon much disillusionment in the ranks of Labour. This was no doubt encouraged by the fact that prices were rising faster than wages and the standard of living of workers was falling, Trade Unionism, helped by the changes in the law introduced by the Liberal Government, developed rapidly, the tamper of the workers became bolder, and a series of major industrial conflicts took place.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While it would be a mistake to think of the loaders of the Unions themselves as being inspired by any elaborate social theories, there was certainly associated with this change a new phase in Socialist thinking which was to last for over a decade.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Whereas on the Continent the theory of industrial action was syndicalism, in Britain it took the form of and became known as Guild Socialism - its ablest and best-known thinker and exponent being a young University lecturer called G. D. H. Cole. (2) [See especially Cole, “The World of Labour” and Hoson and Orage, “National Guilds”.]</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Guild Socialism was completely different from Fabianism both in method and in ultimate objective. It rejected the Fabian thesis of winning power gradually by democratic means, regarding this as a hopeless compromise with capitalism. Instead it based itself firmly on the doctrine of the class war - a war which could only be won by revolutionary notion. Such action would come through the organised workers in industry and could not be based on the ballot box.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The goal was also different. The Guild Socialists were opposed to public ownership by the State, because they believed that this would perpetuate “the wage system”, and therefore made no fundamental difference either to the status of the worker or the economy in which he was employed. He would only be exchanging one master for another; capitalist, employers would go, but state bureaucrats would take their place, instead of this, the Guild Socialists wanted to do away with "the wage system" altogether by transferring the ownership and control of industry not to the state but to the workers organised in their trade unions. After the transfer of power, the workers would form producers’ guilds in their respective industries, whose job it would be to organise and manage production.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">These ideas were in some ways nostalgic - even conservative. They looked back to the craft guilds of middle ages before the days of modern capitalism. They resembled Robert Owen’s plans of 1834 when he had hoped through the Grand National Consolidated Trade Union that the workers would take over industry and run it themselves.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Guild Socialism also represented a revolt against the squalid struggle of a competitive economy, against the dominant role of the consumer which is really implied in all classical economic doctrine. It was certainly much influenced by John Ruskin and William Morris. In terms of political theory, the Guild Socialists rejected the supremacy of Parliament. It was only, they thought, one of a number of institutions of equal power and significance. There should also be an Assembly representing industry - the producers.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Guild Socialism was like syndicalism, anti-rational and emotional; it was expressed often in extravagant and abusive language, especially when it was criticising other Socialist but democratic doctrines, such as those of the Fabians.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The period of intense industrial activity come to an end in the early 1920's, when the post-war depression was accompanied by a series of “Lock-Outs” in which the workers were defeated, and wage-cuts imposed - the final episode being the General Strike of 1926. With the collapse of militant trade union policies, the theories of Guild Socialism, which had enjoyed a considerable vogue in the immediate post-war years, lost their appeal too</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In judging their influence on later events and ideas, a sharp distinction must be drawn between the two aspects - the emphasis on revolutionary industrial action as a method of gaining power on the one hand, and the notion of workers' control in a Socialist state on the other.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The first has been completely rejected by the non-Communist British Labour Movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Experience has shown indeed that such a strategy has no hope of success whatever, unless it is part of a wider, well thought out revolutionary plan for the seizure of power. Even so it is likely to fail unless there is already a state of economic chaos and a breakdown of the machinery of Government, and unless too the movement is led by men of the calibre and determination of Lenin and Trotsky.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">None of those conditions were at any time present in Britain. The leaders of the Unions never thought in terms of revolution at all; although there was serious unemployment, the economy was never near collapse; the power of the Government was more than adequate to defeat any attempt by the workers to ‘take over’ the factories; and finally the overwhelming majority of the people were entirely against revolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">All this, insofar as it was not apparent before, became clear at the time of the General Strike. There could not have been a more vivid illustration of the absurd ‘myth’ of syndicalism that at the right moment capitalism would of itself suddenly collapse. There could not have been a more effective exposure of its emotional, anti-rational outlook, which was in striking contrast both with the cautious planning of democratic Socialism and the ruthless logic and the professional techniques of the Bolshevists. Having been brought to the brink and seen what lay ahead, the British Labour Movement lumbered decisively away. Thereafter it became accepted that political objectives must be fought for through the Labour Party and the ballot box, while the Unions concentrated on their traditional function of improving the wages and conditions of their members.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It was not only the general strike which clarified the mind of the Labour Movement on the issue of how to try to secure power. The success of the Labour Party in increasing its numbers in the House of Commons, becoming the official opposition, and then forming a Government, brought with it a much wider understanding of the nature of parliamentary democracy, and made it scorn more and more absurd to think and talk in revolutionary terms.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This development was on the whole assisted rather than delayed by the Russian Revolution. For the Revolution represented a concrete alternative which though claimed by many to have been inevitable in Russia, made little appeal in Britain; it was followed by the establishment of the British Communist Party which catered for those who believed in revolution (so long, of course, as they were prepared to accept orders from Russia). The Labour Party from the outset has always been completely opposed to the Communist Party, and has always successfully resisted the many efforts of the latter to form a United Front. Finally the education process - the process of bringing home to people the distinction between dictatorship and democracy - was carried still further by the rise of Fascism in Europe - but of this more later.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">If the revolutionary methods involved in Guild Socialism were wholly rejected, its positive idea of more control by the workers in industry - especially in nationalised industry - remained popular. To be sure, nobody in these past thirty years has again seriously proposed that in the case of nationalisation the ownership of the assets should be vested in the workers in the industry, nor is there any talk nowadays of a separate economic parliament existing alongside the House of Commons. But the need to make out of nationalisation something more than the exchange of a public for a private employer, the importance of creating a sense of participation by the workers, the necessity at the least of full consultation with the workers - these ideas which have all become widely accepted in the Labour Movement are at least in part derived from Guild Socialism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In order to explain the effects of Guild Socialism it has been necessary to jump some years ahead. In the second decade of the twentieth century, the emphasis shifted from political to industrial action. But the outlook of the political wing was also changing. Before 1914 the Labour Party, which was almost a purely Trade Union Party and had no individual members, was not committed to a Socialist programme. Its object was solely “to organise and maintain in Parliament and in the country a political Labour Party”, Socialism was the doctrine of the ILP and the Fabians and the SDF, but only a few Labour Members of Parliament were Socialists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Great War, however, the industrial struggle and the growing influence of intellectuals like Sydney Webb led to important changes. In 1918 three decisive steps were taken. First the Party threw open its ranks to individual members organised in parliamentary and local government constituencies - in addition to those who joined through their Trade Unions. Secondly in the new constitution it was definitely laid down that the object of the Party was “to secure for the producers by hand and by brain the full fruits of their industry and the most equitable distribution thereof that may be possible upon the basis of the common ownership of the means of production and the best obtainable system of popular administration and control of each industry and service.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Thirdly the Party adopted a programme – “Labour and the New Social Order” - which was the first and in some respects the best detailed statement of the ideas of gradualist democratic Socialism to appear in Britain. This was chiefly the work of Sydney Webb; it reflected the very great influence of the Fabians upon the Labour Party. It contained amongst other proposals a deliberate policy of Full Employment through State action; big expansions in the Social Services; the nationalisation or specific industries - coal, steel, railways and life assurance; the control of prices and profits in private industry; a more progressive system of taxation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Most of these proposals, with some modification in the light of changed circumstances and of administrative experience, were to remain the policy of the Party for the next thirty years. Many of them were finally put into effect by the Labour Government of 1945-50.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The outlook of the British Labour Movement has been much influenced during the last half century by a number of university professors and lecturers. The name of G.D.H. Cole has already been mentioned as the leading exponent of Guild Socialism. Although in recent years Professor Cole has not been in such direct close personal contact with the trade union or political leaders as he was just after the first world war, he has produced during this time a very large number of books, pamphlets and articles which have naturally had a considerable influence in the Labour Movement. One cannot say that these contain or reflect one particular philosophy or set of doctrines. They constitute rather a running commentary on the economic and social problems of the time written by an extremely versatile and stimulating Socialist. As such, they played an important part in the general development of Socialist thought which is described later in the essay, even though Professor Cole himself would by no means agree with all its manifestations.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Another university professor whose writings have had a profound influence in the Labour Movement is R.H.Tawney. Somewhat older than G.D.H. Cole, far less prolific as a writer, much more of a specialist (in Economic History), Professor Tawney’s chief contributions to Socialist thought are to be found in two notable books – “The Acquisitive Society”, published in 1921, and “Equality”, published ten years later. Concerned as they both are with fundamental issues, these books provide what may be described as a double synthesis - a synthesis on the one hand between the early Fabian approach and that of the Guild Socialist, and a synthesis between the pre-1914 Socialism and the Socialism of to-day.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In “The Acquisitive Society”, Professor Tawney delivers a trenchant and passionate attack on modern capitalism iron w .at is fundamentally an ethical standpoint. His main thesis is that private property to be justified must be associated with some function, and its owner therefore performing with it and through it some task of social value, when this is not so, it is positively harmful to society, not only because of the toll involved in the income which it draws, but also because of the social conflicts created by the fact of some people receiving something for nothing. The city landlord who draws ground rents, the royalty owners, the recipients of monopoly profits are listed as the worst cases, but the ordinary company shareholder who knows nothing of the company whose shares he owns is not much better.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In a decent society, ‘functionless’ property should not be allowed at all. In any case the system by which the owners of such property exercise control over industry and enjoy the residuary profits should be abandoned. This could be done if the shareholders were given debentures or bonds in place of shares, and the control of the industries in question handed over instead to the producers and consumers. Any profits available would henceforth be used either for developing the industry, or for the benefit of consumers.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Influenced no doubt by the doctrines of Guild Socialism, Professor Tawney laid great stress upon the need to convert all forms of work in industry into ‘professions’, with the same outlook and standards and doctrine of service as the learned and liberal professions of the day. To support the argument he used the well known fact of the divorce, between ownership and management, implying that the so-called “business” interests should be, put on one side, leaving industry to be run by ‘professionals’ and ‘technicians’.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The object of nationalising” he wrote “should not be to establish any particular form of state management, but to release those who do constructive work from the control of those whose sole interest is pecuniary gain, in order that they may be free to apply their energies to the true purpose of industry, which is the provision of service, not the provision of dividends.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Professor Tawney’s book was greatly influenced both by his deeply felt faith in Christianity, and by his knowledge of economic history. His soaring criticism of modern industrialism was that its whole philosophy was completely at variance with the teachings of Christ. For it glorified the material success of the individual, it took for granted that the acquisition of wealth was a desirable end in itself, and it assumed that other members of the community could end should as means to achieve this one. Thus the whole system rested on false values.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Professor Tawney many times points cut that this attitude was comparatively new, and quite different from the doctrines accepted in the pre-capitalist era, when society to be sure was divided rigidly into different classes, but the differences in income and status did more or less correspond with different responsibilities and functions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Although his attack was concentrated on particular types of income and property, rather than on the distribution of wealth, Professor Tawney also regarded inequality as a major evil in itself. Almost casually at one point he mentions inheritance taxation as the best method of demolishing It, but in this book the subject is not pursued.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Ten years later, in “Equality”, he returned to it. The emphasis was now shifted from particular forms of property, and indeed from property as such. The attack was broadened to cover the whole of the class structure and the absurd unjustifiable inequalities which it involves. In a brilliant analysis of the causes of all this, Professor Tawney no longer ascribed those simply to property and inheritance; he showed that they were also due to differences in environment, education, and social and economic opportunities, which were themselves the result of inequality. Thus there was a vicious circle - inequality breeding inequality. The evils of such a society in terms of snobbery and false values were again forcefully brought out, and the specious arguments in favour of it torn to shreds.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">He also devoted much more attention to egalitarian policy - especially the expansion of the social services financed by progressive taxation. After disposing of the cruder objections, Professor Tawney conceded that there might be adverse effects on saving and investment if these activities were left to unrestricted private enterprise. But he concluded that in that case it was necessary for the State to stop in to ensure that they were adequate - possibly by insisting that a certain proportion of profits should be ploughed back into industry, and by the establishment of a National Investment Board to central the direction of investment.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Finally, at the end of the book, he returned to the subject of nationalisation. The treatment, however, this time more limited and more practical. Wholesale nationalisation was not really considered. The emphasis was on further control rather than ownership; the candidates for this were confined to basic industries, industries requiring to be reorganised and industries dominated by monopoly. He was not disposed to be too dogmatic about the form of ownership or control…</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“the choice between them is a matter of expediency to be decided with reference to the individual case.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This difference of emphasis, the acceptance of the ‘mixed’ economy and the greater concern with a detailed programme compared with the wider approach of 1924, was no doubt connected with the fact that the Labour Party had since then twice held office, and after the 1929 election was within 50 seats of a clear majority.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Ten years earlier, while Professor Tawney was writing “The Acquisitive Society”, a younger colleague of his - Hugh Dalton - who after studying economics at Cambridge also came to teach at the London School of Economics, had also concerned himself with the question of equality. Hugh Dalton, who was to play a notable part in the development of Labour policy and in the progress of the Party to power, who was to become one of the leaders of the Party and to hold high office himself, was fully trained in and had a real grasp of modern economic science. In this he differed not only from the older generation of Fabians, who were essentially amateurs in economics, but also from his contemporaries, G.D.H. Cole and R.H. Tawney. He also differed from them in committing himself from 1924 onwards to a career in active politics.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">His first book – “The Inequality of Incomes in Modem Communities” - published in 1920, reflects both the influence of modern economic teaching and his own concern with practical reforms. Like Professor Tawney, he vigorously attacked the traditional arguments in defence of inequality, especially those put for hard by some of his fellow economists. But his main contributions in this book were first a most penetrating analysis of the causes of the distribution of income, secondly his concentration on the distribution of income between persons - in contrast with the distribution between ‘factors of production’ - i.e. labour, capital and land-, thirdly the emphasis which he rightly placed upon the significance of inheritance, and finally his suggestions for reducing inequality by fiscal policy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As we have soon, earlier Socialist writers had been inclined to base their criticisms of capitalism on the nature of the payments made, on the wrongness of rent or interest and profits as such, which they thereby treated as the cause of inequality rather than in any analysis of why one man got mere than another. The Marxists who believed that society was rigidly divided into classes, between those who had property and lived on surplus values and those who, having no property, had to work for wages, the distinction did not matter much. And revolutionaries who desired to overthrow the system at a single blow and abolish private property in the means of production altogether, did not need to bother with the details of distribution between parsons.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The classical economists, equally, absorbed with the problem of how in a competitive individualist economy the level of rent, wages and interest came to be settled, had neglected the question of personal distribution, perhaps because it was not ‘economics’ as then understood, perhaps because subconsciously they disliked an inquiry which might challenge one of the basic assumptions of their system - the right of inheritance. The one notable exception was John Stuart Mill, whose outlook become more and more Socialist, and whose discussion of inherited wealth was described by Hugh Dalton as “his most important contribution to economic thought”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But to a modern economist who understood the nature of the pricing system, who was not hopelessly prejudiced against a market economy as such, who realised that the class structure was a great deal more complicated than the Marxists supposed, who was nevertheless shocked by the social and economic injustice which he saw around him, but being a democrat wished to proceed gradually to remove them, to such a man the realistic analysis of why some individuals were richer than other individuals was of immense importance.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It is no exaggeration to say that while some earlier writers had shown occasional glimpses of insight about the problem, Hugh Dalton was the first to publish a really comprehensive study. In doing so, he immensely clarified Socialist thinking and directed it in the right direction - away from the sterile, out-of-date, somewhat academic arguments of earlier writers, and towards the real problems confronting the practical democratic Socialism. His precise, semi-mathematical approach and a brilliantly lucid mind enabled him both to clear up the tangles surrounding the whole concept of the distribution of income; and his knowledge of modern economic theory enabled him to explain far more adequately than any earlier Socialist what actually determined the distribution of income between rent, wages, interest and profit, even though this was not the problem in which he was primarily interested.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Hugh Dalton's conclusions on the vital issue - that of personal distribution - may seem to-day almost platitudinous; that is the fate of the pioneer. What he wrote has become accepted as the true answer. The distribution of income from property was dependent on the distribution of property itself, which in turn largely revolved round the amount a man inherited. He quoted with approval the American economist, Irving Fisher, who described it - the distribution of property - as dependent on “inheritance constantly modified by thrift, ability, industry, luck and fraud”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As to the distribution of income from work, this was principally a matter, not of the amount of work done by the individual, but the different rates of pay. That they were different was of course partly due to the nature of the work, but even more because everyone did not have the same opportunities of entering occupations and professions. This in turn was due to differences in environment, education and training, themselves springing from inequalities in the income and wealth of parents. Thus one could say that the major causes of inequality really amounted to the inheritance of wealth and the educational system.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This analysis pointed the way to reform. Mr Dalton was content to leave to others the question of how equal educational opportunity could be made available to all, and himself concentrated on the subject of inheritance. Starting with the existing system of death duties - which already existed in Britain - he introduced the ideas of the Italian economist, Professor Rignano, who proposed that a distinction should be drawn between the taxation of inherited wealth which had been accumulated by the parent himself on the one hand, and of wealth which the parent had inherited from his father, and again - on yet another level - from his grandfather on the other. Hugh Dalton concluded that a system resembling this, though not identical with it, should be introduced. To counter the argument that this would be detrimental to saving, he suggested that the new tax should not be included in current revenue to be spent by the government, but should be transferred to a fund. He further proposed that the State should accept securities and land in lieu of cash when the tax was paid, and that if possible, in order to increase the total level of saving, half the income of what would thus become government property should be reinvested.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In all this he broke new ground - and it must be admitted, writing over thirty years later - that no great advance has subsequently been made. His ideas were significant not only because of their direct relationship to the Socialist goal of greater equality, but because they broke away from the doctrine that the nationalisation of industry was the sole method of advance. Mr Dalton was of course not opposed to nationalisation. He did not discuss it. But what he was really suggesting was that there could be an advance to greater equality via public ownership without necessarily involving public control - an idea peculiarly interesting if there were to be for a long period an economy with a large measure of private enterprise.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While Professor Tawney and Mr Dalton were analysing the true causes of inequality and suggesting the kind of policy which would be necessary to bring about a fairer distribution of wealth and income, ideas on nationalisation were also beginning to change.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As has been mentioned, Professor Tawney discussed in 1931 the tests by which to decide whether a particular industry should be brought under public control. Interest had thus already moved from the general case from wholesale nationalisation to the specific arguments for transferring particular industries to public ownership. The main reason for this was the advance of the Labour Party to political power, involving as it did the recognition that only a United number of candidates for nationalisation could be included in an Election Programs for one Parliament, and that it was necessary to convince the electorate that there were good reasons for making the change in the case of these particular industries.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Professor Tawney had suggested three particular tests to apply - Were the industries basic? Were they monopolies?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Did they require to be re-organised? In the twenty years which followed, during which the Party was first of all working on its detailed plans for nationalising a particular group of industries, and later putting through the necessary legislation, these three tests continued to be applied - though others were also added.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Thus the case for nationalising coal mining as first that it was a basic industry, and one on which the economic future of Britain depended; secondly the very bad state of the relations between the coal owners and the miners; thirdly the urgent need for a big programme of capital expenditure which private enterprise, because of the depressed state of the industry before the war, would be most unlikely to carry out; and finally the necessity of a complex reorganisation in the structure of the industry. This last argument was particularly stressed during the Election campaign of 1945, and in the debate during the passage of the Nationalisation Bill. It was powerfully supported by a technical report published before the end of the war by a group of mining engineers. They had been appointed as a committee under the chairmanship of Sir Charles Bend by the Coalition Government. Their conclusions were that the collieries must be grouped into much larger units, and that extensive technical changes in mining methods must be far more widely introduced. They did not, of course, recommend nationalisation. But the Labour Party argued forcefully that only under nationalisation was there any chance of, their plans being carried out quickly.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Similar arguments - the need for a change in structure - creating larger units of administration and production in order to achieve greater efficiency - were also used in the case of the electricity and gas industries. These were already in part publicly owned - by municipalities. But the case for ‘tidying up’, and for having larger units of administration embracing both private and municipal undertakings was here again made out by a committee of enquiry under the chairmanship of Lord Macgowan. In electricity distribution as with coal, the committee (which reported in 1937) did not recommend nationalisation, but again the structural changes which it proposed could have been brought about - if at all - only very slowly without it. The transfer of both municipal and private undertakings to national ownership enabled the change to be carried through at once. As for gas, here a committee under the chairmanship of Sir Geoffrey Hoyworth - like Lord Macgowan an one of Britain’s leading industrialists - reporting after the end of the war, actually proposed nationalisation - again on the grounds that greater efficiency called for complete structural change.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the case of transport the case for nationalisation was partly that it was a basic industry, partly that pooling could produce greater efficiency on the railways and in road transport respectively, and partly that the long drawn out problem of road versus rail could only be properly solved by coordination under public ownership. No special committee reported just before or after the war, but the industry as a whole had been the subject in the inter-war years of a whole series of investigations. Here too, although no proposals for nationalisation were made, many of the arguments led in that direction. Intellectually, resistance to nationalisation was greatly weakened.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The nationalisation of the steel industry was put forward loss because of the need for reorganisation - this had already been carried out to a large extant under private ownership - and more because it was a basic industry requiring heavy investment which was also a tighter controlled monopoly. The method of nationalisation in this case meant that the units of control were left more or less untouched - the Nationalised Corporation being in effect a large public shareholding company. In the short period of its existence the Corporation did, not greatly interfere with the running of the individual firms, but the fact that only had to be paid on the bonds issued in compensation to the shareholders undoubtedly saved the industry substantial sums, while it was also in a position to raise fresh capital much more cheaply than under private enterprise.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While these specific efficiency arguments came forward, the general egalitarian arguments originally associated with nationalisation fell into the background. There were two reasons for this. One was, of course, the advance to equality by other means - notably taxation and the development of the social services.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The other reason was that when an individual industry was nationalised, full and fair compensation was paid to shareholders. Thus there was no longer any question of the transfer involving the disappearance of income from property: all that happened was the exchange of a larger uncertain income in the form of dividends for a smaller fixed income in the form of interest. And although the nationalisation of individual industries with compensation makes same contribution to greater equality insofar as it eliminates all possibility of capital gains and large private fortunes, and also has some restraining influence on the level of top salaries, these are small changes compared with complete confiscation, or even the early Fabian idea of paying some shareholders small compassionate allowances.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The Labour Party accepted the doctrine of full compensation because this was the only possible course compatible with a gradualist and democratic approach. It is impossible to justify confiscating the property of particular classes of owners without regard to their wealth but simply because they hold shares in the industries which happen to be selected for nationalisation. And in fact no party which proposed to act in such an arbitrary way would have much prospect of being elected to power in Britain.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Another earlier and more general, if rather sophisticated argument for public ownership which was used more frequently in connection with the nationalisation of particular industries was the contribution made by nationalisation towards successful economic planning.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">If, it was claimed, an industry is transferred to public ownership, then its investment expenditure can be directed by the Government: in times of inflation it can be held back; in times of deflation it can be expanded. Or, to put it more generally, since the level of investment directly affects the level of employment, the more the government can itself decide the level of investment the better. It was no doubt principally for this reason that the various nationalisation acts all imposed upon the Boards set up to administer the industries the obligation to secure the approval of the government for the investment programmes.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But while the economics of this argument are sound enough, its practical significance clearly depends on the relationship between the Nationalised Boards and the Government. On what exactly this should be there has been much discussion during the past thirty years. After the collapse of Guild Socialism, which was itself a reaction against earlier Fabian views, which were thought to be too bureaucratic, the pendulum of opinion moved back to the centre away from syndicalist notions, but did not swing over to the idea that a nationalised industry could be run like a government department under the direct control of a Minister.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Instead there emerged the idea of the public corporation - a body appointed by the Minister to manage the industry, under instructions to see that it pays its way, “taking one year with another”, generally responsible to him for its success or failure, obliged to submit an annual report and accounts, and to secure his approval in certain matters, but free from interference either by the Minister or Parliament in its day to day activities. The man who has been chiefly responsible for conceiving and developing and applying this idea is Mr Herbert Morrison, not only in his book “Socialisation and Transport” (he was Minister of Transport in the 1929-31 labour Government), but also in the very many discussions within the Party and later the Government. Nobody brought home to the Party more clearly the absolute necessity that nationalisation must be efficient, and that its reputation would largely turn upon this.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Nobody insisted more forcefully that efficiency in the running of a commercial enterprise could not be combined with continual political interference. It is a measure of Mr Morrison’s influence that the Party programme on nationalisation which was eventually carried out after 1945 accepted completely the notion of the public corporation. To-day the argument, such as it is, about the form of nationalisation, seldom challenges this conception, but is usually concerned with its precise application. “Exactly how often should there be inquiries into the working of the Nationalised Boards?”, “What precisely is the difference between day to day operations and issues of principle?”,</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“How can Parliament keep sufficient control to secure public accountability without interfering too much?” are the questions raised and discussed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The position of the trade unions in the nationalised industries is also a matter on which opinions have changed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the early 1930's it was still the predominant view that the Boards should include representatives of the Trade Unions - so that the Unions as such would take an open, direct and active part in the organisation. But by 1945 this idea had been largely discarded. The conclusion had been reached and was accepted by most union leaders that the Unions must remain independent of the management so that they could continue in a nationalised industry to fulfil their traditional functions of protecting the interests of the workers. This did not mean that Union officials should not accept posts on or under the Boards, but that if they did so they must sever their connection with the Union. Nor did it mean that the Unions would not cooperate with the management. On the contrary, while insisting on independence, there was an equal emphasis on the need for full consultation by the management with the workers at all levels and a general acceptance of the ideas of partnership: but it was to be a partnership of two sides, each of whom had their distinct responsibilities.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While this is still the view of the vast majority of the Unions - especially in the nationalised industries - a minority, including the National Union of Railwaymen, continue to advocate direct workers' representations on the Boards.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It is natural to ask how the actual experience of nationalisation in the last few years has influenced Socialist thinking in Britain. But the question is premature. Although there have been grumbles and disappointments as well as satisfaction at what has been done, many of the troubles are certainly transitional in character. While anxiety is sometimes expressed about such things as over-centralisation, lack of participation by the workers and the inadequate influence of consumers, some of these complaints are politically inspired, and others are based on sheer ignorance. Certainly so far as the Trade Unions are concerned - with the possible exception of the Railwaymen - their reports show some pride in the technical achievement of nationalisation and the improvements in the condition and status of the workers which have been introduced. They reveal neither any marked dissatisfaction, nor demands for radical changes in the set-up.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The nationalisation of an industry means that it is both publicly owned and publicly controlled. But Socialist thinkers and writers have from time to time put forward the notion of public control without ownership, and also – though less frequently - the idea of public ownership without control. The latter, as we have seen, was</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Mr Dalton in his “Inequality of Incomes”; the former has had of course, much wider support, and, on a liberal interpretation, a much longer history. What have been the ideas of British Socialist thinkers on the notion of public control without ownership?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Socialists generally have favoured State control because so of often in the past it has been an instrument to protect the weak against the strong, the poor against the rich and the worker against the employer. But despite Sydney Webb’s efforts to depict such controls as Socialism, it is not simply of factory and wage legislation, or the Rent Restriction Acts or Sanitary Regulations and the like that the British Socialist who is advocating a policy of controls is usually thinking. Controls in this context mean economic controls - economic controls to assist economic planning for high employment and production, and to assist fair distribution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It cannot be said that before the 1914-18 war any very precise ideas on this subject existed even among Socialists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The war did, of course, involve the introduction of many specific controls and thus accustomed people to the idea that they were practicable. But they were swept away very soon after by non-Labour Governments, and it is hard to find any clear signs of their influence at this time on Socialist thinking. The main reason for this was no doubt that the dominating economic problem of the twenties and thirties in Britain was unemployment, deflation and depression, for dealing with which the specific type of wartime control did not seem appropriate.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While the general idea that the Government, if it really wanted, could get rid of unemployment has for years been accepted by Socialists, the important new thinking on the subject of employment policy in this period came from the professional economists, and in particular from the brilliant mind of J.M.Keynes. As is well known, his central practical idea, which is all that we need be concerned with here, was that the general level of demand determined employment, and that this could easily be influenced by the government through either its budgetary or its credit policy, or by a combination of both. He also gave countenance to an idea which more radical writers, such as J.A.Hobson, had put forward long before - namely that owing to the lower rate of savings by poorer people, a redistribution of income in favour of the poor and at the expense of the rich stimulated demand, and therefore employment.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Generally speaking these ideas, which after some initial doctrinal arguments have been widely accepted by economists all over the world, were warmly welcomed by British Socialists, especially of the younger generation. They justified after all the idea that a government could maintain full employment by economic planning. The only doubt felt on the policy was whether it could really be made to work in a purely capitalist framework. Socialist economists, while avoiding dogmatism, were inclined to argue that the Government’s power to influence the level or demand, oven with full control of the banking system, was still too limited, and that it needed in addition to have some more direct control over the volume of investment. For the time boing, however, qualifications of this kind were dwarfed in the general battle to get the now rational approach to monetary policy accepted. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The significance of the Keynesian doctrines for Socialist policy were admirably explained by a young economist - Douglas Jay - who was later to hold a very influential post in the 1945 Labour Government - in his book “The Socialist Case”. He also put forward in this book both an up-to-date account of a Socialist fiscal policy for reducing inequality, and also a new critique of the free capitalist economy resulting from the work of academic economists on what is usually called imperfect or monopolistic competition. Their analysis showed that instead of the beneficent working of free competition with its constant drive towards greater efficiency and lower costs, in many industries natural forces brought about a kind of stalemate between firms which involved wasteful expenditure on advertising and marketing as well no excess productive capacity and needlessly high costs.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">According to the Keynesian doctrine, a government should be able to bring about and maintain full employment by the employment by the use of indirect controls – the varying of the flow of monetary demand through changes in interest rates and the size of the budget surplus or deficit. The second world war, however, involved the use of an immense array of direct controls over economic activities in Britain on a far larger scale than in 1914-18 war. Indeed, it was not just a matter of controls. The Government bought on public account a high proportion of all imports - especially raw materials and food; it placed orders for a large part of the domestic output of the country and, through the allocation of raw materials and other controls it was able not merely to determine the general pattern of the economy but this details of what was to be imported and produced, and how it was to be consumed. For the first time Britain had a fully planned economy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Such an immense change was bound to influence the thinking of the Labour Party anyhow, but the General Election victory of 1945 meant that the thinking had to be accompanied by urgent decisions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There was, of course, no question of maintaining the whole of the war-time apparatus of control. This would in any case have been impossible because it depended for its successful operation, amongst other things, on a large volume of direct government orders, and on the goodwill and readiness to cooperate of the business community - neither of which were likely to continue in peacetime.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But the question remained – what controls should be retained, temporarily or permanently?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">While it would be wrong to suggest that these questions were approached on the basis of an absolutely clear-cut and generally accepted philosophy, it is possible to detect in the decisions of the Labour Government and to some extent in what has been said and written since the Party has been in opposition, certain principles of thought about controls.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">First, of course, there is no desire to be too dogmatic: there is a recognition that there is no point in direct controls for their own sake, and that whether they are needed must depend on the economic situation. To this extent the defence of continuing some controls for a time after the war was simply that there was, in the economic field, still very much an emergency.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Secondly there is the view that it is, to say the least, very difficult to maintain without inflation the degree of full-time employment and the very low margin of unemployment which has in fact been enjoyed in Britain since the war unless some direct controls are used - especially over imports, prices, foreign exchange and industrial building. It would be admitted that such controls may not be needed under very fortunate conditions - when the terms of trade, for example are moving favourably, but normally, without the protection against inflation and its consequences provided by them, a government would be forced to take deflationary action which would lead to a higher level of unemployment.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Thus the maintenance of some direct controls was justified by Labour’s philosophy of full employment and the conviction that such a policy was not only socially desirable but calculated to give the maximum stimulus to production.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Thirdly, the case for controls in the post-war period has also been bound up with the difficulties which resulted from the war over the foreign trade balance and the balance between the dollar and sterling areas - difficulties which have not yet been wholly overcome.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Fourthly, one important reason for the maintenance of controls - especially those over consumption - was that combined with subsidies they did do something to modify the distribution of real income in favour of the poor. For they involved a deliberate diversion of more of the resources of the country into the prevision of necessities compared with luxuries, and to that extent raised the real income of the poor at the expense of the rich.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This view was never held so strongly as to involve a desire for rationing for its own sake, nor does it mean that the Labour Party intends to reintroduce rationing when it comes back to power. But it certainly was one of the reasons why the Labour Government was disinclined to allow the free play of the market to determine the prices and consumption of essentials. To-day the party attitude in the main is that free choice must be continued and unfairnesses corrected rather through redistribution of income and wealth than through direct controls.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Finally there are certain other specific controls which should be continued and even extended for particular reasons. The most obvious are those – including the restoration of bulk buying by Government agencies in some cases – designed to encourage greater production and more efficiency in agriculture and those at regulating the location of industry.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>’hero is, of coarse, much discussion about how far social are of this kind con be carried and what the prioritise should be as between the different social services. Those<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>y st sr'_ especially interested in creating a more equal society :.u ‘'y^ future are inclined especially to favour education, ’-'-a is no doubt that even now differences in education :	large	part in maintainor^ social and economicyj-' 'y r-oes - even now it is possible for well-to-do parents T^^-uase for their children by sending them to fee-paying education which can be intellectually and usually c?	core valuable than the free system offered by iheVC! ♦ CSnrv^ 1 1   J -L&lt;%  X1 -,_«%	- - ^	.<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>~v- r-5‘ S-'-all wonder then that there is a strong demand for ' ' ’	better	teaching,	more	up-to-date gebooT'r ' Gt-te system, for removing as far as possible<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>hrrhfs ea, handicaps which tend to“beset the path'"-'of poorer 	re.., end for equalising opportunities even further.<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>r\' &gt;<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>a~<hi style="color:red; font-size: 14pt; font-weight:bold;" rend="ERROR">�</hi><note place="margin" type="conversion" resp="#teitodocx"><hi rend="docxError">unable to handle picture here, no embed or link</hi></note>\</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Fiscal policy, the nationalisation of individual industries, full employment, the nature and extent of controls, are all issues with which a democratic Socialist party in or on the threshold of power must be concerned, one could easily add to the list. There is Educational Policy, Housing, Pensions and National Insurance, the National Health Service, and many other important questions on which it would be possible to sketch the development of British Socialist thought. But in a short essay such detail is impossible. There is no doubt that the development of Social Services in Britain, leading to what is now called “The Welfare State” owes a very great deal to the pressure and propaganda of the Labour Party over the last fifty years, as well as to the specific acts of the post-war Labour Government. The demand for these reforms sprang of course principally from the obvious need to prevent hardship or remedy injustice. But taken together with the growth of progressive taxation - Income and Surtax, Estate Duty and</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Profits Tax - they have contributed much to the redistribution and the abolition of extremes in both wealth and poverty which has occurred in Britain in the last half-century. While the case for extending free or subsidised services financed out of taxation is obviously less strong the more equal are personal incomes before taxation, and the more redistribution is already being carried out, for the moment at least the need for some further progress in this direction is certainly accepted by the Labour Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is, of course, much discussion about how far social expenditure of this kind can be carried and what the priorities should be as between the different social services. Those who are especially interested in creating a more equal society in the future are inclined especially to favour education. For these is no doubt that even now differences in education play a large part in maintaining social and economic differences – even now it is possible for well-to-do parents to purchase for their children by sending them to fee-paying schools an education which can be intellectually and usually is socially more valuable than the free system offered by the State. Small wonder then that there is a strong demand for smaller classes, better teaching, more up-to-date schools within the State system, for removing as far as possible barriers and handicaps which tend to beset the path of poorer children, and for equalising opportunities even further. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But there is also much discussion to-day on a subject touched on in earlier writings - namely, the economic effects of high taxation. As in the field of employment policy, Socialists have been able to draw upon the work of professional economists and official committees. Without going into much detail, it may be said that the present state of the debate is somewhat as follows.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It would be generally agreed that high direct taxation has not, save in a limited number of special cases, caused people to do less work. It would also be agreed that the amount of saving is hardly responsive at all to the reduction in not yield resulting from taxing the payment of interest.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The difficulties arise - so far as saving is concerned - more from the refusal of well-to-do taxpayers to react to high taxation by cutting down their standard of living, and their determination to maintain consumption in such circumstances either by reducing saving or by drawing on their capital. These difficulties - though by no means to be underestimated - are made less serious by the fact that so much more saving is done nowadays by companies which are not affected by surtax, and whose managers and directors are inclined to place the development of the company above everything else, including that of the immediate interests of shareholders.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As to investment, while it would be generally admitted that the fall in the rate of return caused by high taxation may affect willingness to take risks, here again the fact that decisions are made from the point of view of the company, not the individual, modifies this effect.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">On policy the modern Socialist would say that even if high taxation can have harmful effects, the right policy, instead of reducing taxation generally at the expense of social services, is to counter these harmful effects by discriminating - in favour of undistributed as compared with distributed profits (so as to increase saving) - in favour of actual purchase of new machinery instead of leaving the money idle (so as to increase investment). He would be attracted by Mr Dalton’s earlier idea of transferring ownership of securities, etc., to the State through death duties, and also by some of his ideas on inheritance taxation. He would be acutely conscious of the evasion of death duties which is at present common, and anxious to stop up the loopholes.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But while favouring more efficient taxation of inheritance plus state ownership (without necessarily having control too) as a sound policy for equality, he would be much concerned with the danger of dissaving or capital consumption which he would see as a lion in the path towards greater equality. Our modern Socialist is therefore inclined to favour the further use of discriminatory taxes in favour of those who save and to penalise those who dissave. Finally, he is also impressed with the extent to which capital gains free of tax have preserved inequality, and he feels that the British system here is out of date and anomalous, and should if possible be brought into line with other countries, such as the USA and Sweden (1). [(1) Among recent books on Socialist economic policy the following are among the more important: “New Fabian Essays”, R.H.S.Crossman and others; “In pursuit of Progress”, Roy Jenkins; “Britain’s Economic Problem,” C.A.R.Crosland; “Principles of Economic Planning,” Arthur Lewis; “Challenge to Britain” – the 1953 Statement of Labour Policy – as well as the records of recent Parliamentary Debates on Economic issues are also relevant.]</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Before concluding this essay, something further must be said on the development of British Socialist thought on wider and more purely political issues. The British as a whole take their democracy for granted, and British Socialists to-day are no exception. In consequence there has been little attempt made to work out the full implications of the democratic approach to Socialism. Indeed, one could go further and say that not a few writers before the war were inclined to sketch out an economic and social policy for the Labour Party without considering sufficiently carefully whether it was really compatible with full parliamentary democracy. There was a tendency on the part of some - especially after the disaster of 1931 - to argue that what was needed was a much more revolutionary tactic in which little trace could be found of the doctrine that democracy requires a basis of consent and a willingness to compromise. It was natural enough at a time when the Party had suffered such a terrific electoral defeat, and it largely melted away as the Party came nearer to power.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Perhaps the most consistent and influential writer in this field was the late Professor Harold Laski. He was, of course, a political scientist, not an economist; and if not a Marxist he was certainly more sympathetic to Marxian doctrine than most of his academic Socialist colleagues; he thought more in terms of revolutionary situations, although he insisted that he was a whole-hearted supporter of democratic methods. Perhaps it was for this reason that his influence was felt more outside than inside Great Britain - and particularly in India and other parts of what was then the Colonial Empire. The many students who came to him from those territories where full democracy still did not exist were naturally more responsive to his views than those who enjoyed the benefit of British Parliamentary Institutions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It was the weakness of Professor Laski, stimulating and kindly teacher and popular writer though he was, that perhaps because of his temperamental liking for revolution, perhaps because of his sympathy for Marxism and for Soviet Russia, he was sometimes inclined to blur the distinction between democracy and dictatorship, to ignore the identical features of the Fascist and Communist regimes, and to place more emphasis on the differences capitalist and Socialist states, whatever the nature of their respective political systems. In this he was not alone. Indeed during the 1930’s the success of Fascism in Europe, together with the economic slump and the political weakness of the Labour Party at home, gave a considerable stimulus to a more revolutionary outlook. In the Universities membership of the Communist Party became fashionable. Interest in Marx and Marxism revived. The writings of John Strachey, who had been a Labour Member of Parliament from 1929-31, joined for a brief spell Sir Oswald Mosley’s ‘New Party’ and subsequently took up a position well to the left of the Labour Party and close to that of the Communists, were much in vogue. Mr Strachey used his considerable intellectual and literary talents to apply Marxist ideas to the contemporary situation. (1) [See in particular, “The Nature of Capitalist Crisis”, and “The Coming Struggle for Power”.]</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Within the Labour Party itself there was also more inclination to view the political prospect both at home and abroad in more revolutionary terms. The Socialist League, led by Sir Stafford Cripps, reflected this outlook. They favoured a ‘United Front' with the Communists, (Sir Stafford Cripps and two of his colleagues were later expelled from the Labour Party for this flagrant breach of the official policy), and proposed that on achieving power at home by democratic means, they should carry out reforms at great speed and without much regard to constitutional traditions. Al1 these left-wing tendencies were greatly stimulated by the Spanish Civil War and its tragic outcome - on which deep feeling existed throughout the whole of the British Labour Movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It must not be assumed, however, that the greet majority of the Party - based on the Trade Unions - ever deviated at all from their democratic principles. I particular they remained adamant against the idea of joining with the Communists in a United Front, and they realised instinctively the practical weakness of the Socialist League proposals.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The philosophical basis of this majority view was brilliantly expressed in a quite outstanding book, “The Politics of Democratic Socialism”, published in 1940. This was the work of another University lecturer, economist and colleague of Professor Laski’s - Evan Durbin - who was tragically drowned in 1948. In this book, Evan Durbin stated with remarkable clarity the true connection between Socialism and Democracy, shared how impossible it was to achieve the former without the latter and drew cut the full political implication of this. He continued with a devastating critique of the central Marxist doctrines which he completely rejected. He cut through the veil of sentimentality and ignorance which caused many British Socialists and others, before the war to combine violent protests about Nazi atrocities with a stony silence about what was happening in Russia.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">With great courage and prescience he emphasised the appalling similarity between the two regimes - even devoting a complete appendix to a comparison of the cruelties perpetrated by each. His book was unfortunately not finished till the outbreak of war, and therefore never received the publicity it deserved. Even now it is still far the best treatment of the subject available.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Though it is the work of one man, it illustrates the attitude of a wider group. For this reason and because it may help to describe the outlook of what was at the time a younger generation of British Socialists, perhaps I might quote some paragraphs I wrote in a foreword to a recent edition.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“This took,” I said, “reflects an outlook on politics which was shared by many of his friends and contemporaries in the Labour Movement, an outlook which marked in its way a new phase in Socialist thought, different both from that of the early Fabians and from the ideas associated with the stormy period before and after the first world war. It marked, one might say, in the field of thought the transition from the pioneering stage to that of responsibility and power.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“This outlook owed much to the influence of R.H.Tawney, but perhaps there was less passion and less puritanism in it than Tawney’s teaching; it also owed much to Hugh Dalton, but it shed his fierce intolerance; it owed a lot to G.D.K. Cole, but through the stimulus of his restless mind rather than any particular gospel he preached; it owed something to J.M.Keynes, but in economics not social philosophy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“The most fundamental ideal of those who shared this outlook was social justice - but it was an ideal in no way inspired by class hatred. They were equally devoted to democracy and personal freedom. They believed in tolerance and they understood the need for compromise. They were for the rational and practical, and suspicious of large general ideas which on examination turned out to have no precise content. They were scornful of those who were content only to talk. They wanted to get results. They believed that modern economics and statistics could help to get those results.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">“They were realistic in politics and critical of armchair politicians who, not understanding what the British electorate was really like, were for ever making bad political judgments. Above all, while accepting the ultimate emotional basis of moral valuation, they had great faith in the power of reason both to find the answers to social problems and to persuade men to see the light. They were for the pursuit of truth to the bitter end, through the patient and unswerving application of logical thought. They wanted no barriers of prejudice to obstruct the free working of the mind or blunt the sharp edge of intellectual integrity.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Partly owing to the work of Evan Durbin and others, partly owing to the much greater understanding of both Fascism and Communism which now exists, partly owing to the experience of the years in power and to the far greater number of Labour members of Parliament, there is a better understanding of the true implications of democracy today among British Socialists than there was before the war. One can say with confidence that its value is far more realised, and that the old confusions appear less frequently. Reason has been brought in to support instinct, and British Socialist thought has become even more democratic. Communist influence makes itself felt in the form of a ceaseless and sometimes subtle propaganda for a foreign policy which would suit Russia: it plays a part from time to time within the Trade Unions. But Revolutionary Communism openly advocated for application in Britain has no support anywhere.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">What, finally, must be said of the change in the attitude of British Socialists to external affairs - to the questions of colonial and foreign policy? The biggest change of all as compared with 1900 is that they spend so much more time thinking and talking about them. At the beginning of the century there were the Marxists, for whom war was simply a capitalist phenomenon, the result of a struggle between rival Imperialisms and for which the only cure was therefore the destruction of capitalism and there were the Pacifists, especially strong In the ILP, inheriting their views largely from the radical wing of the Liberal Party, and also from the Nonconformist church. But the majority of Labour leaders and supporters before 1914 were simply not interested in foreign affairs, and certainly had no conception of the immense changes which were we soon to come about.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the first world war the Party was split - between the Pacifists and the other Labour leaders who joined the Coalition government. During the inter-war years while the pacifist minority remained influential, although less so than before, the majority put their faith in the League of Nations and the doctrines on which it was based. Led by Arthur Henderson, Hugh Dalton and Philip Noel-Baker, they rejected any idea of unilateral disarmament and set out with great enthusiasm and conviction in favour of a genuine system of collective security. By this they meant something in the international field approximating to the rule of law within the nation state, under which disputes could be settled by arbitration or conciliation, and where aggressors could be dealt with by an international police force.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the thirties, after Japan’s aggression in Manchuria and Mussolini’s attack on Abyssinia, and with the mounting danger of Hitler and the Nazis in Europe, the demand for regional collective security become stronger. By this was really meant alliance with the other democratic countries of Western Europe, and with the Soviet Union. The policy was a logical extension of the earlier doctrine in support of the League of Nations, and a great deal more practical too. But although it commanded the support of the majority, it must be admitted that it was weakened by the influence of the pacifists and others who preferred a policy of appeasement, and confused by the decision of the parliamentary Labour Party to vote against the Defence Estimates. This was not because the Party was opposed to Defence expenditure, but because it disapproved of the Government’s foreign policy - in particular its refusal to support the League of Nations at the moment of crisis, its failure to give a lead to the Disarmament Conference, and its weakness towards the Fascist powers on many occasions - especially during the Spanish Civil War.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">During the second world war the Party, of course, joined wholeheartedly in the Churchill Coalition Government, and there was no question of a split as in 1914-18.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Since the end of the war one can trace two conflicting tendencies. On the one hand Pacifism is much weaker than before the war, and there is a far greater acceptance both of the need for adequate defence and for the alliance of the democratic countries. On the other hand, since the danger of aggression comes not from Fascist but from Communist powers, there is a reluctance on the part of some to recognise that the danger can really be so serious, and disposition to resent association with capitalist America against Communist Russia and China. The much greater appreciation of the true nature of parliamentary democracy at home is not always coupled with an adequate understanding of Communist policies abroad. Nevertheless, so far the first of the two tendencies always prevailed, and there is no reason to expect any change. In government the Party can be expected to follow the policies of 1945-51, which are in fact the logical successors to the demand for collective security before the war. But in Opposition the second tendency comes forward, and the consequent struggle puts a strain on the cohesion of the Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As for colonial affairs the change here has been much simpler and more of a natural evolution. Since the basic of democratic Socialism is the doctrine that every human being has the right to equal status and opportunities - without distinction of class, colour or creed - it is impossible for Socialists to contemplate that other peoples and nations should have a permanently inferior status under them. It follows that a Socialist Party must desire to bring forward all Colonies to self-government and self-determination. Admittedly this cannot happen at once because of the backward condition of some of the colonial peoples, and because it would be no part of Socialist doctrine that they should be given independence only to become the prey of a domestic dictator or another foreign power. But the ultimate object cannot be questioned. What has really happened in the last fifty years is that British Socialists have become increasingly aware of this. They have become more and more interested in extending the doctrine of their own democratic Socialism beyond the boundaries of the United Kingdom and have therefore taken a closer and closer interest in the colonies where the British Government, after all, has the power and the responsibility. Perhaps too the very progress of social reform at home, the rise in the standard of living, the welfare state, the reduction in inequality has led some to transfer their crusading zeal to affairs in other parts of the world where it seems to thorn more required and possibly more rewarding.</p></body></text></TEI>