<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Austria</title>
         <author>Benedikt Kautsky</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>21 April 1956</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.VI, No.16</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
   <p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Austrian Social Democracy in its present form is based on the union which took place at Hainfeld in 1889 between the Moderates and Radicals, who until then had formed separate groups. At that time both groups were able to look hack on an ideological development of twenty years. In Austria in the 1860s, as in the Labour movements elsewhere, a new beginning had been made after the reaction of 1849 which had destroyed all promise of the 1848 Revolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Both groups conformed closely to the pattern provided by imperial Germany; in the early days of the Austrian Labour movement emigrants from Germany played a decisive role. The movement's first successes at the end of the 1860s saw that current which had close connections with the Eisenach tendency in German Social Democracy come to the fore. Wilhelm Leibknecht in particular remained in close touch with his Austrian comrades, but August Bebel, too, when he spoke in Vienna in 1912 on the occasion of Victor Adler's birthday, stressed that he had never become reconciled in his heart to the separation of German-Austria from Germany.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">With the advent of the serious economic crisis of 1873, and with the growing reaction to the rising Labour movement, Anarchism developed in Austria, where it was of far greater importance than in Germany. For a time the Austrian was almost the leading Anarchist movement on the Continent. Its development can be explained by the special conditions obtaining in Austria. The power of the State seemed weaker than in Germany, despite the fact that the authorities occasionally acted more brutally in their relations with the workers ; the chances of a violent overthrow of the government therefore seemed better. At the same time the awakening of a working-class movement among the Slav races produced elements who lacked all political and trade union training and could therefore become a relatively easy prey to experiments in violence.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The split in the Austrian Social Democratic movement had much worse results than the split of the German Party into the followers of Lassalle and the Eisenach group. The existence of a strong radical wing was used by the police, with the help of agents-provocateurs and agents, to stage plots which were utilised for a further suppression of the Socialist movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Eventually, conditions became unbearable. The leader of the Anarchists, Josef Peukert, disappeared in suspicion circumstances on the eve of the declaration of a state of emergency; to this day it is not clear whether he was, in fact, honest or an informer. But even granted that he was acting in good faith, he acted unwittingly like an agent provocateur, and he was not by any means the only one of his kind in his group. Internal party strife, even more than police persecution, forced the more important Socialists to emigrate so that the movement lost its spiritual leaders.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As a result of this development the Moderates were more strongly affected than the Radicals, since at this time their policy appeared to be utterly unrealistic. As a result of the split they were forced further towards the Right than they had intended ; their policy became limited to plans for social reform and the introduction of parliamentarianism - both measures which could either not be realised or, if they had been, would not materially have altered the lot of the workers. The first steps towards introducing social insurance and a limited working day, which were being taken during this period, showed this only too clearly.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Radicals, on the other hand, at least had the advantage of initiative and a definite ideology. But they suffered from being unable to distinguish between their honest members and those who acted as spies and informers. The advice to use dynamite and dagger, as Josef Peukert and Johann Most had proposed only too successfully, proved so obviously damaging to the workers' movement that finally even the Radicals began to see that it was impossible, and harmful, to carry Anarchist theory to its logical conclusions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">However, this did not prevent them from retaining their radical philosophy. As a result they were the much more active element when, in the latter half of the ‘eighties, unification came about under the leadership of Victor Adler.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">At this time Adler himself turned Marxist and, for that reason, had no undue respect for parliamentarianism and social reform. His attempts met with strong resistance from the leader of the Moderates, Emilie Bardorf, who, after the unification, retired from the Socialist movement and joined the Christian Socialist camp. This weakened the position of the Moderates even further.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The new Party kept clear of Anarchist practices. This evolution was furthered by the gradual disappearance of Anarchism from the international Socialist movement, which went hand in hand with the industrial boom at the turn of the ‘nineties. With the exception of minor quarrels with individual Anarchists Victor Adler had no further difficulties with the former Radicals. But this did not mean the disappearance of submerged currents of radical thought within Austrian Social Democracy. On the contrary, while the two groups had become organisationally united, their differing ideologies continued to exist side by side. Without taking this factor into account the development of Austrian Social Democracy cannot be understood.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">How strong radical thought always was in the Austrian Social Democratic Party is proved by the repeated appearance of the idea of the general strike as a political weapon. The use of this method was first fully discussed in the '’nineties and again during the first decade of the 20th century. On both occasions it was a question of obtaining universal suffrage. On the first occasion the Belgian Party provided an example of a successful general strike, and many – not only Party members but also Party leaders - put high hopes in this method, But Victor Adler took great trouble to prevent it, from being used, since a general strike could only have led to o defeat of the young party. But by 1905 conditions had changed. In 1905 Victor Adler could doubtlessly have achieved universal suffrage, using the successes of the first Russian Revolution as the basis for a general strike, had not the government by then given in to the Party’s demands.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Thus the Austrian Party was never forced to resort to such means. Nevertheless, it is characteristic that the general strike could continue to occupy an important place in Socialist thinking,</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This radical trend in thinking was not changed by the development of Marxism in Austria. In the early days of the workers' movement Marxism played a much smaller part in Austria then in Germany. The adherents of the Eisenach line followed a Marxist path, even if few of their leaders fully understood Marxist theory. Bebel was, above all, a practical man, despite his great knowledge of historical and economic studies, Even Liebknecht's theoretical knowledge was relatively limited, in spite of his long association with Math. Only Wilhelm Bracke, who died early, really knew how to interpret Marxist theory and how to apply it. The Marxist school did not begin to develop in Germany until the 'eighties. It was only after Engels had written his "Anti-Dühring" that Karl Kautsky and Eduard Bernstein began to write-a great deal and to popularise Marxist thinking.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">There was no similar development in Austria at that time. Only at the turn of the century, and stimulated by German Marxism as represented by Kautsky, did a movement develop in Vienna which eventually was to be known as the Austro-Marxist school. Its principal representatives were Karl Renner, Otto Bauer, Rudolf Hilferding, Max Adler, Gustav Eckstein end Friedrich Adler. Around these men - well-known names lo this day - there were large groups of eager young men who had the same aims and an extraordinary interest in and understanding of the problems of Marxism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It would require a sociological study to explain why Vienna in particular should have become such a centre of Marxism. In the International it has only one parallel - Amsterdam, where conditions were entirely different. The influence of Amsterdam was admittedly not comparable to that of Vienna. Several of the pillars of Dutch Marxism - Henrietta Roland-Holst, Hermann Gorter and Anton Pannekoek - went over to Communism after 1917, only to abandon it shortly after. This none of the Austro-Marxists did. Already at the time of the theoretical discussion between Rosa Luxemburg and Karl Kautsky during and after 1910 the Austro-Marxists followed the line of Kautsky. Thus they all belonged to the "Marxist centre", but it is clear that a radical streak survived among them. Only Karl Renner, who took up a special position within Austro-Marxism, was an exception to this rule.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The reasons why both Vienna and Amsterdam became centres of Marxism have probably something to do with the international character of both towns. Marxist research in Austria and Holland was not limited to local problems. This is especially true of the most important work of theory produced by Austro-Marxism - Rudolf Hilferding<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>s "Finance Capital", which described the trends and developments of German capitalism. Nor was the scope of Max Adler's philosophical writings or of the works of Gustav Eckstein, who died tragically early and who dealt with a field lying between natural science and sociology, limited to Austria. Friedrich Adler spent much more of the period when Austro-Marxism was developing in Switzerland than in Austria.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="bold">* * * *</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The two Austro-Marxists who played a leading part in Austrian Social Democracy after the collapse of the monarchy were both interested in the basic problem of the Austro-Hungarian Monarchy - the problem of the nationalities. Otto Bauer's work, "The National Question and Social Democracy" laid bare the connection between national and social divisions and thus produced an invaluable basis for the rational solution of the national question. If shortly before the First World War Lenin called the young Stalin to Vienna to study the national question there, it was owing to the work done by Otto Bauer in the Austrian capital. But Stalin seems to have been less interested in the work of Otto Bauer than in the teachings of Josef Strasser - who later became a Communist and was already at that time moving away from the Marxist centre, and whose works are merely a simplification - a superficial simplification - of Bauer's theories.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Karl Renner was less interested in theoretical problems than in finding practical solutions to the problems of the various nationalities. In his book "Österreich's Erneuerung" he tried to define the conditions under which the monarchy could survive. The idea of national autonomy within a large state seemed to offer a solution to the national strife. Renner believed, above all, that for economic reasons a largo state had more to offer to the workers than a dissolution or the Danubian Monarchy and the setting up of a number of small national states. Doubtless this was correct in theory, but it presupposed that the monarchy was ready and able to reorganise itself on a democratic basis.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">At times it seemed that such an attempt might be made. In the first decade of the century the granting of universal franchise in Austria, the conflict between the Crown and the ruling Hungarian aristocracy which the Crown tried to resolve by granting universal franchise, a degree of progress in the field of social policy, the modernisation of the administration, and, lastly, the development of heavy industry, all aroused the hope that Austria would be capable of making a new start.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As a result there grew up a kind of alliance between the Crown and Social Democracy, both of whom, as far as nationalities were concerned, represented the centripetal line of thought in the Danubian Monarchy. But, while Social Democracy strove to bring about the co-operation of all national groups on an equal basis within its own ranks, the Crown was unable to depart from its old method of playing off one nation against another in order to maintain its control and, as a result, lost them all, one after the other.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In addition, the alliance between the Crown and the long-established powers of the Church, the aristocracy and the army proved too strong for a serious attempt at democracy. The announcement of universal enfranchisement in Hungary remained an empty promise, and the Crown soon capitulated to the re-invigorated aristocracy. Then, in 1908, during the annexation crisis, it was clearly demonstrated that questions of power politics and military considerations played a much larger part than any plan for internal re-organisation. So in 1914 those groups who believed that the dangers threatening Austria could best be dealt with by military success won the day.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The vigorous development of Austro-Marxian. must not be taken to have decisively influenced the policy of Austrian Social Democracy under the dual monarchy. Some of its most important supporters - Rudolf Hilferding, Friedrich Adler and Gustav Eckstein - during this period spent the greater part of their time abroad. Max Adler was mainly preoccupied with questions of theory, so that only Karl Renner and Otto Bauer played a part in every-day Austrian politics.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Victor Adler's attitude to Austro-Marxism was peculiar. After Karl Kautsky, he was one of the first Austrians to grasp the nature of Marxism and to use it as the basis of his policy. His personal and political attitude to Engels is apparent from the letters exchanged between them. After Engels it was August Bebel who influenced him most in his political views ; he also remained in intimate personal and political touch with Karl Kautsky. But like Karl Kautsky, who could not be counted among the Austro-Marxists, Victor Adler remained outside their circle. Through his educational zeal within the Party organisation and among the staff of the "Arbeiter-Zeitung" he influenced a number of young men and aroused their interest. But Adler was a man of practice rather than theory - or, rather, he was interested in theory only in so far as it could be used in practice. He never had any leanings towards pure speculation, and as he grew older practice became even more important to him.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Fundamentally, it is true, he always remained a Marxist. But his views on the nature of Marxism became more flexible as time went on; it in clear that at a very early stage he sympathised with many of the arguments put forward by Eduard Bernstein in his "revision" of Marxism. The changes in the Hainfeld programme which he proposed and put through in 1903 clearly show that he could no longer reconcile some of his former views with what he practised.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">There is no doubt that the lino of thought developed by Renner was very close to Adler’s ideas on the needs of Austrian politics. Victor Adler did everything in his power to keep Austrian Social Democracy from becoming involved in national quarrels. Although the part played by Germans within Austrian Social Democracy was proportionately far greater than the number of Germans among the population, the German-Austrian areas were on the average more highly industrialised than the rest of the country and, therefore, their industrial workers were more strongly represented - the Party itself was careful not to allow thin unbalance to make itself felt. The same is true for the trade unions whose relations with the Social Democratic Party were particularly close, far closer than was the cane in Germany.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Nevertheless, in the long run it proved impossible to maintain party unity, since the Czech Social Democrats and trade unionists preferred national agreement with their bourgeois parties to wider agreement within a unified Social Democratic party. Czech separatism, which destroyed the framework of Austrian Social Democracy, found no echo among other non-German Social Democrats. Nevertheless, it sapped much of the strength of Social Democracy. There can be no doubt that this particular internal quarrel did much to foster interest in the national problems and the possibility of solving them within Austrian Social Democracy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The prevention of the development of German nationalism within Austrian Social Democracy was one of Victor Adler's greatest achievements. He impressed on all his collaborators that even a mere attempt at establishing German predominance would have the most disastrous results for the whole Party. The impact of his educational work can be felt to this day; the part which Austrian Social Democracy was able to play in the ‘twenties in the newly founded Second International was largely due to the fact that the Party had always held an international point of view.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It would, however, be wrong to ignore the fact that Victor Adler came to Socialism from the German national camp and that throughout his life he felt German. Admittedly his attitude was similar to that of the men of "’forty-eight" which was then already extremely rare in German-speaking territory; for these men democracy and national thinking were two sides of one and the same question.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Victor Adler, like some of his closest friends - among them, above all, Engelbert Pernerstorfer - held fast to the idea that the survival of a united Danubian monarchy was a service to the German people who, in this manner, were able to exert a cultural and civilising influence on the Slavs. Victor Adler never saw any contradiction between supporting this type of German nationalism and opposing narrow chauvinism. Probably his predominantly German cast of thought would not have found further expression if the outbreak of the First World War had not created a situation in which he felt bound to come to a decision.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Victor Adler had long expected the first world war. He realised that both the foreign policy of the Ballhausplatz formulated by Ährenthal and Berchthold and the policy of the General Staff under Conrad von Hötzendorf, both greatly influenced by Prince Franz Ferdinand, heir to the Crown, would gravely endanger European peace. Instead of concentrating on internal reform and re-organisation, these groups, supported by the German, Hungarian and Polish aristocracies as well as by large bourgeois circles in these nations, were bent on foreign adventure.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Victor Adler opposed the full strength of Austrian Social to these powerful groups; at international Socialist conferences he never tired of warning against the dangers of war. At the same time he was sufficiently realistic to know chat the strength of the Socialist parties was insufficient to avert the catastrophe. In this respect he was more pessimistic than his colleagues in the Western countries, who could expect more sense and more awareness of the consequences of a world war from their governments. He knew the ruling circles in the Hofburg and in the Bullhausplatz in Vienne well enough not to have any illusions. Until the last moment before the outbreak of the war he opposed their warmongering and denounced it in the strongest possible terms.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But when the war had become a horrible reality he was faced by an entirely new situation. It was no longer a question on of avoiding the war but merely of who would bear the worst consequences. Victor Adler was faced with the question of what would happen to Europe in the case of a Russian victory and what particularly would be Austria's fate.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Socialists of Germany - not to mention those in the Western countries - had to balance a victory of German militarism against its defeat. The Socialists of the Western democracies, with few exceptions, saw a far greater danger in a German victory than in a Russian one. The German Socialists, on the other hand, feared that a victory of Czarism would greatly prejudice their social gains; it was their fear of a Russian invasion which, on 4 August, 1914, despite their general inclination towards Western democracy, decided them to vote for the war credits. A great majority within the Socialist parliamentary group stood for this point of view ; but even stronger was the instinctive feeling among the working masses that, first of all, one would have to defend oneself against the invader before the question of further international co-operation could be discussed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This point of view of the German Social Democrats was fully understood by the great majority of their Austrian comrades; the tone of the leading article on the German Social Democrats’ support for the war credits, written by Friedrich Austerlitz, editor of the "Arbeiter-Zeitung", is clear from its very title : "The German Nation's Great Day". Such unreserved support could hardly be found at that time even in the German Party press.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In Austria, as in Germany, everything goes to show that not only the Party officials but the vast majority of Party members understood and supported this point of view. In August 1914 only very few of the Austrian Socialists were capable of a sufficiently clear judgment and, like the German Social Democratic parliamentary minority, of opposing a policy of defence of the fatherland. It was a tiny group that collected first round Friedrich Adler; to it belonged Robert Danneberg, Gabriele Proft, Amalie Seidl and others.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Opposed to them was the majority of the Party, the trade unions and co-operatives. Karl Renner now moved into the foreground at the side of Victor Adler; to him the war seemed to conjure up a new age. If before 1914 he had supported the idea of "Grossraumpolitik", which justified the dual monarchy from the workers' point of view on the ground that a larger economic area could offer a better economic future and greater political freedom than a large number of small national states, now, after the outbreak of war, he carried this idea even further: he became a supporter of the idea of a "Mitteleuropa" as put forward by the German Liberal, Friedrich Naumann.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In yet another sense, Adler believed that the war would bring about a fundamental change. He saw in the war economy, in the rationing system, in the planning of industry for armaments and, later, also for the satisfaction of consumer needs, forms of organisation which might eventually be adopted by Socialism. It was a point of view which Karl Kautsky opposed in his book entitled "Wartime Marxism".</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">* * * </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">While the Party at the beginning of the war declared itself for a policy of national defence, and while trade unions and co-operatives became geared to the war economy, Austrian Social Democracy did not have to tie itself to any definite official policy. Unlike German Social Democracy, which had to take up an attitude on the question of war credits in open parliamentary session, the Austrian Party did not have to take an official stand, since the government did not recall Parliament but reigned dictatorially.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As a result the pendulum within the Social Democratic Party gradually swung towards the opposition. The incompetence and evils of absolutism led to a decided change, which turned the Party minority into a Party majority, and replaced the policy of national defence by the advocacy of peace without compensation or annexation. It was in the main the needs of the moment which called for these changes: the total collapse of the rationing system, the brutality of the censorship and the judiciary and, lastly, the obvious incompetence of the army command led to doubts about the justification of a policy in support of the government.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In addition, as the war went on the desire of reactionary circles for annexation became more and more undisguised. Even if the plans of the German, Hungarian and Austrian imperialists did not follow the same lines, nevertheless the statesmen of the two powers were agreed on one point - that the war must not end without increasing their power in terns of territory. If Germany was looking for new territories in the West, Austro-Hungary was aiming at expansion in the East and South-East. In this connection plans for an independent Poland under Austrian protection took first place, to be followed by on expansion of power in the Balkans.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As a result of this development the basic differences between the majority and the opposition dwindled. The idea of national defence could no longer be paramount if the war was continued for purposes of annexation. The Austrian opposition took its place within the international opposition against a policy of national defence, and accepted the Zimnerwald and Kienthal ideas as its guiding principles. This view slowly gained ground, even if it remained a minority view.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">An important turn of events was Friedrich Adler's assassination of Count Stürgkh on 21 October, 1916. Among the Austrian politicians Stürgkh was undoubtedly one of the most important exponents of reaction at home and of annexation abroad. Adler's action was contrary to the principles of Social Democratic policy, which opposed individual terror. Yet this violation of the rule was endorsed by success: in place of Stürgkh the progressive bureaucrat Korber became Prime Minister in the last month of Emperor Franz Joseph's life. This appointment proved that even among the highest Austrian political and administrative circles a feeling of internal weakness was beginning to spread. Under Franz Joseph's weak successor, the young Emperor Karl, there was still some uncertainty in policy but, within the Social Democratic Party, once the shock effect of the attempted assassination had been overcome, a different line gradually triumphed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The March Revolution in Russia brought about a decisive change. Peace now seemed to be within reach; there was no longer any reason for that fear of Czarism which had led the majority to support the idea of national defence in the early years of the war. The trial of Friedrich Adler completely changed the mood within the Party in favour of the opposition. His speech in his own defence, which he made almost without interruption by the judge, was a masterly exposition of the opposition's point of view and the last word on the policy of national defence. From now on, the opposition was the majority and its principles decided the lines of policy. Just as in the yearly part of the war Friedrich Adler and his friends, however firmly they had stated their views, had never gone so far as to violate party discipline, so the former majority in its turn now remained true to this fundamental principle. The split, which at this time ran right through German Social Democracy, did not occur in Austria. Just as at Hainfeld, the flexible tactics of Victor Adler proved sound and it was once more the Radicals who decided the line of policy. But Victor Adler's stand had shifted somewhat; if at Hainfeld he had belonged more to the Radical group, he could now be counted among the Moderates.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In the last years of the war, however, no further major differences arose within the Party, and Victor Adler's leadership was not questioned. This was most clearly seen when in the summer of 1917, he led the Austrian delegation which in Stockholm took part in the negotiations on the re-building of the Socialist International and the restoration of peace. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">*** </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The ideology of the new majority was a mixture. Its strongest roots undoubtedly lay in Austro-Marxism; with the exception of Renner, all the Austro-Marxists who had remained in Austria recognised the new ideology on the correct one. The rejection of national defence, however, became nearly as important to them. In their opposition to the war policy of the Party majority they went hand in hand, at a decisive time, with those groups from which, later, the Communist Party was to develop. Many close ties linked the two tendencies; it is only against the background of their common experience of opposition to the war and to the policy of national defence that the view, upheld by the Austrian Party throughout the whole of the First Republic, can be understood - the view that the division of the working-class movement into democratic Socialism and Communism was only a passing phase, and that nothing must be done to prevent an eventual re-unification.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The main representative of this political attitude wee Otto Bauer, who in the autumn of 1917 had returned from Russia where he had been a prisoner-of-war; he took the place which Friedrich Adler, who was now in prison, had filled during the first years of the war. He maintained this policy to the end of his life, although his fundamental democratic views were never shaken. In addition, he became the representative of a second important viewpoint which shaped Austrian Social Democratic thought during the period of the First Republic; he came to believe that the revolution which had broken out in Central and Eastern Europe represented nothing more than a completion of the national revolution begun in 1848. As applied to Austria this view meant that the Danubian Monarchy would fall to pieces and that the Germans living in it must seek to join their German brothers within the German Empire.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As a result of this conviction, Otto Boner became a supporter of the idea of "Anschluss". To him thin did not mean the fulfilment of nationalism but, rather, sprang from his revolutionary belief that national freedom is an important part of democracy. It should be noted here, however, that although the idea of "Anschluss" remained in the programme of the Austrian Social Democrats until Hitler seized power in Germany, many people within the Party were instinctively opposed to it; the idea was never wholly accepted by the rank and file.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">* * *</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">When, in October 1918, the Hapsburg Monarchy collapsed and in its place a series of national states arose, there remained only the rump of German Austria. Of its viability even many of those politicians who opposed the "Anschluss" with Germany for national reasons were doubtful. But Bauer never took economic reasons into account; for him the "Anschluss” remained a problem of democracy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Within the new state the influence of Social Democracy was at first paramount. The Party was able to realise the greater part of its social and political programme. Ferdinand Hanusch’s work in this sphere fully justified his international fame. For the City of Vienna a situation was created which allowed it great freedom and enabled it to carry out municipal policy for which it became internationally famous. Among the many brilliant names connected with the administration of "Red Vienna" those of Hugo Breitner, Julius Tandler, Robert Danneberg and Karl Seitz should be mentioned.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">At last, the Party was successful in gaining a firm foothold within the small newly-formed Austrian army. The peace treaty had forced Austria to maintain a small volunteer army; at first it was mainly organised workers, some of whom held commissions, who joined up. Through the unique institution of soldiers' trade unions the Social Democratic Party won a preponderant influence over the largest armed force in Austria; even the members of the police and, to a lesser extent, the gendarmerie were organised in trade unions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Social Democratic Party therefore held a number of strong positions which were reinforced by the extraordinary rise of the trade unions. Yet the Party was unable to save the Austrian revolution from the effect of a law which had marked all previous revolutions: namely, that the stabilisation of economic and political conditions, brought about by the peace treaty, meant a strengthening of the bourgeoisie which, until then, had taken second place in the coalition with the Social Democratic Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The bourgeoisie now began to oppose this subordinate role, and by 1920 the Social Democratic Party was faced with the choice of remaining within the coalition or leaving it. The former meant concessions to the bourgeoisie, while the latter held the danger of handing over the machinery of the state to the bourgeois parties. As in all Socialist parties, so in Austria there were supporters and opponents of a policy of coalition. If the latter lost the day and the Party decided to leave the coalition, this must not be regarded as a tactical move but rather as the result of considerations of principle.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">To Otto Bauer, who represented and formulated this policy, it was, above all, a question of the unity of the working-class movement. The example of the once mighty German Social Democracy was regarded by him as proof that a coalition policy rendered a split permanent and enhanced the strength of the bourgeoisie. If the unity of the working-class movement was to be preserved it was necessary to leave the coalition, since only a policy of opposition could minimise the influence of the Communists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Bauer was supported in these beliefs by the strong position which the Party had gained outside the governmental machine and which, he hoped, might place Social Democracy in a stronger position than if it remained within the coalition as a junior partner.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Behind all this was the expectation that, sooner or later, the revolutionary wave, which in 1920 was on the ebb, would rise again. From this Bauer expected the return of the Communist Party into the revolutionary camp; he therefore aimed at keeping the Austrian workers morally and organisationally as strong as possible so that, in the event of a new revolution, he would be able to lead them to final victory.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">To Bauer it remained important that Soviet Russia - in his view a Socialist state, though he condemned the terror there - should be able to continue her political and economic progress unhampered. He was unshaken in this attitude even by the insults hurled at him by the Communists. Just as little did the wrecking of his international plans change his mind ; the "Arbeitsgemeinschaft Sozialistischer Parteien" founded in Vienna in 1921, which was to smooth the path for an eventual re-unification of the whole of the International, though it did succeed in holding talks with the Second and Third Internationals, never produced the least concrete results. It fell to pieces when the German Independent Social Democrats reunited with the old party. Faced with a choice, the Austrian Party decided to unite its own international organisation with that of the Second International in which Austria was to play an important part. Friedrich Adler became its secretary and Otto Bauer one of the leaders of the Bureau of the International,</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">* * * *</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">If Otto Bauer had reckoned that his policy would preserve the unity of the Austrian working class, he was right there can be no doubt that his policy corresponded to the wishes and aims of the vast majority of the rank and file. In Austria the Communist Party remained a small group, despite the fact that untold economic and political difficulties might have given it opportunities to develop. But the workers felt that the Social Democratic Party was fundamentally more radical than the Communists, and that, therefore, their material interests as well as their political hopes would best be looked after by Social Democracy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This unity served to give the workers a feeling of strength, and this feeling in turn became a source of new successes which strengthened the Party's reputation. Intransigence vis-à-vis the bourgeoisie appealed to the radical undercurrents which had been present ever since the Hainfeld days. From it there sprang that variety of organisations, appealing to all sides of human nature, which made the Party the spiritual home of a wide range of people, particularly of the young people growing up under the First Republic. Not only the most diverse cultural and sports organisations, but associations formed for private purposes unconnected with politics were imbued with the spirit of Socialism, not because their purpose was Socialistic but simply because the Socialists who met in them felt more at home in the company of equals than among the bourgeoisie. In this way there came into being that union between enthusiasm, impregnate with Socialist thought and feeling, and practical reformist activity which was seen at its best in the City Council of Vienna and the trade unions and was characteristic of Austrian Socialism under the First Republic.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But the Party had to pay a price for these successes. The view that the Soviet Union was a Socialist state meant, within the Party, dangerous illusions grew up. With increasing Stalinisation of the Soviet Union it led to ever more dangerous demonstrations in favour of working-class unity, i.e. the re-unification of Socialists and Communists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Events proved Bauer's fundamental belief in an early return of the revolutionary wave wrong. Instead of the advent of a new revolution reaction increased. Even if at that time it was not as clear as it is today how close was the connection between the Stalin regime and growing Fascism, it was clearly increasingly dangerous for the Party to cling to beliefs which had come down from the Revolution of 1918 but which, in the entirely different circumstances of the latter half of the ‘twenties, produced totally different effects.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As a final result of the lack of a new revolutionary wave, the Party's oppositional role, supported by Bauer, was weakened. Even though the Vienna City Council was able to reap the harvest which it had sown in the early 'twenties, economic stagnation and the strengthening of the reactionary forces weakened the trade unions and, in particular, the position of Social Democracy in the armed forces. After hard work successive bourgeois governments were successful in slowly pushing the Socialists out of the army and replacing them by their own reliable supporters. The power of the trade unions in the army and police diminished year by year. To compensate for this the Party tried to build up its own armed formation - the "Republikanischer Schutzbund"" - whose origins went back to beginning of the Republic when there had been fighting against intruding Yugoslavs on the Republic's Southern borders. At the same time the "Heinwehr" was built up recruited from peasant and bourgeois circles. Like the "Schutzbund" it took over some of the huge arms stores which had remained unclaimed after the collapse of the Hapsburg army in 1918.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As time went on, increasing tension developed between these two party formations. As long as a large part of the army and at least some of the police remained under the control of Social Democracy this did not represent a real danger. But when the army went over to the bourgeois camp, the balance changed ; the "Heimwehr" became an important political factor.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Consequently, there developed a desire within the Party to strengthen the "Schutzbund" so as to restore the balance of power. In working to this end the Party was successful for a time, but there is no denying that, as a result, it overestimated the military power of Social Democracy and gave far too little attention to the real weapons of the workers.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Within the framework of the "Schutzbund" there could be found the best young members of the Party, those most willing to make sacrifices; but among them the illusion was widespread that, in the case of a revolution or civil war, it would be the task of the Party's armed formation to assume sole control of the Party. This overestimation of the purely military factor was shared by many Party members, who allowed themselves to be lulled into a false sense of security since they believed that the "Schutzbund" was the best guardian of the Party's interests and that the unarmed members would be only indirectly concerned in the case of a revolution or civil war. The more military the structure of the "Schutzbund" became, the stronger — both within its own ranks and those of the Party - became the illusions as to its potentialities.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Party did not even deviate from this path when the unofficial and spontaneous demonstrations of 15 July, 1927, led to the burning of the Palace of Justice. The "Schutzbund" which should have played an important role on this day did not function, and thus the path was open for brutal police action. The workers then remembered that their strongest weapon was not the "Schutzbund" but a general strike. But even then it became clear that the combined action of a loyal army and the "Heimwehr" was sufficient to paralyse any chances of a general strike in the Western parts of Austria. Hence the Party was shaken in its views and sought to discover a way out of this blind alley by the establishment of a new coalition. This time it was Chancellor Ignatz Seipel who scornfully refused the Socialist offer, and so there was nothing left for the Party but to continue its old policy of opposition.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The belief that there was a possibility of re-unification with the Communists found expression in Party terminology. At the Party conference at Linz in 1926, after a thorough debate, the phrase "dictatorship of the proletariat" was inserted in the new programme. This dictatorship was, of course, conceived as a weapon of defence, to be used only in case the bourgeoisie destroyed democracy, for democracy was unequivocally supported by the Party. But there remained an inner contradiction for, even granted that the Party had the right to answer a threat of force against democracy with force, why should the misleading term "dictatorship of the proletariat" have been chosen - particularly since at this time, in Communist use, it was synonymous with Stalin's dictatorship?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In wide circles, both inside and outside the Party, this formulation was regarded as a veiled concession to the idea of dictatorship - a concession which was welcomed by many circles belonging to the so-called Left wing of the Party, but regarded as a doubtful half-truth by other Party members and even more so by sympathisers outside the Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Party's position in subsequent years, particularly in the decisive months before the fateful February 1934, proved without doubt that the Party, in adopting this phrase, had not intended any modification of its fundamentally democratic position. It would also be wrong to believe that bourgeois propaganda, which naturally quoted the formula freely, really benefited thereby. The advance of reaction and Fascism had reasons which went much deeper than a quarrel over words or the oppositional attitude of the Austrian Party. Even those Socialist parties which tried to counter Fascism by concessions, or fought alongside democratic bourgeois parties, were vanquished by it. These were yeans when the victorious advance of Fascism could not be held up whatever tactics might be chosen. German and Austrian Social Democracy met the same fate in the end, although the political methods employed by them were almost diametrically opposed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">* * * </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">For Fascism to be victorious one condition was essential in Europe<hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">: </hi>the strength of the working class had to be so weakened through the economic crisis that it would offer no resistance. In the years following the outbreak of the economic crisis and before the victory of Fascism certain peculiar ideological trends developed which were connected on the one hand with the increasing radicalism of the unemployed and, on the other, with the growing weakness of the organised workers in the factories. For the trade unions, conditions became increasingly difficult; their members demanded that, above all, they should see to it that the wages of those who were still employed were maintained. The trade unions remained strong enough to be able to meet this demand to a large extent. At the same time the fate of the unemployed worsened, since under increasing political pressure the welfare measures – once a model to all - had developed loopholes. While the standard of living of those who actually worked remained above a certain level - even if they were, perhaps, forced to work harder - the circumstances of the unemployed catastrophically charged for the worse.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Among them there arose an urge for political action which would restore to the workers that influence on the policy and the economy of the country which they had formerly wielded, Particularly among the "Schutzbund" there was a rapidly growing group which pressed for action, regardless of the increasing changes in the balance of power in favour of the bourgeoisie which was step by step being pushed into the arms of Fascism by Seipel. When he died in 1932, though he had prepared the path for Fascism in Austria, he had destroyed his own party and offered a few adventurers the chance of taking the fate of Austria into their own hands.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Shortly after his death came the Nazi victory in Germany; this quickened the pace of developments in Central Europe and offered Austrian Fascism the choice of siding with either German or Italian Fascism. Engelbert Dollfuss, Seipel’s successor, after hesitating for some time, chose the latter, but there can be no doubt that he would, without more ado, have joined forces with Hitler if there had been any danger of Social Democracy overthrowing him. There is, therefore, no ground for believing that, in the spring of 1933, the Socialists still had a chance of successfully resisting Dollfuss. Admittedly, in March 1933 when Dollfuss, on the most threadbare of excuses, put Parliament out of action, the "Schutzbund" still survived undamaged and the trade unions, by and large, were still capable of action, but on the other hand the conflict between Dollfuss and the Nazis had not yet reached its climax - a conflict which would have come to nothing the moment the “Schutzbund" had taken up arms.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But this view did not suit the more radical groups within the "Schutzbund", who were rightly worried lest the government would first render the "Schutzbund" incapable of action by the confiscation of arms and arrests and then crush the organisation. That premature action would only have made the Nazis enter Austria in 1933 and that the "blood bath" would then have assumed other dimensions than on 12 February, 1934, was something that members of the "Schutzbund" found hard to accept not only at the time but long after.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Party Executive had the enormously difficult task of preventing passions from leading to rash action, or at least of putting it off until, perhaps because of a change in the external political situation, Fascist pressure had decreased. A warning to go slow was not readily acceptable to a party devoted to a radical ideology, and it needed all Otto Bauer’s authority to retain discipline. Never were his democratic feelings and his sense of responsibility seen to better advantage than in these months, when quite probably his own temperament might more than once have led him to cast restraint to the winds. But he was too conscious of his "responsibility to the mothers of this country", as he used to put it in his speeches, to give free rein to his own temperament and that of many radical members of the "Schutzbund".</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It should not, however, be overlooked that in this situation the basis was laid for that tendency among members of the "Schutzbund" which, after the events of 12 February, 1934, allowed the Communists to penetrate circles which had, until then, remained strictly Socialist. It is not the task of this essay to describe the highly complicated ideological currents which formed under conditions of illegality and in emigration. For there the decisive influences were not native Austrian ones but, in the main, international; to describe them would mean writing a history of the Socialist movements during the whole period.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">We must limit ourselves to the fact that 12 February, 1934, was a hard test for Austrian Social Democracy. Not only had the Party been defeated by a foe who - so it had been believed shortly before - could have been pushed aside with ease, but a conception which had been the basic idea of the whole Party had failed. In place of the expected revolutionary wave events had led to a descent into deepest reaction, into complete lawlessness, into terrible material poverty. The idea that democracy could be preserved at the decisive moment if one were sufficiently determined to counter the use of force by the enemy with a dictatorship proved impracticable. The bitterness resulting from this defeat led many followers to accept the idea of a dictatorship; and if the Communists had not deserted the workers’ cause so shamefully in the February days their influence might have grown even stronger.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But soon their methods, not only in February but also later, showed that they were quite incapable of leading the Austrian workers. After initial hesitation, the majority of Austrian Social Democrats, in the shape of the "Revolutionary Socialists", returned to the old ways of thinking. Communist influence dwindled even more as the great purges not only wiped out all the respected old Bolshevists but also found victims among those members of the "Schutzbund" who had fled to Russia.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">If under Dollfuss and Schuschnjgg illegal action was kept going after the Nazis marched in, it was limited to loose contacts among very small circles. It is therefore practically impossible to speak of strictly Austrian ideological developments at this time. But the tradition of the party of Victor Adler and Otto Bauer could not be lost – a tradition, which, as time went by and as the nature of problems changed, led to a new unity in which the personal heroism of the February fighters found its place. It was this tradition which made possible the surprisingly quick recovery of the Party after the Nazis’ collapse - admittedly on an entirely new basis with a new ideology to correspond to the new conditions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The situation in which the Austrian Social Democratic Party reformed itself in 1945 was completely different from that of 1918. In both instances a large empire broke up leaving Austria as a small rump, but in 1918 the revolution looked forward to a world revolution round the corner of which events in Russia were regarded as a foretaste. Nobody then believed that another war was possible and the economic plight was regarded as merely a pausing phase. The reunification of the working-class movement was regarded as the most important tank whoso realisation would ensure the final victory of Socialism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">1945 throw the people of Austria into a deeper misery than that of the years 1918-20. Moreover, they were robbed of the illusion that their saviour would come from the East. Their joy at being freed from the Nazi yoke was short-lived and the awakening intensely painful. If the thousands of Austrian and German Socialists who had learned as soldiers what Russia was really like had become disillusioned, the disappointment of the Austrian population was general when they encountered Communism in the shape of the looting and raping soldiers of the Rod Army and the occupation authorities. Any belief in Socialism in the Soviet Union and in the possibility of a reunification with the Communists has once and for all disappeared among the Austrian Socialists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Accordingly, their ideology and the policy deriving from it now rest on a different basis. They need no longer be on their guard in their tactics lest a luck of radicalism should alienate large groups of the workers and so drive them into the arms of the Communists. The ten years which have passed since the end of the war have clearly proved that the proportion of Communist electors remains fairly constant at 5% irrespective of the situation in home and foreign affairs. One is dealing with a party of "cadres" in the truest sense of the word - one whose membership is not greatly affected even by failure but which, on the other hand, is incapable of attracting the masses.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In 1918 the Communist Party believed that it could achieve its aim by splitting the Austrian workers, and so tried to win Friedrich Adler over to their side - an attempt which, naturally, he resisted strongly. In 1945 the Communists were certain that they would become stronger than the Social Democratic Party and that it would be up to the latter to come to an arrangement with the Communists. They were led to this view as a result of their experience in the underground movement, when part of the "Schutzbund" and some Party functionaries went over from Socialism to Communism. They were strengthened in this belief by their impression that by its victories over Hitler's armies the Soviet Union had won over not only the workers but also large sections of the bourgeoisie. If in 1945 Stalin had chosen the tactics which Trotsky had employed in 1917 with his radio messages addressed "to all", the conquest of continental Europe for the idea of Communism would have been difficult to arrest. But Stalin made the same mistake as Hitler in the Ukraine in 1941: instead of aiming at moral conquests he appeared as a dictatorial conqueror, thus alienating those whom he might easily have won over.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">At the beginning the Austrian and Russian Communists were too sure of themselves. They thought they could subjugate Social Democracy and, with its help, gain a majority in Austria. Thus they allowed the two most important offices in the new State to be handed over to Social Democrats. The Russian occupation authorities themselves appointed Karl Renner Chancellor and agreed with the appointment of Theodor Körner as mayor of Vienna.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The government appointed by the occupation authorities was originally a coalition of Communists, Socialists and the People's Party, into which - at the request of the Russians- all bourgeois elements were merged. The elections of November 1945 led to a terrible disappointment for the Communists, but the policy of the Russians was too closely identified with the Austrian government they themselves had put in power for them to switch over to a policy on German lines, which would have led to a split of Austria into completely separate zones. The only consequence, from the point of view of the Kremlin, was to delay, for a very long time, the signing of the Austrian State Treaty.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">However, the Communist Party did not stop trying to gain control over Austrian Social Democracy, even after 1945. For this purpose it used a Socialist renegade, Erwin Scharf, who upon his return in 1945 from the ranks of the Yugoslav partisans had been appointed General Secretary of the Socialist Party and had tried to play the part of a Trojan horse until he was unmasked and removed from the Party. His hope, and that of the Communists, that he would take a considerable group with him, was never realised; the Socialist Party became healthier as a result of the removal of this foreign body.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">* * * *</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">After 1945, just as under the First Republic, the major problem for Austrian Social Democracy was that of coalition. In 1918 the Party decided in favour of a coalition, because, without the co-operation of the main social classes, the State would have been incapable of functioning. Neither the differences nor the conflicts between the classes diminished as a result of the coalition, but instead of finding expression in or even outside parliament, they took place within the government itself. Each partner in the coalition could calculate beforehand how far he would be able to go with his demands or with his resistance to the demands of the others without shattering the structure of the State.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Coalition is, undoubtedly, not an ideal form of government and in countries where democracy is of long standing and where a two-party system is established it is almost always superfluous. Even though Austria has only two main parties, it is almost impossible to imagine a two-party system which would function properly. Austria lacks that democratic tradition which regards as natural that the governing party should take into account the wishes of the opposition. However much democracy means "government of the majority", it also means Iterance vis-à-vis the opposition. But such tolerance would never be practised by an Austrian bourgeois government enjoying undisputed power since, as the result of a century-old tradition of an authoritarian State, all official functionaries and civil servants who are not members of the bourgeoisie or represent its ideas are considered to be unwelcome intruders and treated as such. For that reason a coalition is the form in which the influence of the rising working class can slowly make itself felt, even if it has not yet gained a majority.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In present-day Austria the impulse towards a coalition has lasted far longer than it did after 1918. In 1918 the worst consequences of the war were soon overcome, and once the peace treaty had been signed the direct influence of the voters was no longer felt. But in the long years of occupation which followed the end of the Second World War the large parties were forced to consider that a sharpening of the internal conflicts would make the country susceptible to external influences and might, in certain circumstances, seriously threaten democracy. For that reason the Social Democrats regarded the coalition not merely as a passing phase, and acted accordingly. In that sense Social Democracy has leaned more strongly on the tradition of Victor Adler than of Otto Bauer; it was symptomatic how strong a feeling was awakened by the celebration of the centenary of Victor Adler's birth, not only among the older generation who had known him personally or had directly come under his spell, but also among younger members in whom his name aroused no personal feelings.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Nevertheless, it would be wrong to assume that in the Social Democratic Party of today nothing remains of the tradition of Otto Bauer and his time. The strong radical undercurrents which have always informed Austrian Socialism ideologically are still effective today, even if, owing to prevailing circumstances, they have been prevented from showing themselves.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">To a large extent, radicalism has changed its objective; whereas during the ‘twenties it was directed against the bourgeoisie, today it is principally directed against the Communists, whose reactionary character has been revealed and who are regarded as traitors to the working class. Austrian resistance to the idea of the so-called "People's Democracy" has been so successful because it has been supported by the whole of the working class. The bourgeois and peasant elements alone would have been incapable of successful resistance; this is proved by the unhappy example of those satellite states where Social Democracy allied itself with Communism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But it would be wrong to draw the conclusion from this that the contrast between bourgeoisie and Social Democracy has become less sharp. Whenever, on any occasion, the bourgeois parties try to utilise their numerical superiority - which still remains - for a stronger offensive against the Socialist Party, such attempts immediately rouse the strongest resistance, particularly among the membership which is ready at all times to use all possible means - parliamentary and other — to maintain and enhance the position of the Party. Now, with the return of normal conditions after the evacuation of the foreign troops, the Socialist Party may begin to look at the problem of the coalition - and its internal policy - from a different angle.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Socialist Party today is the oldest political party in Austria. Even if the Austrian People's Party is regarded as the immediate successor to the former Christian Social Party - and that is true only to a certain extent - Austrian Social Democracy is about a decade older than the other large Austrian party. The Communist Party and the Union of Independents are very much newer phenomena.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Socialist Party has grown far beyond its original framework. While originally it represented almost exclusively the interests of the industrial workers, in the course of time it attracted large groups of the population of a totally different social character. It not only gained the support of the majority of the clerical employees, but also counts a large proportion of the intellectuals among its members, be they civil servants or members of the professions. Even the number of small traders and small businessmen among its members is not negligible.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Especially remarkable is its penetration into the villages - one of the successes of the Socialist Party since 1945. After 1918 it already had large numbers of forestry workers and labourers on large estates among its members. At present, the Party increasingly attracts farm workers, even though these live in close dependence on their employers. A remarkable fact is that among the small farmers - especially those living in mountainous areas - there is a growing recognition that their interests are best safeguarded by the Socialist Party. It is surprising to find in far-off villages the idea of Socialism taking root and growing ever stronger.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Naturally these changes have not remained without effect on the ideology of the Party. But hitherto it has successfully avoided making concessions to these new members on questions of principle in its programme. The Party remains conscious of the fact that its real strength rests on the industrial workers and that it would lose not only in electoral appeal but also in political influence if it changed its character as a working-class party. The People's Party has always complained that it was treated as a "junior partner" in the coalition even though, numerically, it was the stronger party. This is due to the fact that the Socialist Party is a far more homogenous body than the People's Party. The latter has always attempted - though without any real chance of success - to attract and represent all groups, from the industrial entrepreneur to the worker, from the large landowner to the smallholder and farm worker, from the craftsman and small trader to the intellectual. As a result it lacks the inner cohesion which distinguishes the Socialist Party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The elections of 22 February, 1953, proved that the strategy and tactics of the Austrian Socialists were right; as a result they reaped the fruits. The Socialist Party which, seventy years ago, slowly grow from small weak groups of workers who fought one another in bitter battles no "Moderates" and "Radicals", is today the strongest party in the country, and has expanded well beyond the framework of the class which it originally represented. At its cradle there stood the greatest personality Austrian Socialism ever produced - Victor Adler. After the foundation of the Republic the Party was lucky enough to find a second leader of similar stature - Otto Bauer. The present heirs to this rich tradition have understood how to bring together all the currents - those originally present and those brought by the newcomers - in a powerful stream which is leading the Party towards a promising future.</p></body></text></TEI>