<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Finland</title>
         <author>R.H.Oittinen</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>5 January 1957</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.VII, No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
     <p>In Finland, Social Democracy has not had the same possibilities of smooth and peaceful development as in the other Northern countries. The fact that Finland was linked with Russia from 1809 to 1917 has had a decisive influence on her social development. Political life has likewise acquired its own special character as a result of the changes that have taken place in the relations between Finland and Russia.</p><p>On the other hand, the close cultural connections maintained with the Northern countries have had a considerable influence both on ideological developments and on the practical forms of activity in the Finnish Labour movement. The impact of German Social Democracy was also very strong from the beginning of the century up to the 'thirties. The influence of the British Labour movement in Finland is of a later date and did not manifest itself powerfully until the 'thirties.</p><p>In Finland the labour question began to attract public attention much later than in the Central European countries. This was due first and foremost to the fact that our industry does not go further back than the latter half of the 19th century. True, already in the early part of the 19th century there were a few thousand industrial workers, whose conditions admittedly left room for improvement, but social grievances and the significance of the social movement were not yet understood. Indeed, social grievances in Finland at that time were chiefly felt in an altogether different quarter - in the agricultural sphere.</p><p>In the first half of the 19th century the development of Finnish industry was very slow. This was due to the existing political situation - the reactionary policy of the autocratic Russian Emperors - and the prevailing economic views which were more or less of a mercantile nature. But when in the middle of the century changes occurred in both these respects, there resulted a rapid industrial expansion, which before long also brought the labour question to the fore.</p><p>At the end of the 19th century industrial growth in Finland was phenomenal, due in part to the sanctioning of free trade but above all to an abundance of the prerequisites of industrial activity: easy access to raw materials, plentiful water-power and an almost unlimited supply of cheap labour. The great potentialities of the Russian market also stimulated enterprise and gave rise to new industries.</p><p>However, it was not until the middle of the 19th century that Finland had begun to realise in what direction her industry should develop, and even then there were many differing opinions. No system for the rational utilisation of the forests had yet been worked out and it was only when we finally appreciated, chiefly from observing the experience of foreign countries, what riches our forests contained and understood how they could be exploited, that the foundations of our export industries were laid. After this our sawmill industry expanded rapidly, other branches of the timber industry were initiated and alongside them the facilities of older branches of industry, the metal and textile industries, were expanded.</p><p>The unfortunate condition of the rural population also proved advantageous to the growth of industry. Large numbers of young people from the landless rural population were willing to move into the towns and industrial centres, for in the country opportunities of finding work were few and earnings consequently uncertain. Moreover, as wages were low even during the busy season owing to the abundant supply of labour, in many areas the landless population suffered great want, especially during the autumn and in the early spring when the chances of obtaining farm work was at a minimum. Accordingly, the regular although small wages offered by industry were more attractive than the uncertain temporary earnings obtainable in farming. Rural districts thus furnished a steady supply of such younger and older people as were willing to move over to new fields of work to escape cold and hunger.</p><p>On the other hand, conditions among industrial workers during the 19th century cannot be described as good and comfortable. Owing to the plentiful supply of labour, it was not necessary for industry to pay high wages; when the cost of living went up, wages followed only slowly. Furthermore' there was a great shortage of accommodation, and the housing conditions of industrial workers were wretched. As little legislation had been passed concerning the protection of workers, and as the authorities showed little enthusiasm for compelling employers to observe strictly the existing regulations on workers' protection, conditions at the work sites remained bad.</p><p>The result was that our industrial population in the 19th century had a great number of grievances of which, in the main, only employees and employers were really aware. To begin with, the workers - resigned to everything, as usual. - accepted the state of affairs as something that could not be changed, but as hardships increased and their se1f-confidence grew, they began to find the grievances increasingly burdensome, and this finally resulted in deliberate attempts to remove them. But it was not the workers themselves who initiated these attempts. The Initiative came from other social classes.</p><p><hi rend="underline">Early history of the Labour Movement</hi></p><p>The various persons, not members of the working class, who began to work for the abolition of the workers’ grievances, did so from very different motives. Socially enlightened circles, who kept an eye on developments abroad, realised as early as the 1870s that the Socialist Labour movement would gain a foothold in Finland, too, once industry had expanded sufficiently and the number of workers had increased. This view was expressed, for example, by the leader of the Finnish National movement, Professor, later Senator, Yrjö S.Yrjö-Koskinen in “Kirjallinen Kuukausilehti” ("Literary Monthly Review") in 1874 ; he added that the dangers associated with the Socialist Labour movement could be avoided only by measures aimed at removing the most glaring defects in workers' conditions and by giving the workers economic security. Yrjö-Koskinen was not the only exponent of this view; others were thinking on the same lines, even Bismarck, the "Iron Chancellor", who endeavoured to suppress the German Labour movement by a combination of force and social policies. Ideas tinged with Christian Socialism also appeared in Finnish newspapers and periodicals.</p><p>When organisations, formed for the benefit of workers, were founded in the 1860s-1800s, they all started from an acknowledgement of the fact that there was much to be done for the workers' conditions. Some advocated reforms designed to improve existing conditions motivated by the wish to prevent the spread of an independent Socialist movement in Finland; others in order to implement the claims of morality and justice which they professed.</p><p>Organisations working on behalf of the workers were established as early as 1861 and 1866 in Tampere, 1874 in Turku, 1875 in Viipuri and at the same time also in certain industrial districts, for example in Varkaus. However, the significance of those organisations, aimed principally at satisfying the cultural and gregarious needs of the workers, was very small. On the other hand, the organisations known as workers' associations, which were established in and after the 1880s, had a much greater significance. Helsingin Tybvaenyhdistys (the Helsinki Workers' Association), founded in 1884, the first and most vigorous of them, gained an undisputed leadership among these workers’ associations. This was mainly due to its chairman Viktor Julius von Wright, whose leading position is illustrated by the fact that this period is known as that of the Wrightian Labour movement.</p><p>Wright had visited Gormanyand Denmark for the purpose of study in the 1870s and had become familiar with social questions and the activities of the Labour movement. He had been particularly seized by the ideas of a Dane, C.V. Riemested, and by the workers' association activities initiated by him. It was principally on the basis of these impressions that the programme of the Wrightian Workers’ Associations was formulated. </p><p>The main theme of the programme was a striving for harmony and mutual understanding. It was, therefore, necessary to attract different types of people as members. Employers and employees could learn at meetings of the Association to understand each other's standpoints and difficulties. Thus the Workers' Association could help both parties to find a satisfactory solution. Furthermore, the idea was that through personal contact fear and envy would be diminished, and resort could be had to the expedient of negotiation). On the same principle Wright wanted his Workers ' Association to include members from both the Finnish and Swedish speaking groups and, in addition to workers, university graduates interested in the workers' cause, aristocrats, intellectuals, married and single women, in order to make possible through direct contact mutual understanding and a growth in Intellectual comprehension for all.</p><p>The course adopted by Wright and his supporters was fully in accordance with the existing economic and social system, which they regarded as basically just. Wright was also a fervent advocate of free trade, a feature of the capitalist-liberal system, and defended it especially against the criticism of the artisan classes, which was marked by the guild spirit, and the democratic and socialist views expressed by the workers. He believed that the existing political status of the different classes corresponded to their qualifications for participating in political activity.</p><p>The Wrightians waged their most intensive battle against radical plans for social change advocating the use of strong measures, and they intimidated workers by the argument that these demands would cause such indignation among the powers-that-be and in the ruling classes of society that reforms easy to accomplish and important for the workers might be put aside. Social reform and the improvement of the economic standing of workers was to be effected gradually by peaceful constructive work.</p><p>The Wrightian Associations also regarded self-help as especially important and devoted much time and work to the establishment of various relief funds, the initiation of saving activity, the acquisition of necessities through joint purchase, etc. Special efforts were also made to render the trade unions more effective; it was thought that through them workers and employers within the same branch of industry could - again jointly - find solutions to the specific economic and social questions of their branch. Wright was also in certain ways a pioneer in the collecting of social statistics, but his greatest efforts were aimed at stimulating the workers' cultural interests. In his political thinking Wright started from the principle that the workers had to acquire knowledge and gain intellectual maturity before they could begin to demand political rights. Such opinions were very common among the educated classes and those in power at the end of the 19th century. In this way Wright in point of fact supported the dominance of the Swedish-speaking upper class.</p><p><hi rend="underline">The Labour Movement establishes its Intellectual Independence</hi></p><p>Despite the efforts of the Wrightian Workers’ Associations, only minor improvements were effected in the conditions of the working class. In consequence, the feeling began to gain strength among workers in the middle of the 1890s that the course of action recommended by Wright was not correct after all; the workers gradually became better informed about the Socialist Labour movement, and a period of intellectual fermentation began. This feeling of unease was aggravated by the fact that no bourgeois party at the time was particularly inclined to work for the aims considered important by the workers, not even far the extension of the suffrage. It might be as well to mention that until 1906 Finland had a Diet of Four Estates, the representatives for the Estates of the Burghers and the Peasantry being elected under an electoral system based on wealth.</p><p>Already in the 1890s the working class was permeated by the view that a reform of social conditions was impossible without state intervention. It also gradually became evident that the State would not take action on the workers' behalf as long as the workers had no political influence. The most burning question at the end of the 19th and the beginning of the 20th century was accordingly that of the political rights of the working class.</p><p>It was precisely in this matter that the Swedish-speaking upper class worked clearly and deliberately against the workers. The Old-Finn Party, a typical conservative faction, was behaving very cautiously, though it is true that it had shown some democratic interests in the 1880s. Apart from the working class, the Young-Finn group, which represented liberal tendencies, was the group with the largest number of advocates of universal and equal suffrage. This was due partly to their basic principles, partly to political calculation.</p><p>However, the proletarian self-confidence of the working class, which had gained rapidly in the 1890s, proved to be an obstacle to closer co-operation between the Young-Finns and the workers.</p><p>The fact is that in spite of these fine words co-operation between the workers and the so-called bourgeois elements in the Wrightian Workers’ Associations did not proceed without friction. On the contrary, especially in the major cities, there were many points of dispute. The non-working-class members of the Associations might be inspired by a genuine desire to co-operate, but being poor psychologists and having been educated under a system which disparaged the workers, they were incapable of finding the correct approach. Consequently, the workers did not really feel at home in the Wrightian Workers’ Associations.</p><p>The members of the Workers' Association Movement who were manual labourers would for the most part congregate in the trade departments which were sub-groups of the Workers' Association and had hardly any "bosses" among their members. So-called Outdoor Workers' Associations were established in some localities, drawing their members chiefly from among the workers. In these organisations manual workers felt at home; there they learnt to manage their own organisation and they were also able to discuss freely many questions especially concerning themselves, their disappointments and, later, the ideas of Socialism. In these organisations the workers gained self-confidence which was further strengthened by Socialist doctrines. In this way their demand for a party of their own grew and gained force.</p><p>Information on Socialism was generally sparse and vague among Finnish workers in the 19th century. However, the news that trickled in from various sources gradually brought about a way of thinking suggestive of Socialism and differing from the usual liberal bourgeois thinking.</p><p><hi rend="underline">Foundation of the Labour Party</hi></p><p>The question of founding a Labour party forced itself into prominence in the last years of the 1890s. By 1898 it was arousing lively discussion and in some cities, e.g. Helsinki and Tampere, the workers even took measures which showed that they were ready for independent political action when necessary. In particular, events in connection with the resistance movement caused by the February Manifesto showed that the workers even then insisted on a serious consideration of their standpoint and on the recognition of the Labour movement as an independent political factor. The February Manifesto was the Imperial Declaration, induced by Nikolai Bobrikov, Russian Governor-General in Finland in 1899, which in violation of the country's constitution curtailed Finland’s autonomy.</p><p>The basis for an independent Labour party was prepared, for the demands of the working class began to take definite shape: a thorough reform of the suffrage system and social reforms were demanded. As the other parties were not willing to fight actively enough for these claims, the independent line received ever-growing support, and this compelled the Congress of the Workers’ Associations held at Turku in the summer of 1899 to take up the question of the establishment of a party.</p><p>The establishment of the Finnish Labour Party (Suomen Työväenpuole) was decided at this meeting, but it was founded in a very cautious manner. The programme was drawn up on fairly general lines without a single mention of Socialism; its aim was briefly defined as the social and economic liberation of the working class. The short-term aims were based solely on matter-of-fact possibilities, and no social planning for the future was attached to thorn. Thus the main emphasis was on public reform, and social improvements were to be achieved later.</p><p>The discretion observed in the founding of the Finnish Labour Party was also reflected in the fact that the founders entrusted the chairmanship to a person who could count on the widest possible following because of his social position. N.R. af Ursin, a secondary school classics master, was chosen for this post although he was not a practising politician.</p><p>The new party had many difficulties and considerable suspicion to content with. The Workers’ Association had to take a decision on whether they would join the Party, and as many of them still retained a great many bourgeois members, it often took years before an association joined the Pary. However, from the very outset the party comprised about two-thirds of organised labour and one half of the associations. On the whole the major associations sided with the independent workers’ party.</p><p>The independent line of thought gained force fairly rapidly among the workers after the Labour Party had been established some time tidings of the international Labour movement and Socialism were more and more widely spread in Finland. At the Party Congress held at Forssa in 1903 the supporters of Socialism were prepared to take the decisive step and proclaim the party a Socialist Party. The name of the Finnish Labour Party was changed to that of the Socia1 Democratic Party of Finland (Suomen Sozsialidemokraattinen Puolue) and its programme was wholly based on Socialist ideas, much of it being derived from the programme of the Austrian Socialist Party.</p><p>However, it was not until 1905, the year of the General Strike, that the community as a whole and the workers in particular became, conscious of the Labour Movement's existence. The General Strike was protest against the totalitarian system initiated by Govenor-General Bobrikov, but was at the same time linked with demands for universal suffrage and parliamentary reform. Although it was a political strike in which the whole nation - even the police and the University of Helsinki - participated, it was in fact led by the workers and their organisations. The General Strike, therefore, became for large masses of workers an example of the strength of a "mass demonstration". It seemed to provide the final proof of the assertion that unity is power and that the workers too could be an effective political force if they showed enough energy and perseverance.</p><p>It was not until after the General Strike that one could speak of a Socialist mass movement in Finland.</p><p><hi rend="underline">The Break-Through of the Labour Movement</hi></p><p>The General Strike resulted first in an Imperial Manifesto promising the restoration of lawful conditions, freedom of speech, assembly and association, and a unicameral Diet based on universal end equal suffrage instead of the earlier Diet of the Four Estates which rested on historical and economic privileges. Elections under the new system were held for the first time in 1907, fairly soon after the electoral law reform. The Social Democrats won 80 seats out of a total of 200, a proportion which remained approximately the same for ten years.</p><p>The effect of the General Strike on the Labour movement was both direct and indirect. The strike as such awakened interest in the Labour Movement and the political reform effected as a consequence had a similar effect.</p><p>The division of the country into constituencies brought about a complete change in political organisation. Prior to the Parliamentary reform Finland had no political parties organised on modern lines apart from the Social Democratic Party, which had a solid organisation and a definite programme. The other parties were vague both in structure and programme. In preparing for the first parliamentary elections on the basis of universal and equal suffrage and within the framework of the new constituency system all parties were compelled to revise their methods. The bourgeois parties, too, began to organise themselves around a definite programme and leadership and to establish local associations.</p><p>At the Party Congress held at Oulu in 1906 the Social Democratic Party also changed its fern of organisation and established an doctoral district organisation that linked the Party sections ani the municipal organisations locally. Political educational work within the constituency and above all the election campaigns were pursued under the direction of this constituency organisation. A centralised, guiding organ of this kind was an absolute necessity under the electoral system adopted.</p><p>Another natural consequence of the division into electoral districts was the establishment of local workers' newspapers, a district press. Before the General Strike such newspapers existed only in the three largest cities, but by 1909 their number had risen to 16.</p><p>The press has then a very important am of the Social Democratic Party ever since it made its first lame-scale political contribution in the 1907 elections. Newspapers passed from hand to hand and from home to home; their contents were widely quoted and discussed. In the period after the General Strike the faith in the future and the ideological seal prevailing among the workers was so great that, despite their genuine poverty, surprisingly large funds were raised for the founding of newspapers and printing offices.</p><p>After the General Strike the activity of the workers was characterised by increased self-esteem and energy. There self-esteem appeared for instance in attempts to stand apart from others. In accordance with Socialist ideas, the Labour Movement had become conscious of its historic task of improving the workers’ situation and building a new society. Really class-conscious circles set little store by "bourgeois" society, its education and culture. On the contrary, they believed in a Socialist ideal of their own, embracing all aspects of social existence.</p><p>Accordingly, interest in theoretical matters within the Labour movement grew stronger; Marxist literature was published and widely read. The increase in the workers’ self-esteem was also apparent in other ways, first of all in a considerable growth in the membership of the organisations and in the establishment of new organisation. In the years between the General Strike and the Civil War (1918) special organisations were formed alongside the Party in many different fields of work. The women workers’ movement and the workers’ youth movement came into being, closely associated with the Social Democratic Party both ideologically and organisationally.</p><p>However, the most important development was the centralisation of the trade union movement into an organisation covering the whole country. Trade associations had existed in Finland even before the Workers’ Associations, some of them dating back to the 1850s. For organisational and economic reasons these trade associations started from 1887 onwards to join the Workers’ Associations as sub-groups. With their continual growth in number there arose a need for co-operation between groups within the same trade. From this basis the trade unions originated, many of them starting in the latter half of the 1890s.</p><p>The proposal to set up a joint general organisation for trade unions was brought up for the first time at the inaugural congress of the Labour Party, but the attempt did not prove successful because of disagreement partly on matters of principle and partly on personalities. In the early years of the 20th century, even after the General Strike, the tendency to establish trade associations gained in force. That was when the factory workers began to join the trade union movement which up to then had compromised chiefly workers in snail-scale industries or artisans who had become proletarianised.</p><p>The need for a central organisation was naturally intensified when the numbers of workers in the various trade unions and the number of trade unions increased. Above all a leader was needed to direct the educational work and trade union policy. After careful preparatory work, the Finnish Trades Union Organisation (Suomen Ammattijärjestö) was finally established in 1907.</p><p>Corresponding developments took place in other spheres. In Finland the Labour movement had always comprised not only industrial labour but also rural workers. This is understandable when we realise that the industrial workers were still deeply rooted in the countryside road that the conditions of the rural proletariat left at least as much room for improvement as those of the workers in the factories. In addition, the fact that the tenants, the crofters, needed assistance led to the inclusion of farm workers and crofters. This is a very characteristic feature of the feature of the Finnish Labour movement.</p><p>Co-operation among the crofters themselves began after the General Strike when a large crofters' congress, held in 1906, resulted in the subsequent foundation of the Finnish Leaseholders' Union (Suomen Maanvuokraajain Liitto) in 1910. This union and its successors, the Leaseholders' Union and the Smallholders’ Union (Suomen Maanvuokraajain ja Pienviljelijäin Liitto) as well as the present smallholders' unions have all maintained close contact with the Finnish Labour movement.</p><p>Thus, new organisations with various tasks arose alongside the Social Democratic Party, though the Party retained its central position in the workers movement. The Finnish workers believe that social reforms could be effected chiefly by government agencies and that the new economic system, Socialism, would be achieved only if the workers took advantage of the universal suffrage, gained political power and began to use it for the building of the now economic and social order. In order to realise this programme, the Party as a political organisation - according to the view generally hold by the workers - had to retain the leadership, and other organisations had to be content either with supporting it or with carrying out such tasks as were of secondary importance in the mitigation of grievances.</p><p>At the beginning the Finnish Labour movement was not inclined to grant the trade union movement the right to independent action. Ursin, too, at this time demanded that the Party should be considered the leading force, and as late as 1907, when the Finnish Trades Union Federation was founded, its connection with the Party was considered to be so close that it was natural for trade unions as such to become affiliated to the Party. This was regarded as a settled rule, although people not belonging to the Party were granted the right to join the Trades Union Organisation.</p><p>In the years between the General Strike and the Civil War at the end of World War I the ideological line pursued by the Finnish Labour Party movement was rather vague. On the one hand, the workers were staunch adherents of Marxism and regarded the use of violence as permissible on principle, if social reform proved impossible by other means. On the other the workers expected great things from the Diet, so much so that the insignificance of the results achieved through this channel during the Russian regime proved a considerable disappointment to many and contributed to the transition in 1918 to the path of armed force. Naturally, this was not the sole reason for resorting to arms: historical circumstances and the bitterness caused by social conditions had a decisive effect on the development of the situation and on the prevailing mood.</p><p><hi rend="underline">The Finnish Civil War of 1918</hi></p><p>The deterioration of political conditions into open civil war can best be understood if we study the effects in Finland of the Russian Revolution and scrutinize the political and social grievances prevailing in the country at the time the conflict came to a head.</p><p>The collapse of the Russian Empire in March 1917 aroused among the working class undue hopes of the dawn of a new and brighter era, for the position of the autocratic Russian Czar as the constitutional Grand Duke of Finland had been an effective weapon in the hands of the conservative groups. If Finland’s bourgeois-dominated Diet was not liberal, the Emperor and his circle were even less so. Another important factor was the consent given by the Provisional Russian Government to the formation of a Finnish Government, the “Senate”, on a parliamentary basis. This included 6 Social Democrats and 6 bourgeois members; its vice-chairman, the Prime Minister, was Oskari Tokoi, a Social Democrat and Chairman of the Finnish Trades Union Federation. The workers’ representatives thus had a majority at the sessions at which the Russian Governor-General, the chairman of the Senate, was not present. The composition of the Senate had been based on the relative strength of the parties in the Diet. In the 1916 election the Social Democrats had won 103 and the bourgeois parties 97 seats out of a total of 200.</p><p>After the overthrew of the Russian Emperor, Finland at first behaved as if no change had occurred in the relationship between the two countries. In the course of the spring, however, the Finns discovered that the Finnish Constitution did not allow for recognition of the Provisional Government of Russia. According to the Constitution the supreme power was placed in the Diet, when the ruling dynasty became extinct. The Diet consequently drafted a special law, the so-called Supreme Powers Act, and proclaimed itself the holder of the supreme power. In point of fact this signified a denunciation of Russian rule. Either from wholeness or through force of habit regarding formalities the Diet sent the now act for “recognition” but not for sanction to the Provisional Government of Russia, which refused to recognise the new law and considered itself entitled, as heir to the Emperor’s power, to dissolve Finland’s Diet and to order new elections, a method repeatedly employed by the Emperor. The declaration of dissolution was issued, since the Governor-General and the bourgeois members of the Senate supported it. This attitude of the bourgeois circles was motivated by the desire to obtain a bourgeois majority in the new Diet.</p><p>This aroused great indignation among the workers, and the rest hot-headed elements among then began to say loudly that it was impossible to run Finnish affairs by parliamentary means.</p><p>The bitterness and discontent in the ranks of the working class can be also attributed to political disappointments, to the fact that certain major reforms had been delayed. The most important social reforms waiting to be achieved were the institution of the 8-hour day and the Prohibition act. Local government legislation was not yet on a democratic basis nor had the workers any say in local government. Land-ownership relations were old-fashioned; in particular, the situation of leaseholders, the crofters, was very insecure. The country as a whole had made relatively little progress in creating sound social conditions.</p><p>The bourgeois-dominated Diet had not undertaken reforms and bitterness had therefore accumulated. The great election victory of the Social Democrats in 1916 was one of the manifestations of this discontent. The relatively easy descent from parliamentary action to the use of armed force, which took place in a general revolutionary atmosphere, must be understood against this background .</p><p>Revolutionary views gained force especially as the Social Democrats secured only 92 scats against the 108 won by the bourgeois parties in the elections held in October 1917. The revolutionary mood and general unrest showed in other ways. Bourgeois circles had begun arming already in the summer of 1917. In the autumn the workers resorted to the same course by establishing the so-called Red Guards.</p><p>In the new Diet the workers forced some of their claims through by means of extra-parliamentary pressure, i.e. by calling a general strike. Consequently, the Act instituting the 8-hour day, new democratic legislation on local government, and the Prohibition Act, were issued by the Diet in November 1917, in virtue- of the Supreme Powers Act which was introduced in the spring but still awaited "recognition" by Russia.</p><p>Some acts of violence had occurred in connection with the general strike and this made co-operation between the Social Democrats and the bourgeois centre difficult. The bourgeois elements formed a new Senate under the direction of P.E. Svinhufvud, a district court judge. The question of who held the supreme power was in fact still unsettled.</p><p>The final step towards political independence was taken on 6th December, 1917, the day on which the Diet proclaimed Finland an independent republic. Recognition of this measure was received from Russia and the Great Powers in the beginning of the following year. In arriving at this decision no practical differences existed between the bourgeois parties raid the Social Democrats.</p><p>Within the ranks of the workers unrest continued, the more- radical elements gaining influence. In their hands lay the leadership of the Red Guards, which had received weapons from the Russians, and they also seized the political leadership of the Labour movement by a "palace revolution". The Executive Committee of the Social Democratic Party, which held relatively moderate views, was supplanted. The country thus proceeded towards the Civil War which broke out at the end of January 1918.</p><p>One vital cause of the outbreak of open conflict was that the Bolsheviks had seized power in Russia, in November 1 917 and new encouraged the radical elements in Finland by promising weapons and other help.</p><p>When the fighting started, the whole of Southern Finland fell into the hands of the “Reds”. The Government headed by P.E. Svinhufvud broke up, some of its members escaping to Vaasa to lead the resistance movement initiated by the Finnish “Jägers” trained in Germany and a number of Finnish Officers who had served in the Russian army.</p><p>The fighting went on for three months, the “Whites” being helped by Germany, which sent an army for Finland under the leadership of General ven der Goltz. The Civil War ended in a crushing defeat of the Reds.</p><p>Executions, imprisonments and flights to Russia severely depleted the ranks of the Labour Party movement. The workers’ organisational activities were prohibited, the property of the organisations was confiscated, and the publication of papers banned. A continuation of Social Democratic activity seemed impossible. </p><p>This, however, was not the case. Some moderate Social Democratic leaders had not participated in the "red revolt" and when the shooting ceased, they started to re-assemble the workers. Väinö Tanner, the well-known leader of the Co-operative movement, was a dominating figure in this work.</p><p><hi rend="underline">Birth Pangs of the modern Social Democratic Labour Movement</hi></p><p>The Finnish Labour movement underwent great ordeals at the time of the Russian Revolution and the Civil War. There was eagerness and enthusiasm in plenty. Resolutions differing from previous programmes were passed, courses were taken which it was difficult to justify and the possibilities for which were questionable - and bitter disappointments were experienced.</p><p>The result of all this was that at the end of this period the Labour movement was faced with the necessity of thorough self-criticism. When conditions became more stable, it began to look for a new and firm foundation and for a path which would lead to a brighter future.</p><p>This search, however, was not ended by a universally agreed answer. Some saw the only possibility of solving the problems of the workers in peaceful political activity, whereas others believed that only a world-wide revolution could satisfy their hopes. This basic difference in standpoint occasioned the great split in the Labour movement, the birth of two political forces, the Social Democrats and the Communists. The old Social Democratic Party remained in the hands of reformist elements, but the Communists had an illegal Communist party and from time to time legal political organisations. All Communist activity was banned in the years 1929-1944.</p><p>The split did not mean a disintegration of Party activities. The Labour movement was not only politically active. After the split the uniformity which had characterised the Finnish Labour movement prior to the Civil War disappeared. In the absence of one political party exercising central control, different interests within the movement began to regard themselves as equals of the Labour Groups and entitled to independence.<anchor xml:id="bookmark1"/></p><p>The change in Social Democratic ideology within the Labour movement had largely been concerned with the questions of a purely ideological and theoretical nature. It is often said that this was  due to a keener interest in ideology. However, without completely denying this it must be pointed out that the change of the Finnish Labour movement into a more practical reform movement during the 1920s was a result of the wider scope for operation accordedto the movement.</p><p>The first years of Finland’s independence were, it is true, difficult both politically and economically, but the political changes that had taken place began to make their influence felt as from the early 1920. Once the Czar had been deposed, our political life as a whole was freed from external tutelage. The new republican constitution of 1919 was democratic and guaranteed the workers a say in the country’s affairs. The renovation of political life and the possibilities of effecting social and other reforms through parliamentary work directed the workers’ attention to more practical activities so that the idea of a complete change of society gradually faded out of the picture. The democratisation of municipal life had a similar effect in providing the Workers’ Associations and their representative’s with wider scope for action. Moreover, when we recall the speed at which the Co-operative movement began to spread in independent Finland, it will be readily understood that the national and local leaders of the Social Democratic Labour movement were fully employed in practical work, managing and improving the affairs of society. The existence of new avenues of action also reinforced confidence in the belief that a considerable improvement in the workers' conditions we possible through gradual remedies and reforms.</p><p>Yet the division of the international Labour movement into a Social Democratic and a Communist wing produced everywhere far-reaching theoretical discussions, the effects of which extended even to Finland. The leading Social Democratic theoretician in Germany was Karl Kautsky and his ideas were introduced into Finnish literature and the press as a counterweight to the views of the Communist theoretician, Lenin. Articles by Austrian Marxists, above all Otto Bauer, and developments in both British and Scandinavian social and political thought were also watched with considerable attention. However, the decisive influence on the thinking of the Finnish workers cane from the brisk expansion of social reform activity and its positive development in all the countries where Social Democrats were influential.</p><p>Until 1926 the Finnish Social Democratic Labour movement adopted an attitude of reserve towards the commitments of political action. This was relatively natural after the Civil War. The Social Democratic Party did not wish to Participate in the Cabinet although <hi rend="bold" xml:space="preserve">it </hi>was fairly strongly represented in Parliament. In 1926 a new phase began, which led in the following year to the formation of a Social Democratic minority government led by Väinö Tanner. It was in office for only one year but to the Social Democratic Labour movement itself the formation of the Tanner Cabinet meant the "recognition" of independent Finland.</p><p>Thus originated the conditions, both ideological and political, for the birth of an increasingly consistent Social Democratic way of thinking, which has left its mark on the Finnish Labour movement over since the 1930s.</p><p>The theoretical discussions, caused by the internal split in the Labour movement, together with the changes in political and social conditions led to a line of thought in the Social Democratic Labour movement which may to summarised as follows.</p><p>Political activity is a vital factor in the aspirations of the workers, for the State is such a dominant force in our society that this co-operation is needed everywhere. The workers must therefore organise themselves politically and avail themselves of all the possibilities provided by free political activity.</p><p>At the same time it is not easy to gain political power if one wishes to acquire it by winning the support of the majority of the citizens, a procedure which is essential to a democracy. Nor is the administration of public affaire as simple a matter as was believed in the early days of the Labour movement. The realisation of a new economic system requires a period of preparation. The creation of a Socialist society will take a long time, perhaps a whole generation. From all this it follows that the Labour movement cannot confine its activities to the creation of a better future, but must also work for a happier present. It must think not merely of future generations but also of those who are struggling against present difficulties.</p><p>The self-evident inference from all this is that the Labour movement must at all tines lay stress on economic welfare. Movements such as the trade union movement and the co-operative movement increase day-by-day prospects of a more comfortable life for the working class and lay the foundations of a new economic system. The modern Labour movement consequently recognises the great importance of this work in the economic sphere, which goes on side by side with the work of the political Labour movement, although co-operation between the trade unions and political movement are desirable with a view to achieving better results.</p><p>But the modern worker has other needs apart from his material requirements. The creation of a new social system and the remodelling of the present one make a variety of demands on the intelligence of the worker. A strong will and a firm faith alone are not sufficient to build a Socialist society; this also calls for knowledge and judgement. A more thorough knowledge of the different aspects of social life is, therefore, as essential as political enlightenment, i.e. political interests and alertness. The Labour movement needs a great number of exports and skilled personnel, who are desirous and capable of supporting it when circumstances admit of active social and economic reform work.</p><p>Men must live whilst the future is gradually being built and their various cultural needs must likewise be satisfied. For this purpose, large number of different organisations have grown up within the Labour movement with the special task of satisfying the workers’ intellectual and cultural interests. Most of these organisations were established in Finland after the country had become independent. The tremendous growth in their activities gave proof of the increased inner enrichment experienced by the Labour movement and of its efforts to solve the workers’ problems on a much broader basis than before.</p><p>Prior to Finland's independence intellectual and physical education as well as artistic pursuits in addition to political activity were concentrated within the Workers' Associations. Carried on in the shadow of politics, as it were, they failed to develop the strength that appeared when they were given their own special organisations. The establishment of the Workers’ Associations. Carried on in the shadow of politics, as it were, they failed to develop the strength that appeared when they were given their own special organisations. The establishment of the Workers’ Educational Association (Työväen Sivistysliitto), the Workers’ Sports Association (Työväen Urheilluliitto), the Workers’ Musical Union (Työväen Musiikkiliitto) and the Union of Workers’ Theatres (Työväen Näyttämöiden Liitto) hs given a great stimulus to the workers’ cultural interests and enriched their lives.</p><p>As these pursuits are ideologically linked to the general aspirations of the working class, they are today taken for granted in the movement though, naturally enough, the connection between these interests and the workers’ political activity is no longer the same as in earlier days. Regret is often expressed that the Labour movement has become excessively specialised and that within certain social fields of activity the general objective of the Labour movement tends to be forgotten. Regardless of whether this is true or not, there can be no return to the old state of affairs, and hence the Labour movement must be able to retain its unity in the face of decisions arrived at independently on the basis of a feeling of inner responsibility.</p><p><hi rend="underline">The Charter of the Social Democratic Labour Movement</hi></p><p>The period following upon the achievement of national independence was not only a time of constructive progress for the country's Social Democratic Labour movement but also saw a decisive extension in its scope of operation. The split of the 1920s put a great strain on its powers and the hostile attitude of the bourgeois circles made its work more difficult. It was not until the end of the decade that distinct signs of an improvement in the position of the Social Democratic Labour movement began to be seen in all field of social life.</p><p>However, a sudden change occurred in the development of our political life. Fascist-inspired Right-wing elements brought about by force the suppression of the Communist Party at the end of the 1920s and in the first years of the next decade even began to threaten Social Democracy and the entire democratic constitution. The Social Democratic Labour movement was thus involved in a vehement battle of defence from which however it emerged victorious by the middle of the 1930s, reinforced both outwardly and inwardly.</p><p>This struggle vividly and finally emphasised in the eyes of the Social Democratic workers the significance of a free democratic constitution for the realisation of Labour's objectives. Another consequence was that democracy came to be understood as a principle to be applied not only to political life but also to other spheres, especially economic and cultural life.</p><p>This deepened understanding of the essence of democracy also resulted in Social Democratic activities becoming more responsible. The Social Democrats strove for participation in Government not only in order to safeguard the workers' immediate interests but also with a view to managing the country's public affairs in a manner that would correspond to their aspirations and ideals. The Labour movement no longer found itself to be a movement in opposition, with no share in the management of social and government affairs, but accepted its share of responsibility. In the different fields of social activity the Labour movement had achieved a position in which it could influence the course of affairs, and it now wanted to exert this influence.</p><p>Another important matter, which was largely clarified in the 1930s, was the movement's attitude towards the country's independence and its defence. Finland's independence had been gained in very unhappy circumstances, under the shadow of a civil war in which the victorious army, that of the Whites, represented the forces in support of an independent Finnish state. This, as well as the settling of accounts after the Civil War, left in the workers' minds a bitterness, a grudge, although they recognised the vital importance of political independence. The chauvinism of Finland's Right-wing circles and their patriotic snobbery also engendered hostility and antipathy among the workers, and not only towards the abusers of patriotism tut to some extent towards the idea of patriotism itself.</p><p>With the normalisation of political conditions such negative phenomena decreased in all quarters. In particular, the critical international situation in the late 1930s smoothed out the differences and the ill-feeling, so that when the country was in real danger at the outbreak of the war between Finland and the USSR in 1939 (the so-called "Winter War") the Social Democrats unanimously supported the country's fight for independence. The unanimity of the country, "the miracle of the Winter War", was in actual fact no miracle but the result of developments over two decades in the political, economic, social and cultural fields. The different phases of our two wars, surprising as they may have been, did not affect this basic attitude of the workers, although dissenting opinions on the course of action adopted nay have prevailed among them in many cases.</p><p>The intellectual maturing which had taken place in the Social Democratic Labour movement found significant expression in "The Charter", a statement of principles approved by the Congress of the Social Democratic Party in 1952. This Charter replaced the Forssa programme of 1905.</p><p>The drawing up of a new programme of basic principles was embarked upon as the Forssa programme was increasingly considered obsolete and inadequate. It is worth noting that the Charter takes no definite stand on the old controversial point of Marxism, but the arguments employed include many ideas introduced by Marx which continue to be regarded as tenable. The new programme also incorporates many points on which the Forssa programme took no stand or did so in a manner which often led to erroneous conclusions. Yet the 1952 Charter cannot be said to have contributed anything really new or revolutionary to the ideology of the Social Democratic Party. On the contrary, in the main, it gathered together the ideas which had become generally accepted within the Social Democratic Party in the course of the past few decades.</p><p>The Charter embodies three main points on which the movement’s ideology is based. They are concerned with 1) Socialism and social reform work; 2) democracy and the Party's course of action, and 3) national culture, the country's independence and international co-operation.</p><p>The section in the programme dealing with Socialism and social reforms has its point of departure in the recognition of the equality of all members of society and regards “personal ability, skill and morality alone as the foundations of the social position of both men and women". Everybody must have the right to chose his job or profession, to find work and earn a decent living determined on the basis of results. Society must likewise guarantee a measure of social security to all and create the necessary conditions fur a sound and happy life. These objectives can he achieved by changing the economic basis of society so as to cake it serve the interests of society as a whole. Production must be increased by rationalisation but attention must be paid at the same time to the social conditions of the workers.</p><p>An attempt must be made to bring about a thorough change in the character of economic life by increased planning. The success of a planned economy is ensured by transferring key economic positions to public ownership and administration. The transition to a Socialist planned economy must be furthered not only because it is regarded as historically necessary but above all because it is the lest way of removing the conflict between labour and capital and of doing away with the injustices caused by inequalities in ownership.</p><p>The Charter's section on democracy begins with the assertion that "the achievement of mere material welfare or social security cannot be the highest aim of an individual or of a society”. And it adds that the “expansion, deepening and ensuring of a free and rich cultural life for the individual and for society as a whole are equally important”, and “that this is possible only under a democratic system of government”.</p><p>The principles of democracy must naturally be applied to all social activity. "The awareness and consciousness of responsibility which is the essential requirement for the success of socialist co-existence" is capable of full development only under a democratic system of government.</p><p>The safeguarding of democracy calls above all for the preservation of the citizen's political rights and of the opportunities for free civic activity. The forms of democratic political life must be observed. In the Charter the Social Democratic Party specifically demands the observance of democratic and parliamentary practices in all political activity. The Party has thus rejected the vague and somewhat equivocal passage of the Forssa programme in which "all expedients that served the purpose and were in agreement with the people's conception of justice" were accepted.</p><p>The last section of the Charter deals with matters not contained in the Forssa programme. To begin with it acknowledges the value and significance of a national culture which also enables the working class to enjoy its share of general culture. The passage then goes on to state that only in a free country con the people create, an authentic culture and that independence alone will enable it to work freely and effectively for the realisation of the necessary reforms. “A free working class can exist only in a free nation.” The Social Democratic working class therefore gives its full support to measures aiming at the preservation and safeguarding of Finland's independence.</p><p>Having pronounced itself a supporter of Finland’s political independence, the Social Democratic Party then emphasises in its Charter the significance of international co-operation and the importance of the work directed at securing universal peace. It also stresses the importance of maintaining good relations with all nations, for "a national culture can develop; and retain its vitality only by virtue of reciprocal international contacts on both the intellectual and material planes".</p><p>The present Charter of the Finnish Social Democratic Party is the result of a process of maturing, over nearly fifty years, in the course of which the movement lived through many difficult phases calling for strength and faith. It has come safely through all its trials because it believes that its existence is justified and that it has an important historical task to perform.</p><p>The Labour movement is not bound by dogma, and its members consequently hold differing views on many issues. This only goes to prove the vitality of the movement. Naturally there is agreement on certain basic questions; without this the movement would dissolve into a loose and impotent association. The values which are accepted as being beyond all discussion are, principally, the recognition of the basic rights of the individual; the maintenance and development of a free, democratic social and political order; the establishment of a Socialist, planned economy and the creation, of a rich and varied cultural life based on reciprocal national and international action; and, above all, a deliberate endeavour to ensure universal peace through international co-operation.</p></body></text></TEI>