<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Sweden</title>
         <author>Frans Severin</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>31 March 1956</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol. VI, No. 13-14</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
     <p>The Social Democratic Labour Party of Sweden was formed in 1889, mainly by trade unions, which in those days were few in number. Only a very few intellectuals took part in the constituent congress. Sweden was still in the first stages of industrial development and a labour movement in the modern sense had begun to grow up only during the eighties. In 1880 about 70 % of Sweden’s population made their living by agriculture and associated occupations. The urban population was about 15 % of the whole. Since then changes have been rapid. By the end of 1953 the urban population had risen to 49 %, and agriculture and associated trades accounted for less than 25 % of the population. </p><p>At the 1889 Congress, 69 societies were represented; of those, 51 were trade unions. Initially the Party had about 3000 members most of whom were affiliated through trade unions. The organisation gradually evolved along the following lines: the local organization was to be the so-called "labour commune" to which societies and trade union branches in the locality were affiliated, the "labour commune" in its turn was to be affiliated to the Party. The great majority of local organization affiliated to the "labour commune" were (and still are) the trade union branches. Party dues are included in the union subscription and are paid in to the "commune" by the branch in question. By the end of 1953, the Party had 753785 members, of whom about 60 % were trade unionists. The membership of the national trade union organization at the same date was 1,3 million. </p><p>From the start the trade union movement and the Party have been most intimately connected. In the early days, up to 1898, when the national trade union confederation was formed, the Party may be said in practice to have functioned as the national trade union organization. Thus the constituent congress of the national confederation resolved that membership of the Party was to be compulsory for affiliated organisations, a rule which was, however, rescinded only two years later. The development and growth of the Party and of the trade union movement since then have run more or less parallel, although the trade union movement has always had the larger membership. From an initial membership of 3000, the Party rose to 10000 by 1895, and to 67000 in 1905. A setback came after the so-called general strike in 1909, when the membership figure of the central trade union organization fell by 50 % with similar effects on the Party. Recovery, however, was fairly rapid. </p><p>The Party won its first parliamentary seat in the elections of 1896. In 1902, the number of members was increased to four. Suffrage in Sweden at this time was still limited to persons with an income over 800 kronor. Only few Swedish workers had such an income and only about 10 % of the population had the vote. One of the first practical political aims of the Party became the attainment of universal suffrage. After the electoral reform of 1907-1909, the franchise for the Second Chamber (Lower House) was extended to adult males; proportional representation was also introduced at the same time. In the first elections to the Second Chamber in 1911 after the electoral reform, the Party won 64 seats out of 230, the same as the Conservative Party. In 1914 the Party won 87 seats and became the largest in the Second Chamber. </p><p>In 1917 the Labour Party entered the Government for the first time and four social democrat ministers joined an otherwise Liberal administration. Three years later the first Social Democratic minority Government was formed. Since forming their fourth Government in 1932 the Social Democrats have been permanently in office, either alone, or in coalition with the Agrarian Party (as in 1936-39) or with all democratic parties (as in the war years from 1939-45). Since the autumn of 1951, they have been in coalition with the Agrarians who hold four of the 15 ministerial posts. The Party had a majority in the Second Chamber from 1940 to 1944 and an overall majority in both Chambers from 1940 to 1952. The Party still has a majority in the First Chamber. </p><p>The following account is mainly based on programmes and statements passed by the Party Congress. The author has, however, thought it proper to make some reference to the general debate both at the Congresses and elsewhere. The choice of topics which may be taken to reflect the ideas of the Party must unavoidably be somewhat arbitrary; in a brief account, allusion can be made only to a small section of a very wide debate; in a large Party, where liberty of thought has always been respected, there has naturally been no lack of arguments and ideas. It has therefore been necessary to select those topics that may be regarded as representative. Nor have the Congresses - naturally enough - been unanimous. The decisions have been majority decisions and even when the Congress has been unanimous, this does not necessarily mean that the Party has been so. Thus, the overall picture is necessarily coloured by a general view of the developments, the motives and the thought which lie behind the changes in programme produced over the last few decades. </p><p>Naturally the ideas which inspired the first Congress were neither very precise nor very clearly grasped. Marxism may be said to have been the general ideological foundation, but its somewhat complicated theories cannot have been very familiar to most of the delegates and -later - members of the Party. It is also open to doubt whether there was any agreed interpretation of Marxism as far as it <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">was </hi>known. The Congress did not formulate any basic programme, but the first paragraph of the statutes ran: “The aim of the Party is to realize the theories of Social Democracy as laid down in the programme of the Party.” This probably referred to a programme that had been adopted by the Social Democratic Union (Socialdemokratiska förbundet) of Stockholm in 1887 and which was largely a translation of the Gotha Programme of 1875. There was no ideological uniformity within the Party and other societies elsewhere had adopted different programmes, differently formulated. At the second Party Congress in 1881, there 'was a sharp conflict between a considerable minority of anarchist tendencies, and what might be called the Social-reformist majority, whose attitude might, to use a more modern term, be described as revisionist or reformist. Of course, the Congress cannot be said to have expressed a clearly conceived policy of revisionism as opposed to the doctrines of Marxism. It was rather that a purely practical effort to achieve certain limited but continuous reforms emerged as the more clearly defined aim of the Party in contrast to the idea of an immediate, violent revolution cherished by the minority. But whatever its theoretical links with Marxist ideology, the Party may be said to have followed the revisionist line from the start. The constituent Congress stated "that in its efforts to organise the Swedish working class for the conquest of political power, the Social Democratic Party of Sweden will use only such means as correspond to the natural sense of justice of the people". The reformist standpoint thus taken up from the start has remained that of the Swedish Party in practice and in theory. </p><p>It was only in 1897 that the Party worked out a programme of its own. Both in its terminology and in its general view of Society it was undoubtedly more in harmony with Marxist theory than that of 1889; nevertheless, the revisionist point of view was given conscious and considered expression. For instance, the programme does not presume constantly growing misery among the masses and the practical struggle of the trade union movement for small improvements in working-class conditions is regarded as an important step in the general advance. It was logical that these views should be summed up in the penultimate paragraph of the new programme: "Social Democracy therefore wishes to organise the working-class politically, to take over power and by degrees to transfer to public ownership all means of production - forests, mines, iron and steel works, machinery, factories and land." </p><p>Gradual social change through planned reforms, hence the expression "by degrees", has remained the Party's aim. Theoretically the possibility or necessity of a violent revolution is not entirely excluded - at least not in certain countries - but in practice any suggestion that violence or extra-parliamentary means of seizing power be used has always been rejected. Naturally the acceptance of this policy had to depend on two conditions: that full citizenship became universal and independent of income or property; and that those social groups which were opposed to the aims of the Social Democratic movement would always respect reforms achieved by legal methods. The first condition had not yet been fulfilled when the 1897 programme was passed, but evidently the majority was convinced that this state of affairs could very soon be realised and that in any case this way had to be tried first. In the general debate on the ideas and tactics of the Party, this problem was naturally much to the fore; it was frequently pointed out that in the long run the working class or the poorer sections of the population could not be expected to endure in silence refusal of their political rights as citizens, but would have to conquer them if the rich obstinately clung to their privilege. The Congress of 1891 had already stated that "being revolutionary in character, the Party had to take into account the possibility that organised violence might be the final redeemer of the suffering proletariat", but had added that "so long as the peaceful means of universal suffrage has not been tried", methods of violence were rejected. The Congress of 1900 stated its adherence to the aim of previous congresses namely "to make the workers accept the idea of the conquest of political rights should those in power prove they lacked the will to solve the problem". A warning of the seriousness of this statement may be seen in the three day's strike proclaimed in 1902. But these arguments lost their practical significance as political democracy was in fact achieved. As had been previously laid down, the guiding principle for action remained that social change had to be supported by a majority of the people. Yet for the Swedish Party the problem was never reduced to a mere question of parliamentary arithmetic. The Party was "Marxist" in so far as it pre- supposed a change in the way of thinking of the people parallel to the economic and social change which was taking place. </p><p>Later, the reformist standpoint of the Swedish Social Democratic movement was never questioned. It is true that this problem was one of the many on which heated debate took year and the formation of the so-called Left-Socialist Party. But the number of members who left the Party was comparatively small and when the Left-Socialist Party was transformed into a Communist Party which joined the Third International, most of them returned to the Social Democratic Party and accepted its ideology and tactics, which were by now purely reformist. </p><p>During the Party's 65 years life, its programme has undergone considerable changes both with regard to general principles and to concrete political aims. These changes have undoubtedly in part been reflections of corresponding changes of opinion brought about by new experiences, by changes in social organization and so in the position of the Party place in the years before 1917; the result was a split in that itself, by new problems, and by old problems seen from new points of view. But it is not difficult, in spite of all these transformations, to discern the framework of permanent ideals which have remained through the years although in the course of events they have required to be expressed afresh through the practical activity of the Party, through fresh tactical planning and so on. </p><p>For reasons which will be easily understood, fresh thinking and debate have been liveliest over the problem of socialisation. This is unquestionably the most important question in the sense that it is here that Social Democracy represents views differing in principles from those of other parties; it is through its views in this matter that Social Democracy has become Social Democracy. This is why problems connected with socialization will take up by far the greater part of what follows. </p><p>According to the original formula, which was regarded as authorized by the first Congress, the Party stated that "the liberation of the workers demands that the instruments of labour be transformed into a common utility of society and that social labour be publicly regulated so as to ensure fair distribution of the fruits of labour and their utilisation for the public good." The programme of 1897 deals with the same concepts but, as shown by the quotation above, emphasises that the transformation of the means of production into public property is to be gradual. The statements in both cases are based on the assumption that economic evolution will gradually concentrate the means of production in the hands of a few, while the mass of the population becomes a class of impoverished wage-earners. The large wage-earning class will be more or less directly opposed to the small capitalist class for it has incorporated "the derelict remains of the old middle class", whose social characteristic -- like that of the workers - is "that it is without property and thus lives in a state of dependency and oppression". Following the Marxist line of thought, this development of the economic organization of society inevitably leads to a struggle between the two classes which does not cease till society has taken over the function of ownership from the capitalists and organised production so as to satisfy the needs of all. In its new form, the programme is more coherent and more closely reasoned than that of 1889. This is particularly indicated in the exclusion of the Lassallean recommendation for "the solution of the social question by the establishment of state-aided Socialist productive associations under the democratic control of the workers, from which the socialist organization of united labour will emerge". </p><p>Behind the 1897 programme there undoubtedly lurks the idea that socialization is more or less synonymous with nationalisation or municipal ownership of the means of production. The somewhat vague intermediate stage of "socialist productive associations" is dismissed and the change-over is to be brought about by the complete transfer of the means of production to public ownership. This does not mean that socialization or partial socialization would be regarded as being achieved by the state or a municipality taking over an undertaking and running it under public management. In that case, a certain degree of socialisation had already taken place in Sweden, for in certain fields the Swedish State was at that time already running various undertakings in competition with private ones. But the State - even if not the capitalist State - as the highest centrally organised organ of society was nevertheless regarded as the institution in whose hands all real economic activity ought to rest. All productive means were to be public property. No exceptions are laid down. This is merely the logical consequence of the views previously expressed in the programme, viz. that large scale production would gradually come to be dominant and that "capitalist monopoly" would become universal. </p><p>In time, however, this view was to be modified. At the 1911 Congress, certain important changes were made in the wording of this and other points in the programme. On the whole, the 1911 Congress seemed to indicate somewhat altered views on both the course and the results of economic evolution. This is evident in the first paragraph of the general principles where the 1897 programme states that the aim of the Party is the "social liberation of the working class" while the 1911 programme uses the expression "the liberation of the oppressed classes". The experiences of the past years had shown that social stratification was more differentiated than had previously been assumed and would probably remain so. The main stream of the economic evolution certainly seemed largely unchanged, but in many practical aspects social developments seemed to be becoming more complicated. There is a direct connection between the change in the first paragraph and the statement introduced a few paragraphs further on that "capitalism ... even where it allows the old middle classes ... formally to survive under- mines their independence". The 1897 programme mentions "the disappearance of older social classes" and "the emergence of new classes". But it seems to assume that they all belong to "the derelict remains of the middle class" which become absorbed in the working class. The same difficulty of foreseeing further development in all their detail seems also to have been the reason for another re-formulation. The 1897 programme states that the class struggle "will never cease till the working class has ceased to be a class of wage earners". In 1911 this formula is replaced by another according to which the class war "will never cease until society has been so organised that the fruits of the labour go to those who labour". This does not imply any change in the fundamental idea of the programme but, expressed in this way, it gives a wider choice of the forms in which liberation may be realized. </p><p>As a consequence of these changes, which are evidently inspired by the same line of thought, there follows a paragraph in the chapter on the general principles as applied to agriculture. It reads as follows: "Where means of production and labour are still united (as among the independent small farmers or handicraftsmen), this demand (that the fruits of labour shall go to the labourer) is fulfilled. But we must also demand that in modern production, which is dominated by large scale industry, the monopolies of private capitalism be put under public control and ownership in order to replace the present unplanned modes of production by production adapted to the real needs of the community in which the means of production are used in the way most favourable for their economic utilisation". The 1897 programme states that <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">"in former times </hi>private ownership of production was a natural condition because it assured the producer of his product". The difference between these formulae is important; the 1897 programme regards this condition as belonging to a past era, never to be expected to return, while the 1911 programme considers it to be actually existing and likely to continue into the future. </p><p>A more concrete expression of this line of thought is found in the new passage in the programme setting out the party's view of agriculture. The passage begins with the statement that "the soil and its riches, like other essential means of production, must become the property of the working population". But it goes on: "Since at present small farming still exists side by side with big farming, and since in this field capitalism presses forward under forms differing in part from those in industry, the struggle against exploitation has in part to be carried out on other lines. Among the farming population of Sweden the small farmers, crofters and agricultural labourers are incomparably the most numerous. For the small farmers, the land in not a means of acquiring the fruits of the labour of others, but only a means of earning a meagre livelihood for himself and his family. Like the wage-earners, he belongs to the exploited classes. Any agricultural policy aimed at profiting these land workers must therefore aim to increase the yield of the land; it must prevent the land from falling into the hands of capitalist monopolists and speculators and instead guarantee the fruits of their labours to the cultivators of the soil. Society must at the same time see to it that suitable land is kept available on reasonable and safe conditions to those who wish to devote their labour to the soil." </p><p>In accordance with these views, the Party demands that "private monopolies of special natural assets, such as large forests, mines, water falls and large peat bogs, should be transferred to the community as part of a system of concessions to prepare the transition to socialization. Donations of crown land should return to the community in cases where this is equitable. Important timber floating channels should be taken over by the community. </p><p>"State and municipalities should extend their ownership of land. State domains should according to the circumstances be leased either for large scale cultivation by cooperative or, given satisfactory safeguards for the workers, by individual farmers - or in small lots, on terms which will safe- guard their permanence and the rights of the cultivator. Building land should be made available on lease, with right of preemption or repurchase." </p><p>The changes in the programme dealing with the transfer of the means of production to public ownership limited the general principles to a declaration that monopolies in the ownership of private capital should be placed under public control and ownership. Since everybody in the Party probably agreed that large scale capitalist production would monopolize enterprise, at any rate in industry, this revision of the programme, though it represents a more guarded statement of the aims of the Party, does not represent any real change in its standpoint. But as far as Social Democratic agricultural policy is concerned, a modification unquestionably took place. To judge from a speech at the Congress by Mr Hjalmar Branting, this topic was the main reason for the comprehensive revision of the programme. In 1897, the attitude of the Party was defined briefly as follows: "Agricultural credit should be organised by the State. Legislation of this kind while guaranteeing a rationalized form of agriculture prevents the expropriation of smallholders without compensation or the loss of their right to cultivate". At the 1905 Congress an addition had been made to this statement to the effect that measures should be taken to protect the interests of workers and smallholders against the domination by private companies while the State should lease land with the proviso that rational working methods be applied and the leaseholders' independence and right of cultivation guaranteed. The general principles of the year 1897 however still expressly stated that the land like other means of production, should be transferred to private ownership. In the 1911 programme, the passage quoted above was replaced by an entirely new formula. Its purpose was to widen the Party's range of action and to adapt the Party's practical policy to the possibilities arising from the incalculable changes caused by the general progress of things. The purpose of the Party was said to be to "define the aims and methods of this policy and to unite the masses in favour of it with a view to the ultimate realisation of a socialistic organization of Society along the lines and in the order indicated by the general developments". In this connection, it was considered likely that agriculture would to some extent be run under private ownership. This is further emphasized by a statement in the paragraph concerning agriculture. Here the demand is made that "small-scale cultivators of land belonging to others, such as crofters and lessees of companies should be released, if necessary by compulsion". There is no doubt that the purpose of this statement was that land thus set free should be transferred into the private ownership of the smallholders. Moreover, this operation was to be facilitated by public control of the credits required for this purpose under the direct management of Society. </p><p>In accordance with this declaration, the Social Democrats initiated a policy designed to serve the interests of smallholders and increase their numbers and acreage. In 1947, the Party introduced the latest version of its agricultural policy, by a Government Bill which was passed by the Riksdag of that year. It represents, in parts, a reaction against the parcelling out of agricultural land. The organization of Swedish agriculture should be based on family units of about ten hectares with, in addition, a suitable amount of forest property in those parts of the country where conditions make such a combination useful or even indispensable. This naturally does not exclude the possibility of large-scale agriculture, though the topography of the country renders such an agricultural structure on the whole less advisable. </p><p>There can be little doubt that the important changes in the programme instituted at the 1911 Congress are partly to be explained by tactical considerations. Social Democracy had at that time already attained an important position in Swedish politics. In order to gain a really decisive influence, the number of seats in the Riksdag had, however, to be considerably increased. There were strong reserves of potential electors among the agricultural classes, the great majority of whom were not above the economic level of the industrial working class. But a definite majority among them were property owners. The arable land of Sweden was divided into about 400000 units, most of them small. Big estates were comparatively few and represented but a minor portion of the cultivated land. In addition, there were a great many industrial companies owning enormous land properties, although these consisted less of arable land than of forests. In forestry, organization on a large scale had proved to be decidedly more successful. Peasants living in forest districts were to a large extent dependent on wages earned in forestry, which furnished an essential part of their livelihood. Thus the Social Democrats had every reason to inspire the confidence of these groups of the population. </p><p>It would, however, be a mistake to regard the extensive changes which the programme underwent at the 1911 Congress - although in themselves they would deserve special attention - as manifestations of crude opportunism. In making these changes, the Party did not in any way abandon its work for the liberation of the poor from capitalist "exploitation", which was the object of the Party as defined in the 1911 programme. It was assumed that the smallholders would cultivate only their own piece of land with the assistance of members of their families; they would not employ labourers. As early as 1897 it had been considered that this practice would "guarantee that the fruits of labour would go to the producers". In 1891, however, it was assumed that this system would inevitably be destroyed by the growth of capitalism. Should developments fail to confirm this assumption, there was no other reason for not allowing the principle of smallholdings. Broadly speaking, it conformed to the order of things at which the Party professed to be aiming, viz. "that the fruits of the labour should belong to the workers". As far as small scale agriculture was concerned, the ultimate goal of the Party could be considered to have been achieved. The change in programme could not be said to have produced any real modification in the aim of the Party. It simply implied that concentration of efforts viz. large-scale production, would not be applied in every case as a matter of course as the only mode of production. This mode of production could not always be regarded as necessarily the most favourable. Had this not been the case, the Party would never have been in a position to recommend the formation of smallholdings by compulsory expropriation of land from large estates. This change in attitude of course indicates a different view of the social progress; yet it does not imply anything more than a confirmation of the fact that the Marxist theory of concentration had not held good in all fields. It is a nice question whether up to then the Social Democrats in terms of ideology had not merely accepted concentration as inevitable but had also striven to bring it about as a <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">sine qua non </hi>of a socialist reorganization of Society. This problem never arose in the practical work of the political Party. </p><p>Perhaps it gives a false impression of the social views of Social Democrats if one distinguishes between aims and means; for it might easily suggest that in the Social Democratic ideology there existed some such ready made plan for a socialist society - even in a more or less sketchy form - such as our opponents so often attempt to find there. No doubt, in the terminology of Marx and Engels, phrases may be found which may appear to indicate the existence of a definite goal of this sort. However I do not intend to discuss in this context whether any such ideas were actually entertained. Swedish Social Democrats have probably generally agreed that progress never reaches a final goal i.e. that there is no hard and fast line between the realm of necessity and that of freedom, but that progress is continual and continually changing. This attitude is defined in the Party's programme by the statement that the aim of the Party is to bring about a Socialist organization of Society in the way and the order progress itself will indicate. A Party engaged in practical politics must nevertheless adopt a target dealing not only with immediate reforms in various social spheres, but also with more general theoretical aims which then serve as the Party's guiding star. No Party can exist without such an outline of aims. This general definition of the Party's aims gives a special sense of continuity to demands for reform. It has been defined in the Party's programme and else- where in such terms as "the liberation of the working class", "the liberation of the suppressed classes", "the fruits of labour belong those who work", "the transfer of the monopolies of private capitalism to society", "a share in ownership and control", etc. This implies, on the other hand, that the work of the Party is governed by these ideals, irrespective of what forms economic development may assume. The practical realisation of these ideals may vary with the form of Society, yet the ideals, in principle, remain the same.&#x2028;Such an attitude will naturally produce modifications in the definition of the Party's objectives, in the light of experiences. It also follows that the means of realising the ideals will be adapted to constantly changing situations which cannot be predicted with any degree of exactness. As emphasized above, the Swedish Social Democratic Party has never been doctrinaire. In its practical work, it has always been reformist. The changes in the 1911 programme must be regarded as the fruits of gradual progress during a period when Society had assumed a different shape from that of the preceding fifteen years. </p><p>As early as 1920 it was felt that the time was ripe for a new and extensive revision of the programme. New developments had created new problems and new ideas as well as new views on the old ones. Between 1911 and 1920, enormous developments had taken place both in the life of the Swedish Party and in the world outside. A World War had radically changed conditions in Europe. Revolutions had taken place in Russia, Germany and Austria. The whole of Europe was in a state of turmoil. In Sweden, the Social Democratic Party had split into two. A new Party with communist tendencies had arisen. For the first time, the Party had been represented in the Government. In cooperation with the Liberals, they carried out a revision of the constitution which completed the process of democratic evolution by increasing the number of Social Democrat seats in the Second Chamber and promising a further increase of the strength in the First Chamber. The Party felt that it might at any time be called upon to form a Government. In 1920, the Party was asked to take office and formed its first minority Government. The elections which took place after the formation of the Government were a setback for the Party, which lost 11 seats in the Second Chamber. After holding office for little more than six months, the Government resigned. If these important events had failed to affect the Party's attitude to Sweden's domestic problems, this might easily have been cited as an instance of doctrinaire sterility. In fact, the situation forced the Party to reconsider its tactics on the main problem facing the Party - namely socialisation. This was necessary because of the formation of a new Party, which took its cue from the Russian revolution and demanded that similar tactics should be adopted in Sweden. The fact that the reformist line previously followed by the Party was strictly maintained proved the Party's open-mindedness to new points of view, its determination to keep abreast of developments, to tackle new problems unhesitatingly and its firm character. A minority of Party members had urged that since the Party lacked a Parliamentary majority, the time was now ripe for an immediate and thorough social revolution by force. This course was rejected (as it had been at the beginning of the nineties) in spite of the threat of a Party split, which duly took place. In the course of the debates in the Press and on the platforms, the Party urged that a violent conquest of political power would not help to promote the realization of socialist ideals nor serve the interests of those classes of Society on whose behalf Social Democracy had acted originally. Whatever the result of a revolutionary upheaval, a civil war in Sweden - where the bourgeoisie presented an unbroken front - could end only in general ruin which would not set right for many years. </p><p>The transfer of the means of production into the hands of Society and, consequently, more even distribution of income could not alone put an end to poverty, since from the point of view of the less fortunately placed wage-earners, the gains would be rather insignificant. To get rid of poverty, it was first of all necessary to increase production. The revolutionary upheavals, however, would reduce production for a considerable time to come. In order to secure any material increase in production, the adoption of planned production under the control and supervision of the State would be indispensable. This did not automatically follow from nationalisation. On the contrary, it might be important not to suppress all private initiative, for bold ideas and experiments were by no means always inspired by greed. There is no doubt that an atmosphere of individual independence and freedom is favourable to intellectual work. </p><p>The debate on principles was obviously also influenced by guild-socialist ideas, which at the time were being propounded by certain English socialists who had attracted a considerable number of adherents there. State management was nothing new in Sweden. In particular where communications were concerned, the State had for long shown the way and was later to extend its activities. This also applied to various fields of enterprise in which the State had for long owned large-scale natural resources which had become a source of profit to the Nation through technical advances, modern industrial developments and world commerce, e. g. the exploitation of forest and water power. More recently, the State, for fiscal and temperance reasons, had monopolized the tobacco industry and the sale of alcoholic drinks. It could hardly be maintained that the State had any special qualifications for such tasks - quite apart from the fact that State management was naturally influenced by the chaos that was said to exist in private production. State-controlled trades were run rather like public offices. In view of the way in which public affairs was otherwise managed, the official methods seemed too stiff and bureaucratic to serve as a standard of any kind. </p><p>At the 1920 Congress which was held as a more or less direct result of the debates mentioned above and of the disturbed conditions then prevailing in the world) several fairly important alterations were made in the programme. Several changes were introduced in the statement of principles. They did not, however, entail very remarkable modifications in the Party's attitude to social development. The changes were on the whole simply editorial- the principal purpose being to use a more exact terminology and to make the logic of the arguments advanced more coherent. On the other hand, the most urgent question, i. e. the problem of socialisation, attracted particular attention. Here what was undoubtedly a very important change was made. In the 1911 programme, this question had been dealt with almost in passing in the section on agriculture. In the political programme of 1920, it was treated separately as part of the Party's concrete political programme immediately after the statement of general principles. "All natural resources, industrial undertakings, institutes for banking and credits, means of transport and communications (it read) are to be transferred to the ownership of the State, with expert management and proper guarantees against bureaucratic methods. Workers and consumers should participate in the administration of the State undertakings. State control should be applied to undertakings remaining in private hands." It is debatable, perhaps, whether or not these statements represent a change in attitude. In actual fact, the difference from the brief declarations in the 1911 programme is quite insignificant. In the declaration of principles of 1911, private capitalist monopolies were to be put under the control and ownership of the state in order to substitute a planned economy for the existing confused state of production. In the section on agriculture, the political programme states that private monopolies of specific natural resources are to be handed over to the State. The paragraph on socialization drawn up in 1920 undeniably expresses a similar view. It is nevertheless also undeniable that the formulation or the statement was due to fresh experience and new opinions on the problem. They affect not the fundamental views but the practical procedure. On the other hand, the difference between the 1920 programme and that of 1897 is conspicuous. </p><p>What is perhaps more striking is that in 1920 the question was given a more precise definition in the context of the political programme, the purpose being to concentrate attention on the immediate tasks. This does not, however, signify any fundamental change. The change affects only the view as to the timing of the operation. The discussion on the subject at the Congress strongly indicated that a deeper insight into the problem had come about as the Party felt that the time of realizing its programme approached. This debate not only reflected the determination of the Party to bring about socialization but an understanding of the fact that the question was far more complicated than had so far been supposed and that there were other sides to the matter than simply nationalization of the means of production. It was felt that State-controlled production - if it assumed a monopolistic form - might lead to uneconomic methods. Competition, it was stated, was after all a vitalizing factor. For that reason, new private initiatives in socialized branches of industry should not be prohibited. It was strongly emphasized that socialization must represent a gradual evolution which ought to take place without any infringement of freedom of enterprise. Rigid centralization had to be avoided. The goal aimed at should rather be branches of socialized industry to be self-run with various different groups of opinion represented. Since it was generally accepted that private enterprise would continue to exist, any State enterprise which did not enjoy a monopoly would have to be competitive. Private enterprise should, in various respects, be subject to control; but this must not interfere with a reasonable chance to function. There ought rather to be honest competition in efficiency between State and private enterprise. </p><p>In the light of experience acquired in the course of time and growing insight into the nature of the problems, the Party honestly faces the conclusions; but changes in the Party programme are invariably undertaken cautiously because of the uncertainty of the future and because the constant fundamental principle of the Party's work so require. If a nationalized undertaking were not more productive than a private one, what benefit was to be expected - all things being equal - from the nationalization of an undertaking or industry? Complete nationalization would, no doubt, make it easier to achieve a more even distribution of income. However, such a levelling of income could to some extent be achieved through taxation. Furthermore, the gains accruing to low-paid employees from nationalization would undoubtedly be insignificant - that is to say if production remained more or less stationary in relation to the working population. A real profit could be expected only through more efficient utilization of the productive resources, leading to an increase in productivity. As far back as the 1911 programme, "planned production" had been discussed. The same line of thought, further developed and emphasized, underlies that part of the programme, in which the aim of the Party is stated to be the transfer to public ownership of all resources, both natural and productive, required for the establishment of a planned economy. Strong emphasis should be laid on "planned economy". In order to achieve a planned organization of that kind, it would not be necessary to place all industrial activities in the hands of the State. On the other hand, nationalisation would be of no avail without proper planning. Perhaps full utilisation of all resources, which was the basis of the idea of socialization, could be achieved by the retention in the hands of the State of certain natural assets or of such a predominant part of important natural and productive resources together with the credit system of the country that the State continued to have dominating power over the economic life and public economy of the country - an influence which could be further supplemented by public control over such industrial undertakings as remained in private hands. </p><p>To what one might call this modernized version of socialisation a further point was added, stipulating that workers and consumers should participate in the administration of the public undertakings. The Social Democrats had always criticized the fact that large-scale modern capitalist production turned the great majority of the people into wage-earners, excluding them from all share in the administration of the country's economic life, and made them only incidentally interested in the results of production. In the eyes of the majority of workers, this interest was of so little importance that it seemed to lack reality. As pointed out in one programme after another, such interest could exist in small undertakings where management of the productive process and of the means of production were usually in the same hands. Only some kind of collective cooperation in administration could possibly produce a similar interest in big undertakings. </p><p>In itself, this idea was not new to the Party. Indirectly and admittedly a little vaguely, it had been expressed in the programme by the statement that mere work for wages should cease. These concepts reappeared in new forms through ideas of guild socialism and industrial democracy, according to which wage-earners should participate more directly in and be more responsible for the administration of the undertaking for which they worked. At the Congress, a speaker stated that nationalization and systematic increase in production which went with it might give the wage-workers more bread, but that they would continue to feel themselves to be outside the productive process and only indirectly responsible for and interested in the output. From this point of view, it would be logical to postulate industrial democracy in private industry also. What gains might accrue from this was naturally uncertain - at least at a first glance. The attitude and tasks of the trade union movement also served to complicate the problem. It also went without saying that the trade union movement, through which the wage-earners had already secure certain improvements in their position in the production as well as an indirect influence on the administration, could not be replaced by industrials councils appointed separately for each individual undertaking. As yet the production was mainly in the hands of private owners while the Social Democratic Party still remained a minority. The workers could not abandon the weapon they had created for their protection in the trade union movement. But new ideas exist to be tested in practice, and the Social Democratic Party - not being doctrinaire - has never hesitated to try out new proposals although, on the other hand, it has never moved at a pace which did not allow it to retain a control of the situation. </p><p>The fact that the programme devotes a special section to consumers' cooperatives and attributes an important role to it, is another instance of a more enlightened view of social development. Both the Party and the trade union movement had always maintained an attitude of friendly support for cooperative ideas. Such a standpoint was natural if only because it was mainly workers of a social democratic turn of mind who had originally started and led the cooperative movement, whose members were mostly workers and also deeply interested in the Party and the trade union movement. The cooperative movement had, however, been considered a mere palliative within the frame of capitalist society. Thus, at the 1900 Congress, it was stated that "with reference to the Party's programme for the socialization of the means of production ... the working class could expect no essential improvement in its position in society before that . . . (The Party nevertheless) expressed its sympathy for the cooperative movement as an educational form of transition to the goal fixed by the Social Democrats ..." The 1905 Congress rejected a resolution proposed by eighty delegates. The resolution stated that "the educational significance of the cooperative movement as a mean of instilling into the workers knowledge and capacity to lead and control production and distribution. .. should on suitable occasion be stressed by the labour press and by the Party's speakers and agitators". Instead of this resolution, a briefer statement was made which said in passing that "the cooperative movement should also be dealt with in the Party's agitation, but without being any definite item in speeches made by the Party's agitators". When the existence of private enterprise alongside and competing with socialized undertakings was admitted, the cooperatives which were now more successful, were seen in a new light. In a strict sense, the cooperative societies were private. It was, however, impossible to ignore the fundamental difference between businesses run by consumers' cooperation and private ones. The immediate purpose of the latter was profit for the capitalists while the cooperatives, partly on account of their efforts to maintain fair prices, partly through dividends to the consumers, fundamentally rejected swollen profits as their aim. Were private management to be accepted alongside socialized enterprise, cooperation must, from a Social Democrat point of view, be incomparably the most attractive and suitable form. As the committee, appointed for drawing up the programme stated, cooperation must be regarded not only as a temporary safeguard against capitalist exploitation, but as a form of organization with considerable potentialities for development in the society of the future. Cooperatives must be presumed to be capable of playing an important part in the process of socialization. Even of this did not in any way render direct measures of socialization superfluous, it would be wise to reserve an increasing role within the frame of any general plan for socialization, for socialism in such freer forms as the cooperative method implied. </p><p>As far back as the 1911 programme, cooperative management had been mentioned as a form of large-scale production in agriculture. In this case, the form of cooperation was, of course, different, i.e. a producers' cooperative which, nevertheless, presented an alternative to direct nationalisation on bureaucratic lines as previously practised in Sweden. On the question of the distribution of land, the 1920 programme underwent certain modifications although they were hardly of a fundamental nature. In 1911 it was already considered possible that large-scale agriculture could be managed either by cooperative societies or by private individuals, while small-scale agriculture should be protected by Society against attempts by private persons to monopolise ownership of the land. Broadly speaking, the 1920 programme expresses identical ideas and points of view; they are, however, differently worded. In this section, an amendment was, however, introduced aimed against any partitioning of land under State ownership. Partitioning should be allowed only if specific natural conditions made large-scale production impracticable. In 1928, this amendment was rejected in the course of a revision of the programme, because the statement had in various quarters been interpreted as indicating that the Party objected to the cutting up of Crown land in order to provide sites for workers' houses ("egna hem") ; this had never been intended. </p><p>After the Liberal-Socialist Coalition Government resigned in 1920, the Party took office. This Government at once appointed two committees of inquiry on the questions above which had been recently discussed at a Party Congress. These were a Committee of Socialization and a Committee for the Investigation of the problems of Industrial Democracy. In the directives issued by the Cabinet for these investigations, the ideas referred to in various Party programmes and in the discussion at the 1920 Congress on the same subject reappear. They need not be dwelt on here. In order to shed light on the situation at the time, it should, however, be mentioned that the elections which took place soon after went against the Social Democratic Party and led to a loss of eleven seats in the Second Chamber. The Government resigned immediately afterwards. </p><p>These investigations did not lead to any practical measures. The results of the inquiries will, however, serve to elucidate to some extent the trend of ideas within the Social Democratic Party. The first report published by the Committee on Socialization contained some practical proposals; it dealt with an industrial organisation already under State ownership - namely the railways. The railways which were the biggest single undertaking in Sweden, both as regards invested capital and the number of employees, were run as a civil service department with the Government and Riksdag exerting control over investments and wages. All railway fares including fares on privately-owned lines, were fixed by the Government. The Committee on Socialization proposed a loose form of management for this public undertaking and the appointment of a controlling Board, composed of representatives for the owner (the State), the public and the employees. It was considered that, in principle, the invested capital should yield a normal rate of interest, "since the railways would in this way prove their ability to utilise the capital placed at their disposal in an economically satisfactory manner". The fact that the concern had to pay for capital which may be used for other purposes in the economic life of the country would serve as a powerful incentive to- wards rational management and at the same time be a practical method of preventing mismanagement. Any deviation from this principle would imply that the State railways were acquiring capital to the prejudice of their competitors. </p><p>But because of the intertwining of politics and the railway policy, the capital had not always been invested with these views in mind. Part of the capital would yield no interest and should be set aside as "secondary asset". Part would bear interest. It might be compared to the debentures of private firms. This would be regarded as a debt owed by the concern to the State and carry a fixed interest. The remaining capital, the ordinary shares, would correspond to the share capital of a private undertaking and would have to accept whatever return was available after other liabilities had been fully covered. It was laid down as a guiding principle of the concern that the return from the debenture capital should be on par with the obligation interest and that of the ordinary shares 1 per cent higher. </p><p>The employees were no longer to form part of the civil service hierarchy. They should be engaged according to an agreement between the Board of the undertaking and the appropriate trade union or, in certain cases, with individual managers acting as one of the parties. </p><p>The Committee on Socialization made a considerable number of inquiries concerning different aspects of private and public enterprise. With a few exceptions, the analyses were mainly of a descriptive nature and accordingly not particularly noteworthy as contributions to the general discussion; nor did they greatly influence the aims of the Committee as far as practical reforms were concerned. These remarks do not however apply to the final report on the question of principle. This report is from beginning to end developed to an analysis of the problem of socialization, the purpose of it being to give a comprehensive account of the Committee's views on the principles involved. This report, which was published in two parts in 1936 and 1937 respectively, gives a thoroughly considered overall view of the problem from the point of view of the Social Democratic Party, including the present and prospective aims briefly defined in the various programmes and in the course of the general discussion on them. The Committee rejected totality as a principle of socialization. Accordingly (the Committee adds) uniformity should also be avoided. In principle, no fields of economy can be exempted from transformation through socialization. In no instance does the Committee suggest any total and complete application of socialization. In principle, no special form of socialization can be entirely eliminated nor can any special form be regarded as exclusive. The free choice for the individual whether as producer or consumer must in principle presuppose the existence of competitive marketing. This justifies the application of the system of capitalist accounting and the use of interest as a practical instrument. At bottom, the purpose of socialization is to afford the members of Society an opportunity to live freely in prosperity among equals. Socialization is only a means to an end and must be given those forms which produce the best results. </p><p>The special Committee for the investigation of industrial democracy proposed legislation on the representation of the employees in management although this would be limited to an advisory capacity. The report of this investigation Committee did not result in any proposals from the Government to the Riksdag. </p><p>After the changes introduced in 1920, the programme of the Party remained on the whole untouched until 1944,. Certain amendments were added, but they did not involve any new ideas or principles. While the Party held office, certain leading representatives of the Party made speeches which further confirmed the statements which had been emphasised at the 1920 Congress. "Socialization must be regarded as a gradual process of development, which is only partly compatible with Government intervention. This process takes place to a very considerable extent without a finger being stirred in the Riksdag." This declaration was made by Mr Rickard Sandler in 1925 in the course of the introductory general debate in the Riksdag on Government policy. The president of the Party expressed the same points of view and stated that "in one general view of social development, variations in the forms of production arise as a result of the process which gradually renders higher forms of production possible and in time makes necessities. From this it follows as a matter of course that we do not regard the process of socialization as dependent on any decisions arrived at by a small and perhaps temporary majority in the Riksdag". </p><p>The unprejudiced approach that has always been typical of the ideological discussion in the Party is instanced by the late Mr Rickard Lindstrom's motion at the 1928 Congress: in it he remarked that the declaration of the principles of the Party had remained too dogmatically Marxist. There was an inherent contradiction between the Party's theoretical Marxism and its reformism in practice. As I have already shown this lack of conformity is in fact of long standing. The motion did not effect any change in the programme. </p><p>At the 1928 elections, the election manifesto included sections dealing with the socialization of natural resources and with death duties as well as with industrial democracy and the establishment of a State bank. None of these questions represented any fundamentally new ideas or methods. The fact that the election went against the Party led, however, to a debate, although chiefly of a tactical nature, undoubtedly inspired the general debate which went on between the Congresses of 1928 and 1932. Probably nothing is more typical of the way opinion went than the discussion on both the tactical and ideological plane over the terms <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">class party </hi>or <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">people's party. </hi>The President of the Party, Mr Per Albin Hansson, urged most emphatically that the Party did not represent only the industrial working-class, but the great majority of the people, which was naturally opposed to the small group of capitalists. The conception of class seems restrictive, tends to isolate the Party, while the conception of the people creates a feeling of unity and invites cooperation. In actual fact, there was nothing new in the idea of the Party as a people's party. The view had been expressed at the first Party Congress and was expressed again and again thereafter. These ideas had been generally accepted in so far as the Party now always claimed to represent the people, its aim being to turn the country into a happy home for everyone, i.e. a "People's home", to use the expression coined by the President of the Party. </p><p>The 1932 Congress, like all the political work of the Party in 1931 and 1932, bore the mark of the economic crisis which was sweeping over the whole world. In the 1932 Riksdag, the Party proposed important measures designed to overcome the economic crisis and to bring assistance to those hit by it. These measures were not socialist in character in the same sense of representing a transfer of the means of production into the hands of Society. They involved new economic ideas that could quite easily be embraced by people with a bourgeois conception of Society and were, in fact, supported by certain liberal political economists. The policy advocated by the Riksdag group also formed the basis for discussion at the Congress. There, broadly speaking, no new ideas on ways and means of socialization were put forward. The fact that opinions differed regarding not only the significance and nature of the economic crisis but also the vitality of the system of private capitalist enterprise and its recuperative power can only be ascribed to an underlying conflict of ideas. These difficulties always turn up when this question - it is chiefly one of tactics - is discussed. There were on the whole no differences of opinion regarding the responsibility of the capitalist system for the crisis. In the course of the debate, however, the view was put forward that the crisis originated in a complicated interplay of various factors. One of the speakers pointed to the nationalistic prejudices of governments and nations as not the least important of such factors. Finally the deliberations on the nature of the crisis and the appropriateness of concentrating attention on the problem of socialization in existing circumstances were summed up in a statement which defined the economic crisis as "the general crisis of capitalism ... Conscious of this, the Swedish Social Democrats regard it as a pressing duty to organise the socialist transformation of Society within the limits of our national economy with due regard to the social structure of Swedish society". The resolution further explained that many different lines of action, e. g. the transfer to the State of certain utilities of importance to the welfare of the nation, a more equal distribution and more efficient utilization of the resources of the country by means of fiscal, educational and social policies, the abolishment of privileges, protection against exploitation, all had one aim, viz. to change society in accordance with the ideal of solidarity. Finally the resolution states that the term "socialist" should be-applied to a development which substitutes what is best for the interest and health of the people for privilege of a class. </p><p>The 1932 election ended in a triumph for the Party which again took office. The programme for dealing with the crisis which had been proposed in a Social Democratic motion the year before was once more put before the Riksdag in 1933 in an extended form as a Government project. It was carried in the Riksdag thanks mainly to cooperation between the Social Democratic Party and the Agrarian Party. </p><p>In the same spirit and on the basis of the same agreement with the Agrarian Party, the Social Democratic Party's policy was pursued with indisputable success during the next few years, while the crisis slowly subsided and economic improvement set in. </p><p>The policy adopted by the Social Democrats during the crisis did not entail socialism in the real sense of the word. It presupposed no other changes in the nature of Society than that Society, i.e. primarily the State authorities should steadily pursue a policy which would affect market conditions, increase investments, supplement financial investments with other measures to the same effect and have recourse to a corresponding restrictive action in the event of a boom. Such a policy, nevertheless, implies an increase in the power of the State in the economic field which is fundamentally foreign to Liberalism and is to be regarded as an attempt although limited in its scope at introducing a planned economy. In itself, the important role played by the State both as a seller and a buyer gives great significance to Government intervention in the economic life of the country. To this must be added the position of the State as a political organ and its power to apply pressure by legislation. The anti-depression policy seemed to show that it might have yielded better results had the national sector of enterprise producing mainly for the home market been more extensive. It also became the basis of a new trend of thought which may not have implied any ideological change although in practice it was an important factor in Party policy and probably contributed not only to the fundamental revision of the programme made at the 1944 Congress but to the comprehensive supplementary programme which was put forward with the title "The Post-War Programme of the Labour Movement". </p><p>The tendency manifested throughout at earlier congresses and discussion, viz. not to regard socialization as an imperative doctrine to which the Party must irrevocably bind itself, is further confirmed in the 1944 Programme. It is probably quite correct to say that the Party's general ideas on the subject can be summed up as the complete and effective utilization of the productive resources of Society and the greatest possible equalization of income. Since human labour is the most important part of the productive resources, it follows that the programme presupposes steady employment for the whole or practically the whole of the working population. In accordance with these views, the section on socialisation in the Party programme, as agreed at the 1944 Congress reads as follows: </p><p>"A planned economy aiming at:&#x2028;full and effective employment of all the productive resources of the country,&#x2028;secure employment for the whole adult population,&#x2028;a standard of life for all citizens corresponding to their joint productive effort.&#x2028;In so far as is necessary to achieve this economy the various forms of economic activity are to be <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">co-ordinated </hi>under the control of the community and natural resources,&#x2028;industrial establishments,&#x2028;means of transport and communications&#x2028;are to be <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">transferred </hi>to public ownership."</p><p>There is no further mention in the programme of any other points concerning socialization or the transfer of the means of production and other property into the hands of the nation. In debates within the Party, it has often been emphasized that socialization is in itself not socialist dogma which must be realized for its own sake. In the section on agricultural policy the proposal to transfer large estates into public ownership has been eliminated. According to the preamble to the agricultural programme, agricultural production should be made to pay its way with State aid. This is based on social motives and on the idea of military preparedness which has been accepted as inevitable. The guiding principles of Social Democratic agricultural policy has otherwise been to promote cooperation among farmers and to prevent speculation in land and forests. </p><p>The general principles were subjected to a thorough revision. Although this revision showed due respect for earlier statements, it does nevertheless throw a new light on the declaration of principles. The statement of principles still begins by saying that the aim of Social Democracy is to transform society, not in the sense of "liberation of the exploited classes" but "so that control of production is placed in the hands of the whole people, so that the great majority of the people is liberated from dependence upon a minority of owners of capital and so that a social order based on class economy is replaced by a community of citizens cooperating on a basis of freedom and equality". Later on, more extensive changes were introduced. It was stated that development towards big-scale production would continue, but those forms of production in which the workers owned the means of production would not disappear. In many parts of the world, this fact played a very prominent part in agriculture. In the wake of large-scale production, new activities sprang up in the form of handicraft and small-scale industries. New intermediary groups of employees arose, occupying a position on even although an increase in the national income improved the position of the lower strata. Concentration of economic power which placed capital in the hands of the few and rendered the majority of people dependent on a narrow clique intent only on its profits was, however, more significant than the accumulation of riches. This was at the root of the insecurity of the working masses. In spite of all progress, private capitalist enterprise had failed to liberate the productive powers of the nation and utilise them to the full. This failure was most strikingly manifested in times of acute crisis. The effects of these crises were accentuated still further by the monopolistic tendencies of private enterprise. After a mention of the enormous advances of labour thanks to the trade union movement and political activity as well as to consumers’ cooperatives and to the influence of these factors on legislation, an entirely new line of thought was introduced which had not previously been referred to in the declaration of principles. It was pointed out that civil liberties, under whose aegis this progress had taken place, had been conquered in a struggle against obstinately defended privileges. </p><p>The gains of the Social Democratic Party thus acquired had to be protected. "To the Social Democrats, legal and political democracy was not simply means to an end but an end in itself." Social Democrats would again bring labour and property together. Such an unification was already achieved in small-scale production. As far as large-scale production was concerned, collective forms of participation in ownership had to be created. "On the basis of public ownership or public control of the means of production Social Democrats aim to set up such forms of organization of production as will give the workers more influence and responsibility, more independence and security. But in this process it will be important not only to maintain but also to strengthen the spirit of enterprise and the freedom of movement, which may be threatened by both public or private bureaucracy, but which are a necessary condition for the growth of vigorous production." Finally it was stated that, whether economic activity was founded on private ownership or on different forms of collective control, it had to be coordinated under a planned economy, were the productive resources to be really efficiently mobilized. </p><p>At the end of the World War II, the so-called "Post-War Programme of the Labour Movement" was a clearer expose of the ideas which had been expounded in the Party programme in a less detailed form. As far as the question of principle under discussion is concerned, the Post-War Programme suggested that "joint control by the citizens of the economic organization must not act as an impediment on private initiative. On the contrary it should aim at restoring individual initiative, wherever monopolistic marketing arrangements in the interest of limited groups obstruct competition and freedom of action". After mentioning of the lack of enterprise which, in some cases, stood in the way of efficiency, the programme continues: "in a large number of cases - and they are growing - competition has been abolished by private monopolistic arrangements which limit production and employment contrary to the interest of consumers. In such instances, it is often useful to organise a rational competition, whether publicly managed or under the management of utility companies supported by the State as far as necessary. On the other hand, if the whole productive machine is dominated by one single undertaking, or by a combine, or if competition does not appear advisable from a economic point of view, the existing units of production should rather be transferred to national control." At the last Congress, held in 1952, no changes were made in the programme, although the question of socialization was subjected to a fairly extensive debate, from which conclusions may be drawn on the Party's thought and attitude at the present time.&#x2028;The problem had come up through a series of motions from local associations and individual members. In one instance, a thorough inquiry was urged into the conditions and advisability of a socialisation of the natural resources, industries, credit institutions, means of transport and communications and the form it should take. Other motions referred to socialisation of particular branches of enterprise, such as forests, credit institutions, etc., already mentioned in the above quoted motion. One particular motion was restricted to a demand for a "straightforward declaration by the Party Congress of its continued adherence to the principles of socialist transformation of Society". The argument of this last motion was that existing economic conditions were no reason for suppression by the Socialist movement of its own fundamental principles, thereby making compromise and concealment of its true aims a marked characteristic of the movement. </p><p>In its comments, the Executive of the Party drew attention to the rise in the standard of living, to the increase in social security and to the more equitable distribution of income and property and emphasized that nationalisation represented only one means of transforming Society - the aim being to guarantee economic security and freedom for the individual as well as a broader basis of culture. Even in the longest terms, Social Democrats were not trying to establish total nationalisation of the economy which would always include a sector of private enterprise. On the other hand, the Party planned energetic counter-measures against private monopolies which merely served to increase the influence of private speculators on the production. At the same time, from the point of view of Social Democracy, it was urgently necessary to promote efficiency and coordination of the economy through the extension of such forms of enterprise as made possible an increase in democratic control of industry. The question of the actual forms of democratic enterprise would be considered from case to case as would also that of the transfer of natural resources into national ownership. It had to be borne in mind, however, that progress must not take the shape of centralisation and bureaucracy which might jeopardize the aim of achieving efficiency and a more active influence over the economy by the people. Healthy competition to promote efficiency would be preserved wherever possible. </p><p>As far as the credit and insurance system were concerned, the Executive of the Party drew attention to the fact that the organisation of these branches of activity and the possibility of their nationalisation had recently been the subject of public investigations on the initiative of Social Democrats. It had been proposed that a bank should be started by the public authorities to compete with private banking companies and that the compulsory car insurance should be nationalized. At that time, no further socialisation had been suggested. </p><p>A public business bank had already been founded. Further- more, thanks to the central bank controlled by the State, and to legislation on the regulation of interest and the reserve funds of the banks, etc., the State exerted a very material influence on the credit system. The Executive of the Party pointed out that the saving banks differed in character from ordinary banks. Accordingly, in the first clause of the law on savings, no one whether a founder or not, was entitled to any share of the profits. The State also owned a Postal Savings Bank, which was widely used by small investors. </p><p>The proposal submitted by the Committee of Inquiry on Insurance was still under Government consideration. The Committee of Inquiry had proposed that clients should be represented on the managements of the insurance companies. This proposal had been put into effect. Moreover, the consumers’ cooperatives ran big insurance branches, as did various undertakings e.g. the mutual insurance companies which represented a kind of cooperation. </p><p>Because of this the Executive of the Party concluded that no further steps were called for under present circumstances. When the debate on the general question of socialization opened, the spokesman of the Party Executive said that a misleading idea of the situation would result from over- stressing the argument that the present-day conditions had complicated the question of socialization. The Post-War Programme of the Party had not, in the first place, seen in a comprehensive change in the system of ownership a solution to post-war problems. On the other hand, in the post-war period, the Party had for the first time been in a position to use its majority in the Riksdag to put into effect a system of planned economy on democratic lines. </p><p>This declaration is of particular interest. This planned democratic economy was and still is essentially a free market economy with, on the whole, a free market and a free enterprise as well as free competition in so far as they were not limited by the schemes of private monopolies. Practically all the petty war-time regulations had been abolished by the Social Democratic Government. Agricultural production, it is true, was subject to a fairly detailed Government control, but on this point, there were no fundamental differences or opinion between the Social Democrats and the non-Socialist parties. Agricultural controls had in fact been first adopted by a Liberal Government at the beginning or the thirties. After that time, they had been further developed and had taken on a more or less permanent character. In other respects, the only regulation left dealt with the building industry and a public authorisation for the raising of loans. </p><p>But the economic policy of the Social Democratic Government and the Riksdag majority had given this free market economy a special characteristic which marked it off from the market conditions prevailing in between the wars and before World War 1. This distinctive trait was to be found in the fact that the productive resources were utilised to the full and that the working population enjoyed security of employment as well as a material improvement in their standard of living. It may, of course, remain debateable whether the improved standard corresponded to the increase in social product. A notable equalisation of income had taken place. The extent to which an equalization of income can be borne must depend on economic developments; this, however, can hardly be stated in advance. Swedish Social Democrats have never as such set up the goal of an equal income for everybody; it is in any case impossible so long as the market remains free and strongly influenced by private enterprise. In the view of Social Democrats, a democratic economy is an economy of full employment, with an efficient utilization of the productive resources and a reasonable equality in the distribution of income. The programme says no more than this and this interpretation was confirmed by the 1952 Party Congress when it approved the report of the Party Executive. </p><p>In the past few years, freedom and planned economy have been keenly debated in Sweden and elsewhere. The opponents of Social Democracy have constantly intervened in Parliament to query the actual aim of planned economy. On many sides the question has been asked whether a social democratic planned economy would not result in detailed control which in the end cancel out or reduce to a minimum all individual liberties. F. A. Hayek's <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Road to Selfdom </hi>is typical of this line of argument. </p><p>The Swedish debate produced a number of statements by authoritative spokesmen of the Social Democratic Party who have also published analyses of the problem. Liberty has always been one of the outstanding themes in Social Democratic propaganda. According to Mr Ernst Wigforss in his book <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Socialism in Our Times, </hi>"this is as self-evident as is the fact that this freedom has embraced a great many different ideas - some of them definitely antagonistic to liberties which bourgeois tradition has considered essential. These socialist views on freedom have usually been firmly connected with the idea of democracy. Accordingly, the road to freedom acceptable to the Socialists must aim at freedom for all citizens - an equal right for everybody to share those values which we in our mind connect with the ideal of freedom". In Party propaganda, strong emphasis has been laid on the fact that it is the freedom, the rights and security of the individual which Social Democrats wish to protect. This means not only food and drink, a home and clothes, etc., but also opportunities for personal development, both intellectually and culturally. The purpose of a planned economy is to make it easier to attain such a state of affairs, for to the majority employment, economic security and a satisfactory distribution of income are the prerequisites of real freedom. The Prime Minister, Mr Tage Erlander, asserted in one speech that the Party is prepared to regulate and socialize only so far as is necessary to achieve these aspirations, but no further. This conception of a planned economy undoubtedly differs from the ideas which went in 1911 along with "production planned according to the actual needs of Society". In the words of Ernst Wigforss, more emphasis is now laid on the fact that "collective measures serve to confer on the individuals greater opportunities to follow their own aptitudes and to develop their own capacities". For the "serfdom" referred to by F. A. Hayek, the programme has no place. </p><p>As can be seen from the account which has been given of ideological developments in Swedish Social Democracy, the Party has been fairly free of any tendency to be doctrinaire. Initially without doubt, the Party was under the influence of Marxism; but acceptance in principle of Marxist lines of thought have never prevented the Party from pursuing ideas based on experience. When necessary, the leaders and theorists of the Party have never hesitated to point out that Marx's prophecies have not entirely come true. In the latest version of the fundamental principles, the Marxist terminology has been modified still further; for instance, the concept of capitalist exploitation has been eliminated. Marxist lines of thought have been retained only in part. The whole account of social evolution is empirically based and only partly conforms to the Marxist thesis. This applies also to the practical aims of the Party. For instance, the statement of general principles explains that instead of aiming at the dictatorship of the proletariat, the Social Democrats are prepared to concentrate all their energies on defending civil rights to the protection of which the Social Democrats have contributed in the past, because they consider that legal and political democracy is not only a means but an end and is an intrinsic part of the democratic way of life. Although this declaration does not directly contradict the statement of the constituent congress to the effect that "suffrage is but a means, not a goal", it does nevertheless express a different attitude to political democracy. The term "socialisation" has acquired a new meaning. Other forms of collective democratic cooperation have largely been substituted for nationalisation. Greater stress has been laid on the liberties and civil rights of the individual. The practical application of the Party's ideals have been affected by the changing situation while the ideals in themselves have remained unchanged.&#x2028;Social Democratic thinking does not only deal with the principle of socialization, however essential that may be in itself, since it distinguishes the Social Democratic Party from all other parties. It would, however, be a misinterpretation of the present situation to pass over as of minor significance all the other Social Democratic plans for reform. In practical politics, several of these ideas have played an essential part from an ideological point of view. It is quite possible that such ideas have stood the Party in better stead than propaganda in favour of socialisation. The idea of social security has undoubtedly a particularly important place. In general these plans conform more closely" to the general pattern of Social Democratic aims than is usually understood by Swedish Social Democrats. Since the essential aims of the Party have been to achieve a livelihood, freedom and civil rights for the workers comparable to those of other classes of Society and in addition to equalize incomes, social reforms are to be regarded as definite steps toward a well-defined. goal. In the earliest Party programmes, social security occupied a prominent position. Instances of this are the legislation of safety at work covering working hours, prohibition of child labour and of unnecessary night-work, measures to prevent the risk of injury at work and a comprehensive social insurance scheme covering accidents, illness and old age. All these points had been included in the 1897 programme and in part put forward as early as 1889. It would be beyond the scope of this article to try to give an idea of the revolution that has taken place even within the frame of what is an essentially bourgeois society thanks to a successful Social Democratic social policy. A comparison between the State Budget for social welfare then and now gives a striking picture of this change. When the Social Democrats entered the field, the social budget was practically non-existent. Social benefits were mainly restricted to a shockingly mean and humiliating system of Poor Relief which had to be borne by the municipalities. At present the social budget of close on 2400 million Swedish Crowns amounts to more than a quarter of the total national expenditure. To this must be added municipal expenditure. The social security system comprises adequate old age pensions, insurance against accident and sickness, considerable grants to the voluntary Unemployment Fond, Family Allowances, Child Welfare, Maternity Insurance and so on. In recent years housing has come to occupy an increasingly prominent place and measures taken include subsidies to large families with small incomes. This is part of the Social Democratic plan gradually to transfer to Society the responsibility for providing citizens with a proper standard of housing at a reasonable cost, whether in flats or in their own houses. At the present moment, the state has assumed the chief responsibility for housing on the basis of public grants and largely under municipal management. It should perhaps be added that many of these measures have been decided jointly with numerous members of the non-Socialist parties, although the Social Democrats have throughout kept the initiative. </p><p>The problem of taxation is closely bound up with social policy. If there is to be any sense in economic aid to small wage-earners, or others who are in need through no fault of their own, finance has to be found by taking it from those in a better economic position through taxation. Ever since 1897, the progressive taxation has formed part of the Social Democratic Party programme. Nowadays, it has been fairly well put into effect. This has led to a notable levelling of income since lower taxes are paid by small wage-earners and considerable sums accruing from taxation have been used for social purposes. Progressive taxation has reached such a point that in some sections of the Party it is thought that it cannot be increased further. Recently, there has been some discussion whether finance for social reforms might not also be obtained by indirect taxation. Those with small incomes should be compensated by social measures. Earlier, the Party has been an opponent of the principle of indirect taxation. The problem is at present under investigation. </p><p>The question of national defence has caused great interest among the members of the Party and has led to keen discussion at Party congresses as well as during the intervals between them. When the Social Democrats entered the political field, Sweden had relinquished all aspirations to being a great power. The Swedish nation was not imperialist in the sense of being desirous of conquest. Whatever the task of the armed forces, aggressions were out of the question. However, National Defence has placed, and still places, a heavy burden on the citizens, It is, of course, open to discussion whether or not a purely nihilistic and antipatriotic attitude to national defence is a logical conclusion of Marxian theory. This matter will not be gone into here, though it should be noted that in certain quarters it has been so interpreted. The Swedish Social Democrats have never been nihilists in that respect. Only at the 1897 Congress was a programmatic statement made on the Party's attitude to National Defence by a demand for the substitution of "citizen army for a standing army and resort to arbitration in the event of international disputes. The Riksdag, or in the last instance, a plebiscite (it was stated) must determine questions of war or peace". </p><p>This probably expressed an opinion which has been held within the Party ever since its start. Nevertheless, the Party has always regarded the military organization with great distrust, partly because of the expense, and partly because it represents an oligarchic tradition since the selection of officers from the aristocracy formed the apex of a strict class pyramid with the common soldiers serving as the base. Also, the military organisation was suspected to be directed as much against interior opposition as against any foreign foe. Thus the constituent Congress of the Party approved a declaration addressed to "citizens in military service calling upon them under no circumstances to allow themselves to be used as a force against the liberties and rights of their fellow citizens". The officers were believed to be aggressive chauvinists and it was feared they might provoke military adventures, heedless of such means of arbitration as were available. These objections to "militarism" were never expressed in any Party programme, nor were they unanimously supported within the Party, although a powerful section of Party members were inclined to such views. In the nineties and in the first years of the twentieth century, one wing of the Party consisted of members of the youth organizations. Later on they joined the so-called Socialist Union of Youth which adopted an anarchist line of thought. In 1903, a new Social Democratic Union of Youth was formed. The former particularly stressed its distrust of the military system and adopted a position which did not differ greatly from a pure nihilism on defence matters. After the Party split in 1903, the Socialist Union of Youth or Young Socialist Party, as it later termed itself, became openly nihilistic. The Social Democratic Union of Youth, which later became communist and was succeeded in 1917 by a newly formed Social Democratic Union of Youth, adopted a standpoint which was somewhat peculiar from a logical point of view. Its purpose was to oppose all armament, without being, in principle, nihilistic, for it held that Sweden in spite of all efforts was unable to defend herself. The Union undoubtedly, counted many real nihilists among its members. They may, in fact, have been in the majority. That unity with the Social Democratic Party which once had formed the basis of the Union had probably made them hesitate to agree completely with the rebelling Socialist Union of Youth over the question of defence. There is no doubt that the Party congresses felt obliged, in the interest of unity, to make certain concessions to strong trends of opinion in favour of a nihilistic attitude on Defence. But the supporters of this attitude never succeeded in giving definite expression to their opinion in any programme of the Social Democratic Party. The Social Democratic Party preferred to define its attitude as anti-militarist - a term implying above all a rejection of the mechanical discipline which was regarded as a part of the military system with its ideas of caste and its chauvinism. In the debates on the Army and Navy grants it was constantly urged that the indifference of the working classes to the armed forces and to the patriotic phraseology that was a regular part of the solemn routine of official Sweden, was due to the feeling that the working-class was to all intents excluded from Society and unable to influence politics. The problem of Defence has, in fact, often been set against demands for social reforms, but this has been a matter of tactics and logically implied the existence of a fundamental will to defend the country. </p><p>The outbreak of the 1914 War caused the antimilitarist attitude to be modified. At the turn of the century and during the years which followed, a European War had seemed a distant prospect. Now it had suddenly become a sad reality. The position of Sweden as a neutral nation presupposed that in accordance with international agreements, that neutrality had to be defended - a hard fact which could not be ignored. </p><p>The end of the War and the founding of the League of Nations; an international Police 'Force; disarmament." The world, a marked tendency towards disarmament. The Party's strong position in the Riksdag and Government was demonstrated in the mid-twenties by far-reaching demands for disarmament. At that time, the nihilistic attitude on defence had died a natural death. The Party's attitude entirely con- formed to the standpoint which it had long been urging. In the 1920 programme, it was defined as follows: "Popular control of foreign policy; the abolition of secret diplomacy; the institution of a democratically organised League of Nations; an international Police Force; disarmament." The decisions on disarmament taken in 1925 were based on the hopes of the day that the League of Nations would be able to fulfil the purposes for which it had come into being. </p><p>These hopes were disappointed. Nowadays Sweden, under the leadership of a Social Democratic Government, sets aside very considerable sums for defence. In the State Budget, only the sum allotted for Social Services exceeds the amount of 2 000 million Swedish Crowns set aside for defence. No reference is made in the Party programme to disarmament. </p><p>It would be extremely superficial to state that the Swedish Social Democratic Party has changed its fundamental attitude to this serious question. What has changed is the Party's view of foreign politics and even more, the foreign political situation itself. In principle, the standpoint of the Swedish Social Democrats has remained unchanged in so far as they still strongly adhere to the idea of an international peace organization with sufficient resources to maintain peace. Sweden, with her limited influence, is not responsible for the fact that this goal seems impracticable at present in spite of the existence of the United Nations. </p><p>The programme of the Swedish Social Democratic Party contains a great number of aims which are not peculiar to a Socialist Party; indeed many people with otherwise bourgeois views hold identical opinions. Several items in it do not correspond to precise practical goals but merely state in principle the Party's views of already prevailing conditions. This applies, for instance, to the first paragraph of the Party programme where a declaration is made in favour of "popular self-government and universal equal and direct suffrage for men and women over 21". On these points there has been no fundamental difference of opinion although lively discussions have taken place on the Party's attitude to religion. In the early years of the Party, anti-religious views were fairly strongly expressed. The Party has, however, never given any official directive on religion but always urged freedom of thought in this respect. In the earliest statements on this question, religion was simply stated to be a private matter for the individual. In 1905, a demand was added for the abolition of the State Church. This demand still appears in the programme while the Party's standpoint is defined other- wise as "religious freedom". Opinions undoubtedly differ in the Party, not over the principle of religious freedom but where the State Church is concerned. On the initiative of the Social Democratic Government new legislation was introduced in 1952 stating that everybody has the right to cancel his membership of the State Church and to be relieved of taxation paid to the Church. </p><p>Sections like those stipulating the extension of the educational system by a unified school system, freedom of the press, of speech and assembly (points which have never been rejected during the existence of the Social Democratic Party) and, further, a humanised penal law, etc., are evidence of the Party's general radical outlook on culture which is shared by many middle class citizens - particularly by the Liberals. These opinions are to be regarded as part of the ideological ballast of the Social Democratic Party. The fact that these demands have been put forward and periodically revised reflects various new phases in Social Democratic thought. The changes have principally represented a forward move in the position of the Social Democratic Party parallel with a growth of influence of the Party and the Society's general ability - particularly in the economic field - to satisfy those demands. </p><p>A constant uniform line can easily be traced in all the changes reflected by statements of policy and the comments on them. There is undoubtedly a profound difference be- tween "the free state" of the Gotha programme and the "Folkhem" (People's Home) of the nineteen forties, though both originate from the same ideological basis. All social construction and, therefore, all social transformation must be experimental. No one can predict the future, nor can anyone form an idea of the effects of even a single law in the hurly-burly of life. It is perhaps a characteristic development of the Social Democratic thought that the Party of today is somewhat less sure about the future than it was half a century ago. </p><p>As was stated in the 1944 statement of general principles, the aim of the Social Democratic Party is to establish a community of citizens on a basis of liberty and equality. This formula is so general that almost anybody might agree with it. In fact, however, this formulation of the Party's aim differs little from the realisation - in the words of 1897 - of "the social liberation of the working class" in order to safeguard material and intellectual progress. Both the formulae express a desire fundamentally ethical in inspiration to secure a general, or a higher degree of, fair treatment for all, i.e. a social system of a higher moral order, as Mr Ernst Wigforss pointed out as early as 1910. </p><p>It is, however, one thing to harbour ideals, and quite another matter to carry them into effect. The Social Democrats aspire to cooperation between citizens on the foundation of freedom and equality. But how? In practical political work the ideals must be set forth more concretely. According to the 1944 programme, the Party sets out to establish a planned economy which will enable Society to utilize the productive resources fully and efficiently offering full and safe employment for all who are capable of work and guaranteeing to every citizen a standard of living corresponding to the output of the community. The same ideal undoubtedly animated the founders of the Party. The particular forms into which ideals have been moulded have always been more difficult to define precisely and will always remain so, for the march of events never ceases and perpetually reshapes the existing Society. It is much easier to define them negatively. Experience shows that these ideals cannot be put into effect by Liberal "free enterprise", which is, in the first place, not free but to a large extent characterized by private monopolies and in its extreme form produces a distribution of income and property, which provoked the Socialist opposition. Society must therefore intervene. In this respect no difference can be noted between the position in 1889 and today. As far as the particular forms of intervention are concerned, the continuous process of social development has greatly affected the general concepts. </p><p>The Social Democrats of today have washed their hands of earlier ideas of complete state socialism. State intervention must not lead to an increase of official bureaucracy and red tape. Whenever a crisis or a war have made such measures unavoidable they have been expressly stated to be temporary and accordingly have been cancelled as soon as conditions allowed. The view that wider scope has to be given to publicly controlled (not necessarily State-organised) production is nowadays generally held. Within the Party this applies chiefly to housing either through direct socialization or by control of the credit system. To the Social Democrats, it appears self-evident that private enterprise should be subjected to a certain degree of public control. But even supposing management and coordination to be vested in the hands of the State, there is (to quote the Post-War programme of the Labour Movement) no means of knowing to what extent this will imply an increase in the economic activity of the State itself or a limitation of the freedom of private enterprise. Public control must, as far as possible, avoid detailed regulations but rest on general lines - to quote the directives for official investigations laid down by the Social Democratic Government in 1950. In 1924, the Committee on Socialisation suggested a reorganization of the State-owned national railways which would make the management more like that of private concerns. At the 1948 Party Congress, the Executive of the Party was commissioned to undertake an inquiry into new forms of public enterprise. In the extensive report submitted in 1952, the members of the investigating Committee have analysed the problem closely. The report recommends freer forms of State-management - public companies or companies owned jointly with private share-holders - as well as organization on Civil Service lines. These are all practical questions. Ideas and measures may vary. They cannot be solved once and for all, but must be left to experiment and to the influence of evolution and the experiences gained from it. Nevertheless, the ideals which form a common basis of ideas and measures have, broadly speaking, remained unchanged throughout the existence of the Party. </p></body></text></TEI>