<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
         <author>Editorial Staff</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
            <author>Editorial Staff</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>


<text>
  <body>
    <div>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction </head>
        <p>A new quarterly needs, if not an apology, at least an explanation for its appearance, 
        Socialist World is the joint venture of twenty socialist parties from all over the world members of 
        the International Socialist Conference. The British Labour Party, however, has assumed responsibility 
        for the printing of the magazine. Socialist World is not primarily a persuasive journal and does not 
        wish to put out propaganda. Its articles will reflect the views of Socialists and Socialist Parties; 
        the editorial aim will be to present studies of international interest to stimulate further exchanges 
        of ideas between Socialists of different nationalities.</p>
        <p>No hard and fast rules have been laid 
        down, but we hope to concentrate on two different types of articles: some will report on political 
        situations; others will express different shades of opinion of socialist theory, method and aim. 
        In this first issue we publish an article by Jayaprakash Narayan, Leader of the All-India Socialist 
        Party, on "Socialist India" expressing the ideas and aims of many Asiatic Socialists. Two articles 
        come from across the Atlantic. One, by Philip Taft, a specialist on US labour problems, analyses the 
        complexities of labour movements in the United States, and tries to weigh the chances of the appearance 
        of a third party; the other studies the progress of the CCF in Canada since its foundation and the 
        problems it now faces. From Europe descriptive articles come from two countries where Socialists have a place in the government—the Netherlands and Czechoslovakia. One, by the President of the Dutch labour Party, Mr K. Vorrink, examines a political situation of great interest —a coalition of Socialists and Catholics in Holland. The other, by a member of the Research Secretariat of the Czechoslovak Socialist Party, describes the progress made by the Czechoslovak Government with its reconstruction and nationalisation plans and the part the Socialist Party has played in that revolution.</p></div><div><head>A third party in the United States?</head><p>In this, the first issue of socialist world, we print two articles on labour in the Western Hemisphere. In Canada a young and virile Socialist Party flourishes; in the neighbouring United States no party professing socialist principles has been able to make any headway though the need for such a party has been fall and widely discussed. This lack of a united American labour movement of vital importance to the American outlook, both at home and overseas. It affects, too, all European nations who are applying socialist measures to a greater or lesser extent in their own countries.</p><p>For an understanding of the present position of American labour some of its historical aspects must he examined. Under the New Deal, initiated by President Roosevelt, labour made sonic rapid gains, yet since his death labour has once more been driven on the defensive. Yet, but for the split within its own ranks, labour could be the most powerful single organised force in the life of the United States.</p>
        <p>Labour’s rise in strength and power, even by American standards, has been phenomenal. From very small beginnings in 1881, membership of Trade Unions rose to five million by 1920, declined in the slump of 1029 to below three million members, but stands to-day, as a result of wartime prosperity and the encouragement received by the New Deal, at about fifteen million. Yet despite the fact that the American Federation of Labour (AFL) is the largest single labour organisation in the world—it has over seven million due-paying members- and the Congress of Industrial Organisation (CIO) does not lag far behind with about six million members, the labour movement occupies neither a clear nor assured position, because of its rapid rise to power, labour is politically unformed, its ranks and leaders are divided, and it has no agreed programme.</p><p>The reason for this state of affairs, which is incomprehensible to Europeans, must be sought in U.S. labour's different development. The AFL, which grew up during the nineties of the last century, catered for limited craft unions only, with the one big exception of coal miners. It fought for improved conditions of work, but stood for co-operation with the employers. To gain legislative improvements it was satisfied to work through existing political parties. Only as a result of the great depression which shattered American wealth and prosperity did the workers' attitude change. The general optimistic outlook gone, hopes for rapid rises in standards dashed, the workers faced the need to organise for joint protection. Labour's right to organise and to further its interests through collective bargaining was recognised for the first time in U.S. history by Roosevelt's New Deal policy.</p><p>Meanwhile the structure of American industry, too, had changed: mass production was becoming a factor of paramount importance. Some labour leaders, dissatisfied with the failure of the AFL to organise workers in these new industries, set up the Committee of Industrial Organisation in 1935 led by John L. Lewis and the late Sidney Hillman, this Committee was meant to be nothing more than a gingering group within the AFL. The parting of ways, however, came in little more than a year, and from then on the United States has had two major and rival labour organisations besides a number of independent large unions, such, as the Railway Brotherhoods. The CIO unions – the most important being the United Steel Workers and the United Automobile Workers have catered largely for the semi-skilled and unskilled worker, while the A.F.L., dominating road transport building and printing unions, has to some extent only abandoned the craft union principle.</p><p>Until the 1920 slump there was little class consciousness in the United States. Since then the workers have become stabilised as a separate class out of which they could no longer escape; thus they have to protect themselves inside it. For this reason political pressure on the two parties - the Democrats and the Republicans - has increased, and interest in a third party representing labour has become much stronger. A recent survey showed 19% of AFL and 28% of CIO members in favour of a new, though not necessarily a socialist, party representing labour. On the other side stand 43% of AFL and 31% of CIO members who wish labour to keep out of politics altogether. For some time to come the chances of success for a third party are small. It could not begin to organise until the two large labour movements become reconciled; but they will not overcome their differences until the CIO has purged itself of the Communists who have infiltrated into important positions. In the meantime both the Republican and the Democratic Party have been adept at incorporating any "third party" ideas in their own programme, and convincing the worker that for the time being they can best represent labour's interests.</p><p>Small and relatively unimportant socialist parties have existed for some time in the United States. The American Socialist Party, founded in 1900, had a period of relative glory in its early days under Eugene Debs; he polled nearly a million votes in 1912; the new leader, Norman Thomas, polled little more than 100,000 in 1940. The Social-Democratic Federation is akin to the British Fabian Society: it receives its main support from émigré Europeans. On the other hand the American Labor Party, in the State of New York only, represents something of a Popular Front. It supports the Democrats in national affairs, but claims direct representation in local affairs.</p></div><div><head>      Whither Western Germany? </head><p>The future of Germany is to-day perhaps the greatest enigma in the international political scene. Now that the Foreign Ministers have failed to reach agreement in Moscow on any of the major German issues and are not likely to meet again until November, a good many urgent internal German problems can no longer await the broader decisions on the future of the German State. In fact conversations on the status of the Anglo-American zone have already been held in Berlin at the highest level between the British, and American authorities, and are being continued by the bi-zonal councils at Minden. Allied Military Government no longer rules absolutely in the Anglo-American zone; for the past year it has delegated more and more responsibility to representative German bodies, though in every instance it retains a final veto.</p><p>Until the Landtag elections in the British zone in April these bodies had been nominated by the British controlling authority. In future, in theory at least, each Land will be ruled by a popularly elected cabinet. As at present the Länder governments operate at the highest level, their political complexion is of great importance in deciding such major questions as land reform and socialisation of industry. In addition, the Länder Governments are responsible for local government services, health, education and police.</p><p>In the light of the increasing importance of the Länder Councils, it is worth examining the results of the April elections in some detail. Elections took place in the three Lander of the British zone —North Rhine Westphalia, Lower Saxony and Schleswig Holstein. The free cities of Hamburg and Bremen, voting last October, had given the Social Democrats majorities. Though by German standards participation in the elections was small—only 68% voted—this was fine less to lack of political interest than to desperate food and economic problems.</p><p>Taking votes cast for the three Länder together, the Social Democrats may feel satisfied with the result of the elections; they emerged as the strongest single party with 3.1 million votes against the CDU's 2.7 million votes. The Communists polled nearly 900,000, the Centre Party nearly 600,000 and the Free Democratic Party nearly 570,000 votes. The Communists showed the heaviest gains, centred mainly in and around Essen, one of the traditional Communist strongholds of Weimar days. On the other hand, the right wing Christian Democrats lost some ground, and it appears that a proportion of their former adherents voted for the more progressive Centre Party. In the agricultural Land of Schleswig Holstein, only three parties are represented in the new Landtag; the Social Democrats with 43 sears, the Christian Democrats with 22 seats and the South Schleswig Association with four. The Social Democrats have thus an absolute majority, and a Social Democratic Prime Minister is likely to be appointed in place of the present Christian Democrat. In Lower Saxony the Social Democrats also emerged as the strongest single party with 66 seats, but could be outnumbered by a coalition of the Lower Saxony Party (25), the Free Democrats (13), the Christian Democrats (31) and the Centre Party (6). On the other hand a coalition of the Social Democrats, Centre and Communists (8 seats) could outvote all the other parties. Here there may be some changes in the complexion of the existing government, but it is likely to remain a coalition headed by its present Social Democratic Prime Minister, Herr Kopf.</p><p>The situation in the industrial Land of North Rhine—Westphalia is naturally the most interesting. Though the CDU lost a proportion of its votes since the Kreis elections in October, it remains the strongest single party with 91 seats. Yet a coalition of the Social Democrats (64 seats) and the Communists (28 seats) could outvote the CDU alone, but could not stand up to a likely combination of Christian Democrats and Free Democrats (12 seats). Thus the Centre Party with 20 seats holds the balance between the two differing factions. The Free Democrats are Liberals in the European sense, and of all parties most warmly advocate private enterprise, while at the same time they strongly oppose any form of socialisation. The Christian Democrats can therefore count on their wholehearted support in fighting the Social Democrats1 demand for socialisation of the basic industries. The Centre Party, on the other hand, will vote with the Left on economic issues.</p><p>Much will depend on the composition of the future Länder cabinets. Great Britain, the occupying power, has agreed in principle to socialise basic industries. Temporary custodians are in the process of being appointed to take over coal, steel, engineering and chemical industries until their future status can be decided; it will be up to the Länder Councils to determine the permanent shape of these industries. Similarly the Zonal Advisory Council, consisting of a General Council and a Länder Council, will in future express the political will of the German people of the British zone. While the General Council consists of members of all parties, who advise on matters outside the sphere of the Länder governments, the latter, comprising the Minister Presidents of the three Länder as well as the Mayors of Hamburg and Bremen, are free to discuss any subject within the scope of the Länder governments and to communicate decisions straight to the Control Commission. The outcome of the conversations between the responsible British and American authorities will determine the degree of authority of these newly-elected governments.</p></div><div><head>Bevin’s parliamentary critics</head><p>Since the House of Commons reassembled in the Autumn of last year the Government’s foreign policy and the commitments it Since the House of Commons reassembled in the Autumn of last year the Government's foreign policy and the commitments it involves have been attacked by groups of socialist MP’s vaguely termed "The Rebels". On two occasions these Labour critics have pressed their opinions in Parliamentary debates of the first importance. First, in November, when the policy of the Government in the coming year was being debated, R.H.S.Crossman and J.Reeves (a number of the Party Executive) tabled amendment, critical of the general tenor of Bevin’s policy. The second "revolt" in April 1947 was on a specific issue, the Conscription Bill. In the first instance a group of more than fifty Labour members out of four hundred abstained from voting for the Government after many had spoken against Bevin; in the second, approximately seventy-five carried their disapproval of conscription to the length of voting against the Government.</p><p>It is not easy for the average person to understand why some of the “rebels”, like R.H.S. Crossman, who sponsored the amendment criticising Foreign Policy in November, should have spoken and voted with the Government on the Conscription Bill in April. Or why Mrs Paton and many with her, 0n the other hand, voted with the Government in November but against it in April?</p><p>To estimate the true strength of this confused opposition it is necessary to make distinctions between several groups holding different opinions. By the Autumn of 1945 and early months of 1946 one small group surrounding Zilliacus had become critical of Bevin. It opposed the Foreign Secretary’s policy in Greece and criticised the results of Hector McNeil’s visit to Athens, as well as the formation of a Greek Coalition Government. This group was consistently sympathetic to the coalition governments in Eastern Europe which are generally considered to be “Communist dominated.” Several of these Members, including John Mack and T. Platts-Mills, visited Eastern Europe in the summer of 1946 and returned more vociferous in expressing their views. For this reason the group, which numbered less than ten, is sometimes called “crypto-communist” or “fellow-traveller.” This epithet has been cast generally at all Bevin’s critics and has served to blur proper distinctions of opinion between different groups.</p><p>In the Spring of 1946 William Warbey’s criticism of the influence and continuity of office of “old time diplomats” in the Foreign Office added some supporters to the small “anti-Bevin” group. R.H.S. Crossman was a member of the Anglo-American Commission reporting on the Jewish problem, and it was this that first brought him into opposition to the Foreign Secretary. A misunderstanding about the extent to which the report of the Commission should, or could, be implemented, and Crossman’s sympathy with the Jewish Agency led him to second a protest made in the House of Commons by Sydney Silverman against the internment of Jewish leaders in July 1946. R.H.S. Crossman, as Assistant Editor of the New Statesman, had some responsibility for a distinct change of emphasis of editorial opinion on foreign policy during the summer of 1946. The views of a group, many of them 'intellectuals', were expressed in several articles in the New Statesman. In general the group criticised Ernest Bevin for waiting upon and for waiting upon, and then following the American initiative in foreign policy; for forming too close a liaison with the United States that made meaningless the Anglo-Soviet Treaty, and for failing to encourage the socialist development of Europe. No particular stress was placed on Eastern Europe. Crossman, when he spoke in the House of Commons declared it the task of a socialist government to show that there is a third way open to the world, "faced with the bleak and blank alternatives of American free enterprise or Russian Communism".</p><p>The two "groups" with some other individualists and a small number of Zionist critics of Mr Bevin abstained for different reasons from support of the Government’s foreign policy last November. It must not be thought that they represent the majority of Labour members actively interested in the Foreign Secretary is assured of active expressed many Labour MPs and not merely a lame number of automatic votes of loyalty to the Government.</p><p>During the winter foreign policy became associated with internal industrial affairs. Commitments overseas necessitated an army 400,000 larger than the House of Commons approved the previous February. A Government White Paper was issued in January 1947 indicating that 500,000 extra men are needed in industry to carry through the export programme. In these circumstances the opposition to the Conscription Bill was increased by a number of members who were primarily interested in industrial development at home. Ian Mikardo, who also writes frequently in the New Statesman is one of this "manpower" group. The long tradition in the Labour Party of opposition to conscription and in general a conscientious objection to armed force, has lost strength since the war; but a "pacifist" group, led by Rhys Davies, opposed conscription and around them the "manpower” group and the extreme left. (Zilliacus and others) gathered. R.H.S.Crossman and others who followed him on Foreign Policy, maintained conscription to be necessary for an independent and "European” foreign policy, and added that it has become an acceptable part of the European democratic tradition. They therefore voted, consistently, with the Government on this motion after expressing in speeches the wish that the duration of conscript service should be reduced from 18 months to a year. This alteration to the measure has been accepted, by the Government.</p></div><div><head>Sweden’s trade</head><p>The long-established Social Democratic Government of Sweden is meeting difficulties familiar to Great Britain. The productive resources of the country are unable to meet accumulated home demands’ particularly for houses, and inflation threatens. A severe shortage of dollars and a surplus of “soft” European currency, with which Sweden cannot obtain her basic needs, have compelled the government to take emergency measures. A ban on inessential imports, generally evaded, has now been succeeded by a general ban except for such essentials as cotton, leather and oil. All other imports require a special licence. Domestic consumption has been drastically reduced and the Government has courageously laid itself open to criticism by reversing its policy of the past year which permitted rises in wages, an excess of spending rather than saving, and an encouragement of imports. The inevitable lowering of the high Swedish standard of living is being carried through by the use of “control” on prices and a budget over a five-year period to prevent the downward trend in unemployment since December 1945 from being reversed.</p><p>Sweden, though she enjoyed the prosperity of a “neutral” during the war, has suffered from the economic paralysis of Europe since 1945. The Swedish trade statistics recently published show that in 1946	imports exceeded exports by Kr. 800 million. This import surplus of approximately 25% reversed the position during 1945 when exports exceeded imports by at least 65%. The total of imports have recently reached their pre-war level but their character has changed from “essential” to “inessential.” It is this change that has created an inflationary potential. Before the war Sweden relied upon Great Britain for 45% of her coal supplies. As this source is closed to her and Poland has not been able to supply sufficient coal, the only means left to Sweden to maintain her industrial production — it has, indeed, been raised 5% above the 1939 level — is to use timber as fuel. Unfortunately for Great Britain, Sweden is therefore unable to export much timber or wood pulp. In this event, with European markets valueless to her, Sweden has sought new directions for her trade.</p><p>An agreement with Russia was signed in October 1946. The Soviet Union obtained a large credit of £69 million (repayable within 15 years, at 3%) to purchase capital equipment in Sweden such as electrical plant, locomotives and fishing vessels. In addition Sweden will supply high-grade steel products (ball-bearings in particular), optical instruments and livestock to be set against supplies of raw materials from the Soviet Union that will include chrome, manganese ore, silver, copper and fertilisers. The agreement was fiercely criticised by the Swedish Opposition Parties but the Socialists, in power, backed it resolutely and were supported by the Communists. The Minister of Commerce, Professor Myrdal, met American apprehensions by denying that the trade agreement meant Russian economic “penetration” of Sweden. The Soviet share of Swedish foreign trade will barely exceed 10%. Nevertheless the US Government, suspecting that the bilateral agreement had an exclusive character, addressed a note of protest to Stockholm.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>