<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>An Indian Plan for socialism</title>
         <author>Jayaprakash Narayan</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>An Indian Plan for socialism</title>
            <author>Jayaprakash Narayan</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Indian" party="Socialist Party of India"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>No intelligent person to-day will doubt that the next stage in the evolution of human society is Socialism. But there will not be a like agreement on the question, “What is Socialism?” Different theories of Socialism and different pictures of a socialist society have been presented from time to time by socialist thinkers and workers. These differences are reduced somewhat when one takes into consideration only one of the several broad schools of socialist thought. Thus, if we accept Marxism, or belong to the Marxist School, as I do, the differences are greatly narrowed down, but they are by no means removed or obliterated. There are socialist movements in the world to-day professing allegiance to Marx that widely differ among themselves; even quarrel and fight with one another. The Stalinists and Trotskyists, for instance, both profess to march under the banner of Marxism, but they not only differ from each other, but are even thirsty for each other’s blood. Which of these two “Marxian” schools presents a true picture of Socialism? Those who belong to neither of these warring camps would doubtless say, neither.</p><p>In India the Communists and Royists both swear but we have seen the kind of "socialist" policy they have followed in the name of Marx. We have seen that to 'them Marxism included even working as hirelings of Maxwell and spying on Indian revolutionaries. Moreover, both these "Marxist"’ groups are each other's bitter enemies. There are other little groups too in this country flying Marxist colours, but never agreeing among themselves as to what is Marxism.</p><p>It seems to me, therefore, that in view of all this confusion and rival claims, the socialist movement in India must evolve its own picture of socialism in the light of Marxist thought, of world history since Marx’s death, and of conditions in this country and our historical background. Marxism is a science of society and a scientific method of social change, that includes social revolution. As such, there can be no room for dogmatism or fundamentalism in Marxist thought. Those who on the one hand call Marxism scientific and on the other introduce dogmatism into it, do it great disservice. In science there is no such thing as final truth. Science progresses by the progressive elimination of untruth from human knowledge. If Marxism is a science, Marx could not have expounded ultimate truths, but only made approximations to them. To-day, with a vastly developed store of human knowledge and vastly greater experience and observations of capitalist society, we are in a position to make far nearer approximations to the truth than Marx. The unending merit of Marx, however, is that he has given us a method to understand and change history even as Darwin gave us a method of understanding life. Darwinism and Marxism were born almost together, but not even the most ardent Darwinist to-day believes in the theories of evolution as they were propounded by Darwin. Yet he would proudly call himself a Darwinist. My professor of Biology at Wisconsin ranked the Origin of the Species only next to the Bible amongst the world’s books, but he never thought for a moment that he was being disloyal to his master when he proceeded to show where modern research had proved Darwin false or only partially true. It is open in the same manner for a Marxist to give not the second but even the first rank to “Capital” and yet to seek to develop and refine the partial truths of Marxism.</p><div><head>The socialist society </head><p>With these introductory remarks let me turn now to the subject in hand. The creation of a socialist society involves two stages: the stage of transition, and the stage when Socialism has been established. It is obvious that the form of the transitional period will be determined by present conditions and final objectives that is, the final picture of Socialism in view.</p><p>I shall consider here only the final picture of Socialism. The objectives of Socialism are: elimination of exploitation and poverty; provision of equal opportunities to all for self-development; full development of the material and moral resource in accordance with the needs and wishes of society as a whole rather than in accordance with the dictates of profit; equitable apportionment of national wealth and social, educational and other services between all who labour and serve society.</p><p>A system of social organisation that serves these ends is a Socialist society. Anything that does not is not Socialism. Not preconceived theories, no matter by whom propounded need detain or confuse us if they do not subserve these ends in practice.</p></div><div><head>Vital changes needed </head><p>I believe that these ends can be achieved only if certain vital changes are made in existing society, and the economic and political organisation of the future society is based on the foundations described below. First of all, there must be complete political freedom. In other words, India must become an independent nation. There can be no socialism under British rule.</p><p>Second, there should be no privileged economic or political class, as at present, i.e. a self-perpetuating class wilding economic and political power. In other words, the "ruling" Princes and the Zamindars (not the peasant farmers of the Punjab, but the landholders of U.P., Bihar and some other Provinces) and the Capitalists must be made to surrender their economic and political power and privilege.</p><p>After the removal of British power, the abolition of Princes and of the Zamindari and capitalist system should be comparatively simpler problem. If the Indian people proved strong enough to destroy the British Raj in India, nothing could stop them from destroying feudalism and capitalism if they desired to do so. The only limiting factor would be the stage of development of the political consciousness of the masses. In other words, if the socialist movement were to become strong enough to move the masses in the right direction, all these changes could be made without much difficulty or opposition.</p><p>Abolition of Princedom hardly raises any technical problem for socialism to solve. Bourgeois society has the solution ready at hand and we could draw upon the history of bourgeois revolutions. The Princes will only have to be removed from their gadis and reduced to the status of the ordinary citizen, and their States made part of regions scientifically determined with due regard to geography, economic resources and cultural affinities.</p><p>Abolition of Zamindari system is also only the first step in a socialist reorganisation of our agrarian economy which indeed involves rather difficult questions of theory and practice. By merely saying that there will be no zamindars in socialist India, we say practically nothing as to the real form of socialist agriculture we wish to develop in this country. I shall describe below the main outlines of our socialised agricultural economy as I visualise it</p><p>Abolition of Capitalism is undoubtedly a great step forward towards Socialism, but by itself it can hardly be called Socialism. It is merely a negative half of which the positive half has yet to be created. In what manner Capitalism will be abolished and what will take its place will determine to a large extent the kind of Socialism that we are going to have. I shall try to give below the picture have in mind of socialist industry in this country.</p><p>To a consideration of agriculture and industry I shall hate to add a few words about banking and trade. That would give us, fair picture of socialist economy. The political half of my picture would then remain to be drawn up. I shall first, deal with the economic part of my picture.</p></div><div><head>A socialised agriculture </head><p>Let me take up agriculture first. The land systems in this country are complicated beyond description, but they all agree more or less in exploiting the tiller of the soil in the interest of a small landed and moneyed class. All these systems have to be scrapped completely and a new system created in their place. In building up socialist agriculture, we will have to pass through two stages — the co-operative and collective stage. I shall naturally deal here only with the first stage.</p><p>After the abolition of zamindari, there will be a redistribution of land with a view to breaking up big holdings and making the smaller holdings economic. No peasant would have more than a certain maximum acreage of land, let us say 30 acres, and none less than five. No one shall be allowed to own land who does not reside in the village and actually till his land. The unit of agricultural economy would be the village. The legal ownership of land would vest with the village, as a whole, and the' village panchayat would have the power, according to laws made by the State, to settle its lands with individual peasants. Thus the peasants will have a sort of proprietary right over the land settled with them. Present proprietary rights will be respected, except where it is found necessary to alter them in order to bring about a fairer re-distribution of land and remove gross inequalities at both ends. But the proprietary rights would he restricted merely to the right of the peasant to receive from the produce of the village lands his share in accordance to the size of his holding. No village will be allowed to sell land to anyone except to the gram panchayat. Peasants will not be allowed to carry on cultivation farming operations separately. Each gram panchayat among other things, will also function as a farmers’ co-operative. The co-operative will conduct all farming operations including buying, selling and borrowing. All who labour in the fields will receive wages in kind or money, according to the wage laws of the state the produce will be distributed after deducting costs according the size of holdings.</p></div><div><head>Collectivism </head><p>This is the co-operative stage of socialist farming. The next stage is the collective stage in which no individual proprietary rights in agricultural lands (in Russia each collective farmer is allowed to own privately up to three acres of land around his homestead for kitchen gardening, raising poultry or other similar purposes) are recognised, and all lands to the village, or farming unit, are owned and run by village collectives. In Russia collectivisation was pushed through at great human cost and under a ruthless dictatorship. Estimates run up to as high a figure as twenty millions of those who had to be "liquidated" in order to make collectivisation a success. I do not favour such a colossal repression of the toiling peasant masses, nor does socialist theory permit it. Abolition of landlordism, re-distribution of land and breaking-up of big holdings would require State coercion to be used against fifteen to twenty per cent of the agricultural population perhaps. But collectivisation might require sixty to seventy per cent of that population to be represented. I do not find any justification for any political party, speaking and acting in the name of the toiling masses, to indulge in such wholesale repression. Twenty per cent may be coerced in the interest of the eighty per cent, but there is no justification for repressing seventy per cent of the peasants, even "for their own good". Co-operative farming itself would require a good measure of coercion But in that case a wise mixture of coercion and persuasion, as also concession of certain economic advantages, might be, and I am sure will be found to be sufficient. Collectivisation on the other hand would require a degree of wholesale repression that is repugnant to socialism, which, above all, is the expression of the will of the toiling masses. Therefore, collectivisation will follow as the second stage and its pace would be necessarily slower and adjusted to the results of propaganda and demonstration. I need not, however, emphasise that new agricultural colonies and settlements need not pass from the co-operative to the collective stage. They can and will be put on a collective basis from the start.</p><p>Conversion of peasant agricultural economy into the sort co-operative economy described above would result in a considerable part of the present agricultural population being thrown of employment. A place will have to be found for this surplus agrarian population in industry, particularly in industries subsidiary to farming.</p><p>Industry socialised </p><p>We turn now to a consideration of socialist industry. I visualise two types of industries in a socialist India, large-scale and small- scale. It goes without saying that both large and small industries, together with agriculture, will form parts of a balanced national economy, democratically managed and controlled.</p><p>All large industries would be owned and managed by the Federal or Provincial Government. Representatives of trade unions would have an appropriate share in the management from the lowest to the highest levels.</p><p>All small industries would be organised into Producers' Cooperatives, who would own and manage their industries. Apart from passing legislation for the regulation of these co-operatives, the State will not interfere with their work. These industries will include subsidiary agricultural industries, as well as existing and new handicrafts and other small industries.</p><p>I visualise and advocate another type of industrial ownership apart from State ownership and Producers’ Co-operatives: that is, municipal or community ownership. A township or a city may own and manage, if not large, middling and small industries. The representatives of the workers in these community-owned industries would naturally have adequate voice in their management.</p><p>I advocate development of these co-operatives and community- owned industries, firstly, because I do not believe it is possible to find employment for many years to come for our surplus population, which would swell further at least by twenty per cent, by the Revolution in agriculture and large industry alone; secondly, because I desire to prevent the State from acquiring the sole monopoly in industry and employment. The State under Socialism threatens, as in Russia, to become an all-powerful tyrant, maintaining a stranglehold over the entire life of the citizen. This leads to totalitarianism of the type we witness in Russia to-day. By dispersing the ownership and management of industry and by developing the village into a democratic village republic, we break this stranglehold to a very large extent and attenuate the danger of totalitarianism.</p><p>In the field of trade I have the following picture in mind. Foreign trade will be entirely in the hands of the State.</p><p>Internal trade will he shared between the State, the local community, and the co-operatives. All banking will be in the hands of the State. Here then is the economic picture of my socialist India—</p><list type="unordered"><item>Co-operative farming run by gram panchayats.</item><item>Collective farms in new settlements.</item><item>Large-scale industry owned and managed by the Stale</item><item>Community-owned and managed industry.</item><item>Small industry organised into Producers' Co-operatives</item></list></div><div><head>The socialist state </head><p>I come now to the political part of my picture.</p><p>The State in socialist India must be a fully democratic. There can be no Socialism without democracy. It is a common mistake these days to think that there must be dictatorship of the proletariat in a socialist State. This is against the teachings of Marx. The dictatorship of the proletariat has a place only in the transitional period from capitalism to socialism. And in this period, too, it is not inevitable in every case. Marx visualised a capitalist State, such as England, where political democracy was in full vogue and there was no large standing army, where democratic process could be used to bring about Socialism. But apart from such rare cases, dictatorship of the proletariat has been considered in Marxian thought as essential for the transitional period. It is, however, the very essence of Marxism that once is over, the State must become a fully democratic institution. When the old ruling classes have been destroyed and society has been converted entirely into a society of workers, it is idiotic to talk of a dictatorship of the proletariat because the proletariat cannot dictate to itself. </p><p>Let me stop here to say a word further about the dictatorship of the proletariat. Whether our transition in India from present society to Socialism takes the democratic or dictatorial form - I personally think it would take the democratic form - it should be remembered that dictatorship of the proletariat in Marxist theory does not mean the dictatorship of a single party, such as the Communist Party in Russia. It means the dictatorship of a class, or industrially backward countries such as India and post-Czarist Russia, of a combination of the toiling classes, such as the workers, and peasants and the lower middle-class. These classes have one or more political parties, and these parties must all be united in the dictatorship or have freedom to function freely under the dictatorship. The dictatorship of the proletariat never meant that parties of the working-class or other toilers would be suppressed: it meant only the suppression of the ruling class and their political and economic institutions.</p><p>Coming back to the question of democracy under Socialism, it is necessary to explain in some detail what this democracy should mean concretely. First of all, it should mean that there will be no one-party-rule and that there might be more than one political party of the working people and that the workers, the industrial and peasant co-operatives, the trade unions, etc., might form different political parties and that these parties should function freely. It should mean that there should be full freedom for expression of opinion and to form voluntary organisations for political purposes. The trade unions, the local communities, the co-operatives and other such corporate bodies of the working people might have their own newspapers and broadcasting systems and conduct their own schools and educational institutions.</p><p>Democracy under Socialism should further mean that the trade unions should not be limbs of the State and subservient to it, but independent bodies supporting the State, and also exercising a check over the government of the day. In Russia the trade unions have no independence whatever and have been subjected to the will of the State on the theory that the State, being a workers’ State, all workers’ organisations must be subject to it. Here the State and the Government have been confused. A particular State may be a workers’ State, but the Government of the day might be making mistakes and wilfully or unwilfully acting contrary to the workers’ interests. In that case there must be independent organs of the Working-class, such as trade unions—and in a socialist society the trade unions will be second in importance only to the Government itself—in a position to check or correct or change the Government in power.</p><p>Thus my picture of a socialist India is the picture of an economic and political democracy. In this democracy man will neither be a slave to capitalism nor to a party or the State. Man will be free. He will have to serve society which will provide him with employment and the means of livelihood, but within limits he will be free to choose his avocation and station in life. He will be free to express his opinions and there will be opportunities for him to rise to his full moral stature. There will be no great difference between man and man, except the difference of physical and mental endowments — for there will be no great difference in incomes.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>