<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Czechoslovakia on the road to socialism</title>
         <author>Anonymous(Czechoslovak)</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Czechoslovakia on the road to socialism</title>
            <author>Anonymous(Czechoslovak)</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Czechoslovak" party="Czechoslovak Social Democracy"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text><body><div><p>Any observer who judges Czechoslovak post-war economic developments by Western European standards can easily reach false conclusions. Looking from the viewpoint of the homogenous and established Western nations, he is naturally tempted to apply the same yard-stick to the social and economic structure of Czechoslovakia. Thus he leaves out of account the national element and, particularly, forgets the long struggle of the Czechs against powerful German political and economic pressure. In the history of the Czech nation social and political factors have been closely interlinked. The Czechs in their struggle for national rights strove to reduce the economic privileges enjoyed by the German mobility, and later by the German bourgeoisie. Any step strengthening the sense of nationhood, such as the acquisition of civil rights, the enlargement of suffrage, or economic emancipation, was welcomed. This long struggle developed the democratic character of the Czech people, and educated them to think progressively in social and political matters. The results of this development were revealed in the period from 1918 to 1938 during the existence of the Independent Republic.</p><div><head>Under German domination</head><p>The progressive trend of Czechoslovak political life was disturbed from 1933 onwards by Hitler’s aggressive regime which, actively supported by the German landlords and industrialists in Czechoslovakia, was later aided secretly by powerful sections of the Czech bourgeoisie. Following the German occupation of Czechoslovakia, the Workers’ Movement was completely suppressed; the entire productive capacity of the country was linked to the military requirements of the Reich. At the same time the door was opened to economic exploitation of the country’s industry by German finance. Various methods were employed, such as the setting of an unfavourable rate of exchange between Czech crowns and German marks, and the freezing of wages at a low level.</p><p>This, however, did not satisfy the Germans; after a time they began to confiscate outright. They Aryanised businesses and industries, dictated mutual agreements between industrial concerns covering the so-called “Sudeten enterprises" and the enterprises in the Protectorate, insisted on force purchases of foreign, such as French, capital investments; and finally used persecution and violence. The effectiveness of these measures is shown by the following figures: in 1940, German capital investments in Czechoslovakia amounted to 876 million crowns; in 1941 they had risen to 1,113 million crowns; and by 1945 German capital investment in Protectorate territories was ten times larger than in 1938. Thus more than 300 limited liability companies fell into German hands, because their central organisations had been taken over. In addition, many non-industrial concerns were acquired by the Germans. In Czechoslovakia, unlike Great Britain, banks are intimately linked with industrial concerns; in fact they often function, as industrial holding companies. According to 1940/41 statistics, 80% of the basic capital of all undertakings was governed by these focal interests. They together controlled more than 86,000 million crowns worth of investment property. Nine of the largest banks had invested 3,366 million crowns in these concerns. This close link between industry and finance explains the great success of the German "booty hunters"; for the same reason the banks could not be left in private hands when nationalised.</p></div><div><head>The problems in 1945 </head><p>To anyone who has seen some of the war-ravaged industrial cities of Western Europe, damage in Czechoslovakia may appear negligible. Nevertheless, Czechoslovak factories have suffered from bombing; in the Eastern part of the Republic much large-scale devastation occurred during the closing stages of the European war. On an average, war damage in the whole country is estimated at 40-50 per cent, of the total industrial and economic capacity, and such important auxiliaries to industry as railway and road transport.</p><p>But war damage alone does not constitute all the losses suffered by the country’s industry. Its production branches serving war purposes were overdeveloped, while peace time industries were neglected. Machinery was worn out; much of it was taken to Germany during the last phase of the war. Stocks of raw materials were used up or taken away. Financially all enterprises were sucked dry and owed large sums of money to the Reich. Generally the position was such that even capitalist defenders of private enterprise would have agreed to far-reaching state intervention in so far as this meant the socialisation of their losses.</p><p>In addition, the country faced another special problem, whose solution implied a radical change in the economic structure. Czechoslovakia was determined to become an independent national state again and, after her past difficulties with national minorities, to expel the German population. This decision was arrived at by the Government with the unanimous agreement of the nation and with the full knowledge that it would cause far-reaching changes in the economic, structure of the country. A clause in the Potsdam Agreement dealt with the question, and later agreements concluded with the occupying powers of Germany provided for the completion of population movements by Autumn, 1946. Implementing them meant the removal of two-and-a-half million people and a resulting decline in the labour force of about 20 per cent deluding many highly-skilled workers. Without state intervention serious economic disorder, particularly in the export industry would have ensued.</p></div><div><head>Nationalisation of industry </head><p>Immediate measures had to be taken to ensure the proper administration of the confiscated property of Germans and Hungarians, traitors and collaborators. The problem was solved by nominating thousands of national administrators to act as trustees. They were controlled by, and responsible to, central, or in some cases, local government authority. The property of traitors and collaborators was thus assured to the nation during the first period of reconstruction by a revolutionary act that met with widespread approval by the workers. It then became possible to survey production possibilities and economic trends and to plan for the future.</p><p>The Trade Unions and, particularly, the Social Democratic Party demanded nationalisation of key industries. Special commissions were set up in the summer of 1945 to draft the necessary legislation. All political parties were generally agreed on the principle of nationalisation; it was essential, however, to determine the extent of nationalisation, its timing, and whether to nationalise the banks. Since the measure had the character of a national revolution it was unanimously accepted by the people.</p><p>Nationalisation was carried out by proclamation. Four decrees, on 24th October, 1945, by the President of the Republic, made the property of the nation the mining and heavy industries, the power industry, all key factories in the wood industry, the textile and leather industries and manufacture of building materials and plastics. Some factories in the food industry were also nationalised. By another decree limited liability companies, carrying out banking and monetary transactions, and all insurance companies, were taken over. In these decrees a limit was established for single industries, either according to the number employed, or to production capacity. All factories above the set level were nationalised. Undertakings regardless of former industrial groupings were linked into new production units under the management of national industrial boards. On 15th January, 1946, the Government decree laid down the juridical status of the nationalised industries: they become the property of the State but retain individual status as a "corporation” and pay taxes as independent units in the same way as private enterprise. According to the statute they will be administered commercially, and the State will not be responsible for their obligations.</p><p>After the reorganisation of the nationalised industries, 17 central hoards were formed. Each directs varying numbers of nationalised industrial undertakings. A list of these central boards reads as follows: —</p><table rend="rules"><row><cell/><cell>Number of National Enterprises on 31.12.46</cell></row><row><cell>Mining industry</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>Power industries</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Iron and Steel industry</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Metal works and Engineering industry</cell><cell>57</cell></row><row><cell>Chemical industry</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>China and Clay industry</cell><cell>26</cell></row><row><cell>Glass industry</cell><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>Paper and Pulp industry</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>Textile industry</cell><cell>29</cell></row><row><cell>Leather and Rubber industry</cell><cell>11</cell></row><row><cell>Wood and Furniture industry</cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Sugar manufacturing industry</cell><cell>36</cell></row><row><cell>Distilleries</cell><cell>13</cell></row><row><cell>Breweries and Malt manufacture</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Flour mills</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Edible Fats manufacture</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Chocolate and Sweet manufacture</cell><cell>5</cell></row></table><p>In addition, the film and gramophone industry was also nationalised. Under the statutes other new boards may be set up to govern industrial enterprises acquired through confiscation. Such properties may also be brought under any existing nationalised industry board. At present negotiations are proceeding about such confiscated properties in the border areas ("Sudetenland" etc.); these will be incorporated into various nationalised industries and their equipment taken over.</p><p>The food industry was nationalised under a special decree which differs from the decrees dealing with key and heavy industries. The food industry is closely linked to agricultural production and its problems are special and regional. Its administration has been taken over by the State in such a way that its regional interests are fully represented. In the first instance the whole food industry was nationalised outright, but where it might prove to be advantageous co-operatives could be formed.</p><p>After nationalisation has been carried out, industry in Czecho-Slovakia will fall into three distinct groups: —</p><p> (1) Industry nationalised and taken over by the State;</p><p> (2) Industry nationalised and turned into co-operatives, e.g. part of the food industry;</p><p> (3) Private industry in medium and small units.</p><p>Trade, both internal and external, as well as small factories and workshops, remains within the sphere of private enterprise.</p><p>Industries already owned by the State, such as State mines, were transferred to the nationalised sector; in the same way most power and gas undertakings previously owned by municipalities were taken over. Thus, in the majority of instances the nationalised sector of industry forms only a part of producing units, but is both by number of employees and industrial capacity the largest and most important. Its productive capacity stands at about 70 per cent, of total pre-war capacity; it employs roughly 65 per cent, of all industrial workers. The table on the previous page sets out the relationship between the nationalised and private sectors in the more important industries.</p></div><div><head>Compensation payments </head><p>Compensation has been settled in an unorthodox, indeed revolutionary manner. Only thus was the Republic able to protect its economy from the consequences of the years of German activity; at least partial compensation was received for the enormous economic damage suffered. Where the nationalised property belonged either to the German Reich, to Hungary, to public corporations set up according to German or Hungarian law, to the German Nazi Party or to any Hungarian political parties, or to corporations of these regimes, no compensation was paid. In the cases of German or Hungarian individuals compensation will only be paid if it can be proved that these people remained loyal to the Czechoslovak Republic, and either participated actively in the struggle for liberation, or suffered under Nazi or Fascist terror. Individuals convicted of treason or who collaborated with the enemy will be refused compensation.</p><p>For other owners the amount of compensation paid will depend legal portion of the property on the day on which it was taken over by the nation; the value for compensation purposes will be commercial price of the property calculated on the basis of be current index. If no index is available, the value of the property will be assessed by official valuation after all liabilities have been deducted. It was found necessary to set up a Special Nationalised Economy fund in Prague to deal with all questions of compensation.</p><p>Compensation is paid in various forms: either in securities of the bearing interest, which will be paid off gradually from any profits of the nationalised industries; or in cash or other securities. From the outset the government has emphasised that compensation for nationalised property will be paid to all foreign owners without discrimination. On the other hand, the government could not accede to certain demands from abroad that particular industries, on which large amounts of foreign capital had been invested, should be exempt from nationalisation. It was also essential to investigate some of the foreign claims to ensure that they were not, in fact, concealing claims by former German owners. Negotiations are proceeding between the Czechoslovak and foreign governments with regard to the amount and mode of payment of compensation for foreign assets acquired by the State.</p></div><div><head>Psychological effects of nationalisation </head><p>Though doubts had been voiced about nationalising industry on such a large scale, these have proved to be unfounded. As nationalisation was carried through in one stroke, a period of uncertainty was avoided and the pattern of the economic structure immediately made clear. Nationalisation had excellent psychological effects on reconstruction. The working class parties were satisfied, and trade unions given a share in management through factory committees. As a result the workers’ attitude towards industry has changed radically.</p><p>Difficulties in Czechoslovakia in the immediate post-war period resembled those of most other countries. Production was declining, and working morale was low. A quarter of a million people returning from concentration camps, and seven hundred thousand workers who were deported to work in Germany had to be reassimilated. Unlike most other countries Czechoslovakia had to resettle its border regions, where Czech workers are taking the place of Germans.</p><p>These difficulties could be overcome because the workers realised that they were no longer working for the private profit of others, and that it was in their own interest to raise production. In this connection it should be noted that not a single big strike has taken place since the war. Increased industrial effort helped to raise production very quickly, so that, for instance, the output of brown coal rose from 479,380 metric tons in May 1945 to 1,781,817 tons in March 1946. Similarly, the output of hard coal over the same period from 239,089 metric tons to 1,268,762 tons and thus reached the 1937 level. In a number of industries the proportion of labour cost to total production charges was reduced: it declined on an average from 30.9 per cent, in January, to 25.3 per cent, in September 1946.</p><p>The Czechoslovak Republic, by nationalising the basic means of production, changing from a liberal to a planned economy, and laving down a two-year development scheme, has set out on the road of progress towards socialism to be achieved within a democratic structure of society.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>