<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Canada and the CCF</title>
         <author>David Lewis</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Canada and the CCF</title>
            <author>David Lewis</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Canadian" party="Co-Operative Commowealth Federation"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Like the rest of the American Continent, Canada emerged from the recent war much stronger industrially than she had ever been. Instead of the destruction of plant and equipment which was the unfortunate lot of European countries, Canada’s industrial capacity increased substantially. The standard of living of people in all classes rose considerably over that of the depression decade preceding the war. Labour unions made gains both in the field of organization and in wages and working conditions.</p><p>A great deal of the industrial expansion during the war was financed from the public treasury. The Canadian Government invested approximately $1,000,000,000 in building plant and equipment for war production. In most cases this public investment has since the end of the war been handed over to private corporations, many of them monopolistic in character, at a very small proportion of the original cost. Without going into detail, it is a fact that the concentration of wealth and economic power has been greatly increased as a result of the policies of the Canadian Government as well as of normal capitalistic development.</p><div><head>Price control </head><p>In one sphere, official policy in Canada registered considerable success compared with that of other countries, namely, the field of price control. The official price index in Canada at the end of the war (August, 1945) was 120.5, as compared with 101.5 in 1939, an increase of approximately 19 per cent. This compares very favourable with the 30 per cent, increase in the United States, and the 29 per cent increase in Great Britain.</p><p>However, as soon as the war ended, the Canadian Government began a policy of de-control. This has proceeded much more slowly in Canada than in the United States. Important fields of price control are being maintained even to-day, and are likely to remain for many more months. Nevertheless, there has already been a jump of six per cent in the cost of living in Canada since the end of the war and there is every indication that the cost of living index will continue to rise in the months to come. Whether or not the Government will succeed in avoiding serious inflation remains to be seen.</p><p>The de-control policy has been completed in all fields other than that of price control. Almost every instrument of planning the national production has been abolished. The declared policy of the Government, fully supported, of course, by the other, nonsocialist parties and big business, is the quickest possible return to what they call “free enterprise”. The consequences of this disastrous policy are already beginning to emerge. Housing, for example, has proceeded extremely slowly, even though Canada suffers very little from the shortages of manpower and materials which hinder housing programmes in the European countries. Some few shortages there are, of course, but they are nothing compared to the European experience. Yet the total of homes built in Canada since the end of the war compares very unfavourably even to the accomplishments of Britain, which has so many difficulties to overcome. Furthermore, the houses which are being built are entirely under private construction and in private hands, with the result that they meet the needs of the well-to-do rather than those of the low-income groups.</p><p>     Housing has been given merely as an example. Put briefly, the general economic situation in Canada is comparable to that of the United States at the present time. Canada is experiencing considerable capitalist prosperity. Unemployment is at a minimum, standards of living are better than they were before the war, business and production activity is relatively high, and profits continue to be made at a fairly healthy rate. At the same time, evidence has begun to appear of the crisis which is to come. Without any attempt at national planning, the economy has been left completely to the vagaries of the capitalist market and of the greed of monopolistic control. It may be started with certainly, although without any joy that when the depression hits the United States, it will have immediate and severe repercussions in Canada. Further, there is no indication whatever of any official policies designed even to mitigate the effect of that depression, let alone to avoid it.</p></div><div><head>Labour’s position</head><p>The labour movement is having a hard struggle to retain the gains which it won during the war. The year 1946 saw a very considerable strike wave which allotted many basic industries in Canada, such as automobile, steel, rubber, parts of mining, lumber workers, and several less important branches of the economy. The results of the strikes were 0n the whole favourable to the labour movement. The unions have retained the largest part of their strength, and have registered some advances.</p><p>However, one sees signs of a determination on the part of Canadian big business to follow the footsteps of their brothers in the United States, and to institute a concerted campaign to lessen, if not to destroy, the strength and power of the trade union movement. It is possible that 1947 may be free of major labour struggles, with the exception of the coal miners in one part of the coal industry. However, one may expect a sharpening of the struggle in a year or so, when some of the signs of recession begin to emerge.</p><p>Unfortunately, the Canadian trade union movement is divided along the same lines as in the United States. In fact, most trade unions in Canada are branches of international unions, with headquarters in the country to the south. When the split between the C.I.O. and A.F.L occurred in the United States, it was inevitable that it take place also in Canada. We have, therefore, two major central labour organisations, the Canadian Congress of Labor, which comprises the unions affiliated with the C.I.O. in the United States, and the Trades and Labor Congress of Canada, which comprises unions affiliated with the A.F.L. in the United States. Although the division between the two organizations in Canada is very much less bitter than it is in the United States, it is nevertheless a handicap to labour’s struggle. Canadian socialists look anxiously toward unity developments in the States, which would immediately he reflected in our situation.</p><p>One of the results of the Canadian labour movement’s dependence on the American is that it has not followed the British tradition of independent political action. Development in this direction has been slow. At the present time, the Canadian Congress of Labor stands committed, by resolution of their annual convention since 1943 to support of the C.C.F. as the political arm of labour. The other Labor Congress in Canada has so far refused to take such action. A small section of the trade union movement, considerably less than 10 per cent, has affiliated directly with the CCF and there is every reason to hope that progress in this direction will continue to be made. In any case, it is undoubtedly true that by and large, the labour movement recognises the C.C.F. as its party, even when it does not officially say so.</p><p>One of the major obstacles in the path of bringing the trade union movement into political action through the C.C.F. is the Communist Party, known in Canada under the name of Labor Progressive Party during the past few years. Because the C.C.F. Because the CCF has consistently refused any political collaboration with the Communists and constitutionally excludes a Communist from representing an affiliated union in the Councils of the C.C.F., the Communists oppose vigorously and ruthlessly any tendency in the trade unions towards joining with the C.C.F. While the Communist Party is relatively small in numbers in Canada, it does hold important key positions in sections of the trade union movement.</p></div><div><head>Trends in agriculture </head><p>The position of Canada’s farmers continues to be fairly prosperous, particularly as compared with what it was during the decade before the war. Farm production in Canada is very great, and world demand for food has supplied our farmers with a steady market. A measure of the improvement in the farmers’ conditions over the pre-war years is suggested by a comparison of farm income in 1945 and in 1938. In the last pre-war year the total farm income in Canada was $423,857, while in 1945 it was $1,061400.</p><p>However, Canada’s farmers are increasingly uneasy because Government policies are gradually removing those instruments which might promise stability to the agricultural industry. Farmers remembering the disastrously low prices of the ’30’s are, therefore, extremely worried about the future when the world demand for food is likely to decrease. So anxious about the situation are they that a farm strike occurred in some parts of the Canadian west, that is to say, a delivery strike. Significantly, that strike was concerned very little with immediate demands for increases in prices; it was concerned very much more with demands for national machinery to guarantee security and stability to the agricultural industry in future.</p><p>The Canadian farmers, like those elsewhere, are determined to win a policy of guaranteed prices sufficient to cover their cost of production and secure them over a period. Canada’s dependence on the export market for its farm products places the farmer in a very vulnerable position the moment world food prices begin to go down. It is against this contingency that farm organisations are snuggling at the present time.</p></div><div><head>The political scene </head><p>The brief description of the economic situation and the position of labour and agriculture in Canada gives a clue to the general political situation in this country. In power at the present time is the Canadian Liberal Party which is, by and large, considerably more to the right than, say, the Liberal Party of Britain. The official Opposition is in the hands of the Canadian Conservative Party, which manages to squeeze into the narrow space left to the right of the Government.</p><p>The C.C.F. (Co-operative Commonwealth Federation) is the third party in Parliament. As is well known, our party is relatively young, having been formed in 1933. In a very short period— slightly more than a dozen years—the party has registered very considerable progress. It failed to make the gains most people expected in the general election of the summer of 1945, but it made progress nonetheless. Its popular vote is about 20 per cent, of the total vote in Canada. It increased its representation in Parliament from 9 to 28. In 1944, it was elected to power in 0ne of Canada’s provinces. Saskatchewan, and it is the alternative to the Government in three other provinces. All signs point to continued progress, although no one in the C.C.F. has illusions about a quick advance to power.</p><p>The general political atmosphere in Canada is characterised at the present time by a swing to the right, very mild compared to the swing in the United States, but real nonetheless. The reason for this tendency is the same as that in the United States, namely, general economic prosperity and a feeling of fear about upsetting the "good” times. This situation will undoubtedly change if and when the depression hits this continent.</p><p>A dangerous development is the progress made by the Social Credit Party of Canada among the French-speaking Canadians in the Province of Quebec. The Social Credit Party began its activities in the Province of Alberta in the West, and won power in that Province as long ago as 1935. It has continued in power since, although with decreasing popular support. Until recently, it failed completely in every attempt to spread beyond the borders of the Province of Alberta. However, in the past year or so, it has made dangerous progress in Quebec.</p><p>The reason for calling this development dangerous is that the Social Credit movement of Canada shows many signs of Nazism in a mild form. Thus it is outspokenly anti-Semitic; it opposes violently every form of international organisation, including even the United Nations itself: it is frighteningly anti-labour, and appeals to nationalist elements among the French-speaking people of Quebec Significantly enough, it also wraps itself in a sort of religious mysticism and speaks about the building of a "Christian Democracy" in terms which are reminiscent of statements in Italy and Germany and some of the Eastern European countries before the war. There is reason to believe that there may be some kind of informal understanding between Canada’s Conservative Party and the Social Credit movement. If this should prove to be so, the danger will be greater, because a combination of these two groups in the Canadian political community might become a pretty powerful force of reaction.</p><p>Having described the situation, it is important to emphasize that at the present time the development is still in its beginnings. It may well be that it will not last and that Social Credit progress will be slow and short-lived. The C.C.F. is watching the situation closely, and hopes that the deep democratic sense of the Canadian people will resist the demagogic appeal of the Social Crediters.</p><p>Briefly, the general political situation may be summarised as follows: The power of monopoly and big business having been increased by the war and post-war policies, the political parties representing capitalism are also very strong. Relatively prosperous economic conditions have produced a tendency toward political disinterest and resultant conservatism among the people. At the same time, there is a growing political consciousness in the ranks of the labour movement and also of the farm organisations. This is the basis from which the C.C.F. has grown. Future political development will depend largely on economic development.</p><p>One final point about the political situation may be mentioned briefly. The majority enjoyed by the Federal Government in Canada is rather small. A serious crisis of some sort might easily upset it. The result is that many people expect a general election much sooner than the Constitution requires. The present Government could continue until 1950, but it is likely that an election will come at least a year or two before that, and perhaps even sooner.</p></div><div><head>CCF party organisation </head><p>The general condition of the C.C.F. has already been referred to in the discussion of the political situation. Organisationally, the party is stronger than it has been in the past. Its membership is fairly large, about 60 to 70 thousand, in a total population of only 12 million. It is hoped that during this year the membership may be increased up to 100,000 through a national membership drive which is being planned for the autumn months. </p><p>The C.C.F. suffers and has always suffered from a very severe lack of funds. Because of the attitude of the trade unions mentioned earlier, the party receives almost no financial assistance from them. The party is therefore entirely dependent on individual membership dues and contributions. The result is that in spite of the strength of the CCF in Canada, there is no CCF daily paper anywhere, and the party does not even have a national weekly paper. The party, however, owns seven provincial papers, some of them weeklies, some fortnightlies and one monthly.</p><p>Recently the party acquired its own "home" in Ottawa, the capital of Canada, which now serves as the National Headquarters of the CCF; a new system of financing the national organisation has been inaugurated and there is reason to hope that the organisational future of the CCF may be one of greater co-ordination and effectiveness. </p><p>The party is particularly fortunate in its leadership in many of the Provinces and more especially in the calibre of the Premier and Cabinet of the CCF Government in Saskatchewan, and of the National Leader, Mr J.Coldwell. The great qualities of these men have won the confidence of the Canadian people, even of those who do not support the party. The C.C.F looks forward to very favourable results from the accomplishments of the Government in Saskatchewan. It has a record of progress unequalled by any other provincial government in the history of the country. It has established a measure of security for both industrial workers and farmers in that province which is a model to the rest of Canada. It has developed a goodly sector of industry under public ownership and has placed on the Statute Book social security legislation of a very advanced character. All this has been accomplished in two and a half years, in a province which is relatively poor in resources and depends almost entirely on agricultural production, mainly wheat.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>