<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>American labour trends</title>
         <author>Philip Taft</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>American labour trends</title>
            <author>Philip Taft</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="American" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The attack by Congress upon organized labour in the United States evoked demands for the unification of the labour movement. However, neither the Congress of Industrial Organisations nor the American Federation of Labor is yet ready for discussions on mending the rift, and it may require a severe setback before serious negotiations are begun.</p><p>To an outsider the division in the ranks of American labour may appear incomprehensible, for no major ideological differences divide the two groups. The C.I.O. arose because the older unions in the A.F. of L. refused to recognize the industrial form of organization in the mass-production industries. Forfeiture of jurisdiction would have in fact involved no loss of actual members, as the older unions had few of the workers in those industries enrolled in their organizations. Their obstinacy on this point led to a break in 1935 and eventually the labour movement divided into two competing and at times hostile segments.</p><p>The new central organization, the C.I.O., was able to establish itself and solidify its position, despite the scepticism of the A.F. of L. The latter had assumed that no rival organization could survive under American conditions. However, the C.I.O. refused to conform to the historical pattern. Instead of failure it expanded, entrenched itself and now competes with its ancestor, the A.F. of L.</p><p>Any discussion of labour politics in the United States must keep in mind the existence of two organizations, their rivalry and their open and concealed hostility. It must also be remembered that the rise and success of the C.I.O. was, to a large degree, made possible by a favourable government. Prior to 1933 the unions in the United States were largely concentrated in building construction, printing, clothing manufacture, coal mining and railroads. Unionism in the heavy and mass production industries was virtually non-existent. Dominated by large-scale units, these industries were able, by the use of force, to prevent the lodgement of any labour organisation on their properties.</p><p>The tremendous expansion in union membership of the last fourteen years was rendered possible by the Administrations of President Roosevelt, through a series of laws beginning in 1933. The change in attitude of American society and American business; shown by the general acceptance of union organisation and collective bargaining. In 1933, the heads of the largest steel companies refused even to discuss labour conditions in their industry with the head of the American Federation of Labor.</p><div><head>The New Deal </head><p>While the support and protection of union labour was an important permanent achievement of Roosevelt s New Deal, this policy met only one of the problems—and at the time not a major one—facing the United States. When he took office, Mr Roosevelt found the country involved in an industrial and economic crisis of unparalleled intensity. The unemployed numbered between twelve and fourteen million; agricultural prices had been sharply deflated and farmers were being forced oft their land by foreclosure; the banks were in serious trouble and many were closing. Mr Roosevelt took office as the candidate of a mildly Liberal party. Whatever social radicalism existed in the United States was weak and disorganized. Considering the impotence of the radical and Socialist movements; considering the absence of any organized support for a programme of reform or reorganization, considering the political instruments he was forced to use and the political inexperience and ineffectiveness of his supporters, Roosevelt’s legislative achievements appear as the work of a political genius.</p><p>Mr Roosevelt was initially elected as the result of deep and widespread dissatisfaction in the cities and in the countryside. Programmes for the economic rehabilitation of agriculture and for the relief of urban labour were immediately instituted. But the measures taken were often contradictory. This was inevitable in view of the multitude of problems and the absence of any potent political group with a co-ordinated plan for basic reform or social reorganization. Those who complained of the New Deal’s inadequacy gave little help when it came to votes at election time. Yet the Roosevelt programme not only halted the price and income declines in agriculture, but reversed the downward trend. For the first time the federal government assumed the responsibility for direct aid to the needy unemployed. The humanity and understanding shown in the administration of these programmes was something new in American life. It convinced the industrial worker that Roosevelt was a devoted and humane friend, and labour showed its confidence by voting for him in large numbers in all of his subsequent campaigns. He was the greatest gatherer of labour votes in American history.</p><p>In contrast, Mr Roosevelt did not permanently retain the loyalty of his rural constituents. As soon as the farmers had gained some improvements in their economic position, they began to lose enthusiasm for the New Deal. They were, of course, not opposed to receiving benefits from the government, but soon showed their hostility to measures designed to improve the position of labour. Moreover, a charge that the federal government was threatening individual enterprise was an effective propagandist device in the rural areas. As a result the farmers began to desert the New Deal, and by 1940 only a few agricultural states gave their electoral votes to Franklin D. Roosevelt.</p><p>The New Deal retained the loyalty of the large urban and industrial communities, and it is these areas which gave Mr Roosevelt majorities in the elections of 1936, 1940 and 1944. Yet while he retained the loyalty of the rank and file worker to the last, a section of the leadership of organized labour disapproved of Mr Roosevelt and supported his opponents. Even many of his supporters refused to join with him in building a permanent organization or movement to perpetuate and extend the principles of the New Deal.</p></div><div><head>Labour’s attitude to politics </head><p>The backwardness of American labour in utilizing its opportunity to build a political movement was due in part to the long-time opposition to political involvement. While this opposition has, in the last few years, been seriously weakened, it has by no means been extinguished. For many years the majority—but by no means all—of American labour leaders were opposed to direct participation in politics. Instead of sponsoring an independent Socialist or Labour Party, American labour leaders followed a bi-partisan or non-partisan policy of pressure politics. This meant that candidates who were favourable to suggestions on legislation desired by labour were endorsed; the others were opposed. Independent political action by labour was discouraged. At no time was the labour movement unanimously in favour of this policy. For many years a strong minority of Socialists and others existed who urged that labour should create a political instrument of its own, and devise a long-term programme of reform. Yet the dominant opinion in the labour movement favoured pressure politics and opposed independent political action. This view still commands a large and influential following, though it is perhaps declining.</p><p>The opposition to independent political action was closely related to a sort of labour laisser-faire. Partly as a result of government and court intervention on the side of the employer in labour disputes, and partly due to the influence of ideas and ideologies dominant in the American environment, large sections of American labour developed an anti-government philosophy.</p><p>This is best illustrated by the long opposition of the American Federation of Labor to unemployment insurance, an opposition which was reversed only during the Great Depression at the convention of 1952. The validity of these beliefs in laisser-faire was severely shaken by the Great Depression. Increasingly since 1933 labour as well as other sections of the community have begun to recognize that government must assume some or all of the responsibility for economic prosperity and full employment.</p><p>These changes in attitude might have stimulated organized political activity in the ranks of labour, which in turn might have attracted middle class and professional people anxious to find a democratic solution to contemporary social and economic problems. The split in the labour movement was, perhaps, the most important factor in holding up this development. In the United States secession movements have been regarded as a serious offence against labour, for it was widely believed that they broke down the solidarity vital to the survival of the unions. As the Congress of Industrial Organizations acquired the status of a permanent rival, co-operation between the leaders of unions affiliated to the American Federation of Labor and those of the C.I.O. became increasingly difficult. This division made it impossible for the many leaders of the A.F. of L. who were sympathetic to the New Deal to devise a common political policy and organization with the C.I.O.</p></div><div><head>Attempts at reconciliation </head><p>As an attempt to unify the forces of labour politically the Labor Non-Partisan League was formed in 1936 to help re-elect President Roosevelt. But A.F. of L. and C.I.O. political co-operation soon faded, as the fight between the two movements grew in intensity. Nevertheless, many labour leaders recognized the necessity for building a political instrument. While a few extremists believed that the best policy in politics was to have no policy, their numbers were and are diminishing. Government to-day offers vital protection to the unions without which many would be at the mercies of the employer; government not only operates social security programmes, but by its fiscal policies can influence the level of employment. These facts are increasingly recognized in labour circles; nevertheless any active political labour movement will first have to overcome the division inside the labour ranks.</p><p>Even if the movement were united it is unlikely that the trade unions would support an independent political party', since it; might at present entail too many risks. The labour unions are vitally concerned with specific, even narrow gains, and their failure to support the election of their friends to national and state legislatures would adversely affect the outcome of many important union issues. Moreover, while a new political party finds it hard union to gain a place on the ballot, it is relatively simple for an organized group to enter the primary of an old party. As in most American states party candidates are chosen by the members of the party in the primary, it is possible for an organized or unorganized group to support a candidate favourable to its views. Thus candidates favourable to labour can be put on the old party tickets. Therefore, while the chances of an organized labour political party are not promising for the immediate future, the possibility of a labour-sponsored political movement is much greater.</p><p>Many people in the American labour movement recognise that the anti-governmental unionism of some of the older leaders is outmoded; and that labour will have to fight its battles on both the political and economic fronts. Yet there are serious obstacles to political action. Perhaps the most important is the division inside the trade union movement, which colours the attitude of many labour men and blurs their views on various issues. The important position of the Communists presents another serious obstacle in the political movements dominated by the unions affiliated with the CIO. The experienced officials of the A.F. of L. are not easily fooled by the camouflage and false front of the Communists. The youth and lack of sophistication in some of the CIO membership and the initial absence of trained leadership has enabled the Communists to gain important places in the councils of this organization. Moreover, the day-to-day duties of the trade union officer leave little time for political activity. As a result Communists have infiltrated into important political posts such as the Political Action Committee—originally set up by the C.I.O. for the elections of 1944. Nevertheless, this organization played an important part in the re-election of Roosevelt in 1944 and Sidney Hillman, its leader, was able to prevent the Communists from totally dominating its councils and policies. The Communists were not, at that time, eager to control the organization as long as such conduct aroused opposition. Since then conditions have changed, the Political Action Committee has been reorganized as the! Progressive Citizens of America, and it seems that the Communists are in complete command. According to their usual tactics, the Communists have assembled a collection of stooges and innocents headed by the former Cabinet officer, Henry Wallace, who, for all his other estimable qualities, is rather a babe in the woods in the field of left-wing politics. Communist influence in the P.C.A. has been so much discussed in the American press to make its support of a candidate in most instances a doubtful advantage. The key position of the Communists in the C.I.O., the centre in which a progressive programme would normally be developed is therefore a serious deterrent to the growth of labour political action.</p><p>Recently a group of progressives and Social-Democrats have organized the "Americans for Democratic Action". This is an attempt to unify the shattered and dispirited forces of American progressivism on the basis of a democratic programme, but excluded Communists and their allies. While the organization has the approval of some distinguished names, including Mrs Roosevelt, it is doubtful if it will be able to carry out its set task. "Americans for Democratic Action" lacks substantial trade union support, although a few important union officers attended the inaugural meeting. The CIO, under strong Communist pressure, opposed a resolution calling for participation of CIO officers in the councils of the "Americans for Democratic Action" at a recent CIO Executive Board Meeting.</p><p>Trade Union unity is the most urgent need of American labour. The gains from division are small and the dangers great. While the possibility of punitive legislation has somewhat abated, the labour movement needs a programme assuring the American people of a high level of employment, adequate protection from insecurity resulting from unemployment, sickness and old age. Unless the American labour movement wakes up in time, the United States may again be forced to improvise in handling the difficult domestic and international problems. A united labour movement could devise a programme, not perhaps socialist, but which aimed at avoiding serious unemployment at home and the promotion of peace and security abroad. The power of the Communists would thus be reduced to proper proportions: the movement would be able to evolve the progressive programme essential to a great democratic nation, if it is to avoid dangers at home and abroad. A political genius of Franklin D. Roosevelt's calibre can successfully improvise solutions in time of crisis, but it is dangerous and foolhardy to tempt the fates more than once. The American Labour movement must develop greater political consciousness; it will never take the first step as long as it is divided in mutually warring factions.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>