<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Dutch Labour Party</title>
         <author>Koos Vorrink</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Dutch Labour Party</title>
            <author>Koos Vorrink</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.1</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Dutch" party="Dutch Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>The 9th February, 1946, will stand out in Dutch political history as the date when it was decided to found a new political party. Several political groups formed during and shortly after the war combined with the old Social Democratic Party, the Labour Democratic Union, and the Christian Democratic Union. The new party consisted of people with widely different backgrounds and views: there were Catholics and Protestants, as well as people from the Resistance Movement holding more radical views. It was founded with the declared aim of striving for a new socialist and democratic society.</p><p>Political life in Holland before the Second World War had reached a deadlock. Religious and non-religious groups were sharply divided by a rigid barrier which prevented party action on a basis of economic or political principles. The serious effect of this division was much evident in the years following 1929, when the Netherlands, among many other countries, was hit by mass unemployment. Apart from other problems facing the Government there was the question of 400,000 unemployed men. As a result of the slump, the Socialists evolved a “Labour Plan” which formed the basis of their election appeal during the campaign of *937-</p><p>Though these elections in 1937 were fought with energy and enthusiasm and in close co-operation with the trade unions, the results to the Socialists were disappointing. The Party gained only one seat, giving it 23 seats (out of 100) in the new Parliament. The religious parties in coalition, however, increased their representation from 52 to 56 seats, proving once again the great difficulty of obtaining an electoral verdict on the many burning social issues. The previous Prime Minister, Colijn, again formed a Coalition Government which was based on the religious parties (two Protestant Christian and one Catholic Party). Events, however, proved too strong for this artificial combination.</p><p>On the eve of the Second World War, the policy which had governed Holland for so long and which had proved utterly incapable of coming to grips with any major problem, was quietly laid into its grave. For the first time in the history of the Netherlands two Socialists, Dr J.W.Albarda and Dr J.Van den Tempel, joined the Cabinet. A new era had dawned for the Socialist Party; after a period of successful but one-sided opposition, the party began to shoulder a more responsible task. In the interval between the two world wars the Christian parties had systematically prevented the Socialists from entering the Government. During the latter part of this period their followers grew increasingly uneasy about the exclusion of the Socialists, particularly when fresh undogmatic and constructive reforms were put forward by the Left. Leading members of the Christian Party, such as Mr J.E. Van Walsum (now a member of the executive of the new Dutch party), and Professor Lieftinck (the new Minister of Finance) openly criticised their party's action.    </p><p>The long German occupation gave an opportunity for a completely new start. People who had been active in support of the Resistance Movement felt no longer tied to the narrow sectarianism of the religious parties. Having won a new freedom they were impatient to establish State and Society on a new model. At first it seemed as if the wind of war had blown the leaves off the political trees and scattered them in a different pattern. At one time the Dutch People's Movement, a "personalist" Socialist Movement, was sweeping the country. Yet inborn Conservatism proved stronger than wartime experience. The majority of pre-war political parties soon re-established themselves. Nevertheless, a noticeable gap remained; it was filled by the Labour Party, formed after much discussion.      </p><p>More than a year of experience has now been gained since the Labour Party was founded. Elections held in May 1946 for Parliament were eagerly awaited; the results disappointed many. The Labour Party and its adherents and sympathisers had hoped confidently to gain 35 out of a total of 100 seats. They did, however, win only 29 seats, while the Catholic Party, winning 32 seats, became the largest Parliamentary faction. It was clear that the Socialist Prime Minister, Professor Schermerhorn, would have to resign; Dr Beel of the Catholic Party succeeded him. This setback was caused principally by the attitude of some members of the old Social Democratic Party who fought with the Communists and helped to increase Communist representation from three to ten seats. The post-war political pattern of Holland is, therefore, comparable with that of many other Western European nations.</p><p>The Communists were not drawn into discussions about the formation of a new Labour Party. Their pre-occupation with dialectical materialism totally excluded them. In addition their adherence to the dogma of proletarian dictatorship, strictly modelled on the Russian pattern, their tactics of slander and demagogy regarding the socialist movement, precluded any approach by the Labour Party. Following the elections, the Labour and Catholic Parties formed a coalition government. That this should have been possible indicates the fundamental changes which had taken place in Dutch political life. The coalition formulated an agreed policy, having as its pivot a possible settlement of the Indonesian question. The Labour Party consented to this policy under the leadership of M. Jonkman and Professor Schermerhorn in the hope that the Linggadjati Agreement would be the foundation of final and lasting co-operation between the Netherlands and Indonesia. Besides, a radical fiscal policy and improvements in provisions for the aged—points on which the Labour Party laid particular stress—were incorporated in the Government programme. Structural changes in agriculture are planned; the Dutch Bank is shortly to be nationalised, and it is hoped that the Dutch coal mines left in private hands will follow. No other coalition of parties could have agreed on so radical a policy.</p><p>Inside the Labour Movement a new unity has arisen. Various groups within the Party Executive, in Parliament and other representative organisations, have their own spokesmen. As in other democratic political institutions with a left-wing outlook radical and moderate currents flow through party life, but in this instance cut across old formations and groupings. The Party aims in its publicity to appeal to widely different sections of the population Catholics Protestants and Humanists within the Party each run study circles for their sympathisers and issue their own publications. A series of conferences has been organised by the party as a whole on such subjects as Indonesia, local government, education and agriculture. A special programme committee which includes representatives of every group and shade of opinion inside the party unanimously framed a programme of principles, which leaves no doubt as to the democratic and socialist character of the new party.</p><p>That agreement should have been possible was largely due to the members of the old pre-war party. It had not leaned too heavily on Marxist dogma, though, of course, it had contained many members who were Marxists. Some of these have joined the new party. We may conclude by remarking again that the formation of this Dutch Labour Party has delivered Dutch political life from the bondage of two rigidly opposed political groups - the one a religious coalition, the other Marxist - and so made possible the development of a Democratic Socialist State.</p></body></text></TEI>