<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
         <author>Editorial Staff</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
            <author>Editorial Staff</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><div><head>Anti-labour legislation in the United States </head><p>The anti-labour forces in the United States Congress had a shortlived victory. No sooner had the Senate over-ruled President Truman's veto of the Taft Hartley Bill—popularly known as the Slave-Labour Bill—than John L. Lewis, the miners’ leader, won the greatest victory of his career. He signed an agreement with the coal — owners by which the owners agreed to help the workers evade one of the most damaging provisions of the Bill. The contract applies only as long as the miners are "willing and able to work", which means that the unions are not liable for damages because of unofficial strikes by their members. This is a great victory for the workers, but it does not mean that the Bill has been rendered harmless. On the contrary it is a very grave attack on the American labour movement.</p><p>It is true that the Bill does little to affect the structure of organised labour as it exists. What it does most successfully is to hamper the power of the unions by surrounding them with restrictions. Under the guise of forbidding "unfair labour practices,” it prohibits the closed shop, nation-wide strikes and sympathetic strikes and boycotts. It sets up a complicated mediation apparatus in order to prevent strikes, whose only result is likely to be endless litigation. Two political provisions, by-products of the current Red witch-hunt, ban political activity by unions and forbid a Communist to be a union official.</p><p>These last two provisions will in practice be the most difficult to enforce and as palpable limitations of civil rights are most likely to be declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court. The effect of the other clauses is that strong well-organised unions (as the miners have already shown) will be able to survive, but weaker ones will suffer. In addition, the organisation of non-union workers, such as those in the Southern States, will be full of difficulty.</p><p>The unions’ reaction to the threat was swift and encouraging. Already the C.I.O. and the A.F.L. are studying together ways and means of fighting the Bill, which is all the more vulnerable to attack because of its sponsors’ eagerness to include everything. If it should be a means of re-uniting the American Labour movement, the "Slave-Labour Bill" would indeed be a dubious victory for the reactionaries.</p></div><div><head>World government </head><p>A group of British Labour Members, including Henry Usborne, the Rev Gordon Lang and Evelyn King, has set in motion a scheme for a World Government. They have insisted that the only feasible approach to a federal system of World Government is through a constituent assembly elected by all peoples. To develop this idea the Group sets out to attract membership and supporters from the whole world. They are planning no European Federation, nor a Western European bloc.</p><p>The movement is gaining ever wider support from Labour Members of Parliament, its organisation is growing rapidly and other movements in European countries, particularly in Holland and Belgium, with similar aims, are adhering to the organisation which is British in origin and entitled the “Parliamentary Group for World Federal Government".</p><p>The line of argument adopted by this group is that, in the first place, the United Nations has not removed the elements of national sovereignty; it merely provides a different set of rules for playing the old game. The group insists that the only means to World Government is the formation of a Constituent Assembly, elected by direct universal franchise. As an immediate aim the Group has planned an assembly (the People’s Constituent Assembly) to meet in Geneva in the Autumn of 1950. The whole project for World Government would then be in the hands of this Assembly. The approach of the Group to the practical problems to be overcome—the obvious fact that one or other bloc of Powers might boycott the scheme and so render it merely another cover for an aggressive organisation—is to insist that the normal method of Government and relations between Governments by diplomacy are showing signs of intense strain. The only means to case the strain appears to the Group to be to step outside the normal grooves of politics and reconstruct on the basis of a universal popular movement and a resulting People’s Constituent Assembly.</p><p>By stepping outside the field of normal international relations— through Governments—the Group has placed itself above the criticism that it is another weapon of power-politics. The question how to compel present sovereign Governments first to permit the growth of the movement and then to accept what the Constituent Assembly puts forward is answered by the assertion that the popular strength of the movement will compel all parties in every Parliamentary Democracy to accept World Government under what might become the "Geneva Constitution of 1951.”</p><p>This movement stands in striking contrast to other movement, since the war that have taken their origins from, the manifest need of Europe to form a politically and economically sound federation. Count Coudenhove-Kalergi, who has devoted his life to the propagation of the ideas in his book “Pan-Europa," is still working through his Committee for the European Congress. Count Coudenhove-Kalergi's ideas have no basis in Socialism. He wrote his book, in 1923, to meet the menace of Communism—and he used the word communism in a very wide sense to cover all firms of socialist doctrine. To-day his conception of a United States of Europe is plainly “political”. Writing last April the remarks that "Not all European States are free to join the Federation now. But Britain and France, with some of their neighbours, can go ahead. Inevitably all of Europe will follow in due course”. The Count believes, then, that a federalised “Western bloc” will attract the rest of Europe to it.</p><p>A “United States of Europe” has been planned by Mr Churchill, who with some advice from Count Coudenhove-Kalergi, has developed his scheme on the basis of a rapprochement between France and Germany. In rather the same direction M. Herriot and M. Briand, with Stresemann, tried to mould a European Federation within the loose structure of the League of Nations, twenty-three years ago. Mr Churchill’s United Europe Movement has, however, attracted some sincere Socialists in England, and in none of its overt declarations has shown itself opposed to socialist development in Europe.</p><p>Mr Bevin, in the House of Commons in November, 1945, said: “We need a new study for the purpose of creating a World Assembly elected directly from the people of the world... I am willing to sit with anybody of any party, of any nation to try to devise a franchise or a constitution for a World Assembly.” It is on this task that Henry Usborne’s group of Members of Parliament is working. Mr Bevin’s approach to the problem was, apparently, far removed both from the normal machinery of diplomacy and from the interest he has in the functional co-ordination of activities of many nations by bringing them together to operate some particular scheme.</p><p>There is a great gulf between, on the one hand, the primarily Conservative schemes, depending on the acceptance of Governments and the formation of a federation because of certain common material and geographic factors (such as the sharing of the Rhine and the “necessity” for Franco-German Union as a cordon sanitaire), and on the other hand, the mainly socialist schemes that depend, idealistically but not impossibly, on ah affirmation of the “General Will,” the vox populi of all nations.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>