<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>A new Socialist International</title>
         <author>Max Buset</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>A new Socialist International</title>
            <author>Max Buset</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Belgian" party="Belgian Socialist Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The establishment of a Socialist International has always been one of the corner-stones of the Belgian Socialist Party’s policy. As parties to the formal winding-up of the old Second International in November 1946, we Belgians feel that the time has now come to re-build an International Socialist organisation. We find three main reasons why an International should be re-established.</p><p>Great men from all countries have served the cause of International Socialism in the past: Jaurès and Blum from France; Troelstra from Holland; Branting from Scandinavia; Marx, Engels and Kautsky from Germany; Turati from Italy; Iglesias from Spain. And we ourselves are proud of the part played by Belgians in the International Socialist movement, particularly by such men as César Départ, Emile Vandervelde. Camille Huysmans and Louis de Brouckère. From meetings of the International these Socialists, and many others from all countries, gained great advantages; exchanges of opinion over a wide range of problems were possible. While we still have with us some of the men who shaped the old International, and before the old traditions are forgotten, the torch should be handed on to a younger generation.</p><p>Secondly, there is the point of doctrine. We Belgians are convinced that Socialism can only survive if it becomes international, that it cannot succeed in any one country unless it is supported by an international movement which, in creating a favourable world public opinion, can overcome the difficulties and obstacles in its path. We know from experience that it is impossible for any one party to resist a determined attack for long, whatever its present degree of security and solidarity. Appeals for help have come from parties who were badly hit by the war, by occupation, or by difficulties in their own countries. It will, therefore, be essential to set up some socialist organisation which can come to the material aid of socialist parties in many countries—perhaps a socialist entr'aide'.</p><p>But to achieve our final aim—a fully socialist state in our own country—problems of great complexity will have to be faced. These problems have one common characteristic: they can only be solved on an international plane. Economic problems alone forbid purely national solutions Socialism can flourish only if it is not constantly menaced by fascism or reaction just beyond its frontiers. </p><p>Thus there can be no realisation of Socialism unless all countries are assured of lasting peace. We must therefore draw the conclusion that contacts, exchanges of information etc. do not suffice: our actions must march in step. We can only be successful if we support one another's aims. To this end socialist solidarity is indispensable.</p><p>The third reason is one of tactics. In the age in which we live all political action is bound to have international repercussions. Are we who were the first to stress the importance of international action, to be the last in reaping its fruits?</p><div><head>Other political internationals </head><p>Though the Comintern was officially liquidated, it is no secret that there exists to-day an international Communist movement Through Russian legations on the one hand, through Russian control of Communist Parties on the other, a very active, well-organised International has grown up. This type of internationalism has gained several advantages for Russia and Communist Parties in many countries. At the other end of the scale we are faced with American imperialism, a force which supports conservative and reactionary elements wherever these can be found. The Vatican represents yet another powerful international force—to our wav of thinking a formidable foe. Obviously, the Catholic influence varies from country to country: the British Labour Party considers it of secondary importance. But in a country such as Belgium, where the Catholic Church is an established force, it must be regarded as an important enemy. Its influence is difficult to define- it is less aggressive or general than capitalism or Communism but it is met with at every step. Catholicism may be disguised as a conservative conception of political democracy or a reactionary attitude to social democracy. Unless care is taken we shall find one day that corporative ideas have infiltrated into our movement.</p><p>The Liberals, remnants of a past century, were no exception in expressing a desire for an International when they met in England last year. There is no single aspect of public life to-day where it has not been found advantageous to organise internationally. Are we, the pioneers of internationalism, the first to practise international action, too much afraid now to take up our international tradition?</p><p>There are objections and difficulties of various kinds. First of all, our Eastern European comrades, living in closer proximity to 1 the Soviet Union, have to be careful not to complicate their political position at home. Their objections raise the issue of World Socialism’s attitude towards Soviet Russia. In Belgium we believe that workers' unity will be achieved one day; and workers' unity is the fundamental condition if Socialism is to have a future. But in the Belgium view nothing can be gained by making overtures to the Communist Party at the present time. However, many believe that the USSR has laid the foundations of an economic and social democracy which will in the long run, bear fruit. At present social the Russian structure lacks political democracy - an element which we consider as a first essential. This difference in development between Soviet Russia and Western Europe has historical causes. Sooner or later political democracy will be introduced in Russia, while the Western European countries, once they have overcome the last vestiges of capitalism, will add economic and social democracy to their state structure. At that point Eastern and Western Socialism will have established an equilibrium, and unity then becomes possible.</p></div><div><head>Difficulties and objections </head><p>Until that time, contacts, common action, and reconciliation must be hoped for. On the one hand, national parties must be left free to solve their own problems of unity; on the other all must strive together to bridge the chasm dividing disciples of Marx from those of Lenin. The reconstitution of the International cannot form a fundamental, insurmountable obstacle. It is almost a truism to say that the possibility of unity requires at least one condition: that Socialism does not disown itself, that it keeps its character and that, frankly and firmly, it builds up a personality of its own. Only under such conditions can Socialism become a power which will later enable it to discuss the question of workers’ unity.</p><p>To turn to British Labour Party objections. A few days before the last International Socialist Conference in Zurich (June 1947), Mr Hugh Dalton, in the name of the Labour Party Executive, expressed his strong disapproval on the subject of rebuilding the International. It is not difficult to understand the position of the Labour Government. That Government is at present carrying through an experiment which will have far-reaching repercussions on the future development of Socialism. If British Labour succeeds in nationalising essential sectors of the British economy, if it succeeds in building up nationalised industries, it will have proved that Socialism can be realised through democracy. If it fails, however, all our political enemies will use the British failure as a propaganda weapon, thus creating a hostile public opinion to the ideal of Socialism.</p><p>By meeting in International Conferences we do not create difficulties or even embarrassment for the British Labour Party, which has just begun its difficult task of socialist reconstruction. Yet a party must not only support its chosen Government. It is far more vital that it should sow the seeds of socialist thought, which will bear fruit by creating strong currents of world opinion. The Belgian Socialist Party too, supports the Belgian Government- it forms part of that Government- yet it considers it a duty, a right, and a privilege to shape public opinion well in advance of Government action. Only thus can Government action be effected with any ease. It seems possible, therefore, to rebuild the International without creating difficulties for parties which have decided on complete support of their respective Governments.</p><p>The third type of objection is of a different nature. Though it has been the subject of much discussion and many articles, let me re-state it briefly. Many voices of warning have been raised against repeating the “mistakes of the past” in the organisation of the International. For fifteen years I served on the Executive of the International, together with such well-known men as Louis de Brouckere, Salomon Grumbach, and Louis Levy. I was deeply involved in the famous discussions on problems which the International then had to tackle. Now it is said that these discussions only serve to demonstrate the weakness of the old International; and these arguments are used to-day as a reason for opposing its reconstruction. Surely it is a feeble excuse to speak of “errors of the past” in order to condemn in advance any fresh attempts to create a new International.</p><p>The present organisation of international socialist relations is obviously unsatisfactory. It has been said that the bonds which held us together formerly were too rigid. Those of to-day are far too loose. After careful examination of all the problems involved an attempt must be made to reconstruct the International. Of course, the “lessons of the past” must be taken into account, as must the present circumstances of international socialist action.</p><p>In balancing the advantages against the disadvantages of setting up a new International, it seems to me that the advantages far outweigh any possible disadvantages. Firstly, it will be necessary to agree in principle on the reconstruction of the International; secondly, a small International Committee must be set up to study in detail the problems posed by such action. On the one hand, there is this aspiration, on the other, the realisation that the reconstruction of an International will create difficulties. If our wish for an International Socialist movement is sufficiently strong, then all difficulties which stand in our path to-day can be overcome. The Socialist International has been for many past decades a vital symbol of socialist faith. Let us now create a new, living symbol of our faith and our ideals.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>