<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Italy – Political battleground</title>
         <author>Anonymous(Italian)</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Italy – Political battleground</title>
            <author>Anonymous(Italian)</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Italian" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>With the fall of fascism the different social forces in Italy were left free to search for new political alignments. These alignments varied with the regions of the country and the economic status of the people. Italy may be divided into two parts: from the North to Rome, where the people, having reached a certain level of political consciousness, have already chosen their parties—Communists, Socialists, and Christian Democrats: and from Rome to the South, where the political orientation of the people is still uncertain.</p><div><head>The North</head><p>Economically and socially, northern Italy is on the same level as western European countries; both large- and small-scale industry in the towns; large estates with up-to-date equipment, as well as a considerable number of medium-sized agricultural holdings; a fully developed commerce; a strongly organised working-class; an independent middle-class; an economy controlled by a small group of industrialists.</p><p>While the people found their way to the older political parties— 85% of the workers, 40% of the peasants and a fair percentage of the urban middle-classes went to the Communists and Socialists, and the rest to the Christian Democrats—the big industrialists, who had once been tied to the Liberals and later to fascism, remained independent of party, preferring a “wait and see” policy.</p><p>In Central Italy the bulk of the population consists of smallholders and mezzadri (share-croppers, who pay the landowner part of the product of the land they cultivate). Both these peasant classes had given strong support to fascism in its early stages and after the war were without political affiliations.</p><p>The Communist Party has played an important role in this area.</p><p>It began a strenuous campaign among the mezzadri, demanding for them a share of 60% of the agricultural product instead of the previous 50%. The obtained 53%, and the long struggle made the Communists the strongest party among the mezzadri. As many of these people have become either small-holders or agricultural labourers. Communist influence is not limited to the mezzadri but is more widespread.</p><p>Although this struggle had been directed against the landowners, who were really parasites, this question had its demagogic side. The mezzadri, represented by the Communists as poor people exploited by the landowners, had in fact themselves exploited others —high prices and the black market enabled them to make a lot of money during and after the war.</p></div><div><head>The South</head><p>In Southern Italy the ruling class is composed of big and medium landowners, who live in the towns and are usually engaged in some profession, but who still derive part of their income from their land. They are particularly disliked by the peasants, who look on them as exploiters of their labour and as the most unconditional supporters of private property.</p><p>There was formerly no direct link between the political parties and the poorer classes. Parties, left and right, were satisfied to secure the support of the reactionary or progressive elements respectively of the ruling class, which through their personal and economic influence brought with them the support of a certain number of peasants. Nevertheless, the Right had no hope of enlisting the lasting support of the farm labourers, who demanded agrarian reform, contrary to the interests of the landowners</p><p>The votes given by the Southern peasants to both the Christian Democrats and the Qualunquisti were not the expression of full support for those parties, but arose from special circumstances. A few weeks before the General Election a Congress of the Christian Democrats voted 78% in favour of a Republic. This decision brought the Vatican openly into the electoral campaign. The clergy was mobilised in support of the Monarchy. Where it was impossible for the parties to exert any influence, the clergy succeeded. Because they were against the government which seemed to them to be dominated by Republicans and did nothing for them, and because they were told to do so by the clergy the Southern peasants voted in favour of the Monarchy in the plebiscite.</p><p>Since the electoral votes had been cast on religious grounds, and not in support of the party’s programme, the Christian Democrats were unable to maintain their hold on the Southern peasants. The latter became more and more dissatisfied with the negative attitude towards them shown by the government and the parties which formed it, and drifted, owing to their lack of political education, to the Uomo Qualunque, the most violent opposition movement, not realising that this was the party of reactionaries and big landowners.</p><p>But this situation is now changing again as a result of the Communist Party’s activity. Since the end of last year, the Communists with their special interest in the peasant question inherited from the Russian Revolution, have started a strong campaign among the southern peasants.</p><p>This direct penetration breaks the traditional way of approach through the ruling classes. The election results in Sicily are a first portent of more and greater left-wing successes throughout the whole of southern Italy. Communist Party policy aims less at improving the condition of the peasants than at strengthening its own position in the rural areas, which are steadily becoming more and more important. It must be recognised, however that this direct link formed by the Communists between the workers in the North and the peasants in the South will be a powerful basis for a democratic policy in Italy.</p><p>The importance of this Communist policy is emphasised by the following conclusions: the Communists will become the strongest party in Italy; the Southern middle-classes, which used to fill the administration, the army and the judiciary will eventually be ‘politically liquidated; and the radicalisation of the peasants will cause a conflict within the Church, where the lower clergy are much more closely bound to the poorer classes than to their bishops.</p></div><div><head>Jockeying for position</head><p>In a country without democratic institutions, real political power lies less in constitutional bodies than in key positions in the administration, the army, and economic organisations. The struggle for political power is therefore carried on in two directions: in the parliamentary sphere, and in the control of key positions.</p><p>At the end of the partisan war, the Left-wing parties controlled all positions in the whole of Northern Italy. In the majority of the provinces, the mayors and prefects were either socialists or communists; in most of the big industries Left-wing Commissari had been appointed by Allied Military Government under pressure from the CLNAI (Northern Italy Committee of Liberation).</p><p>But in spite of their presence in the Government, the Left-wing parties could not hold on to these positions. The coalition of six parties before the elections and the Christian Democrat majority afterwards, made it impossible to maintain the anti-fascist prefects in office.</p><p>In industry the Commissari and the factory management committees were in a particularly delicate position. The industrialists refused to give financial support, the bankers declared they had confidence in the former managers but not in the new ones. The Communists worsened the situation by pushing into the factory management committees ordinary workers quite incapable of performing their new duties. A year after the war, workers in many industries were calling for the return of their former employers, even if they had been removed for fascist activities, in order to stave on bankruptcy.</p><p>The situation could have been mastered by economic control at the top. But a coalition government in which the Ministries of Finance, Treasury, and Industry were held by a Communist, a Liberal, and a Christian Democrat respectively, made that impossible in practice.</p><p>In addition, it must be noted that the Communists bear a particularly heavy responsibility. Their avowed purpose of encouraging unrest, as well as their dogmatism and lack of ability, have prevented them from putting economic reconstruction into effect. The most striking example of this is Scoccimarro, who was Minister of Finance for two years. During the whole of that time he failed to present any proposal to reorganise taxation.</p><p>About a year ago, as a move in the struggle to control key positions, the Socialist Party took over the post of Minister of Industry. In a very short time Morandi, the Socialist Minister had become Public Enemy Number One to the industrialists. He refused to subsidise industry on the application of an industrialist, unless the application could be justified. When one of the wealthiest men in Italy threatened to stop paying wages unless he received subsidies, Morandi replied: “To-morrow I will requisition part of your plant.” The decisive battle was fought for mastery of the IRI (the Institute of Industrial Reconstruction), the powerful financial body through which the whole of Italian economic life can be controlled. Morandi was able to discover the actual position of the financial and industrial groups in the IRI and planned some changes in its administration. At the same time he presented his fourteen-point programme to overcome the economic crisis. The Cabinet endorsed the Socialist proposals, but the Confindustria (the industrialists’ organisation) led by Costa, a very intelligent and capable man, opened a violent campaign against the Socialist Ministers.</p><p>De Gasperi realised that the Left-wing parties had lost control of the last key position, and precipitated a government crisis.</p></div><div><head>The Christian Democrat government </head><p>Tied on the one hand to the democratic movement of the workers and the middle classes, and on the other to the big Southern landowners and to the Vatican, the Christian Democrats cannot follow a consistent political line. Only the demands of the Vatican on such questions as religious education, marriage, and church right, find a prompt response in their Catholic minds.</p><p>That is why the Christian Democrats have a foreign policy initiated by the Vatican which is much more powerful than that the Palazzo Chigi - and a domestic policy which backs any proposal to strengthen the hold of the Church on the country and aims at a completely clerical control of education, but have no economic policy.</p><p>For this reason, and also because the industrialists have not yet finally decided on their political affiliations, Professor Einaudi has been appointed Minister of Industry, and the removal of Morandi has not brought the final victory of the Confindustria.</p><p>Einaudi is not a representative of the industrialists and he should theoretically be able to follow a firm economic policy, but he is likely to become a prisoner of the monopoly capitalists.  They will back Einaudi if he removes some of the economic controls which prevent them from taking full advantage of the seller’s market, but they are not against economic controls as such. They know how to control the controllers; what they dislike are controls they cannot touch.</p><p>It might have been good tactics for the Left to back Einaudi in an economic policy directed against the industrialists sectional interests but the Government crisis made that impossible. All the centre and left-wing parties are now in opposition, but they are likely to have a majority at the next election.</p></div><div><head>Outlook for the future </head><p>The Government can only prevent this defeat if the economic situation improves appreciably before the election. They are, therefore, making urgent appeals for aid from the United States, and at the same time seeking to postpone the election. If they succeed, both Parliamentary power and key positions in administration and industry will be in the same hands, and events will take a new course. A new reactionary alliance of high administrative officials, army officers, and powerful economic interests under Vatican leadership is a likely result, and democratic forces will have to face the threat of another Catholic dictatorship, similar to that of Dollfuss or Salazar.</p><p>If the Government does not succeed, Parliamentary power will be in the hands of the Left, but the actual administrative and economic power will remain in the hands of the Right.</p><p>In Spain, in similar circumstances, the Right began the Civil War. But Franco was backed by aggressors like Hitler and Mussolini, and could rely on Chamberlain. To-day neither the U.S.A. nor the U.S.S.R. is willing to see civil war break out in Italy, and they will advise their supporters to be cautious. Even Italian extremists do not want a civil war. They know what would happen: initial successes by the former partisans, with the murder of many leading industrialists and landowners, and final repression of the civil war through American military intervention. No one likes such a prospect.</p><p>A good deal of criticism has been directed against the Socialist leaders who declared their party's final aim to be fusion with the Communists. But it must be recognised that the revival of the Socialist Party was largely unexpected - even Saragat did not believe it possible. This revival was due to a spontaneous popular movement and to the courageous activity of a small handful of people.</p><p>The Pact of Common Action between Communists and Socialists called for equal representation or the two parties at all levels. Socialist successes among the industrial workers were consequently mainly due to the fact that the Communists brought Socialists into the factories. Without the pact, all the workers would have gone with the Communists. The same thing is now being repeated among the peasants. The Socialists themselves would never have sacrificed the certain votes they obtained from their political supporters among the progressive elements of the ruling class, in order to appeal directly for the uncertain votes of the peasants. Because of the Pact they are forced to follow the Communists, who are going straight to the peasants.</p><p>A Socialist Party of workers and peasants must, sooner or later, become a rival to the Communisms. Consciousness of this had already grown when the party was suddenly weakened by the split earlier this year. At present it cannot afford openly to challenge the Communist Party, because the latter would reply by attacking it in the factories, and destroying it as a workers' party. But its self-confidence has not been entirely lost. There is sign of this in the replacement of Lizzadri, a passive follower of Di Vittorio, by Santi, a well-known anti-fusionist as a socialist representative on the C.G.L. (Trade Union Organisation), that is the most delicate point of contact with the Communists.</p><p>Of course, there is still a danger that the Socialists may foil. But it is absurd to underestimate the efforts which they are making to increase their strength, however much the leaders may be considered responsible for the party’s former weakness. The Socialist Party aims at regaining the position it had before the split—that is to become no less important than the other two leading parties.</p><p>If the Socialists succeed, they will be called on to put into effect a plan for the country’s economic recovery, within the framework of the Marshall Plan. Nobody can foretell whether the Communists will support a Socialist Government. But Communist opposition can only be resisted by Socialist activity among the workers and peasants. If the latter were controlled by the Communists alone, they would, as in France, undermine the Socialist Government.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>