<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Bund – A Jewish socialist movement</title>
         <author>Lujan Blit</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Bund – A Jewish socialist movement</title>
            <author>Lujan Blit</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Polish" party="Bund"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text><body><div><p>Fifty years ago, in October, 1897, Jewish illegal socialist groups in Tsarist Russia held a conference at Vilna and formed the first Jewish Socialist Party, which they called the Bund (Union). The Bund was one of the first socialist parties in Russia (the Russian Social-Democratic Party was constituted in 1898). It was also the best organised, the most revolutionary, and politically the most homogeneous group in Russia, which at that time included the greater part of Poland.</p><div><head>Background </head><p>The 18th and 19th centuries saw in Western Europe the disappearance of the last remnants of feudal society, and the consolidation of national states. Consciousness of national unity and of national cultural tradition developed freely among the peoples of the West, helped by the industrial revolution, by the spread of elementary education, and by the extension of popular suffrage. These circumstances made possible the slow growth of religious, racial, and political tolerance.</p><p>Eastern Europe developed in a different direction. National consciousness awoke much later among the oppressed peoples of this area. “Forgotten" nations, such as the Czechs and Lithuanians, discovered their historic past and started to build their own new national culture in their own language. But to do this they had to fight the artificial cultural assimilation forced upon them by the oppressor states. This movement was strongest and most successful in the old Austro-Hungarian Empire; it was much more difficult in Tsarist Russia.</p><p>The beginning of industrialisation in Russia at the end of the 19th century' had the usual effect of bringing together in the new towns illiterate peasants from remote villages. It was comparatively easy for young students of the same race to reach these people to arouse in them a feeling for their national tradition and language and to stimulate their growing desire for political independence. The Jews in Tsarist Russia, numbering about six millions, were compelled to live in a prescribed area called the "Jewish Pale of Settlement" which included Poland, the Ukraine, White Russia, and the Baltic States. It was precisely this region which witnessed most extensive and dramatic struggle for cultural and political independence from Moscow. The Jews, forming between 10 and 15 per cent, of the population of this area, were placed in a dangerous dilemma. They could support the unpopular Russian rulers; they could try to become assimilated into the smaller national groups with which they had neither religion nor language in common, and among whom they lived so inextricably mixed that to take sides with any one group would inevitably entail persecution from others; or they could form their own national group, scattered though they were over the whole region.</p><p>Small groups of the Jewish intelligentsia did become absorbed into Russian and Polish intellectual life. The great majority however, having lived for centuries in social isolation, was almost untouched by either culture. But the Jews were influenced by the prevailing nationalist spirit, which in their case was reinforced by a distinctive religious tradition and by the experience of intermittent persecution, which took the form, in 1881, of widespread pogroms.</p></div><div><head>Policy of the Bund</head><p>At first the Bund took a neutral line over this problem. But in order to spread its socialist propaganda the party had to use the language of the masses. That language was Yiddish — hitherto regarded with contempt by the Jewish intelligentsia and clergy— and neutrality was no longer possible.</p><p>In 1902 the Bund adopted a socialist programme for solving the “Jewish Question." It recognised the special position of the Jews, as outlined above, and accepted Jewish nationhood as a fact; a fact which was proved by the tremendous outburst at this time of Yiddish literature and drama and the growth of Yiddish schools. The Bund believed that a socialist society would enable this Yiddish culture to develop freely, and at the same time, would allow Jews to play their full part in the larger community in which they lived. The Bund rejected strongly any tendency of Jewish nationalism to create a new ghetto in any form. Herein lies the main reason for its opposition to Zionism.</p><p>In Tsarist Russia the Bund had been a member of the federal Russian Social Democratic Party. After the Revolution and with the formation of new states in Eastern Europe, the Bund in Rumania and Latvia joined the national Social-Democratic Parties, representing the Jewish workers and being active in the Jewish communities of these countries.		</p><p>It was in Poland, with its three million Jews, that the Bund played its biggest role between the wars. Though prevented from becoming part of the Polish Socialist Party, it did everything possible to co-operate with Polish workers, as well as with the minority groups of Ukrainians, White Russians and Germans, and achieved great success, especially in the united Trade Union movement. It was by far the largest Jewish party, and in the elections for district and city councils in 1938 and 1939 it received 70 per cent of the Jewish vote.</p><p>From the very beginning the Bund was accepted as a member of the Socialist (Second) International. During the First World War the Bundist leader, W.Kossovski, took an active part in the international conferences in Switzerland, and in 1917 another leader Henryk Erlich, was one of the six delegates sent by the Russian Workers' Councils to Stockholm, where a vain attempt was made to save the Second International, which had disintegrated under the stress of war.</p><p>Henryk Erlich and Victor Alter represented the Bund in the Labour and Socialist International until 1939. In the last years before the war the Bund was in full agreement with the French, Belgian, Norwegian and Austrian Socialist Parties.</p><p>The same spirit of internationalism was displayed by former Bundists who emigrated to America after the collapse of the first Russian revolution of 1904-5. It was no accident that Sydney Hillman and David Etabinsky, who both received their early socialist education in the Bund, succeeded so magnificently in building up the most internationally-minded Trade Unions in the U.S.A.</p></div><div><head>The War</head><p>During the war, under Nazi occupation, the Bund held true to its early heroic tradition. It led the underground movements among the Jews who were forced by the Nazis into the ghettos of Poland, and produced many clandestine papers, including even children’s papers. It joined with other groups in forming the combatant organisations whose greatest achievement was the long battle in the Warsaw Ghetto during its liquidation by the Germans in April and May, 1943, and the less well-known, but equally bloody battles in the ghettos of Bialystok, Krynki, and many other places. Bund organisations were even created in the concentration camps for as long as the people remained alive.</p><p>But even the most heroic resistance by Jewish socialists or by the Jewish people generally could not change Hitler’s decision to exterminate all the Jews he could find. During five years of war this massacre accounted for six million Jewish lives, among them one million children.</p><p>During the whole of this time the Bund took part in the life of the International Socialist movement. The late Zmul Zygelbojm participated in the last meeting of the executive of the Socialist International in the Spring of 1940 in Paris. He went there direct from Warsaw and for the first time revealed the sufferings of the people living in Nazi-occupied territory. From 1942 onwards representatives of the Bund belonged to the International Socialist Committee in London.</p></div><div><head>After War </head><p>The massacre of the Jews in Europe decimated the Jewish Labour Movement. But in spite of that, the Bund never ceased to exist in Poland, and is now working actively with the Polish Socialist Movement. At the same time it is the only non-Zionist organisation amongst Jews.</p><p>The result of war-time persecution was not only to decrease the number of Jews, but also to strengthen immensely the national consciousness of those who survived. Jewish nationalists are now strongly urging these survivors to leave the countries where they have been living for centuries. The Bund is fighting this idea. While taking part in all kinds of Jewish cultural, educational and reconstructive activities the Bund stresses the need for Jewish workers and intellectuals to regard themselves as part of the whole society of the country in which they live, and to join in the fight for a democratic socialist solution of all problems - including the Jewish problem. </p><p>The Bund is strongly opposed to the Zionists using the lamentable situation of the 200,000 displaced Jews in Europe for their own party ends. In the U.SA as in other countries, the Bund organisations are organisations are leading a campaign for the absorption of Displaced Persons into all free countries.</p></div><div><head>World Bund Co-Ordination </head><p>In May, 1947, the fist conference of world Bundist organisations took place in Brussels, Sixty delegates represented the organisations in 16 countries.</p><p>Before the war the Polish Bund was, in fact, if not officially the spokesman to the world for all Bundist organisations. As the result of the Nazi catastrophe there are now about 100,000 Jews in Poland and ten millions elsewhere (including five millions in the USA). The Brussels conference therefore decided to form a world Co-ordinating Committee. This was done with the full approval of the Polish Bund which was represented by seven delegates led by Dr Schuldenfrei, a member of the Polish Diet.</p><p>This World Bureau will have its headquarters in New York, and there will be a European secretariat.</p><p>Among the five million American Jews are a million workers in strongly organised Trade Unions le by good Socialists. They also have friendly societies and clubs, Yiddish schools for children also have to attend on Sundays, theatres, and a press with a wide circulation (the Yiddish paper "Forward" has a circulation of 150,000 copies daily). The Jewish Labour Committee, representing 500,000 workers, has among its most prominent members many well-known Bundists. It is hoped that the newly-created World Co-ordinating Committee of Bundist and Jewish Socialist Organisations will be able to influence the political development of this great movement of American Jewish Labour.</p><p>The conference did not attempt to formulate a common political line for all Bundist organisations to follow in their separate countries. The difference between the political situation confronting the Bund in Poland and that with which it is faced in Britain or America is obviously so great that it was decided, after a thorough discussion, to leave group to work out its own policy.</p><p>All delegates were united however, when they came to deal with purely Jewish questions. The conference again confirmed the movement's non-Zionist stand, and called on members to support all efforts to rebuild Jewish community life, in places where it existed before the war, on a non-religious and democratic basis. The conference also repeated its belief that only Socialism can guarantee the final elimination of anti-Semitism and racial discrimination.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>