<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Correspondence</title>
         <author>Anonymous(American)</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondence</title>
            <author>Anonymous(American)</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="American" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>The Editor, “Socialist World,”</p><p>Sir, — I fear that the final paragraphs of the article “American Labour Trends" in your first issue may seriously confuse your readers. In general, they may form the impression that the Communist Party has more importance in the American scene than it really possesses. In particular, they may seriously overestimate its influence in the C.I.O. The following brief outline of political organisations on the left may help clarify the picture. </p><p>First in the field among the newer American progressive organisations was the Union for Democratic Action (UDA). This was formed in 1940 with a programme calling for social reform at home and aid to those fighting fascism abroad. Since the Communists at that time opposed the second part of the programme, this organisation was by definition non-Communist.</p><p>In 1944 three new organisations appeared. Most important was the CIO Political Action Committee (CIO-PAC) founded by Sidney Hillman as the political arm of the CIO to help re-elect Roosevelt. Shortly thereafter, Hillman also formed the National Citizens' Political Action Committee (NC-PAC) which was composed of independent progressives (i.e., people not affiliated with trades unions) and which had no organic connection with the CIO. At about the same time there appeared the Independent Citizens' Committee of the Arts, Sciences, and Professions (ICCASP). The CIO-PAC did a great deal of actual election work; the two others did little but raise funds.</p><p>Communist influence in the CIO-PAC is about what it is in the CIO, i.e. 20 per cent. The Communists did not officially control NC-PAC, but rapidly took it over after the death of Hillman. Although ICCASP included a great many leading personalities who brought to politics nothing but well-known names plus goodwill and naiveté, its inner organisation was probably under Communist control from the beginning.</p><p>In 1945 there appeared the National Educational Committee for a New Party, headed by the well-known Negro trades union leader, A. Philip Randolph. This was largely a socialist project.</p><p>Early in 1947, NC-PAC joined ICCASP to form the new organisation, Progressive Citizens of America (PCA). Contrary to the impression that Mr Taft, probably inadvertently, gives, the CIO-PAC was not involved in this merger in any way. Simultaneously, the Union for Democratic Action greatly broadened its membership, taking in most of the non-Communist left, and became Americans for Democratic Action (ADA). Recently Mr Randolph and his Committee have pledged their support to ADA, stating at the same time that they will seek to persuade ADA to direct its efforts to building a new political party.</p><p>In the beginning, both PCA and ADA had prominent CIO, officials among their sponsors, although ADA was well ahead in this respect. Rightly or wrongly, some CIO people felt that it was a mistake thus openly to air the division within the ranks of the CIO. Hence, the CIO ordered its people to withdraw from both organisations. CIO activity as such will be channelled through the CIO-PAC which, to repeat, remains independent of both ADA and PCA.</p></body></text></TEI>