<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Britain meets the crisis</title>
         <author>Anonymous(British)</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Britain meets the crisis</title>
            <author>Anonymous(British)</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The British Labour was expectant on the 6th August, when the two-day debate on the State of the Nation opened in the crowded House of Commons. Another economic crisis, all the more terrifying because its effects were unknown, was rapidly approaching. The crisis was imminent - it had been prophesied for months - though no one knew exactly when it would come. Just what its result would be was a matter for guesswork; what seemed certain was that there would be a serious deterioration in the British standard of living. There was consequently a sense that Britain’s whole future might depend on the measures to be announced by the Government.	</p><p>To many people in Britain the speed at which the crisis developed, the sudden urgency of the situation, was somewhat bewildering. They had realised, of course, that the balance of payments situation was unsatisfactory—there had been plenty of warnings from members of the Government. But few were prepared for the alarm, which spread during July like circles in a pool, as the enormously increased drawings on the American loan became known.</p><p>The Government took the opportunity before the Parliamentary recess for a debate in which the Prime Minister announced the emergency programme to meet the worsening economic situation. The previous week he had met the Parliamentary Labour Party, who greeted him with applause, and gave him a vote of confidence after he had outlined the new policy. And so the stage was set.</p><div><head>The background </head><p>Britain’s economic prosperity has long depended on her external trade. In the nineteenth century she had been the leading manufacturing country in the world, importing food to feed her workers and raw materials to feed her industries, and exporting machinery, textiles, and other manufactured goods. At the same time British shipping overseas investments, and financial services brought in a great additional income, and gave Britain a favourable trading balance. By the beginning of the First World War British supremacy had already been successfully challenged by other industrial powers, especially Germany and the United States. The war of 1914-18 accelerated this relative decline. The favourable trading balances disappeared; overseas investments had to be sold to pay for Britain’s war effort, and a vast was incurred to the United States. Britain never recovered, and in 1938 she had an external trade deficit estimated at £70,000,000 which had to be met by the sale of overseas investments.</p><p>In the Second World War, Britain’s tremendous effort completely transformed her economy. Exports were cut to the bone, overseas assets sold and almost the whole industrial potential diverted to war production. At the end of the war Britain emerged victorious but exhausted.</p><p>When the Labour Government took office in the summer of 1945, it had the tremendous task of restoring British economy and finding ways to make ends meet. A loan of £937,000,000 was negotiated with the United States, for the purpose of helping to tide over the period until Britain was on her feet again. At first all went surprisingly and deceptively smoothly. The change-over of industry from war to peace production, the demobilisation of the armed forces went off without serious trouble, and by the end of 1946 exports were back at the pre-war volume. Only £150,000,000 of the American credit had been drawn.</p><p>Then came the worst winter in living memory and a tremendous set-back to Britain’s recovery. Coal stocks ran low, transport was held up, industry slowed down, then came to an almost complete standstill. For a fortnight unemployment figures were back almost at the level of the black pre-war days. This was a blow from which even yet Britain has hardly recovered.</p><p>The "Economic Survey for 1947,” an analysis of Britain’s position, was issued shortly after the fuel crisis. In it were set out minimum targets for the basic industries (200 million tons of coal 1947) and for exports (140 per cent, of the 1938 volume by the end of 1947). But the stoppage had been too disruptive. In June the targets were revised; the export figure of 140 per cent, of the 1948 volume was postponed to the middle of 1948. Early in July there was a debate in the House of Commons in which Herbert Morrison gave a grave warning. “The gap in our balance of payments ” he said, “is at present far too wide to be closed by any increase in production and exports that can be expected in the early future. The plain truth is that increased production and exports are unquestionably a long-term solution. Equally certainly they cannot provide the entire short-term solution - they cannot enable us to pay our way in time.”</p><p>The major factor in the rapidly worsening situation was the dollar shortage. The United States emerged from the war stronger than the rest of the world together. Economy recovery in the war-shattered countries of Europe and Asia was slow, and consequently the world was dependent on American supplies of food, raw materials and machinery. In the face of this unprecedented demand, price of American products rose steeply and continuously, dollar reserves began to run low, and Britain's American credits were drawn on more heavily. In July, under Article VII of the American loan agreement, sterling became freely convertible. By October of this year, Hugh Dalton said the loan would probably be exhausted.</p></div><div><head>Bridging the gap </head><p>To combat the crisis Clement Attlee announced measures to bridge the gap in Britain’s balance of payments from both sides: cuts in expenditure, especially of dollars, and increases in production, especially for export.</p><p>Food imports from hard-currency areas were to be reduced by £12,000,000 a month. Efforts would be made to replace these supplies by purchases from soft currency areas. If this should prove impossible, and reductions to the basic rations have to be made, preference would be given to heavy manual workers. In any case some restriction would be imposed at once, which would include limitation on meals in restaurants and hotels, and a rise in the points value of non-basic foods.</p><p>Other cuts involved timber, imports of which were to be reduced by £ 10,000,000, and petrol. The basic petrol ration was to be cut by a third from the 1st October. A 75 per cent, tax was imposed on the earnings of foreign films.</p><p>To reduce Government expenditure abroad a further cut was proposed in the number of men serving overseas. 133,000 will return to Britain by the end of this year, and another 67,000 in the following three months. The total number of men in the forces would be reduced to 1,007,000 by 31st March, 1948.</p><p>On the other side new targets were set for the basic industries and export. An average output of 4,000,000 tons of deep-mined coal a week was aimed at for the rest of 1947, and as mush opencast coal as possible. The steel target for 1948 was to be 14,000,000 ingot tons—just, but only just, within the industry’s capacity, as the Prime Minister admitted. Transport was to be reorganised to give priority to coal and other important freight. Possibly the most ambitious measure of all was the proposal to increase the value of British agricultural products by £100,000,000—another 20 per cent — by 1951-2. Finally, the export target was set at 140 per cent, of the pre-war volume by the middle of 1948, and 160 per cent, by the end of that year.</p><p>All this would involve considerable hardship. Longer hours would be necessary in key industries, especially in the mines, and the Government is taking powers to control labour by prohibiting the taking up of employment in inessential industries. Increases in profits and wages will be restricted.</p><p>The Chancellor of the Exchequer said later in the debate that these measures were expected to save about £200,000,000 - about a third of the estimated deficit for the year. At the same time discussions were to be opened with the United States in order to obtain some modification of the provisions of the American loan agreement which enforced convertibility of sterling and non-discriminatory imports. This was a stop-gap effort, not a permanent solution. "We shall only get straight", Hugh Dalton emphasised; "when we can pay with our current exports, visible and invisible, for our necessary imports... We must close this gap within, at the outside, a short span of years, and all other devices must be no more than bridging devices for a year or two.”</p></div><div><head>Criticism </head><p>The Government can hardly have foreseen the general disappointment. It was to be expected that the Conservatives would oppose them politically. But what was far more remarkable was the widespread criticism from the Government’s own supporters.</p><p>Labour Members of Parliament concentrated on two main points. Firstly, there was the question: did the proposals go far enough, and were they socialist enough? It seemed to many that the main burden would fall once more on the workers, who would have to work longer hours and surrender some of their freedom to choose what job they wanted, while no comparable sacrifice was forced on the rich. Firms had been asked not to declare “too high dividends”—who was to decide when a dividend was too high? It was feared that the Government’s plans involved some delay in the - housing programme and many members were disturbed by rumours that the Government was not going to carry through the nationalisation of iron and steel promised in the election programme. Nationalisation of steel had become a symbol of socialist faith and its abandonment a betrayal.</p><p>But dissatisfaction was most widely felt on a comparatively narrow issue—the proposed reduction in the armed forces. During the debate Hugh Dalton came under fire from the “Keep Left” group over the smallness of the cuts. One of the main planks in their platform is that the present heavy Government expenditure on large armed forces, and the immobilisation of so many workers, is beyond Britain’s economic capacity. Britain’s foreign policy, they argue, should be readjusted so that British troops can be withdrawn from overseas. Support had grown for this policy which aims at killing two birds—reduction of dollar expenditure and an increase in manpower for industry— with one.</p></div><div><head>Outlook for the future </head><p>The impact of the cuts on the everyday life of the British people is not yet clear. It will be some time before the reduction in food imports by £12,000,000 a month will mean anything to the housewife in terms of smaller rations. Some explanations of this kind would obviously have been welcomed by many people, but as the whole programme was an emergency measure, it was too much to expect these details. In any case, the Government’s announcement was only a broad outline, and left a great deal to be worked out later.</p><p>The possibly increased inflationary pressure, for example, which may arise from the proposals-more purchasing power from overtime pay fewer goods for the home market-may be corrected by the Chancellor in an emergency Budget.</p><p>No matter what the sacrifices, there is no doubt that a great effort will be made by the workers to overcome the crisis. The Trade Unions pledged full support for the Governments programme, and began immediately to work out plans to increase output. The miners were ready to sacrifice their hard-won gains, and would work longer hours to produce more coal, the foundation of Britain’s economy.</p><p>In its wider implications the future of the crisis remains as obscure as the effects which the cuts will have. Much obviously depends on the outcome of the talks in Washington on the revision of the American loan agreement. The assumptions on which the provisions regarding, non-discrimination and the convertibility of sterling had been based had never really been valid: the expectation of a steadily expanding world trade has not been fulfilled. If these clauses are waived—and even the Americans have begun to admit their inapplicability—the drain of dollar resources would be partially checked. No one knows, or can know, how the export drive will succeed, or whether American prices will fall as dollars run out in the rest of the world.</p><p>In the long run Britain’s recovery depends on the recovery of the rest of the world, so that the present dependence on the Western hemisphere can be broken. If that recovery is delayed, the resulting crisis will bring a considerable reduction in Britain’s standard of living and will seriously weaken her economic system. The Government s plans are the first instalment of an attempt to insure against this disaster.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>