<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Social Democracy in Sweden since the war</title>
         <author>Karl Fredriksson</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Social Democracy in Sweden since the war</title>
            <author>Karl Fredriksson</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Swedish" party="Swedish Social Democratic Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>Before the Second World War the Social Democratic Labour Party in Sweden already had the support of the majority of the electorate. The peak of its success was reached in 1940 in the election for the Swedish House of Representatives, the Riksdag, when the Social Democrats gained 134 0ut of 230 seats. In the second chamber, which is elected indirectly by a body of elector the Party at the same time had 75 out of a total of 150 seats.</p><p>This change in the parliamentary position of the Labour Party had no immediate effect on the Government’s policy. Difference of opinion between the names on domestic policy were overshadowed by the war, and from 1939 to 1945 Sweden had a coalition government representing all parties in the Riksdag, with the exception of the Communists. The government’s main task was to guide the country through the critical war years, and it was generally agreed that action should be avoided on issues likely to provoke conflict between the parties. This meant that the Social Democrats could not use their strong parliamentary position to put forward a socialist programme which would have been opposed by the other parties.</p><p>In 1945 the Coalition Government resigned and a Social Democratic cabinet was formed. Economic difficulties had not ended with the armistice, however, and for this reason some consideration had been given to the possibility of maintaining the Coalition even after the war. In principle no party was against continued cooperation of this kind, but in the important reconstruction period the Social Democrats were no longer willing to refrain from influencing economic and social developments in the spirit of their party programme.</p><p>This tendency was already evident while the Coalition was still in office. The Labour Party and the Trade Union Movement had published early in 1944 a programme of social and economic reforms for the postwar period. This was adopted by the Labour Party Congress in the summer of 1944, and formed its platform in the election in the autumn of that year. The programme was also accepted by the Communists, but it would be wrong to conclude from this that it was of a revolutionary nature. For example the recommendations about forms of enterprise and the system of ownership were far from revolt. The programme listed three main proposals: (i) full employment; (ii) fair distribution and higher standards of living; (iii) greater productive efficiency and increased democracy.</p><p> “Socialisation” in the sense of nationalisation of private enterprise was proposed as only one of a number of alternative courses of action for those sectors of the national economy where private enterprise had shown significant deficiencies. This is emphasised in the following declaration embodied in the programme:</p><p> “In so far as private enterprise succeeds in giving citizens as many of the comforts and necessities of life as ought to be possible if labour and material resources are fully and effectively used, it will be allowed to operate in much the same way as before the war. But if it fails to fulfil this obligation, the State will have to intervene, employing in each individual case such methods as it may consider necessary: for example, encouragement of co-operatives and other non-profit-making production; extension of the economic activity of public or semi-public bodies, with or without expropriation of privately owned productive resources; regulation of investments; expansion of purchasing power.</p><p> “The entire economic system must be based on the principle of production for needs. This in its turn involves placing economic power in the hands of the majority. Democracy and the co-operative spirit must be fostered throughout industry. Workers should be guaranteed their share in responsibility for production. Only in this way is it possible fully to convince them that technical and economic developments benefit them also. There is no other way of bringing their creative interest in production problems into full development.”      </p><p>This unorthodox attitude to the problem of socialisation did not imply any change of opinion, but on the contrary corresponded to an old tradition in Swedish Social Democracy. Hjalmar Branting, the first great leader of the party, emphasized this more than once. In the preface to a government report on the industrial structure of the country he wrote;      </p><p>"A systematic socialisation of the whole production is as far from the thought developed here, as it is from the concept of continued economic progress, which forms a part of the ideology of the Swedish Social Democracy."</p><p>In practice, the work of the Labour Party and the moderate character of the mass of its members ruled out any possibility that plans for revolutionary action to change the forms of production could be found in the post-war programme of Swedish labour. In any case the economic structure of the country does not favour far reaching plans for socialisation. The Swedish economic system consists of more than 200, 000 concerns, while the number of farms amounts to more than 300,000. An economy divided into so many individual enterprises scarcely lends itself to State ownership under centralised public administration. This is clearly understood by the Labour Party and the Trade Unions.</p><p>In spite of its modest character the right-wing parties refused to accept the post-war programme as a plan of action for social and economic reform. No alternative remained for the Labour Party but to form a government of its own. The opposition has used every opportunity to criticise the Labour Government, its programme and its policy. The capitalists even tried to scare the people by telling them that the Social Democrats were planning to expropriate small businesses and to introduce a system of Government regulation and supervision. Already during the election campaign of 1944, when the Coalition was still in office, the start of this type of propaganda could be seen. As time went on its motive has become clear, the opposition wants to defeat the Social Democrats and regain political control. Sweden is at present the scene of a struggle for power between Right and Left</p><p>At first the hopes of the capitalists and the bourgeoisie seemed about to be realised. The Labour Party suffered losses in the election of 1944, but the parties of the Right made no gains; it was the Communists who gained in the election. The Social Democrats were reduced to 115 seats or exactly half of the 230 in the Riksdag, and the Communists increased their numbers from three to 15. The proportion of the electorate that voted for the Social Democrats fell from 53.8 to 46.4 per cent, while the Communists increased their vote from 3.5 to 10.3 per cent. In the municipal elections of 1946, which partly determined the composition of the second chamber, the social Democrats declined still further to 44.8 per cent, while the Communists rose to 11.3 per cent.</p><p>In spite of these defeats the Labour Party has maintained its key position in Parliament. The post-war programme has been put into effect step by step, a number of reforms adopted, and social legislation greatly improved. Pensions have been adjusted to meet the real needs of the old people. Family allowances for each child are another example of a very necessary and popular reform. A national health service, a general scheme for school meals, and a new housing policy are among other reforms initiated by the Labour Government to bring a greater measure of social security to the Swedish people.</p><p>In accordance with one of the main objectives of the post-war programme - a fairer distribution of income-a tax reform has been proposed to reduce the burden on practically all earned incomes.</p><p>Instead property taxes and death duties will be increased. This has been one of the most controversial questions during the present session of the Riksdag. But in spite of the most vicious propaganda financed by big business, the Social Democrats do not appear to have lost ground on this question. On the contrary various public opinion polls which have recently been taken, suggest that the tax reform is popular with the majority of wage earners and farmers.</p><p>It may also be mentioned that the Labour Government has introduced a land reform which will affect the future structure of agriculture, the size of farms and the distribution of land. The aim of this land reform is to give small farmers a better opportunity of earning a decent living by helping them to acquire more and better land. This will, of course, increase efficiency in agricultural production and reduce the need for workers.</p><p>In the economic sphere the Government has had to cope with tremendous problems. Though Sweden was a non-belligerent, the war has left many marks on the country’s economy, which meant that more power was entrusted to the State. But the State is not in a position to exercise absolute economic power. Wages are determined by free bargaining between employers and workers. Commodity prices are controlled. They are, of course, not arbitrarily fixed; costs of production are taken into account, and for this reason prices depend upon wage movements, which are not determined by the Government. Industrial development and capital investment are influenced, and in the main controlled, by the State. But the original initiative and executive responsibility remains with the individual enterprise and its management.</p><p>Wages, salaries and farm income have been steadily rising during the last two to three years. This tendency, together with the programme of social reform and the substantial trade credits to foreign countries, has a certain danger, for, with the present shortage of raw materials and consumption goods, this increased income and purchasing power may easily result in inflationary price-movements. This risk is recognised by the Trade Unions, who agree that any demand for higher wages now must be kept within the margin of increased productivity. But in the present situation with a seller’s market for labour at a time of more than full employment, not even the Swedish trade unions have complete control over wages.</p><p>This excess of purchasing power over commodity supplies has, in fact already had severe effects on the foreign trade situation. Since 1945 imports have increased steadily and exceeded exports. To maintain the necessary balance of payments the Government has been forced to impose further limitations on imports, and in order to encourage increased exports, has limited supplies of exportable goods on the domestic market. The rationing of paper and coffee may serve as an example of this rather unpopular policy.</p><p>So far the inflationary process has not got out of hand. It is still a threat, and not a reality. While in the U.S.A. retail prices have increased by about 20 per cent, since the middle of 1946, the cost of living in Sweden during the same time has risen less than two per cent. The rise in wages has, therefore, meant some increase in real income. According to employers’ statistics, real wages of industrial workers are at present 10 per cent, higher, and real income of farmers and farm workers is between 15 and 20 per cent, higher than before the war.</p><p>That the social reforms have contributed to this rise in the standard of living of the Swedish people goes without saying. It is recognised that some mistakes have been made; it is the usual fault of all Government action to be slow and insufficient, and this has been apparent in the field of controlling and regulating investments and foreign trade. The traditional liberal attitude to State regulations has in part been responsible for this. But there is no truth in the statement, frequently made by the opposition parties in their attempt to convince the people of the mismanagement of the Labour Government, that a catastrophe is threatening. On the contrary, the Swedish economy is basically sound.</p></body></text></TEI>