<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The radical democratic party of India</title>
         <author>V.B.Karnik</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The radical democratic party of India</title>
            <author>V.B.Karnik</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1947</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Indian" party="Radical Democratic Party of India"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>The Radical Democratic Party, the youngest of the Indian political parties, was formed in December, 1940. Most of its members, however, are by no means new to the Indian political scene. Many were prominently associated with the national movement, especially in its advanced sections such as terrorist and communist groups, trade unions, peasant and student organisations. Thus much experience, suffering and sacrifice extending over two decades has gone into the formation of the Radical Democratic</p><p>The Radical Democratic Party was born as the logical development of the Indian people’s fight for freedom. That struggle was not mainly and essentially a struggle for national independence alone, but for independence as a means to social freedom. In the course of the struggle, however, the movement lost sight of the end; the means became an end in itself. This was due to a group of nationalist leaders, who under pressure of the Indian upper classes, began to influence the policy and programme of the national movement during its later stages. As a result the national movement developed into a nationalist movement with the aim of replacing British imperialism by the rule of the native upper classes. Simultaneously, the Indian National Congress, since 1920 a broad people’s movement, fell under the sway of industrialists and financiers. The revolutionary elements in the national movement thus had no alternative but to break away from the Congress Party and build a new instrument for developing social and political freedom.</p><p>The war precipitated the break. The nationalists took up an anti-war attitude and penalised those who supported the war. On 1st September, 1940, radical members of Congress were expelled for organising anti-Fascist demonstrations. From that date the nationalists increased their pro-Fascist propaganda and anti-war activities. To combat this trend radical members of the Congress Party decided in December 1940 to form the Radical Democratic Party. Though war hastened the birth of the Party, the more fundamental issue was the nationalistic and socially reactionary outlook of the older organisation, the Indian National Congress.</p><p>The Party would have been formed even if war had not intervened. The Radical Democratic Party is being developed as a broad people’s party. It is not a class party of either industrial workers or peasants. The class structure of Indian society differs greatly from that of Western European countries, since industrial workers form only a very small part. They are not, moreover, a separate class, but part of the large peasant class. Owing to the ignorance and backwardness of the workers and peasants the most important role is played by the lower middle class, whose interests differ little from theirs.</p><p>'The Party’s programme takes into account the present social and economic condition of India. Considering that the country has not passed through a democratic revolution, the Party has adopted as its immediate objective a programme which includes: the establishment of a democratic regime, with power in the hands of the people through direct control over government legislative and executive action; abolition of landlordism and modernisation of agriculture; large scale industrialisation under State control; State ownership of basic industries, land and mines; an eight-hour day and rising standard of living; compulsory free primary education; and freedom of press, speech, assembly, organisation, etc.</p><p>The Party has published an elaborate plan for economic development, which is known as the People’s Plan. It differs sharply from the Bombay or Taha-Birla Plan prepared by Indian industrial magnates and accepted by the nationalist movement as their economic blue-print. The Party has also prepared a draft constitution, known as the Draft Constitution of tree India. This demonstrates how political democracy can be combined with economic security and social equality. Thus the People’s Plan and the Draft Constitution of Free India set out the economic and political programme of the Party; both have attracted much popular support in a short period.</p><p>The Radical Democratic Party is alone in insisting on the practice of scientific politics; Indian politics have hitherto lacked a clear social and political outlook. The Nationalist movement, with a reactionary social outlook, was based on the ignorance of the masses with their rabid religious and nationalist prejudices. The “Left” groups advocated a negative policy, anti-imperialist or anti-British, which lacked any positive social content. On the other hand the Radical Democratic Party sought support for a programme based not on hero worship, blind emotion or race hatred, but on an intelligent understanding and acceptance of a defined programme and the conscious desire and determination to work for its accomplishment.</p><p>The Party has dissociated itself from the Nationalist movement, since it regards nationalism as out-of-date, and is convinced that the pursuit of nationalist politics will culminate in the establishment of a Fascist regime in India. Their policy has often been misunderstood as a desire to see the continuation of the British regime, even though they fought for a democratic Indian government. What the Radical Democratic Party demanded was that political power should be transferred to the people and not to the politicians of the two upper-class political parties. As a corollary it asked that the Constituent Assembly should be elected on the basis of adult franchise and that the various political parties should prepare drafts for a constitution on which the people could vote. These suggestions by the Radical Democratic Party were distasteful to the nationalists, since they desired only to step into the shoes of the British, and thus secure control of the political and economic power in the country.</p><p>The radical Democratic Party pointed out that this would be mere change of master, and that the political and economic status quo would continue. Close observers of the Indian political situation now realise that events are taking the ugly turn predicted by the Radical Democratic Party.</p><p>Nationalism will not find a solution for pressing social and economic problems. It has not even been able to solve the communal problem. Inevitably Indian nationalism divided into rival Hindu and Muslim nationalism, thus disrupting the country's unity and establishing two communalist states. These, the Radical Democratic Party fears, may become armed camps of the two communities. Such problems can only be solved by a people's movement with a clear programme of social and economic progress inspired by the ideal of human liberty and freed from narrow nationalist, racial, religious or communal prejudices. This the Radical Democratic Party is endeavouring to do all over India.</p><p>While the Radical Democratic Party opposes Nationalism, it has also nothing in common with Communism, since it believes that Communism has lost its liberating force and purpose. Though the Party is inspired by Marxism, it is not prepared to accept it as an unalterable dogma. It is developing a philosophy of its own—the philosophy of Radical Democracy. The Party's founder and present leader—M. Roy—has during the last few years devoted a good deal of thought to defining the basic principles of that philosophy. Adopted at the last Party Conference in Bombay in December</p><p>1946 these principles show a way out of the spiritual crisis that has overtaken the world. They indicate that capitalist free enterprise and nationalism or totalitarian planning and communism are not the only alternatives before the world. They point the way to a world-wide humanism with its emphasis on individual freedom. This philosophy embraces the problems of all humanity. For this reason it is important that the World Socialist Movement take note of the valuable contribution that the Party and its leaders are making to the development of human thought.</p><p>The Radical Democratic Party is convinced that no effective democratic political movement can develop while people’s minds continue to be dominated by the age-old philosophy of fatalism, helplessness and utter dependence on providential will. To develop a rational and scientific outlook is therefore regarded as one of the Party’s basic tasks. The people’s spiritual emancipation and a rising level of education and culture are regarded as just as important as political and economic liberation. Thus the Party represents more than a political movement: it is a movement which aims to establish a new way of life, not merely in India but all over the world.</p><p>During the last six and a half years the Party has made considerable progress. It has built up an all-India organisation with a network of provincial, district and local committees claiming a membership of about 150,000. It is associated with the powerful trade union organisation, the Indian Federation of Labour, with a membership of more than 400,000 workers organised in about 300 unions. It takes a prominent part in the peasant and student movement, and has a large number of active, enthusiastic and earnest political workers. Its influence in the country is growing and will grow more rapidly with the disappearance of foreign rule and with experience of nationalism in power. Once the national problem is solved, social problems will play a more important part and more people will turn to the Radical Democratic Party as the only party which can deal with them effectively.</p><p>The Radical Democratic Party has been much maligned. The nationalists and more particularly their leftist supporters, the Communists, have campaigned against it, in India and abroad. A number of socialists have not remained unaffected by that propaganda. Since the Party is radically opposed to nationalism, and as it supported the anti-Fascist war, nationalists have every reason to attack it. Communists regard it as their foremost enemy, since the Party criticises some aspects of Soviet Russian policy and is rapidly becoming a rival rallying centre for young Indians disillusioned with nationalist parties and politics.</p><p>The Party’s support for the war has been misconstrued in many quarters. The sum of £1,000 per month which the Government of India granted to the Indian Federation of Labour over a period of three years for carrying on war propaganda, has been used as a basis for slanderous attacks against the Party. It is not possible here to reply to all accusations. The charge that the Party supported the war because of the “subsidy” is patently absurd. The grant to the Federation of Labour began in May 1942, while the Radicals supported the war from the early days of 1940. Since its foundation the party carried on war propaganda, and thus did not think it wrong for the Federation to accept some financial help from the Government for carrying on more vigorous propaganda. All the money received was spent on war propaganda and has been accounted' for. These rumours created many difficulties for the Party but nevertheless it has survived. It will overcome other difficulties, such as a press blackout, physical violence and intimidation, and grow into a powerful parry of the Indian people.</p></body></text></TEI>