<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
         <author>Editorial Staff</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
            <author>Editorial Staff</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><div><head>Elections in Europe </head><p>Since our last issue there have been elections in a number of European countries. Denmark and Switzerland have had parliamentary ejections: in Italy. Norway. France and Great Britain the issues were nominally local, but in fact the results were of wider importance. It is not possible to draw any general conclusions from such widely separated countries. It is much too sweeping to assert, as some commentators have done, that the results reveal a general swing to the Right all over Europe. Such a claim is not borne out by a close analysis of the voting figures, which show something quite different. To obtain a balanced view the particular circumstances in each country must be taken into account.</p><p>There is admittedly a certain resemblance between the position in Norway and the position in Great Britain. In both cases the elections were for local councils: in both cases the Labour Parties increased their total vote, but lost seats to the Right-wing parties: in both cases the Communists lost heavily. In Norway about 85 per cent, of the total electorate voted—a big increase compared with the 65 per cent, who voted in 1945—and this “mobilisation” of those who had previously not bothered to vote helped the Right-wing parties, as the number of seats allotted is based on proportional representation. The Labour Party recovered a great deal of the ground it lost to the Communists in 1945, and this is perhaps one of the most significant features of the result. The losses to the Right are comparatively small: there is certainly no great swing of public opinion away from the Labour Government.</p><p>In the elections for borough councils in England and Wales on 1st November, one third of the total seats were contested. Here again there was a greatly increased total vote with the greater part of the increase going to the Right. Labour lost about 650 seats, and the control of thirty-three councils, including the great cities of Birmingham and Manchester. In Scotland, where voting took place separately, the Labour Party had a loss of over 60 seats and lost control of nine councils. These results are a great disappointment, but nevertheless, the losses are only a fraction of the great gains which Labour had made in the local elections of 1945 and 1946. There is no doubt that discontent among the middle-classes about food shortages, the abolition of the basic petrol ration, and other symptoms of Britain's economic crisis caused many votes to be given blindly to anti-socialist candidates - often by people who had never before voted in local elections. The solid core of Labour support remained unshaken. The Communists, with 194 candidates, could not gain a single seat, and lost all the nine they were defending.</p><p>In Italy and France local elections were even more overshadowed by national issues than in Britain or Norway. On 12th October municipal elections in Rome gave the People’s Bloc 28 seats, and the Christian Democrats 27 seats, out of a total of 80. These elections were an attempt to break the deadlock which had existed in the municipality for the past year. It has just been reported that a Christian Democrat has been elected as Mayor by a majority of a single vote—the stalemate had left Rome without a Mayor.</p><p>The most spectacular local elections for many years took place in France on the 19th and 26th October. General de Gaulle's Ratliement du Peuple Français made an all-out effort and succeeded in capturing most of the Right-wing voters, especially those who had previously supported the MRP. But the Communists more or less maintained their position, and the Socialists improved theirs. This latter achievement was particularly important in view of the very rapid polarisation of French politics into two opposing authoritarian camps. After the elections, the Ramadier government gained a vote of confidence by the slender majority of 20, another triumph for the Socialists and the moderates supporting them.</p><p>The national elections in Denmark and Switzerland showed no change in the balance of forces between Left and Right. In Denmark the Social Democrats made gains—they won back nine seats from the Communists, who thus lost half their representation. But the Social Democrats, although the largest party with 57 seats, still do not have a clear majority. In Switzerland the Social-Democrats, formerly the strongest party, lost seven seats to the newly legalised pro-Communist “Labour Party,” and were therefore overtaken by the Radical-Democrats.</p><p>One general feature, except in France and Italy, is the eclipse of the Communists. In Britain they remain a negligible factor; in Norway and Denmark they lost heavily; in Switzerland, after five years of suppression, they polled less than four per cent, of the votes. In all these countries the Socialists are indisputably the leading working-class party.</p><p>What has happened generally, then, is that Left-Wing support has remained constant, or even improved. Right-Wing gains were achieved mainly by the votes of those who had not previously voted. If there can be said to be a swing to the Right it is not caused by any widespread desertion of Socialism by working-class voters. The fact is that anti-socialist forces, under eclipse immediately after the war, have now rallied. Demagogically exploiting Europe’s economic difficulties, they have made a successful appeal to the middle-classes. Middle-of-the-road parties have lost support, the more reactionary parties have gained. It is not without significance that General de Gaulle, the symbol of French resistance during the war now wins the votes of Vichyites and collaborators, nor that an openly Fascist party could take part in the Rome elections and poll over 24.000 votes. Socialists everywhere have been warned by these elections.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>