<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Finland since the armistice</title>
         <author>Vaino Leskinen</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Finland since the armistice</title>
            <author>Vaino Leskinen</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Finnish" party="Finland"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>On 4th August, 1944, the Finnish Diet, by a special law, confirmed the change of President already secretly agreed on. Risto Ryti resigned, and Field-Marshal Mannerheim, at that time Commander-in-Chief of the Army, took up the Presidential duties. On 8th August, Hackzell’s “Peace Government” was appointed, and overtures for peace immediately began. At the same time, measures were studied to maintain supplies without the aid of Germany. On 4th September, Finnish troops on the Eastern Front laid down their arms. On 7th September, the peace delegation, under the leadership of the Prime Minister, left for Moscow. On 14th September the Government learned the Armistice terms, and on the morning of 19th September, the Diet agreed to the terms of the armistice between the Soviet Union and Finland.</p><p>Neither Finland’s sufferings during the second World War nor the country’s position at the end of the war was worse than in some other countries. There are nations which have suffered more since 1939, and which greeted a peace even more melancholy than ours. It has even happened that the names of some small nations are no longer numbered among the independent peoples of the world. Nevertheless Finland, too, had its own bitter experiences.</p><p>The situation at the end of the war is best illustrated by the following facts. Under the armistice treaty territorial losses were about 13 per cent, of the country's area, and included the city of Viipuri and the northern side of Lake Ladoga, together with the nickel mines at Petsamo with their outlet to the area and the extensive Porkkala district to the west of Helsinki. This meant a reduction of 10 to 12 per cent, in agricultural and forest production, as well as in industrial production. In addition a quarter of the existing hydro-electric stations and a third of the fishing industry were lost.</p><p>Material losses were exceedingly heavy, but four other factors, which stretched the Finnish economy and the people’s endurance to the utmost, must be added. These factors were: the loss of manpower, the crippling of industry, war reparations, and the struggle for power in internal politics. The pre-war population of Finland was about four millions. Eighty-five thousand men in the prime of life fell in the war. That is 7.2 per cent, of the total manpower of the country. About 50,000 men were maimed for life. That is a further five per cent of the country’s manpower. More than 450,000 inhabitants of the ceded territories moved into the rest of Finland, and prompt measures had to be taken to arrange new living accommodation for them. For example, over 35,000 families had to be given land, a task which is still incomplete.</p><p>Industry was crippled. Raw materials were at an end. The majority of the machines were worn out, and there was a crying demand for spare parts. The possibilities of using electric power were greatly limited, and oil stocks were exhausted. During the war normal merchant shipping connections had naturally been severed. As these were renewed, it was evident that our own tonnage was unable to cope adequately with its task. Fully one-third of our tonnage had been lost in the war, and in accordance with the armistice treaty, the best of our remaining ships had to be delivered as war reparations to the Soviet Union.</p><p>According to the armistice terms Finland undertook to deliver reparations to the Soviet Union to the amount of 300 million dollars. This amount was to be paid in goods over a period of six years. On 17th December, 1944, however, the negotiations laid down in the nth article of the armistice treaty concerning the “details", that is, the prices of the different goods, took place. As a result of these negotiations, the $300,000,000 reparations bill is calculated in 1938 dollars, plus 15 per cent, for machinery and plant, and 10 per cent, for other finished products. In practice this agreement means that the amount of reparations is doubled. In the first reparations year the items delivered formed about 80 per cent, and in the second year about 65 per cent, of our total exports.</p><p>Naturally lowered efficiency and svaboda mood in industry caused by war weariness increased the economic difficulties already described, The lack of skilled labour was an especially troublesome factor, and the sudden expansion of the new metal industry made the situation still worse. In addition to this, the shortage and occasional absence of food supplies caused understandable restlessness among the workers. The chief danger, however, lay in the critical struggle in internal politics.</p><div><head>The elections</head><p>Even before the elections for the new Diet in March, 1945, the political aspect of the armistice period was interesting. After approximately fifteen years of illegality the Communist Party reappeared. From the very beginning it began determinedly to occupy key positions in the administration, especially in censorship and the police. Having silenced and humiliated the bourgeois parties by dissolving their auxiliary organisations in accordance with the armistice treaty, the Communists then directed their attack against the Social-Democratic Party. Following their well-known tactics, they founded the People's Democratic Union (SKDL) for election purposes, in order to attract sections of the Social-Democratic Party over to the Communist side. Simultaneously they tried to bring about a split in the Social-Democratic movement which was already in a critical situation. In this the Communists achieved considerable success.</p><p>The election results fulfilled their expectations - the Communists gained a splendid victory. In the 1920‘s they had had 27 representatives at their best, but now in the elections of 1945 the People's Democratic Union gained 49 seats, of which over 40 went to noted Communists. The rest of the seats went to members of the so-called "Six-Group," who had been previously dismissed from the Social-Democratic Party, and to a couple of Social-Democrats who had gone over to the SKDL at the eve of the elections, one of whom was the present Prime Minister, Mauno Pekkala. In the Communist group the most notable "new faces" were those of Hertta Kuussinen, the daughter of Otto Ville Kuusinen, the well known president of the Soviet Carelian Republic, and her husband, the present Minister for Internal Affairs, Yrjo Leino. Naturally, the Communists made progress mainly at the expense of the Social-Democrats. The latter lost their strong position, and the number of their representatives dropped from 85 in 1919 to exactly 50, i.e., one fourth of the members of the Diet. When two representatives subsequently withdrew from the party, its strength became 48 representatives. Unfavourable external conditions as well as the internal friction caused by these conditions, which took the form of bitter personal quarrels during the election campaign, resulted in the Social-Democrats' failure at the elections. During the campaign phase the party almost entirely lost its old leaders, among them Vaino Tanne, Vaino Salovaara, the Chairman of the Party, and Vaino Hakkila, the Speaker of the Diet, who had all been marked by Paasikivi's Government as unqualified for election for reasons of foreign policy. Rejuvenation of the party was consequently greater than ever before. </p><p>The Bourgeois front was mainly divided into two groups: the Agrarian Union and the Bourgeois opposition. The latter was formed by the so-called National Coalition Party, which has 29 seats in the Diet (25 in 1939) and the Progressive Party, which has 9 seats (6 in 1939). The Agrarian Union, which is a typical agrarian party, secured just as many seats in the election as the People's Democratic Union In addition to this there is in the Diet the election alliance of the Swedish minority, the Swedish People’s Party, which acts as a kind of pointer in the political scales and consists at the moment of 15 representatives (18 in 1939). The Swedish People's Party follows the economic policy of big land owners and capitalists, but is ready to compromise with any party on questions which further its specifically linguistic aims.</p></div><div><head>The new diet</head><p>The new Diet began work under new conditions. After the Diet had assembled, the Communists strove immediately to conclude a working agreement with the Agrarian Union and the Social-Democrats, and after a series of negotiations these parties agreed to sign a joint proclamation in which, in addition to general statements on economic and social policy, they laid special stress on the need for close and friendly relations with the Soviet Union and for conscientiously carrying out the provisions of the armistice treaty. The practical significance of the proclamation was more in the nature of propaganda, since each party interpreted its details according to its own point of view, except for the last-mentioned points, on which the nation as a whole agrees. Thus, the agreement of the "Big Three" did not result in the bloc so much desired by the Communists, in which they would have been the ruling party. On the other hand, it cannot be said that it has caused any harm. It is not unlikely that it created a better basis for parliamentary work in the confused conditions of the time, and thus "the battle of everyone against everyone" so characteristic of Finland’s present-day political life was postponed.</p><p>After the armistice the Government of the present President Paasikivi had two main duties: firstly, to strengthen Finland’s foreign policy in accordance with the demands of the new political situation and to create conditions for final peace: and secondly, to fulfil or to begin to fulfil the political and economical provisions of the armistice. In many respects the work of Paasikivi’s Govern in carrying out these chief aims can be justly criticised.  Above all the wav in which the Government interpreted the political articles and carried them out awakened very contradictory public feelings at times. On the other hand Paasikivi’s activity in stabilising foreign policy must be regarded as a success. Unfortunately the same cannot he said of the work of the second government during the armistice period, that of Pekkala. Its chief duties, in addition to those already mentioned, were to ensure democratic principles in political life and to stabilise Finland’s economy and currency. In these two aims the Government, under the leadership of this former Social-Democrat, has failed. Instead of re-establishing democratic methods and stopping the development of inflation, we have become involved in “the battle of everyone against everyone,” in which now prices, now wages, give rise to rapidly increasing inflation, while simultaneously methods foreign to democracy have crept into political and social life.</p></div><div><head>The rising cost of living</head><p>That such criticism of government policy is justified, is shown by the following figures. If the general cost of living index in the years 1938-39 is taken as 100, it had risen to 201 at the end of the war in 1944, to 282 in 1945, to 450 in 1946, and to 595 in September, 1947. (Pekkala’s Government took office at the beginning of 1946.) The wage index rose during the same period as follows: 1939—100, 1942—194, 1944—238, 1945—505, 1946—612, and in 1947 it will almost certainly be over 700. The corresponding index for women was 717 in 1946, and is probably over 800 at the present moment. Wholesale prices have risen as follows: 1939—120, 1944—305, 1945—438, 1946—685, and in July, 1947—799. The growth of the national debt gives a rough picture of the financial state of the Government.</p><p>In 1938 the national debt was 3,5 milliard Finnish marks, of which about a third were foreign debts. At the end of the war in 1944 it had grown to 67 milliards, of which foreign loans accounted for only' 4,8 milliards. At present the national debt probably amounts to a grand total of 115 milliard marks, 32 milliards of which consist of foreign loans.</p><p>Naturally all the responsibility for the economic situation cannot be laid on the Government. The serious political conflicts have been an effective reason for such an inflation. But above all it has been the barefaced way in which the Communists “trade” promises and favours with the producers of farm products which has kept prices and wages racing upwards and prevented all attempts at stabilisation. Endeavours to change the Government have, however, failed in the face of the Communists’ bitter opposition. At the moment it is quite evident that a firmer financial basis for internal policy is impossible until the new Diet elections which, it is hoped, will take place next summer, before they are due under the Constitution.</p></div><div><head>The present position of the Social-Democrats </head><p>After their defeat in the Diet elections the task which lay before the Social-Democrats was a difficult one. The disintegrated party had to be united again into a fighting political organisation, and a politically reliable body of men and women had to be schooled for this purpose. The confidence of the Labour Movement in democracy as a help in its struggle for liberty and security had to he restored. At the same time the violent attacks of both Communists and Bourgeois, which had for their object the elimination of the Social-Democratic Party as an independent and vital political force, had to be repelled. These tasks were immense and required time. But Finnish Social Democracy has once more stood the test. As a matter of fact, it has practically broken through already, and is marching on towards its former position as the leading party in the country.</p><p>The best proof of this is seen in the elections in the trade union movement which consists of over 300,000 members. In 1946 the Communists gained a majority in the trade union conference. The conference had to be cancelled, however, because of election forgeries which were verified and admitted, as well as the downright treacheries of which the Communists were guilty. But in counting the returns it was evident that the Communists would have gained a majority of 30 even without these frauds. New elections for the statutory trade union conference carried out last spring resulted in 170 representatives for the Social-Democrats and 128 representatives for the Communists. For example, the situation in the Metal Workers’ Trade Union, which is the strongest of all and represents the most disciplined trade unionists in this country, changed from when it was 21-18 in favour of the Communists, to 23-16 in favour of the Social-Democrats. At present elections for the general assembly of the same union are being carried out. The results obtained so far show that the victory of the Social-Democrats will be quite certain.</p><p>A similar change has taken place in the opinions of the working class in general. The major cause for this lies in the tactics of the Communists, which no longer obtain the support of intelligent working people now that political circumstances are becoming clearer. The too obvious tendency towards a police-state system with its direct suppression of opinion and its acts, of terror arouses opposition already, even in those most interested in "unity.". Contempt for freedom of thought and support for a system of secret police as “the eye guarding democracy" does harm to the Communists. But the Communists have done themselves the greatest harm by treachery in the Trade Unions and other movements in which the Social-Democrats are active. The situation on the eve of the new municipal and Diet elections is such that an election alliance between the two labour parties is impossible.</p></div><div><head>The future of democracy </head><p>Social-Democracy in Finland may be accused of being too outspoken. But it must be remembered that the Finnish trade union movement was created by Social-Democracy, which reformed the system of representation long before Communism appeared in the country. Because of Communist activity the united labour movement in Finland disintegrated in the early 1920’s. It disintegrated for exactly the same reasons as those which make co-operation with the Communist Movement in Finland impossible at present. In every country the prevailing conditions, as well as the cultural level of the working class and the level of political and social development, determine the method of achieving Socialism. It is apparent that in Finland the method generally follows the lines of the Scandinavian Labour Movement.</p><p>With respect to foreign affairs Social-Democracy already stated its own realistic policy in 1918. It calls for neighbourly relations with the Soviet Union and other countries on the basis of mutual confidence and sincere harmony. In internal politics freedom of thought must prevail above all, as this is essential for true democratic development. A police system does not belong to free Democracy. The standard of living of the workers and poorer people must be protected by carrying into effect a social plan for the entire economic life of the nation on the basis of which sufficient stimulus is given to all those powers which increase production and thus raise the standard of living.</p><p>Such are the lines along which the Social-Democratic Party will proceed in the coming municipal elections, which will take place on 4th and 5th December this year. In addition, the programme for the Diet elections which take place in the middle of next year at the latest will be based on these principles, for Finland’s internal democracy and liberty, as well as the safety of the working class, are dependent on Social-Democracy.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>