<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The United States and socialism</title>
         <author>Victor Larock</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The United States and socialism</title>
            <author>Victor Larock</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Belgian" party="Belgian Socialist Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Two years after the end of the First World War a Socialist Eugene V.Debs, gained almost two million votes in a United States presidential election. To-day there are still two groups which claim to be socialist: the Socialist Party (led by Norman Thomas) with its paper "The Call" and the Social Democratic Federation, with "The New Leader". Both are, to all intents and purposes, without influence.</p><p>A number of American intellectuals—publicists, professors, and writers—call themselves socialists. Their books are little known. If they have talent, their articles are more widely read, but most of the journals and reviews which publish them—with complete liberalism —do everything to reduce the reader's receptivity to zero.</p><p>Some of the big unions have first-class leaders such as Carey, Antonini, Reuther, and Dubinsky—most of them born in Europe— who are true socialists, and who have considerable influence. But their followers prefer them not to use this influence in the political field.</p><p>I was told that there were one or two places with socialist mayors: Norwalk in Connecticut, Milwaukee in Wisconsin... “And that’s all”.</p><p>One reason for this is that, to nine hundred and ninety-nine Americans out of a thousand, socialism as a doctrine is something visionary and dangerous—a system of fixed ideas. Politics in the United States has no connexion with this or that philosophy. The less politics is concerned with abstractions the better everyone likes it.</p><p>There are, of course, two parties. What are their reasons for existence? Is there a conflict of principles, ideals, or aims? For most of their members such a question never arises. They are Republicans or Democrats by tradition, or by loyalty to this or that leader. They belong to a big “team.” The parties’ periodic contests have nothing to do with general principles.</p><p>Again, socialism is of European origin, and that is no recommendation. Americans are curious about Europe. They are astonished at its changes and complications. To them Europe is an elderly relative who deserves consideration and respect, even though she is slightly mad. But to pay any attention to Europe's political theories—that is quite another matter. The United States are self-made—at least they like to think so. They have chosen their own “way of life", and mean to stick to it. Europe with its ideologies, they say, belongs to the past.</p><p>Socialism calls for a more rational organisation of production, for equal distribution of goods according to work. You might as well tell Americans it is a doctrine for the poor—another cause suspicion. The country can produce more goods than it can consume. In times of prosperity what are called minimum living standards elsewhere are left far behind. These times do not always last but all the same they are there long enough to convince the people that economic security and social justice can happen of their own accord. People pay less attention to social injustices than to the continual changes in social conditions. The waste caused by capitalism means little to them—they get their share out of it. With higher wages and standard of living than in any country in the world—at least for the present—they have no taste for revolution. Above a certain level of material prosperity, however precarious it may be, “exploitation of man by man” loses its sting. It is hard for the navvy, the clerk or the mechanic, going to work in their own car, to become bitter about the condition of the proletariat.</p><div><head>Prosperity versus Class-Consciousness </head><p>Socialism, in fact, calls for class-consciousness. In the United States the vast majority of workers arc nowhere near to this. They have a sense of professional solidarity so highly developed that it is not infrequent for two unions, or two contesting groups within the same union, to strike to assert their rights against each other.</p><p>Nevertheless, many of the workers still have the illusion that they can deal with the boss as man to man: so strong is the idea that one person is as good as another.</p><p>The fact is that class differences are less clear-cut, and in any case less noticeable in America than in Europe. A leader of the CIO said to me, “When I am on a joint factory committee, I cannot at once pick out workers from the employers representatives.” Nothing—neither dress nor manners nor accent—enables one to recognise them.</p><p>Finally and above all, if there is one idea firmly fixed in an American's mind, from top to bottom of the social scale, it is the value of the individual with its many chances and possibilities. Every day newspapers tell the most spectacular “success stories”, which confirm this universal optimism. Such a state of mind does not fit in very well with class-consciousness.</p><p>At first sight everything combines to give the impression that in America socialism has few chances of developing or even of being understood. It is certainly true that the word "socialist" has neither prestige nor attraction. The New York Communists know this, and instead of proclaiming themselves the only true socialists, as our Communists do, they modestly give themselves the label of "liberal" and quote Thomas Jefferson. </p><p>Superficially then, in spite of Marx's predictions, in spite of the existence of a powerfully concentrated capitalist system and a great industrial working class, the USA seem closed to socialism.</p></div><div><head>Lessons from America </head><p>Yet if socialism is something more than a mere dry-as-dust theory of political economy, worked out by doctrinaires for a community of robots. If its final aim really is a peaceful equalitarian society which will give everyone - in the words of our Party programme— "the maximum of liberty and well-being"-if this is so, then the Americans, however inhospitable they may be to some of our ideas, can teach us a few lessons.</p><p>The American people hate war, and those who are at present trying to split the country by denouncing “war-mongers” know what they are doing. The Americans hate war and everything that leads to it—national, racial and religious intolerance, nationalism and militarism of every kind. No nation demobilised its forces faster than the U.S.A. in 1945. It was done with a magnificent recklessness, which can only be explained by their complete faith in peace. Highly-trained cadres of specialists were broken up, training-centres closed, tanks and aircraft thrown on the scrap-heap, so that it is no secret to anyone that the U.S. Army to-day has only three combat divisions available.</p><p>And what other great power possessing the atom bomb would have agreed to reveal its secrets of manufacture and destroy its stockpiles, on condition that a rigid international inspection system is instituted in every country? The American government has agreed with this—American public opinion demands it.</p><p>The American people is passionately attached to democracy and individual liberty. It would not tolerate state control of information or censorship or political police. There is no country in the world in which the government is more closely in touch with public opinion—to a point where it may have become a weakness.</p><p>It is true that the people accept the capitalist system, at least in principle. But nothing could be more mistaken than to imagine that the whole of America is ruled, politically and economically, by Wall Street “plutocrats” (as the Nazis called them) or "Fascist bankers” (as the Communists now call them).</p><p>In spite of Wall Street, Roosevelt passed social security legislation. By the institution of the National Labour Relations Board he protected trade union rights. In spite of Wall Street and the public utility trusts he carried out the gigantic project of the Tennessee Valley Authority, which would be the pride of any socialist government.</p><p>Roosevelt is dead, but his work lives on. The stimulus he gave to the trade union movement was decisive. More and more the workers’ organisations are taking part in formulating vast plans for the automobile industry, the metal industry (Nathan Plan), and others. Of course, capitalist reaction has already made its presence felt. The Taft-Hartley Act has been passed: but it is doubtful whether it will ever be fully enforced.</p><p>What is certain is that this law had the effect of exciting for the first time a series of defensive reactions among American workers which were not merely industrial but political. For the first time the two big rival trade union organisations, the AFL and the CIO, joined forces in the State of New York and agreed on a common programme. Their manifesto bears the names of many social-democratic trade unionists, and begins: “We, the representatives of 500,000 workers affiliated to the AFL and CIO, have to-day decided to unite in the struggle against the reactionary forces which arc at present in control of Congress.” This is a language to which American trade union leaders have not accustomed their members.</p></div><div><head>Progressive trends </head><p>For the rest, it is unlikely that a third party will be formed before the coming presidential election, for both strategical and tactical reasons. Even Henry Wallace has realised this. It is inside the two traditional parties that a powerful “progressive” force is at present operating by means of “pressure groups.”</p><p>In what sense is ‘progressive” the same as “socialist?” In the sense that socialism means the will to extend political democracy into economic and social democracy. This is with the reservation, of course, that capitalism is not frontally attacked—it is not to be mentioned, as I have tried to show, just as the very word “socialism” is as it were under a ban.</p><p>It is under a ban, at least in internal politics. The same prejudice for a long time governed American opinion about international affairs, but already a change is noticeable. I need only quote the following evidence, taken from the “New York Post” which wrote on 9th October, 1947:</p><p> “The true allies of democracy in Europe are the Socialist Parties. They alone give us any hope for the preservation of personal liberty. We have systematically despised and under-estimated them, just because we do not want socialism here at home. We have never taken the trouble to understand the historical development of these parties. They alone are capable of forming strong democratic states and if they perish, the hope of democracy will perish with them. By our policy we are splitting every country into two extremist camps, which aim at a tyranny of either Left or Right".</p><p>Socialist parties in Europe and Great Britain have so far managed very well without American encouragement, but what is chiefly interesting in this statement by an important New York daily is not so much the favourable opinion as the change it reveals. This change of opinion is spreading, and is a sign of an evolution which internal economic conditions or international developments might well accelerate.</p></div><div><head>Public opinion and the future </head><p>The most striking aspect of the United States to the outsider is not only the decisive influence -which public opinion has on the conduct of affairs, but also the speed with which public opinion can change. If a depression were to threaten—which is much less probable than the Soviets believe, but is nevertheless not impossible —then a vast social movement might well arise to alter the political alignment which is now controlled by conservative Republicans and Democrats from the "Solid South” who are indistinguishable from them.</p><p>Public opinion in America, uninformed and prejudiced, recalls that which predominated in Great Britain at the end of the First World War. There too the word “socialism” had a sinister sound, even to workers’ ears. There too most trade union leaders did not believe in the class-struggle, opposed organised anti-capitalist activity and radical reforms, and would not take a definite political stand. It took twenty-five years and a prolonged economic crisis to awaken British workers to a consciousness of their strength and their rights. In America history moves faster.</p><p>In the meantime we must not blind ourselves to the obstacles in the path. They are the result not only of a capitalist system organised to the highest degree, but also of habits of life and thought conditioned by prosperity.</p><p>One thing is certain: even if the United States ever arrives at socialism, or at an economic and social structure similar to socialism, they will never abandon individual liberties without which democracy cannot exist. What has happened in Russia shows how dangerous it is for a country to pass from servitude to the dictatorship of the proletariat, without learning the lesson of freedom.</p><p>The American learned this lesson long since. That is one of the reasons for their prosperity and their greatness. It is unlikely that they will surrender their liberty for a dictatorship of either Right or Left.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>