<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Poland’s Three-year plan</title>
         <author>Anonymous(Polish)</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Poland’s Three-year plan</title>
            <author>Anonymous(Polish)</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Polish" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Before the war Poland was one of the poorest countries in Europe. If we take the figure of national income (based on the value of agricultural and industrial products) per head of the population as an indication of the average standard of living, then only the Balkan countries and Portugal of all the European countries were below Poland in the scale; Rumania was on about the same level, while the standard of living in Spain, Hungary and Italy was between 20 and 30 per cent, higher.</p><p>There were many reasons for the country’s poverty. Although it would be impossible to analyse them all in this article, one in particular must be emphasised. During the period of servitude, when national existence itself was suppressed, Poland was first exploited by aggressors who used colonial methods, then completely ruined by the war of 1914-1918. Between the wars the country raised itself by its own efforts, but for a number of reasons —the unsolved agrarian problems, the survival of pre-capitalist economic conditions, the lack of financial aid from abroad—it was not until 1938 that national income and standard of living regained the level of 1913—itself appallingly low, by any standards. These hard-won achievements were destroyed by the German occupation. Material destruction was equivalent in value to five and a half years’ national income; more than six million lives were lost—a quarter of the entire population. Material losses consisted chiefly of industrial plant and machinery; most of the lives lost were those of the youngest and the fittest.</p><p>To all these difficulties which faced Poland after the war must be added the problem of repatriation and resettlement. In 1945 Poland, already heavily engaged by the task of reorganisation, had the additional task of receiving and resettling those Poles whom the war had dispersed all over the world. It was impossible for many of them to return to their original homes. In addition, large stretches of land had become deserts sown with mines; their inhabitants, too, had to be resettled. Eight millions, or one-third of the total population, were affected by the resettlement programme. In other words, out of every three Poles, two had to bear the cost of resettling the third.</p><p>It is not surprising that the national income at the beginning of 1945 was less than a quarter of that of 1938, and only rose to half of the 1938 figure at the end of 1946. Nevertheless, this state of affairs eased the task of working out the fundamental aims of Poland's economic policy. Clearly the main effort had to be directed towards raising the national income per head of the population, which meant raising the level of industrial and agricultural production. In addition, it was essential that there should be a proportional rise in the level of expenditure on consumer goods. This presents two separate problems. If an increased national income were gained, the surplus could be directed into capital investment, while allowing the expenditure on consumer goods to remain stable: alternatively the surplus national could be spent on consumer goods, while making no capital investments for an indefinite period. The latter course is obviously impossible in a country ruined by war. This is the central dilemma in a planned socialist economy. It is difficult to sacrifice the present generation for the good of generations to come, to impose a heroic destiny on the people of to-day in the name of some future community. Needless to say, the choice of one of these two policies entails decisive political consequences; in other words, a policy conditions the methods by which it is administered. In the case of ruined Poland there was no difficulty in choosing the right policy. It was impossible to ask the Polish people to submit to the heroic alternative of increased capital investment at the expense of consumer goods. In view of the standard of living at the beginning of 1945, such a policy would probably have made doubtful the continued survival of the Polish people and would certainly have brought an enormous increase in the number of cases of tuberculosis, which already stood at a million and a half—a figure previously unknown, constituting six per cent, of the total population.</p><div><head>Targets of the plan </head><p>Poland’s three-year reconstruction plan lays down the broad outlines of economic policy for the years 1947 to 1949. Its aim is stated in the preface to the plan:</p><p> “The main purpose of the national effort in the period 1947-9 is to raise the standard of living of the working classes above the prewar level.”</p><p>If the index of national income per head in 1946 is taken as 100, it will be: —</p><p>If the index of consumption per head in 1946 is taken as 100, it will be:	</p><p>Capital investment, which was 15 per cent, of the total national income before 1939, will fluctuate between 16 and 20 per cent during the plan.		</p><p>What do these figures mean compared with the West? National income per head of the population, calculated in U.S. dollars at 1938 value, will reach 167 dollars per annum towards the end of the three-year period, while the average expenditure on consumer good will be about 133 dollars per annum. It is obvious that even at this level, Polish standards are several times lower than those in the West. In 1929 the average national income per head in France, Germany and Britain was over twice the planned Polish figure for 1949, while the 1929 figure for the U.S.A. was over four times greater.</p><p>What do these figures mean in terms of food? The plan provides that the average person will be consuming slightly more in 1949 than he did in 1938, in terms of calorific value. By 1949 agricultural production is intended to be roughly at the 1938 level, though more wheat and sugar beet is to be grown and less rye and potatoes. The aim is to produce a surplus of these four crops for export after satisfying the needs of the Polish people.</p><p>A similar unspectacular goal is set in another field of reconstruc?tion: housing. Except in the large cities, no considerable improvement in housing conditions can be expected. Warsaw, the ruined capital, is to have more than half of the total number of new dwellings planned. Elsewhere priority is being given to the repair and construction of farm buildings, schools and factories. Such an attitude towards housing is a result of the plan’s practical basis. A more extended housing programme would have demanded increased capital expenditure, which would have involved lowering the production of consumer goods.</p></div><div><head>Chances of success </head><p>How can such a vast plan be realised under the present conditions in Poland? There are three main factors which contribute to its success.</p><p>Firstly, there is the liquidation of the remnants of feudalism. After the war an extensive programme of land reform was carried out. Large estates were broken up, existing smallholdings enlarged, and new farms created. This transition from a primitive economy of large feudal estates to an economy of peasant proprietors raised the standard of living not merely of the peasants, but of the people as a whole.</p><p>Secondly, nationalisation of the most important branches of industry allows the economic effort to be concentrated on the most urgent social needs. All large industries are now under public ownership, but co-operative enterprise is encouraged, and individual ownership of certain small industries, especially handicrafts, which employ only a few workers, per factory, still continues. In the three-year plan, great emphasis is laid on increased production in the basic industries of coal, iron and steel, electric power, transport, and chemicals for fertilisers. Exports of coal will increase and contribute greatly to the success of the plan.</p></div><div><head>The recovered territories </head><p>Lastly, there is the change in the geographical basis of Poland. Thanks to the incorporation of territory east of the Oder, Poland's industrial potential will have risen from 100 in 1938 to 150 in 1949. Moreover the planned reconstruction of war-damaged industry is not as costly as the construction of entirely new plant, so that in spite of the comparatively low level of capital investment we can hope to achieve the plan’s aims. These factors show the question show the question of the Recovered Territories in a new light. The destruction of the Polish nation’s biological and economic basis of existence, scientifically planned by the Nazi occupation, created a situation which would have automatically continued and intensified the process of national extinction. Our standard of living had been reduced by the Germans to a quarter of the low pre-war level, and only rapid amelioration of living conditions could prevent the process.</p><p>Such a weak foundation did not allow real reconstruction or large capital investment. Better living conditions for the people had to come first. Improvement in conditions by Polish standards, though still miserably low on the international scale, was only possible by the injection of ready-made capital equipment. The Recovered Territories east of the Oder, with their industrial equipment, were just such an injection. For Germany this area was mainly one of agricultural production; for Poland it is an industrial area which will replace the ruined industries of Central Poland. Thus, as a result of geopolitical changes, the character of this area has also been altered.</p><p>The Polish Three-Year Plan is, therefore, a plan for reconstruction. Its achievement is not an end in itself, but merely the foundation for the greater plan, which from 1950 onwards will aim at completely transforming Poland’s economic structure.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>