<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Socialism in Latin-America</title>
         <author>Robert J.Alexander</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Socialism in Latin-America</title>
            <author>Robert J.Alexander</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="American" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The Latin-American Socialists are out of touch with their European comrades. This is not due to any particular divergence on doctrinary matters, because there are all shades of socialist doctrine represented among the American Socialist parties. Rather, this growing isolation is due to the fact that the European Socialists continue to pay absolutely no attention to the mere existence let alone the importance of the Latin-American Socialist Parties.</p><p>It is high time that the European Socialists began to take note of the American Socialist Movements. There are to-day Socialist parties or groups in Argentina, Uruguay, Brazil, Chile, Peru, Ecuador, Colombia, Panama and Cuba, and there are other groups which arc very closely allied with the socialist point of view in Peru, Cuba, Paraguay and Venezuela. There are Socialist deputies in the Parliaments of Uruguay, Ecuador, Chile, Colombia and Panama; in Peru and Venezuela socialistic groups have a parliamentary majority. The labour movement of Ecuador is controlled by the Socialist Party of that country, while socialistic parties control the labour movements of Peru and Venezuela, and the Socialists have strong minorities in the labour movements of most of the other countries.</p><p>The Socialist Party of Argentina is the oldest of the American Socialist groups, and probably the best known to Europeans. It was organised in 1896 by the great leader, Juan B. Justo, who was the first to translate Marx’s Capital into Spanish. He led the party until his death in 1928. The Socialist Party of Argentina belonged to the Second International from the foundation of the party, and belonged to the Labour and Socialist International between the two wars. It first elected a Member of Parliament, the famous Alfredo Palacios, in 1904, and from then on had representation in the Chamber of Deputies until the rise of the Peronista Movement. Its strength in the Labour Movement has varied from time to time, but during the early years of the Confederacion General del Trabajo, from 1930 until 1943, that central trade union organisation was controlled by the Socialists. They lost this position of dominance with the rise of General Peron after 1943. However the Socialists still represent an exceedingly important force in Argentina, have been the chief fighters for the maintenance of the democratic form of government in that country, and hope to make a come-back in Parliament in the elections of 1948. The Argentina Socialist Party is certainly worthy of recognition by the sister parties throughout the world, because of the quality of its leadership, its honourable history, and its position of prestige, if not actual political strength at this time, in the political life of its country. The Socialists of Europe should be proud of their Argentine Comrades.</p><p>The Uruguayan Socialist Party originally dated from 1910 though in 1922 it voted to enter the Comintern, and a minority group withdrew to form the present Partido Socialista. It is still led by its principal founder, Dr Emilio Frugoni, who has long been recognised as one of the most important figures in the political life of his country. The Uruguayan Socialist Party is noted for its exceedingly brilliant leadership, having within its ranks some of the most outstanding intellectuals in the country, and certainly the most outstanding intellectuals in politics. The Uruguayan Socialists control the second largest group of trade unions and they are working exceedingly hard to win over the majority of the workers of their country. The Party has two deputies in Parliament out of one hundred, and seems likely to attain an increasingly important place in the political life of its nation. The Argentine and Uruguayan Socialist Parties, incidentally are the only Latin-American organisations which have taken, or even been invited to take part in the post-war International Socialist Conferences.</p><div><head>Progress in Chile </head><p>In Chile there exists one of the most combative of all the American Socialist Parties. The group is comparatively new, having been founded in 1933. There were previous socialist groups. As far back as 1887 was founded the Partido Democratico, which had a programme which was mildly socialist, and was the principal spokesman for the artisan labour movement. It had correspondence with the Second International before World War One. In 1912 the leader of the left wing of the Partido Democratico, Luis Emilio Recabarren, broke away to launch the Partido Socialista Obrero, which actually joined the Second International just before the outbreak of the First World War. However, this group went over to the Communist International in 1922, and for more than a decade there was no socialist organisation in Chile.</p><p>After the fall of the Carlos Ibanez Dictatorship in 1931 a number of small Socialist groups were launched, which in 1933 were amalgamated to form the Partido Socialista de Chile. This party had an exceedingly rapid growth and by 1938 polled eighty thousand votes, and was the second largest party in the country. However with the entry of the party into the Popular Front Government President Pedro Aguirre Cerda, it began to decline. It was not yet mature enough to take office, and the disintegration that followed resulted in a series of splits and a decline which did not end until 1946. In October 1946 the party was reorganised, with a new and vigorous leadership coming to power within the party. The internal divisions have apparently been more or less forgotten, and the party made a remarkable recovery in the municipal elections of April, 1947 when it received nearly fifty thousand votes, in comparison with the twelve thousand which it had in the 1946 Presidential elections. The Socialist Party of Chile seems to be on the road to recovery to be one of the two or three principal parties in the nation.</p></div><div><head>Ecuador and Panama </head><p>The Socialist Party of Ecuador has been growing rapidly recently. In recent elections for Parliament it returned almost one-third of the members of the lower house. About a year ago, they wrested the control of the Confederation de Trabajadores del Ecuador the principal National Labour Federation, from the Communists, who had dominated it since its foundation in 1944. This party had been for long accused of being too sympathetic to the Communists, but recently there has been a widening of the gulf between the two groups due to the high-handed tactics and foreign loyalties of the Communists.</p><p>The Ecuadorian Socialist Party also dates from the early 1910s having been organised in 1933 after an earlier Partido Socialista, founded in 1928, voted to go over completely to the Communist International.</p><p>Dating from the same era is the Partido Socialista of Panama, which has considerable influence in the local labour movement, the Secretary-General of the Labour Federation being a Socialist.</p><p>It has two deputies in Parliament, and they had much to do with pushing through measures which made the new Panamanian Constitution one of the most advanced in the New World. One of the principal leaders of the Panamanian Socialist Party, Dr Porras, is now his country’s ambassador to Great Britain.</p><p>The Peruvian Socialist Party, too, is a product of the early thirties. It is a comparatively small group, confined to the oilfield areas in the North, and to a considerable degree is a personal party of its leader. Dr Luciano Castillo. The Aprista Party, which we will discuss in a moment, is a more significant movement than the Partido Socialista in Peru.</p><p>In Colombia there have been several attempts to launch a Socialist Party. The first of these was early in the 1920's, but came to little. In the late 1920's a Partido Socialists Revolucionario was formed, but this went over to the Comintern a few years later. In the early 1940's there existed the Liga de Accion Politica, which assembled a group of leading intellectuals and Labour leaders under a Socialist programme. However, Communist infiltration broke up this group. There were finally founded in January, 1947, the Partido Socialista de Colombia, whose leader is Dr Antonio Garcia, a professor in the Economics Institute of the National University. He has around him a number of important labour leaders, but as yet the party has little mass base.</p><p>In Brazil, perhaps the new Socialist Party, also organised in early 1947, has more opportunities than in many other countries. Heretofore the labour movement of that country has been largely controlled by the Communists and the followers of the ex-Dictator Getullio Vargas, but there were elements in both the Communist and Vargas camps who would have welcomed the formation of a real Socialist Party. It is these elements whom the new Socialist Party, under the leadership of a young journalist, Mario Pedrosa, is hoping to attract. The party issues a very lively weekly newspaper, Vanguard Socialista.</p><p>In Cuba, there has never been a strongly organised Socialist Party, though since the early years of this century there have been active Socialist groups. The principal figure among the Socialists now is Juan Arevalo, editor of the widely-circulated journal Accion Socialista, who was an old-time leader of the Maritime and Railroad Workers’ Unions. At the moment, due to persecution at the hands of the Communists, he is outside the trade union movement, but he still keeps publishing his journal, and is one of the more important figures behind the scenes in the Cuban labour movement. He is the leader of the Federacion Socialista de Cuba, which was launched as such in 1943. It is a loosely federated organisation of Socialist groups and individuals throughout the island. An attempt —in which the Federacion Socialista participated—to launch a Partido Laborista, patterned after the British Labour Party, in 1945, came to an unfruitful ending.</p></div><div><head>The Aprista parties </head><p>Closely allied with the strictly Socialist Parties are what we will call the Aprista Parties. These are organisations - including the Partido del Pueblo or Partido Aprista of Peru, the Accion Democratica of Venezuela, the Partido Febrerista  of Paraguay, the Partido Revolucionario (Autentico) of Cuba, and the party which is led by President Jose Arevalo of Guatemala-which are more or less socialist. The Apristas started out as Marxists, and though they have wandered somewhat afield, the labour wing of the party at least, considers the Partido del Pueblo as the Socialist Party of Peru. This writer several times heard members of the Accion Democratica of Venezuela refer to themselves as "the Socialists." The Febreristas also regard themselves as in the general socialist political current. One of the Autentico labour leaders labelled his group as Socialist Nationalists.</p><p>The Aprista parties generally have tried to adapt socialist thinking specifically to American soil and they do not tend to be Marxists in any orthodox sense. They believe in the ultimate socialist organisation of society, but believe that the first thing necessary is to industrialise and modernise their respective countries. As Haya de la Torre, the leader of the Peruvian Apristas said to this writer, “In these countries it is not so much the question of dividing the wealth as it is of creating it,” and that is the job which these parties stress. These Aprista parties are popular parties, are very influential if not the controlling influence in the labour movements of their respective countries, and co-operate quite closely with the more important Socialist Parties.</p><p>There exists a loose federation of these principal socialist groups and the Aprista parties. In March, 1946. There was held the Second Congress of Socialist and Popular Parties in Santiago de Chile, with representation from the Argentine, Uruguayan, Chilean, Ecuadorian, Panamanian, and Colombian Socialist parties, and from the Aprista, Accion Democratica and Febrerista parties. In May, 1947, a further conference of trade union leaders of these parties was held in Montevideo. In Santiago a loose Federation of Socialist and Popular Parties was established, to which the Socialist Party of the United States and the Canadian Co-operative Commonwealth Federation later affiliated. However, for all practical purposes, this Federation has existed only on paper.</p><p>There is great need for contact among the Socialist Parties of America, not only with one another, but with the Socialist Parties of other parts of the world. Most of the American Socialist Parties are very poor, and are not able to do much in the international field. It is for this reason, as well as because of the greater experience of the European parties that the Socialists of Latin-America look to their European big brothers. The Socialist Parties of Latin-America need the aid of the European Socialist Parties, but they feel that the Europeans also need the participation of extra-European elements in Socialist international gatherings, and specifically they need the participation of the Latin-American Socialists, who now constitute one of the strongest groups of socialist movements anywhere in the world, and with perhaps more future than many of those in the Old World.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>