<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Imperialism – New Style</title>
         <author>J.D.Krivine</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Imperialism – New Style</title>
            <author>J.D.Krivine</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="British Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Is the British Labour Government pursuing a Socialist policy in the colonies? To most people outside Britain this would seem a perplexing question, based on mistaken assumptions. They claim that, even if an industry in one of the colonies is nationalised, it means that the power of exploitation is merely concentrated in the hands of an irresponsible alien government. "Socialism" or "Liberalism" or Conservatism,” they would say, have nothing to do with colonial politics. The only expression with any meaning is the old-established, well-tried label of “Imperialism” - "British Imperialism”.</p><p>This view implies that nothing has changed in the British colonies since the time of Joseph Chamberlain under Queen Victoria, or, going even further back, since the days of the “nabobs” in India and the slave-owning sugar-planters in the West Indies. The word “Imperialism” suggests toiling blacks, working long hours for miserable wages, with no laws to regulate either, owning nothing and producing wealth, all of which is drained off by the Mother Country in the form of profits.</p><p>Both these assumptions are mistaken. Firstly, political progress in England has had a corresponding influence in the colonies. Not only would the old sugar planters not recognise their industry to-day - they had already been ruined by changes operating within the industry over a century ago. Secondly, there is no longer unstrained exploitation of labour. Strikes are legal in the British Colonial Empire; and behind the strikes are Trade Unions formed on the British model, generally—particularly in the more backward territories such as the African dependencies — introduced and framed by the British administration itself.</p><p>The fact is that the general impression of “British Imperialism,” held not only overseas but even in Britain, is remarkably mistaken. Few people are interested in learning what actually goes on in dependent territories. They are too remote, too peaceful and do not play melodramatic roles on the stage of international relations. In default of new facts, people are content to prolong old theories.</p><p>Let us, therefore, before examining the present, do justice to the past.</p><p>The four British dependencies in West Africa, which contain nearly half the population of the colonial empire, do not permit foreign-owned plantations - that is plantations owned by white men or non Africans. Cocoa, the chief export of the Gold Coast, and palm oil, the chief export of Nigeria are grown on native peasant smallholdings, which cannot be sold to, since cannot be bought by Englishmen or English firms. Again, the British dependencies' which have already gained independence, such as India and Burma, and those which are approaching it, such as Ceylon, were already largely self-governing before the war. And in nearly all the British colonies the native populations have some part in their own government: not much yet in Tanganyika, Northern Rhodesia; considerably more in Malaya, the Cold Coast, Nigeria; a great deal in Jamaica, Trinidad, Malta. Each colony again has its own budget. No tribute is paid to Britain. Incoming revenue in a colony is all available for outgoing expenditure by and for that colony. If its government runs an industry (such as Nigerian coal), not a penny of the profits goes to Britain or the British Government.</p><p>These things—development of self-government, preservation of native tenure, growth of labour legislation, expansion of social services—were carried out under Conservative as well as Socialist governments. The Colonial Development and Welfare Acts, for example, granting altogether some £142 millions as a free gift from Britain to the Colonies, were passed by Mr Churchill’s Coalition government; and so was the provision that allotments under the Acts could only be made where the colonies concerned possessed adequate Trade Union legislation. The Ten-Year Plans based on these grants, which call for a total expenditure of about £300 millions are plans for the extension not only of social services such as education and health, and public works such as water supplies and communications, but also for the development of agriculture and industry, all worked and controlled by the colonial government themselves. These plans too were introduced under the Coalition.</p><div><head>From tribal society to socialism </head><p>The point is that it is not only socialist legislation, even by socialist standards, that the colonies need. The African territories are all based on an antique tribal society that is pre-feudal. According to the strict Marxist dogma, the next step for the primitive village society of South-East Nigeria should be to emulate the Moslem Emirates of Northern Nigeria. Instead, British administration is being remarkably progressive, and is skipping several centuries, by individualising land tenure—just as is happening in Eastern Europe at this very moment. The Conservatives and the Socialists are in effective agreement over a whole field of policy that can best be described as “progressive.”</p><p>There is even agreement on a measure of purely socialist control. A most remarkable piece of legislation initiated under the Coalition government is the state marketing-scheme for West African cocoa. Throughout the war all produce for export was bought up by the Government's  West African Produce Control Board. In the field of cocoa alone, a total profit of some £25 millions has been accumulated and made over to the governments of the Gold Coast and Nigeria. Now a Gold Coast Cocoa Marketing Board and a Nigeria Cocoa Marketing Board have been permanently established, so that from the sowing of the British West-African cocoa crop (constituting nearly two-thirds of world supplies) to its sale on the world market not one penny of actual profit goes into the pocket of an Englishman. Co-operatives, too, date from pre-war days, a method capitalising production and marketing by the joint efforts of small producers, of which Lord Milverton said when Governor of Nigeria, “True co-operation amounts to economic democracy.”</p></div><div><head>Progress under the Labour government </head><p>But now we must come to the work of the Labour Government. And here in a little over two years—let it be recorded to their credit—they have already set new standards both in pace and scale of activity. Not only has the whole tempo of development, political as well as economic, been accelerated, but massive schemes of socialist enterprise have been, and are being, launched, which may herald a new era for the colonies. The greatest of these undertakings, the East African Groundnuts Scheme, is already under way, and may be said to constitute the most substantial effort yet made in colonial development. The cost to Britain will be £26 millions; those employed will number 32,000, in addition to 25,000 for clearing three million acres of tsetse-infected bush; total production will be 600,000 tons by 1951. Two particular points deserve notice. The first is that a complete little society will be created, consisting of 107 new villages each with 250 houses, a school, a dispensary and all the amenities of village life for the 300 workers with their families in each village. The second is that as returns begin to pay off outlay, the scheme will be handed over to the Governments of Tanganyika, Kenya and Northern Rhodesia respectively, and ultimately will be passed on, it is hoped, to the workers themselves organised into “clan-farms".</p><p>Similarly in West Africa a quarter of a million acres of ex- enemy plantations have been bought by the Government or Nigeria and made over to the people. A Cameroons Agriculture Development Corporation has been formed to work these lands, with a capital of £1.750,000; and as the scheme develops it is intended that African representatives will take their place on the Cooperation until they are able to assume control of the whole enterprise themselves. In the field of industry hydro-electric schemes are being launched on the Nile by the Government of Uganda, on the Volta by the Gold Coast Government, and on the Zambesi under the auspices of the Central African Council - a consultative body representing the colonies of Northern Rhodesia, Nyasaland, and the self-governing body of Southern Rhodesia.  The Nigeria scheme comes under the Ten-Year Plan. But other and wider schemes are pending. A Colonial office circular has expressed the desire of the Secretary of State that colonial governments should in any future sale of public lands reserve mineral rights to the Crown; and that they should consider re-acquiring mineral rights already alienated; and that they should be prepared where necessary to undertake mining operations on their own behalf. The colonies have also been encouraged to see what assistance they could give to industrial development by loans, guarantees and adjustments of taxation and by government participation in share capital. Colonial governments are also advised to consider the possible use of public development corporations and generally, again to be prepared directly to operate industries and services. A Colonial Development Corporation has been established in London, with a capital of £50 million, to stimulate enterprise, including private enterprise, beneficial to the colonics concerned. An Overseas Food Corporation has also been formed, with a capital of £50 millions; and a Colonial Primary Products Committee is studying possibilities of new agricultural production.</p></div><div><head>Social services and welfare </head><p>All this goes on within a rapidly expanding framework of up- to-date welfare legislation and social services. Malayan workers before the war had a nine-hour day and a six-day week. Minimum wages on estates were fixed through a calculation allowing for reasonable diet, clothing, festival expenses, maintenance of dependents, $1 a month savings and a holiday to India every three years. Workmen’s compensation ensured payments ranging, in the case of death by accident, to $2400. Holidays with pay for expectant mothers, crèches for children with free milk and rice, were all laid down in the Labour Code.</p><p>To-day provisions of this kind are rapidly becoming more general. Before the war only two colonial territories had Labour Departments. By 1943, 30 territories had them, and by the end of the war they existed in all but two territories. Labour Advisory Boards are formed from representatives of workers and employers. Workmen's compensation legislation is universal in Africa, and so is provision for fixing minimum wages. Arbitration Tribunals adjudicate disputes, with the consent of both parties. There are now well over 700 registered trade unions in the colonies.</p></div><div><head>Towards self-government </head><p>At the same time, as Professor Harold Laski reported to the last Labour Party Conference, "since the Labour Government came into power more than twenty constitutions have been revised in the direction of greater democratisation.” It is a part of “British imperial policy” to develop native participation in government, to withdraw British administrators and replace them gradually with colonials, and to canalise the rising energies and capacities in the colonics along directions leading to self-government. Local government at district and municipal levels, provincial and regional administration, government at the centre, are all shifting and changing and developing in a kaleidoscope of progress. Parliamentary institutions exist throughout the colonies, and one territory after another has reached the significant stage where its popular representatives come to constitute a majority on the Legislative Councils. Under the Labour Government such unofficial majorities have been achieved in the Gold Coast, Nigeria, Malta, Hongkong and Mauritius.</p><p>Thus progress and socialism go hand in hand. Much is necessarily experimental. Perhaps the most interesting effort is the attempt to bridge the gap between tribal society and a modern socialised economy by means of co-operative organisation. There is a strong realisation that welfare is now the criterion by which all economic enterprise is judged. Is it good for the colony, it is asked, to allow factories to be established in such and such a place by, say, European private firms? And if so, on what terms? How far at present can government enterprise go? For government has gradually to develop its own resources in order to take over a widening sphere of responsibilities; as Karl Marx says, it is under monopoly conditions that socialisation becomes an effective possibility.</p><p>Meanwhile there is an immense amount of basic groundwork for government to do. The Secretary of State for the Colonies, Mr Arthur Creech Jones tells how “We have to conserve water, get fertility, drain swamps, bring irrigation, supply pure water, overcome diseases of all kinds which are fatal to man, beast and plant. That is an infinitely difficult, patient, slow and expensive task.” The methods? Mr Creech Jones summarises them in the same speech on Labour’s Colonial Policy. The Labour Government, he says, “believes that responsibility in government must be achieved as quickly as practicable, that there must be greater community action, that social change must bring higher standards and a richer life for the people, and that economic development must be planned, and as far as possible created upon the basis of community responsibility and co-operative practice".</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>