<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Revival of German Social-Democracy</title>
         <author>Erich Ollenhauer</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Revival of German Social-Democracy</title>
            <author>Erich Ollenhauer</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1947-February 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.3</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="German" party="Social Democratic Party of Germany"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The German Social-Democratic Party was among the National- Socialist dictatorship’s first victims. Its officials and members were persecuted; many were arrested, tortured and killed in prisons and concentration camps. The exact number of Social-Democrats who fell victim to fascism is still uncertain, but there must have been tens of thousands. Party Funds stolen by the Nazis have been estimated at too million marks. The National-Socialists knew what they were doing when they persecuted and attempted to wipe out the Social-Democrats, whose logical policy in defence of freedom and democracy, peace and international understanding, was the most dangerous weapon against the Nazi dictatorship and its war policy.</p><p>German Social-Democracy suffered grievously, but neither terror nor suppression could wipe out Social-Democratic ideas. In the spring of 1945 while the Nazi regime was fighting its last desperate battle for existence, German Social-Democracy began to rebuild, first illegally but tolerated by the occupying authorities. Then, after official sanction had been given by Military Government, the party re-built its local and central organisation. Former party officials formed the skeleton of the new organisation; many of them had been active in the socialist youth movement before 1933, but at the same time the party attracted many new recruits. In May 1946 the party held its first congress, which was attended by delegates from the three western zones. This conference decided on Hanover as the seat of the party offices, chose Schumacher as its first party chairman, and issued a programme.</p><p>During the following year, culminating in the Nuremberg conference in June 1947, the party made considerable organisational progress, above all in increased membership. On 31 December 1946, membership in the three western zones and in Berlin stood at 711,448; by 30 June 1947 it had increased to 834,000 members and this increase has been maintained. Membership in these areas in 1931 stood at 602,084, so that present party strength is relatively greater than in 1933. In considering these figures it has to be remembered that the party's membership is built on individuals, and that at Hanover the conference decided to limit the entry of former National-Socialists. All applications by former members of National-Socialist organisations have to be submitted to a local committee. The applicant has to be recommended by two SPD members, and his application can only be granted if he can convince the committee that he behaved decently during the Nazi regime.</p><p>In 1946 the party began to build up its own party press and started party newspapers under Military Government supervision. The policy of the various occupying authorities varied. While the Americans have licensed only “non-party” papers, the French and British have permitted party organs in their zones and in Berlin. At the present time 17 SPD papers appear in these zones, the Berlin papers being published six times weekly, the British zone papers twice weekly.</p><div><head>The Russian zone </head><p>Only in the three western zones and Berlin is open party activity possible. In the eastern zone the SPD is prohibited, since the SPD and Communist Party were forcibly merged in April 1946, the new Socialist Unity Party (SED) being under Communist control. With the support of the occupying power, the SED has built up a new totalitarian regime in the eastern zone. Not only does the party occupy all important posts in the government, but it suppresses any opposition. Faithful Social-Democrats are being persecuted; many of them, as during the Hitler regime, find themselves in concentration camps and prisons. The SPD Executive possesses a list containing the names of many such victims of the new dictatorship.</p><p>The battle for unrestricted political activity was fought in Berlin in the spring of 1946. There the SPD demanded a referendum on the question of a merger between the Communist and Social- Democratic Parties, with the result that an overwhelming majority voted for the continuation of an independent Social-Democratic Party. The fight rose to a new pitch during the Berlin municipal elections on 20 October 1946 when the SPD polled almost 50 per cent, of the votes, while the SED obtained only 18 per cent. Thus Social-Democracy in Berlin has become a political outpost of German Social-Democracy.</p></div><div><head>Politics under the occupation </head><p>SPD policy has been determined by the special circumstances brought about by the “unconditional surrender of May 1945.  Germany is occupied by the Allies; there is no central government - its functions are carried out by the Allied Control Council on which Germans are not represented. The country is divided into four zones, each under the jurisdiction of one of the Allies. Berlin is the exception, since it is governed by the Kommandatura, a four-power commission. Since the beginning of this year, closer economic co-operation has existed between the American and British Zones, based on the Anglo-American Agreement concluded in the autumn of 1946.</p><p>On the other hand, the last two years have seen the gradual development of democratic methods in German self-government. To start with Gemeinde and Kreistag elections took place, followed by the Länder elections. The elected parliaments chose the chief officials of the local councils as well as the Länder governments. Such parliamentary representation exists to-day in all three western zones and in Berlin. Elections were also held in the Russian Zone, but since the SPD—probably the strongest party in the zone— was excluded, one cannot speak here of free elections or democratic and representative parliaments.</p><p>The administration of the Gemeinde, Kreise, and Länder is under the democratic control of the parliament; that is, it can only function while it enjoys the confidence of the parliament. On the other hand, Military Government limits the right to self-government since the military authorities retain the final power. In addition, Military Government also frequently intervenes at lower levels in the German administration with the result that, though Germans have the right to choose a policy by voting in elections and thus express their political views, these views cannot necessarily be taken as a basis for action because of frequent intervention by the occupation forces.</p><p>It is possible to judge the present German political scene only after a thorough appreciation of these facts. An essential condition for a constructive German policy is freedom to shape a new social and political order, while military security is preserved by occupation, de-nazification, and disarmament.</p><p>Under present conditions the main task confronting all parties is the political education of the German masses and the realisation of party aims within the bounds of possibility. So far, German Social-Democracy has not put forward a final political programme, though it has worked out general policy lines which are used as a basis for all its actions. German Social-Democracy fully admits the Creation of the German people to make good the damage done Hitler. The party stands for disarmament and wants to see war flawed as a political weapon.</p><p>Both these aims can he achieved only when the German people receive adequate food and are enabled to work. The latter is an essential condition, if essential production needs are to be fulfilled and if sufficient goods are to be exported to pay for imports of raw materials and foodstuffs. Such a basis of existence cannot be found if Germany is to be deprived of the eastern territories which arc at present being administered by Poland. In addition, the loss of industrial plant and machinery—not all of it for war purposes— through dismantling will be felt severely, since these arc indispensable for peace-time production.</p><p>German economic and political recovery, in the opinion of the SPD, can be achieved only in an economically and politically united Germany. The unity of Germany is one of the fundamental aims of Social-Democratic policy.</p><p>The SPD considers that the world can best be protected from future German aggression by a soundly based democracy, which can only be built on a socialist economic basis. The type of democratic regime set up after 1918, where all important economic positions were occupied by a small group of industrialists and landowners, is always unstable. In times of stress such a democracy would inevitably be endangered by the use of economic power by political reaction and or by a new kind of National-Socialism.</p></div><div><head>The need for nationalisation </head><p>But in the Germany of to-day nationalisation means more than political security. Germany will for years remain a country of shortages, considering the destruction wrought by the war, the industrial mismanagement under the dictatorship, and the lack of machinery, raw materials and skilled workers. Everything is lacking, yet 10 million more people—the German populations of the eastern territories and Czechoslovakia, and others repatriated from the east—will have to be fed and have work found for them. This problem can be solved only if production can be planned, and if products are shared out on an equitable basis. It could never be solved if an economy of private capitalism were permitted to survive.</p><p>For these reasons the SPD is campaigning for the socialisation of heavy industry and for land reform, which would create a healthy peasant population and would increase agricultural production. In addition, the party stands for an equal sharing of the burden. The war and its results have split the German people socially into two camps: one group, by a series of lucky accidents remained wealthy and lost little in material goods; the other larger group lost everything as a result of bombing or population transfers. It would be only just if war losses were spread over the whole population according to economic capacity. </p><p>Since 1945 these economic and political demands have been the focal points of the party’s political work. At the present time the battle over nationalisation is being fought in the Länder parliaments. The SPD is in a majority only in Schleswig-Holstein, Hamburg, and Bremen; in North Rhine-Westphalia, the most important from the point of view of nationalisation, the CDU is in a majority. Socialisation in individual Länder is not regarded as desirable by the SPD, since it wishes to see all key industries taken over. While Germany remains divided it regards the Länder governments solely as trustees of the Reich.</p><p>But international issues affect the question of nationalisation While the British Labour Party repeatedly stressed the necessity of nationalising German key industries, the Americans wished to see it put off for several years, until the zones are re-united and the whole question can be put to the vote. The French government has opposed socialisation of the Ruhr industries since it regards this as a dangerous concentration of industry and thus a danger to France. These discussions between the Allies about the future administration and economic structure of the Ruhr industries will eventually provide the answer to the vital question of nationalisation and the basis on which German economy is to be rebuilt.</p></div><div><head>Denazification </head><p>The second big task confronting German Social-Democracy is the democratisation of the administration and the building of a democratic Germany. During the early post-war period denazification was in the hands of the Allies, though it was later handed over to the German authorities. The result so far has satisfied no one. It proved impossible to use existing laws for the purpose of trying men and women for political offences, or to cleanse National- Socialists and their hangers-on from public service by these means.</p><p>The SPD believes that the process of de-nazification should be completed as quickly as possible. The guilty must be punished; active Nazis must be removed from all official positions. In all other cases some rule should be laid down which would, within a reasonable space of time, permit former nominal members of the Nazi party to exercise their rights as ordinary citizens, provided that they can be tried later if any specific charges are preferred against them.</p><p>At its Nuremberg Conference the Party laid down guiding lines for the rebuilding of a democratic government and a new German Republic These are based on the assumption of a united Germany. This new republic must have a central administration, in view of the complexity of modern government and the need to plan production and a rationing system for consumer goods and food. Within the framework of a central administration, occupied mainly with foreign and economic policy, currency problems, and foreign the Länder governments are expected to retain far-reaching lowers of self-government.</p><p>This extension of self-government to local authorities is regarded essential by the SPD, in the knowledge that a live democracy an only exist if individual citizens arc permitted to play their part at the lowest and middle levels of administration. Otherwise bureaucracy and direction “from above” endanger democracy.</p><p>The drafting of a new German constitution on this basis remains a purely theoretical question, since as a first essential political and economic unity of the country must be achieved; this is not a German but an Allied decision. Since 1945 there have been some federalistic tendencies, in some areas even a degree of separatism; nevertheless, in a free vote Germans of all zones would be 90 per cent, in favour of German organic unity.</p><p>In the present state of development the Social Democrats aim at putting their principles forward during the discussion of the Lander constitutions in the Lander parliaments. In the majority of Länder the bourgeois parties, led by the CDU, are in a majority. As a result the agreed constitutions in the American zone mirror this preponderance of the CDU. While the constitution in Hesse most nearly approaches SPD conceptions, it was only after considerable misgivings that the Social-Democrats accepted the Bavarian constitution. In the Lander of the British Zone the constitutions are still under discussion, while in the Russian Zone constitutions were discussed in record time and adopted unanimously; they were based on plans put forward by the SED.</p><p>In all fields German Social-Democracy wages a battle on two fronts. The part played by the Communists has already been des?cribed: they are the executive organ of Russian foreign policy. This is not only true of the SED in the Russian Zone, but also of the KPD in the three western occupation zones. Everywhere the Social-Democrats differ sharply in policy from the Communists.</p><p>Yet the SPD’s most powerful political enemy is without doubt the Christian Democratic Union. This is a party built on a variety of elements, such as former members of the old Catholic Zentrum, the People's Party (backed by heavy industry), and the German National Party. It unites Catholics and Protestants, and in addition it receives support from Catholic industrial workers and small farmers. Nevertheless the party's policy is determined by the bourgeois middle-class which wants to maintain its political and economic advantages, and which has no intention of bearing the consequences of a lost war. On the question of nationalisation the CDU voted against the SPD: it opposes a far-reaching land reform and desires a cultural and educational policy which would secure for the churches a wide measure of control over education and schools.</p><p>The CDU wages its battle against the SPD by asserting that the SPD as a party opposes religion and is materialistic in outlook. But this is merely an attempt to side-step the many the many pressing political and economic problems, since many members of the CDU are in fact more nearly in agreement with SPD policy than with the conservative and reactionary wing of the CDU. The parties are almost equally strong; all other parties arc small fractions. Future development now depends on the degree of CDU success with those workers who adhere to that party for traditional or religious reasons.</p></div><div><head>A peaceful democratic Germany </head><p>The social and political programme of the SPD is based on the needs of the great majority of the German people. Its attraction will be decided by the vitality and honesty of Social-Democracy. The party will have to combine its socialist and democratic programme with a tolerance for those who differ from it for religious or philosophical reasons, so that a democratic socialist policy can be carried out. Social-Democracy looks at these problems honestly. Not only is the party strong in organisation, but it is alive in spirit.</p><p>In the present state of Germany, the chances of success for Social-Democracy depend on its own exertions. German democracy can only develop when the German people live a full life, and if Germany once more becomes a part of Europe economically, politically and culturally. By tradition, Social-Democracy stands for peace and understanding between peoples. The party is ready by all means at its disposal to support a policy which would lead to the establishment of a peaceful democratic Germany and a new Europe. But above all, it realises that by its policy it must win the confidence of other nations, and in this the party bases its hopes on the understanding and on the confidence of all European Social Democrats.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>