<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
         <author>Editorial Staff</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
            <author>Editorial Staff</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><div><head>Antwerp and after </head><p>No one who saw the reporters thronging the lobby of the Hotel Excelsior in Antwerp during the fourth International Socialist Conference early in December, or the crowd of nearly two hundred journalists at the press conference after the first meeting of the Committee of International Socialist Conferences in London on 10th January, can doubt the public interest in international socialist co-operation. When all allowances have been made for the sensationalism and lack of understanding in some press reports, the fact remains that these reports in the world’s press are the answer to a wide demand for information about the socialist attitude to present world problems.</p><p>Times have changed since the informal meetings of Socialists in the last years of the war. Socialist parties now control, or share responsibility in, most of the governments of Europe. They are a power. At the same time the international outlook has steadily worsened; the division of the world into blocs continues. All this has inevitably meant an increasing interest in a movement which seeks to prevent this division of the world, and whose aims of political democracy, social reform, and economic planning, unite Socialists in countries with quite different traditions, political conditions, and geographical situation.</p><p>What did the Antwerp Conference accomplish? What practical results of international socialist co-operation can be shown? The first point to emphasise is that the Conference was a step forward in international socialist co-operation—a marked contrast to meetings of other international organisations since the war. The step forward may not have been as great as some parties wish, but there can be no doubt that as a result of the Antwerp discussions there was a greater mutual understanding between parties of all countries. In addition, there was noticeable progress in organisation. The setting-up of the new Committee of International Socialist Conferences (COMISCO), composed of fully-mandated responsible delegates from all member parties, is a considerable advance on the old Consultative Committee, set up by the Bournemouth Conference in 1946. The financial resources of the Socialist Information and Liaison Office are to be doubled and its activities extended. In fact, the international socialist movement is showing healthy growth.</p><p>There is no question yet of founding a new International. The new Committee is not an executive on the model of the old Labour and Socialist International—the executive remains the Conference itself. But the bonds uniting Socialists are being strengthened in spite of the differences which separate them.</p><p>The first meeting of COMISCO took place on 10th January at Transport House, London, with Morgan Phillips, Secretary of the British Labour Party, in the chair, and aroused world-wide interest A notable feature was the presence of the German representative Dr Schumacher, Chairman of the SPD, and Dr Katz — their first appearance since the admission of the German Social Democrats by the Antwerp Conference. The Committee dealt mainly with practical organisational matters. In fact, it is true to say that what distinguishes present-day socialist co-operation is the general wish to stick to discussion of practical problems, and avoid general and inevitably vague resolutions—though Antwerp was an exception in this respect. This business-like approach is one of the most encouraging signs for the future.</p><p>Vienna was chosen by the Committee as the place for the next International Socialist Conference early in June. COMISCO’s next meeting in March will deal with the arrangements for this conference.</p><p>A by-product of the COMISCO meeting was the proposal to call a Conference of socialist parties of the Marshall Plan countries, sponsored jointly by the British and French parties. This Conference, to take place on 21st—22nd March, is not connected with the International Socialist Conference. It is also reported that there is to be a Conference of Eastern European socialist parties shortly to discuss economic co-operation.</p><p>What of the future? Inevitably, the present international tension is a major obstacle to the progress of international Socialism. Post-war political developments in Europe have meant that socialist parties in different countries are working under widely dissimilar conditions, have meant especially that there arc differences between parties in Eastern and Western Europe. But the essential socialist principles remain the same in all countries. This can be seen in two articles in this number: one by Dr Oscar Pollak from Austria, the other by Dr Vilem Bernard from Czechoslovakia, who express their own views on international socialist co-operation, from what might be called the Western and the Eastern point of view respectively. What they have in common is much more important than their disagreements.</p><p>The International socialist movement has gone through many changes in its history. It has suffered many setbacks in the hundred years since Marx and Engels published the “Communist Manifesto,” the first great landmark of international Socialism. It may suffer more setbacks in the future. But Socialists learn from their defeats and their mistakes: their movement now is immeasurably stronger than ever before. International socialist co-operation is being built on a firm foundation. Every step forward is made with the free consent of all socialist parties. Only in this way can the international socialist movement remain effective and united.</p></div><div><head>Socialists in Spain </head><p>One of the decisions of the Antwerp Conference was to set up a commission, under the Conference’s Chairman. Louis de Brouckere, to examine the question of the Spanish Socialist Party (PSOE). The Commission’s task was to decide which of the Spanish Socialist groups in exile should be recognised, and it was agreed that activity inside Spain should be the determining factor. The Commission met in Brussels on 14 February, and after a long examination of the documents and talks with various Spanish Socialists, agreed that the PSOE inside Spain and its representatives in exile in France should be recognised.</p><p>The decisive proof of the extent of socialist activity inside Spain is the fact that Socialists are the chief victims of Franco’s attempt to suppress all opposition. From the day the Civil War ended the Socialist Party was slowly built up again by the devotion of members in every part of the country, even inside Franco’s prisons and concentration camps. Naturally the Fascist police was ruthless in its methods. In February, 1943, the whole of the underground Executive Committee of the Party was arrested, except for one of its members who managed to escape into France. Their places were immediately taken by other Socialists, while they remained a year in prison before being tried in February, 1946, at Alcala de Henares. The pressure of world public opinion prevented the court from passing the death sentences which the prosecution demanded, but all the accused received sentences of from four to twelve years’ imprisonment.</p><p>A short time later, in May, 1946, four members of the new Executive were also arrested, together with a number of other Socialists. They too were kept for months in prison before being brought before the military tribunal at Ocana in November, 1947. Early in January the sixteen accused were sentenced to periods of imprisonment ranging from two to twenty-five years for having “plotted against the security of the state’ by re-organising the Socialist Party. COMISCO was speaking for Socialists and democrats everywhere when it sent a telegram to the Franco government protesting against these savage sentences and calling for the release of these victims of oppression.</p><p>In spite of persecution, in spite of a fresh wave of arrests in December, 1947, the underground socialist movement in Spain continues. It maintains regular contact with the Spanish Socialist Party in exile, which has its headquarters at Toulouse in France. Many Socialists have repeatedly risked arrest, and many have arrested, in passing backwards and forwards across the front- keep contact between the movement inside Spain and the outside world.	</p><p>Towards the end of March, the Spanish Socialist Party will hold its third Congress at Toulouse, when representatives of thousand of exiles in Europe, North Africa, and Latin America will meet representatives of the thousands of Socialists inside Spain — demonstration that the Spanish socialist movement is undefeated</p></div><div><head>The Social democratic party of Iceland </head><p>At its meeting on 10th January, COMISCO agreed to recommend the admission of the Social Democratic Party of Iceland. A fifth representative of the Scandinavian countries will therefore take part in the Vienna Conference.</p><p>The Althyduflokkur (Social Democratic Party of Iceland) was founded in 1916, while Iceland was still under Danish sovereignty. Although the country lies in mid-Atlantic, its labour movement went through the same kind of vicissitudes in the inter-war years as the movements in other countries. The influence of Communism was felt in Iceland, too, and in 1930 the left wing of the party split off to the Comintern. There was another split in the Social Democratic Party in 1938, when some members left and joined with the Communists in a Socialist Unity Party. Weakened by these successive blows, the Social Democrats polled only 8,455 votes in the elections of 1942, against the Unity Party’s 11,059 votes.</p><p>This 1942 election, however, was the low-water mark in the party’s fortunes. Since then there has been a gradual improvement, though at the last elections in July, 1946, the Social Democratic vote was still lower than that of the Communist-dominated Unity Party. The Social Democrats polled 11,914 votes against the Unity Party’s 13,049. 67,896 votes were cast, so that the Althyduflokkur gained 18 per cent, of the total. There are nine Social Democratic members of the Althing, the Icelandic Parliament, which has 52 members. Since February, 1947, Iceland’s Prime Minister has been the Chairman of the Social Democratic Party, Stefànsson, who presides over a coalition cabinet formed of representatives of the Social Democratic, Progressive, and Independence Parties. The Unity Party with ten members is in opposition. One of the main achievements of the present parliament has been the passage of comprehensive social insurance legislation which came into operation last year.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>