<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>International socialist co-operation</title>
         <author>Vilém Bernard</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>International socialist co-operation</title>
            <author>Vilém Bernard</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Czechoslovak" party="Czechoslovak Social Democracy"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The question of international socialist co-operation gives rise to important political problems. First of all we must take into account the present position and power of socialist parties, their political activity, their common features and their differences. Then we must recognise what is the political basis of this co-operation and what are the obstacles which interrupt its development and prevent socialist parties from acting in the same way in each country and from giving one another the greatest possible mutual assistance. Once we have established these facts, it will then be possible to consider what form the co-operation should take to correspond to the degree of unity of opinion and policy which exists, for it goes without saying that such an appreciation must precede discussion and decisions concerning questions of organisation.</p><p>As far as the present power of European socialist parties and their influence on governmental and parliamentary policy is concerned, it is encouraging to be able to state that socialist parties in almost every European country are an important factor, and in some the strongest party and therefore the determining political power. All the hostile propaganda spread by our political enemies, which talks of the decadence of socialist parties or of their inner conflicts, or of their imminent fusion with the Communists, should be critically examined, for few of these stories bear any resemblance to the truth.</p><p>When we come to look for common features in the various socialist parties, we can at once notice that there is a large group of parties whose political activity in the last two years has been marked by the successful laying of the foundation of a socialist system in their countries by the nationalisation of industry and the banks. These parties have passed from the stage of socialist programme to that of socialist action, and their common task now is to ensure that the social system they have created develops into Socialism. Most noticeable in this group are the socialist parties of Central and Eastern Europe, but we must also include among them the Labour Party, which is gradually carrying out the work of Socialism in Britain. This fact must not be forgotten, for in considering socialist activity, we should concentrate on discovering what progress socialist parties have made on the path towards Socialism: this progress is also their contribution to international Socialism. In Czechoslovakia it is often thought that the socialist world is bounded by the line Stettin—Trieste, but the example of Britain shows how false this idea is. Socialism has not been brought about in Britain in a single bound as in Czechoslovakia—the situation in Britain is different—but at the same time the extent of nationalisation which has already been carried out in Britain is greater than that in at least one country in Eastern Europe. We must realise that Britain’s Labour Government is carrying out nationalisation without any support from outside, indeed against the opposition of American capitalism. This is all the more reason why we should praise what has been achieved so far.</p><div><head>The basis of democratic socialism </head><p>If we try to classify socialist parties into groups according to their common features, we should also consider to what extent they have succeeded in maintaining democratic regimes in their countries, and in those countries where important economic and social reforms have been realised, to what extent they have succeeded in advancing towards Socialism by the path of democracy. It is this question above all which causes the greatest disagreement between socialist parties, partly because of lack of information and partly because of lack of mutual understanding. It is well known that the various regimes in some countries of Eastern Europe are severely criticised in the West, even by Socialists. On the other hand, parties in Western Europe are often reproached in the East because they have not yet brought about economic reforms of any importance so that the capitalist system therefore remains intact in their countries. Both criticisms are quite understandable, but we must demand that the socialist programme in both East and West should unite the principle of democracy and the principle of Socialism so that the two aspects of socialist activity are equally balanced. If political democracy is not accompanied by large-scale intervention in the economic field, it is continually threatened, as is seen in France to-day; at the same time, it must be emphasised that economic and social reforms without the guarantee of the rights of the citizen and of democratic institutions can lead to a system which has no right to be called Socialism. From both points of view, socialist activity in East and West can be sincerely criticised in a spirit of comradeship—provided, of course, that this criticism is accompanied by mutual understanding and that it does not prevent the co-operation of all countries in both Eastern and Western Europe.</p><p>Even in countries where the capitalist system has remained intact, whether because of socialist weakness or because of influence from outside, the socialists continue to have their own programme and therefore the possibility, after having conquered their weaknesses and corrected their mistakes, of putting Socialism into practice, once a favourable stage in the international situation has been reached. At present these parties form a bulwark against the attacks of political reaction, and in many European countries their socialist policy has brought a remarkable improvement in working-class conditions, even under a capitalist system. These parties to-day are in the same position as the Czechoslovak party was in the period before Munich.</p><p>At the same time, Western European Socialists, who often criticise the situation in Eastern Europe, must be brought to realise not only the danger represented by the reactionary classes, who have not yet abandoned hope of a return to former conditions, but also the lack of democratic traditions in countries which for the first time in their history have taken the road towards democracy. The character of democratic institutions in a country depends on the stage of economic development and on the political and cultural level of the population. This is why democracy in every country has its own particular features and why there are countries without favourable conditions for parliamentary systems of the Western European type. Socialists should appreciate the economic and social reform which marks the end of the political power of the feudal land-owners. These reforms constitute an important social revolution, and together with other measures, form the economic basis for political democracy. It is the task of socialist parties to work for the strengthening of a democratic regime everywhere.</p></div><div><head>Government policy and socialist solidarity </head><p>It is true that what unites and forms the basis of co-operation of socialist parties are the principles and aims, laid down in party programmes, though these are, of course, put into practice in different ways in different countries. But in judging a party’s political activity it is not only its programme and the way it is implemented which must be considered, but also its country’s international position and the foreign policy of the government in which the party is represented or which it supports. In fact we must not forget that socialist parties in Europe to-day are mostly government parties partly, or in many cases fully, responsible for foreign policy. They are often called on to reconcile government policy with their fidelity to international socialist solidarity—not always an easy task, but a very necessary one in the interests of world peace. Both government policy and socialist solidarity should serve to nations closer together, to facilitate peaceful solutions of international difference, to extend international co-operation in every way. It often seems that, in the present state of the world, divided as it is into two blocs by the Great Powers, any effort towards peace and international understanding is useless and doomed to failure. Socialists cannot adopt this false and dangerous attitude. It would be a grave mistake to ignore the innumerable causes of disagreement in international affairs, but it would be an equally grave mistake not to admit the chance of at least a temporary improvement in Great Power relations or of even limited agreement on single questions. This would, of course, not solve the whole complex international problem, but by postponing an open conflict might afford breathing space to the socialist parties, who are after all the only elements capable of establishing a durable peace and thus of completing the task which the Great Powers have not performed and cannot perform. It is generally, but mistakenly, believed that only the Great Powers have enough means and resources to be important factors in international affairs, and that action by any other power would be useless. Socialist parties have no intention, however, of forming a third bloc: they are active throughout the whole world both East and West—that is one of their advantages— and their task is to unite not to divide.</p></div><div><head>International difficulties</head><p>There is still one big gap in the ranks of the international socialist movement: the USA have no socialist party of importance. But we can confidently expect that the development of American capitalism will rapidly create favourable conditions for the growth of political consciousness among the working classes. Great union organisations, who have the support of Socialists everywhere, are fighting against the anti-labour law recently passed by the U.S. Congress. Political activity is growing, for the working classes are beginning to realise the need for political action to defend their rights. In these circumstances it is the duty of European socialist parties to act as a model in unity and action to American workers, and to avoid anything which might make conditions more difficult for progressive forces in America.</p><p>Socialist parties must take care that nothing in their activity resembles that unreal bourgeois pacifism which we came to know too well at the time of Munich. At the same time they must avoid anything which might, even involuntarily, support those seeking to stir up another war. It is their duty to isolate and weaken world capitalism wherever it occurs. In this connection the interest of the socialist parties is similar to that of the Soviet Union, for international capitalism is their common enemy. Socialist peace policy ought to be so directed that it removes the Soviet doubts and distrust concerning attempts at international socialist co-operation which is accused of being directed against the Soviets.</p><p>Of course, socialist parties should give every support to the United Nations. Nevertheless they should not lose sight of the fact that it is the capitalist system which favours war-mongers and that efforts towards peace must be closely bound up with’ progress towards Socialism. It follows that they should not over-estimate this new organisation nor fail to understand Soviet insistence on the principle of unanimity in the United Nations, for it is not in the interests of international Socialism to help to isolate the Soviet Union and its allies. Moreover, it cannot be socialist policy to look for the reasons for the present weakness of the United Nations in matters of form, or to see no other way of improving matters but in changes in procedure—for example, in the suppression of the veto.</p><p>Relations between the Great Powers arc also disturbed by disagreements about international economic co-operation. Of course, it is agreed that as soon as there is even partial agreement between the Great Powers about economic problems, that may lead to a wider agreement on political matters and the solution of some pressing international problems. Socialists know very well that there is an intimate connection between economics and politics, and if they could concentrate on the economic field and make positive proposals, they could do much to help the cause of peace. Planned international co-operation in the economic field is very close to the socialist ideal. European economic anarchy in the 1930’s has not been forgotten, especially as it contributed to the deepening of the world crisis and brought serious political consequences. Socialists should maintain their point of view, even though differences between the Great Powers and attempts to use economic power for political ends have so far meant little hope of success. What is certain is that international co-operation is constantly increasing; what remains to be seen is what political tendency will have the greater influence over this development: capitalist reaction or Socialism. It is the duty of socialist parties to work in unison to guide international co-operation in a socialist direction.</p></div><div><head>Organisation of international socialist co-operation </head><p>We now come to the problem most often discussed at inter-national socialist conferences: the kind of organisation to be established. This has always aroused great and perhaps exaggerated interest. After the war socialist parties had to consider whether they should establish a new International, such as they had previously had over a long period, or whether they should choose a different means of co-operation. Most parties were again an immediate reconstruction of the International, and the Bournemouth Conference in the autumn of 1946 formally decided to wind up the old Second International and dispose of its funds. F0r first time for a number of years, therefore, there is no firm organisational bond between socialist parties.</p><p>The Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party, along with almost all other socialist parties, has always maintained that the time is not yet ripe for the reconstruction of a formal International, because there is not enough political and programmatic unity to serve as a firm basis for such an organisation. If a new International were to be founded at the present time, it would run the risk of interior dissension which would make it incapable of playing the decisive part in international affairs which would be expected of it. We already had experience of this in 1938 in the period before Munich, when the Second International was not able to exert any influence on the course of European politics. As is well known, the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party left the Second International in protest against its weakness and against the attitude of some of the other socialist parties.</p><p>Our negative attitude to the formation of the International does not mean, of course, that we abandon the idea of international socialist co-operation. On the contrary, socialist parties can work together in ways which correspond more closely to the needs of the present situation. The form of the present organisation should not be regarded in any respect as a new International, for it has none of the characteristics, such as a central executive with the right of taking decisions binding on all members, which belong to an International. Every decision has at present to be taken unanimously by all parties. In the West where the plan arose to re-establish the International, the principle of unanimity is fully recognised, so that there is no risk of dispersing socialist forces in a Western European organisation. Similarly an Eastern European organisation would be equally undesirable. Any steps of this kind would mean that the present division of the world into two blocs had also extended to the international socialist movement, which would make its task much more difficult. Relations between socialist parties should not be determined by the geographical position of the respective countries but by their work for Socialism.</p></div><div><head>Socialist and communists </head><p>One other important question which must be mentioned is that of relations between the socialist parties and the Communists; this also is a problem belonging to the realm of international affairs. Relations between Socialists and Communists do not follow the same pattern in every country; there are differences not only in the form but also in the degree of collaboration between the two parties. In some countries both parties are in the government; in others only the Socialists, with the Communists in opposition; in others both parties are in opposition. One reason for this is of course the difference in the strength of the different communist panics. In some countries of Eastern Europe and in Italy, socialist parties have formed an electoral bloc with the Communists or have joint lists, while in other countries, including Czechoslovakia, each party has its own candidates and its own independent programme.</p><p>This is perhaps the ideal position, and it would be a convincing proof of unity if all socialist parties not only had the same programme but also pursued the same tactics. But to expect such a course would hardly be realistic. This may be a weakness in international Socialism, but it corresponds to the present situation. Perhaps at some future international socialist conference we shall discuss this question, for an exchange of views on the subject would certainly not be without interest. But such a discussion should not lead to any general ruling. Socialist parties must make their own decisions in accordance with the needs of the situation in their countries; they have not created a centre to direct them—their co-operation is equal and on a voluntary basis. Newspaper reports on this point, especially those which claim that the British Labour Party gives orders to European socialist parties, are without foundation.</p></div><div><head>Division means weakness </head><p>Naturally, this does not mean that one party can remain indifferent about the tactics of socialist parties in other countries. While recognising the right of any socialist party freely to decide its own policy towards the Communists, we in Czechoslovakia hope that socialist parties in other countries will refrain from any attitude which might injure us, directly or indirectly. We believe that divisions on the Left ought not to take as serious a form at present as during the inter-war years, for that would benefit reactionary forces everywhere, and the cause of Socialism throughout the world would suffer. But at the same time we must be allowed to say that socialist parties should remain faithful to their principles and their special task, and maintain their complete independence of ideas, programme, and organisation, which does not necessarily mean giving up collaboration with other progressive forces in the interests of Socialism.</p><p>Any improvement in relations between Socialists and Communists on the international plane would be a source of satisfaction.</p><p>But we must admit that there is no sign of it. I must emphasise here that in every international activity in which they have engaged socialist parties have done everything possible to avoid provoking further disagreements with the Communists and so causing further complications. One of the reasons—though not the most important reason—why a new International was not formed was to avoid any action that might give the appearance of causing a fresh split in the socialist forces. This was a sincere effort on the part of the Socialists not to complicate a situation already complicated enough Unfortunately, the Communists have not responded to this approach. The Executive Committee of the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party quite rightly condemned the declaration published by the conference of nine communist parties in Poland, which it feared would only accentuate international suspicion. Other socialist parties have also protested—not only those parties attacked in the Communist declaration, but also parties which co-operate closely with Communists, such as the Hungarians and the Italians. It is possible to criticise socialist parties in Western Europe, but it is quite unjust to accuse them of betraying Socialism and of being tools of international capitalism. Such an attitude on the part of the Communists causes immense damage to Socialism and democracy in countries threatened by Right-wing forces, in which Communists ought rather to help the Socialists than attack them more strongly than they attack Fascist reaction.</p><p>There can be no objections against common action on the part of the Communists—it is even an advantage in the present situation if they do this in public. In so far as co-operation between communist parties is directed towards improving relations between countries, they have no reason for disagreement with Socialists. But we have seen that the common attitude of communist parties has had the opposite effect, and has not served the cause of international co-operation and peace, which is the cause of the socialist parties.</p><p>From a report presented to the XXI Congress of the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party in Brno on 16th November, 1947</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>