<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Third Force</title>
         <author>Oskar Pollak</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Third Force</title>
            <author>Oskar Pollak</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Austrian" party="Socialist Party of Austria"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>For over a year and a half now the Austrian Socialist press has been discussing the idea of democratic Socialism as an independent "Third Force.” The same idea became current in socialist movements in other countries over the same period—the “Keep Left1' group in Britain, Leon Blum in France, Schumacher in Germany, Silone in Italy—and has now passed into the field of international politics. The expression "Third Force” which we first used has quickly spread, and has become a kind of slogan in international political discussion, so that we must be especially careful to avoid confusion and imprecision in our ideas about it.</p><p>To me the Third Force means democratic Socialism. It stands “between blocs, and against blocs" in international affairs. For this reason it is not unexpected that it should be attacked from both sides on geographical, political, and ideological grounds—its opponents define it wrongly in order to refute it the more easily. Another argument used against it is that a Third Force is an attractive idea, but the socialist movement is much too weak to put such ideas into practice.</p><div><head>What is the third force? </head><p>What kind of definitions are there of the Third Force? In my speech at the last Austrian Socialist Party Conference I tried to define its essentials in the following passage:</p><p> “Socialist Parties in other countries are watching us; they expect from this Conference an appeal to the self-confidence of free Socialists all over the world. The Third Force is not a centre party. Just as we Socialists in Austria are not just a centre party, not just a half-way house between the People’s Party and the Communists, so we are not just a centre party in the international field. Throughout the world we constitute the great independent force of the Left.</p><p> “What contribution does this force make? It brings social reconstruction in a framework of liberty. We Socialists stand for a new society, but we cannot do without freedom.</p><p> “Unfortunately we have not the driving force of a reconstituted Socialist International to help us, but we have passion and the need for freedom on our side. This is a historic chance: throughout the world Socialism is now identical with human liberty. Do you know what that means? It means that everyone in the world who does not want to be pro-American or pro-Russian—that is, the vast majority of mankind—can all be brought on our side. In every country man’s longing for social reconstruction and freedom is a force, and we, who in our country have already mobilised this force and given it a programme of action, can also mobilise it internationally”.</p><p>Everywhere men want freedom and social security. One Great Power promises a new society, but men know that there is no freedom there. The other Great Power talks of freedom, but men doubt whether this is true freedom. Mankind wants neither one nor the other: it wants to be “neither Soviet nor American," as Leon Blum has said. Mankind wants something else, something positive —a third alternative. We are that third alternative. Are we to be unequal to our responsibility? Shall we lose heart and fail?</p><p>This is the choice before us: is the socialist movement to have its own policy, or is it to allow itself to be overwhelmed by the opposing power blocs, so that it loses its independence?</p><p>Of course, it is not enough to say that we are opposed to both blocs. A negative policy is no policy at all. Sitting on the fence, zig-zagging, and pettifogging theorising—that may be a Third Something, but it is certainly not a Third Force. Passively standing in the middle of the road would soon mean not standing at all, but being knocked down and run over.</p></div><div><head>How strong is the Third Force?</head><p>But are we capable of carrying out an independent policy? Have we strength enough to be a Third Force? Let us examine the question in the international field.</p><p>As Socialists we are all aware that the scientific, industrial and social developments of our time make a supra-national union of states an urgent necessity. In the age of radio, of jet-propelled aircraft, of atomic energy, in an age in which food and freedom are no longer national but international problems, the continued independent existence of nation-states on the nineteenth century pattern is an anachronism which the twentieth century must replace. The resolution of the conflict between the supra-national development of science and industry on the one hand and: out-of-date political organisation on the other is the historic mission of our generation.</p><p>It is a matter of life and death in the contemporary world—and the socialist movement, which first represented the principle of internationalism in the modern world, must be the force which finally accomplishes this historic mission.</p><p>During the last few decades, and especially since the end of the Second World War, the need for a supra-national organisation has been obvious. But how is it to be achieved? Instead of a process of internationalisation, there has been increased incorporation of small and medium nation-states, no longer capable of independence, into the power blocs of the Great Powers. National sovereignty is being surrendered in the process of polarisation now taking place in world politics: the Eastern bloc and the Marshall Plan for Western Europe. Instead of this false solution proposed by power politics, Socialists must present the right solution.</p><p>What can we learn from the experience of the United Nations? In so far as the veto does not paralyse the organisation altogether, it is just a battleground for the opposing Great Powers, each con-wavering position, the states which are not bound to either of the two blocs. These include the three less powerful Great Powers - Britain, France, and China, future great powers like India, important medium powers such as Australia and some of the South American countries, and almost all the countries of North-West Europe - in fact, the great majority of the countries of the world. Common action or co-operation among them is at present haphazard, without direction or organisation, depending on the moves and divisions between the two blocs. Socialists like Leon Blum, always a spirited supporter of the United Nations, long ago pointed out that here was the opportunity of bringing together and disunited and therefore powerless majority of the United Nations. Only democratic Socialism can undertake this task, for in the most important of these countries Socialists hold the leadership: the Third Force of democratic Socialism here faced with a task on a world scale. It can become a unifying, organising, ever-growing force within the framework of a world organisation.</p></div><div><head>The Third Force in France </head><p>In national as in international affairs the significance of the socialist movement's independent role is not to be assessed by whether the Socialist Party is strong as in Austria, Britain or the Scandinavian countries, or in a difficult position as at present in France, or weak as in some other countries.</p><p>It is true that in foreign affairs the British Labour Government, intent on the problems of socialist reconstruction at home, is not as strong, does not give as clear a lead, as we could wish. It is true that French Socialists are at present in a difficult position between the two opposing forces of world politics—though the collapse of the communist policy, which had increased the threat from the Right, may now give them a special responsibility and a possible chance of success.</p><p>Nevertheless, the idea of the Third Force has crystallised in at least one country—France. There the Third Force appears the resolutions of the Socialist Party Executive, in manifestos in newspaper headlines. Leon Blum has devoted numerous articles to the subject in the “Populaire’’; intellectuals of all shades of opinion have signed a manifesto acclaiming it. At the recent meeting of the Socialist Party National Council a number of speakers dealt with the subject and tried to define its purpose and tasks, and some dealt particularly with the question of extending the Third Force from France to the international field.</p><p>In France the Third Force signifies the co-operation of all forces standing between the Communists and the Gaullists, directed against and quite separate from both the movements now threatening democracy. In practice, the new group is supported by the Socialist Party, the Christian-Democrat MRP, the new non-communist trade union movement, sections of the old Radical Party, and non-party intellectuals of the Left and Centre. Great efforts are being made to build up a solid foundation among the masses like the Front Populaire of 1936—but this time minus the Communists. The Third Force is an attempt to save the Republic: it is the one way out.</p><p>So far it is not clear what organisational form the French Third Force will have in practice, or what political success it will have. All discussions about its programme have mainly concentrated on whether it should include economic planning and reconstruction as the foundation for democracy.</p><p>It is possible that this manifestation of the Third Force will have more effect in the maintenance of freedom than in social renewal: if this happens it would not fit our definition. It is possible that the Socialist Party, as the originator of the idea, will be able to infuse its own ideals into it and give it inspiration: if this happens the extension of the Third Force to other parties would still leave its essence the same. France, the country where political polarisation is the strongest, has in this, as in so many other respects, a special importance in Europe. What happens in France to-day, may happen to Europe to-morrow. France is the microcosm of the whole continent. We shall watch intently how the Third Force fares in parties other than the Socialist Party and among the broad mass of the people.</p></div><div><head>The Third Force and the International </head><p>We now come to the question which our political opponents ask us pityingly or mockingly, when attacking the Third Force: what about the Socialist International? Let us deal openly and frankly with this question.</p><p>When the Second World War ended, socialist parties left the underground movement and began to renew their international contacts, and so made it possible to consider the revival of the Socialist International. Two things were then clear and have since become even clearer. Firstly, the different experiences that each party had undergone and the different conditions in which each party has to work, have reduced what parties have in common to a very small compass; certain general principles and a few practical aims are all that is generally and firmly accepted. Secondly, all parties are convinced of the need for an international socialist policy, and wish to co-ordinate their actions in the international field. But all parties give priority to the need of domestic policy, and none is prepared to sacrifice national politics on the altar of general international principles.</p><p>If the Socialist International is to be rebuilt, it must be on these foundations. Any attempt to give the International a programme, even merely a declaration of principles, would be premature and bound to fail. Nor has such an attempt been undertaken, for principles shared by all socialist parties would have first of all to be worked out and accepted. At the last Conference in Antwerp the attempt to return to the former practice of passing broad resolutions on political questions may appear to constitute progress towards fuller co-operation, but in fact such resolutions can only be compromises which say little and commit no one. All the post-war international conferences have concentrated on organisational questions: who belongs to the International, who is admitted to conferences, what kind of permanent organisation is to develop? The question of what authority the organisation is to have will arise much later.</p></div><div><head>Our present problems </head><p>Yet it has become more and more obvious that the organisational problem is really bound up with one of the most decisive political questions concerning the International. Is it possible under present conditions for the socialist parties of Eastern Europe to continue their co-operation with other socialist parties, while at the same time denouncing them, under Communist pressure, as “Right-wing Socialists'’ and “Social traitors”? From the Communist point of view, the existence of socialist parties in countries inside the Soviet sphere of influence—not to mention these parties’ relations with socialist parties elsewhere—resulted from the policy of “democratic unity,” a tactic which has now been discarded. It is not the place here to discuss how socialist parties in the Eastern bloc got into this position or whether it was avoidable or not. However that may be, the decisive question is clearly whether these socialist parties have in fact, and not merely in words, an independent policy. The continued existence of the parties depends on the answer to this question. If there is no longer an independent socialist policy, in time there will be no independent party organisation. Only those who maintain the independence of the socialist movement - that means, the idea of the Third Force - can remain Socialists.</p><p>All this means, of course, that the political and organisational problem already mentioned is really the problem of the Third Force. The Socialist International is not the Third Force - but without a rally to the idea of the Third Force—but without a rally to the idea of the Third Force there can be no Socialist International.</p><p>This idea is, consciously or unconsciously, one of the few fundamental principles shared by all socialist parties one of the ideals and aims on which the Socialist International is based.</p><p>Consciously or unconsciously—that is the key phrase. It must be remembered that the history of the socialist movement gives other examples of an ideal or principle recognised by some parties as the sine qua non of membership of the socialist fellowship, and expressly denied by other parties, though they may in practice have followed it. The most famous instance of this is the theory of the class struggle. Karl Kautsky’s argument, recommending the admission to the International of the British labour movement, which expressly denied the class struggle, will be recalled: that the British put it into practice better than anyone else. It is no argument against the correctness of a policy to say that it is not formulated by the International or by individual parties, and there is no ground for scorn about it, either. As Marxists we knew in the past that the class struggle is the motive force of socialist activity everywhere in the world—even if it is not mentioned in the British Labour Party’s programme. We also knew that what then united all socialist parties without exception was the recognition of the necessity for an independent policy of the working class. It was this necessity which created the Labour Party in Britain, and which is to-day in the process of changing the American trade union movement. Have we forgotten all that to-day, when this necessity must be recognised in international as well as national politics?</p><p>To be a Socialist means to have faith. To be a Socialist means to pursue an independent policy of freedom and reform—opposed to any powers or blocs, national or international. To be a Socialist means to know that this independent policy incorporates the objective needs of social progress as well as the subjective aspirations of mankind—an ideal which cynics now call an illusion, but which to-morrow will be a Force whose triumph is assured.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>