<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Holland’s Economic position</title>
         <author>G.M.Nederhorst</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Holland’s Economic position</title>
            <author>G.M.Nederhorst</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Dutch" party="Dutch Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Although remarkable progress has been made since the war economic recovery in the Netherlands is still meeting difficulties’ and production has only just regained the 1938 level.</p><p>The factors which obstruct recovery fall into two classes: long-term and short-term. Among the former must be mentioned firstly the elimination of Germany as both supplier and consumer. The importance of Germany in Dutch economy before the war may be judged by the fact that in 1938 Germany supplied 21.3 per cent, of Dutch imports and took 14.9 per cent of Dutch exports. The comparable figures in 1946 were 2.6 per cent and 6.7 per cent respectively.</p><p>A second obstacle to recovery is the situation in Indonesia. In addition to the loss of valuable supplies of raw materials and of a large market for exports, the present disturbances in Indonesia are causing a great drain on national income in the form of military expenditure. It is estimated that reconstruction in Indonesia costs 300 million guilders, military expenditure another 300 millions, while the loss of income amounts to 600 millions—a total of 1,200 million guilders at present values.</p><p>To these two special factors must, of course, be added the worldwide changes in agricultural and industrial conditions resulting from the war, which have, of course, affected all countries.</p><p>Less permanent factors which hinder reconstruction include the shortage of both skilled workers and women workers; the decline in individual output, which may be partially due to the widespread deterioration in morale as a result of occupation and war, and as a reaction to liberation; the shortage of raw materials, especially timber, and lastly and most important, the dollar shortage.</p><div><head>The task of reconstruction </head><p>All this means that reconstruction has still not advanced sufficiently and that Holland is still very much dependent on foreign aid. How is the Dutch economy to be revived, so that living standards are improved, the need for foreign aid reduced, and the foundations laid for a progressive socialist society?</p><p>The main tasks to be accomplished are firstly, industrialisation of he country, which even before the war was already lagging behind in comparison with the increase in population. The need for new capital investment will of course set a definite limit on the rise in the standard of living for a number of years. Secondly, it will be necessary to build up new trade relations to replace destroyed by the war and its aftermath. To achieve this the customs union with Belgium must be transformed into an economic union, and steps taken to bring other countries into it - France and Britain in the first place. It will also be necessary to stimulate trade with Eastern Europe, no matter what the political and ideological differences may be, at the same time giving the strongest possible support to the Marshall plan as the best means of strengthening the European economy. Finally, Holland must attempt to take Germany's place in the trade of the countries which Germany formerly supplied (for example China and Latin America), and also try to raise the economic level of Germany without at the same time strengthening it as a political power.</p><p>What are the prospects for success? What is the present position?</p></div><div><head>Need for increased output </head><p>Notwithstanding the steady rise in industrial and agricultural production, the Dutch economic position is still weak compared with other countries. Industrial production in March 1947, for example, was only 89% of the figure for 1937; in Belgium the figure was 94%, in Norway 114%, and in the U.S.A. 165%. Similarly Holland’s share in the total world export trade dropped from 2.7% of a total of 40 thousand guilders in 1938 to 1.6% of a total of 110 thousand million guilders in 1947. (Only 45% of imports in 1947 will be covered by exports, instead of 74% in 1938). As a result Holland’s deficit in its balance of payments for 1947 will probably amount to about 2,000 million guilders.</p><p>The need for increased exports is obviously urgent, and it is true that Dutch export figures are showing improvement. But compared with other European exporting countries Holland is lagging behind both in volume and in value.</p><p>Price increases affect imports more than exports, so that the deficit is continually increasing. To bridge the gap overseas assets have been liquidated. For example, out of a total of 1,900 million guilders’ worth of American shares. 280 millions were sold in 1947, together with a further 335 millions of other assets.</p><p>It is obvious from these figures that more production and more exports are urgently needed. And increased production means increase output from every worker. In addition, careful watch must be kept on the relation between Dutch prices and those of other exporting countries. For example, Britain is an important competitor in industrial exports, and Dutch wages and costs will have to conform to British standards in order to compete, while with agricultural products costs in Denmark and the British Dominions must be considered.</p><p>But the most important and most urgent need of all is increased output. At present productivity is still not enough to maintain a decent standard of living. In the first quarter of 1947, for example, output was only two thirds of that of the corresponding period of 1938. Increase output depends mainly on the efforts of the workers themselves, but the workers must see some personal benefit in the form of higher wages or lower prices. Reduction of subsidies on essential consumer goods as a result of increased output may be a good thing from the point of view of the national budget but bad from the point of view of the workers. The confidence and willing co-operation of the workers must be won. The fear that increased production may mean the dismissal of redundant workers must be removed. Inflated profits and high dividends cause discontent among workers, especially if their wages do not increase in proportion. There must be more publicity about profits and dividends, and more consultation with the workers in the management of industry.</p></div><div><head>Wages and prices </head><p>In Holland an attempt is made at a national wages policy, though this needs considerable improvement. Redistribution of incomes, for example, may become necessary to prevent the lowest incomes from falling below the minimum cost of living, while at the same time maintaining enough difference between wage rates to stimulate effort and reward skill. The wage system should be constantly reviewed. At present it risks becoming unbalanced because of the labour shortage. As long as this shortage exists the upward pressure on wages will remain. But in spite of this lack of balance, the planned wages policy has succeeded in maintaining the purchasing power of wages at roughly the same level and so prevented wildly inflationary wage movements.</p><p>Discontent among workers is caused partly by the ever-present gap between wages and prices, and partly by the differences between some wage-rates and others, caused by uneven wage-fixing. The ceiling on wages is threatened in many ways. There is the fact that it has not been applied in the same way to all workers. While civil servants’ salaries remain unchanged, private businesses often pay wages or illegal bonuses far exceeding the official standard. Again, if dividends are high, the worker is unwilling to accept a ceiling on wages.</p><p>But one of the main causes of the tendency of wage continue rising is the shortage of labour. This shortage, which has been estimated at about 300,000 workers, may be just a temporary phenomenon which can be removed by a better organisation of technical training. On the other hands, it is possible that we are confronted here with a fundamental flaw in our social structure. Even before the war the increase in the number of workers did not keep pace with the increase in the population as a whole, for there was already too small a rise in the numbers of manual workers. Measures are obviously needed to regulate the labour market in order to remove this shortage.</p><p>To improve the workers’ standard of living there is a choice of two policies to raise wages or to lower prices. The second is to be preferred because lower prices benefit pensioners and other fixed-income groups, because they automatically involve state control and therefore reinforce labour’s right to take part in management, and because they help the export drive. The government has so far followed this policy in spite of the greater mass appeal and simpler administrative problems of higher wages, but its programme has not completely readied expectations. Insufficient control over production, so that too many luxury goods are being manufactured instead of cheap mass-production goods; rising prices of raw materials in the world market; inadequate subsidies on some essentials; too little standardisation and too many competing models of the same article; a lack of energy in introducing the “utility” system, especially in textiles; controls which are too loose in some respects and too rigid in others; ineffective measures against infringement of controls—these arc some of the reasons for the failure of the government’s price policy.</p><p>The question of subsidies is particularly important. Generally speaking, subsidies on essential consumer goods are much lower in Holland than in surrounding countries; 60 guilders a year per head of the population in Holland against 115 guilders in Britain and 110 guilders in Belgium.</p></div><div><head>Policy for profits and investments</head><p>Industrial profits are still unduly high, and as we have seen, have an adverse effect on workers’ output. Public control over profits is essential in Holland’s present economic position; it is also necessary, of course, as part of the groundwork of a planned economy. At present, enterprises are allowed to declare dividends without publishing the actual profit on which the dividend is calculated. This discretion is liable to abuse and should be abolished.</p><p>Dividends must be limited, and any surplus profits should be directed into investment through the Reconstruction Bank. The effect of swollen dividends on wages and prices, and the consequent repercussions on the entire economic system, cannot be exaggerated. Similarly the need for a great increase in investments would also be sufficient argument in itself in favour of control over dividends.</p><p>The necessary investment for reconstruction in the years 1946-52 has been estimated at 22,100 million guilders, exclusive of government spending which amounted to 2.400 million guilders in 1947. It is obviously necessary that this enormous sum be provided as far as possible out of Dutch resources. If, for example, reconstruction could be financed out of an excess of exports over imports the foundations of Holland’s future prosperity would have been well laid. But this is not possible at present, and in the meantime more than 13 per cent of the national income has to be saved to establish economic recovery. As taxes are gradually removing large private incomes as a source of saving, public concerns and the state must be the main source of investments—which means a further tendency to socialisation of production.</p></div><div><head>Planned production </head><p>Enough has been said to show that economic recovery in the Netherlands is not possible without a planned economy. A central planning office does exist and a production plan has been published, but the idea of planning has not yet taken root in Dutch economic life. Present policy—called economic planning—has many faults, and cannot yet be the basis of a future planned economy. The official plan itself is not a success and shows much needless duplication. More important, there is no provision for enforcing production-only recommendations to individual enterprises. The whole scheme has been looked on in official circles as a temporary expedient, with the result that capable men have been unwilling to take jobs on the planning staff. Lastly, the lack of organisation and inadequate representation of consumers and workers has meant that government policy is too much dominated by private interests. All this must be changed: a carefully thought-out and well-directed plan is essential for Holland’s prosperity.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>