<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Socialist Movement in Greece</title>
         <author>A.Gregoroyannis</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Socialist Movement in Greece</title>
            <author>A.Gregoroyannis</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Greek" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Before the Second World War there was strictly speaking, no socialist movement in Greece. Only a small section of the working class was politically conscious and that section was under Communist influence. The Socialist Party at that time was a group small in numbers and without political influence.</p><p>It was only during the German occupation that the socialist movement began to develop. While the ruling class collaborated with the enemy, and the old bourgeois parties lapsed into shameful inaction, a great resistance movement arose. This movement became more and more political in inspiration and threw up large numbers of men with militant socialist ideals who helped to found underground socialist groups. After liberation these organisations were successfully united to form the Greek Socialist Party (ELD).</p><p>There is therefore a great difference in origin between socialism in Greece and socialism in the rest of Europe. “Western” socialism was an outcome of capitalist development and existed as a political movement before the rise of Communism. In Greece, on the other hand, it was during the disintegration of capitalism that socialism became a political force for the first time, after Communism had already left its mark on the working class movement. For this reason, the new socialist movement in Greece cannot follow the exact pattern of the West. The Greek Socialist Party has neither the tradition, nor the massive Trade Union organisation which are the strength of Western socialist parties. It is essentially an avant-garde organisation whose general political influence is many times greater than its organised strength.</p><p>Within the Greek Socialist Party may also be found the beginnings of a new type of working-class political organisation, which is quite different from both Social-Democracy and Leninism. The Party considers reformist Social-Democracy out-of-date, both politically and organisationally; at the same time it regards Leninism as the crystallisation of the needs of the working-class struggle in an extremely backward country, and therefore not a model for the international working-class. The long experience of the interwar years revealed the failures of both reformist Social-Democracy and dogmatic Communism: the working-class movement’s main ideological problem is to synthesise the two lines of thought—which leads to the conception of an avant-garde party, well disciplined and homogeneous, able to take the lead but at the same time more democratic than Communist parties have ever been. Historically, this conception is derived chiefly from Rosa Luxembourg.</p><div><head>The social basis of the movement </head><p>Since the industrialisation of Greece in the 1920's, the working-class has formed an important section of the population, and a second generation of industrial workers has already appeared, in which the petit bourgeois and peasant tradition, which was still active in the earlier generation, no longer exists. Class consciousness can thus develop more freely. The so-called middle classes too, are extremely numerous in Greece, and form an important factor in the political struggle. The land reform already carried out means that the overwhelming majority of the rural population are poor peasants, while in the large towns there is a very large number of “white-collar workers” and people of the professional class employed in finance and commerce. These peasants and petit bourgeois are exploited by Greek capitalism in its monopolist form, as well as by foreign capital, so that the standard of life of most of this class is no higher than that of the industrial workers. On the other hand the Greek ruling-classes are intellectually and politically decadent, while working-class and middle-class political consciousness is relatively advanced. In general there is an anticapitalist feeling among the working population very favourable for the development of a socialist movement.</p><p>At present it is the Communist Party which has profited most from the people’s anti-capitalist orientation. The Communist Party was formed in the inter-war years, and because of its superior organisation was able to attract the majority of those who took part in the resistance movement. Only a very small fraction were definitely won over, however, for it was above all a belief in democratic ideals and social justice which led most people into the resistance. The more this democratic faith crystallises into political consciousness, the more the progressive elements among the people will see that the democratic ideal is most clearly expressed in the socialist movement.</p><p>It must be remembered, however, that, while the ruling-classes inside Greece are becoming weaker and weaker, world imperialism is more and more taking its place in the struggle. If the Greek bourgeoisie had not had the support of British imperialism in 1944 and American imperialism at present, it could not have survived.</p><p>The present regime in Greece is historically out-of-date and economically parasitic and can only survive with the support of world imperialism. This is why the struggle against imperialism. This is why the struggle against imperialism in Greece is not the task of the Communist Party alone, but a question which concerns the whole people.</p></div><div><head>The programme of Greek socialism </head><p>The programme of Greek Socialism is based on the fundamental idea that the bourgeois democratic period is over, and that the disintegration of capitalism makes socialism necessary. The Party’s programme is therefore essentially socialist, and includes a number of measures to facilitate the transition to a planned society.</p><p>In the economic field the programme does not call for complete collectivism. The large number of small-holdings and small-scale industries, as well as the party's need for support from the peasants and lower middle classes, does not allow such a solution. The programme advocates the creation of a mixed economy with two sectors: one public and the other private. The public sector will comprise those enterprises which should be nationalised: banks, insurance companies, mines, heavy industry, transport, foreign trade, and food distribution. The private sector will consist of small-scale agriculture, and industry, and individual initiative will be made socially useful by the development of co-operative societies. The whole economy will be integrated in a single plan. In this way the predominance of the bourgeoisie will be definitely abolished, while the economy will become planned without having to undergo disturbances which might provoke the middle-classes to rise against the socialist revolution. In the political field the programme is based on the idea of a democratic social revolution. This does not rule out the possibility of violence (especially since the rise of fascism), but the Party sees the social revolution as the result of the conscious will and action of the great majority of the people. The role of the avant garde party is to lead this movement and not to disperse its revolutionary fervour in a coup d’état. The same holds good for the post-revolutionary period. The Greek Socialist Party stands for a democratic regime—against the monopoly of political power by any single party.</p></div><div><head>The present struggle </head><p>Conditions to-day are unfavourable for the socialist movement in Greece. The lack of cadres prevents the development of the people’s movement. Counter-revolution was unleashed after the crushing of the popular rising of December 1944, and terror against the workers and the Left in general, as well as the new partisan movement which resulted from it, have only increased the confusion. A new political movement like the Socialist Party, in order to consolidate and extend its influence, needs a more normal political atmosphere than that which exists at present in Greece.</p><p>It is widely believed that the counter-revolutionary measures in Greece are directed exclusively against the Communist Party and that the whole political struggle is reduced to a duel between the Right and the Communists. Nothing is further from the truth. Counter-revolution in Greece is directed with equal fury against socialists and other progressive elements, and against the entire working-class. All Socialist Party district organisations have been dissolved except those in the three large towns and in Crete. Many of our supporters are working underground. The socialist press cannot he distributed in the provinces. Trade union organisations have also been dissolved and a very large number of socialists and trade unionists sent to prison or into exile. At the same time, the organisations which form the EAM (which is directed by the Communist Party) contain a considerable number of non-communist elements, who stay in this organisation because of counter-revolutionary pressure and because they have no means of democratic political action.</p><p>In general terms the fate of the Socialist movement depends on the situation in the country as a whole; only if Greece returns to democracy in the near future, will the socialist movement become an important factor in the country’s political life.</p></div><div><head>Immediate objectives </head><p>The whole Greek socialist effort is concentrated, for the present, on the struggle for democracy. Confronted with the prolonged political and national crisis, Socialists maintain that there is only one solution: a return to democracy. In consequence, the Party has always opposed the succession of Right-wing governments based on fraudulent elections—a regime of legalised counter-revolution, reintroduced into the country by fascist legislation, directed against the working-class and supported by a reactionary government machine. It is for this reason that the Party was forced (not without regret) to take a stand against the policy of the British Labour Government, which failed to lead Greece towards democracy as it intended. In the same way the Socialist Party now opposes American intervention whose object is to prop up a bankrupt bourgeois system.</p><p>The Communist-directed partisan movement is the direct result of a terror which has forced large numbers of men to leave home and take refuge in the mountains. The movement is directed against counter-revolution, but from the socialist point of view it cannot be allowed to develop into another dictatorship. The only real solution is a return to democracy which can be brought about by a general amnesty, the restoration of individual and trade union liberties, the weeding-out of reactionary elements from the army and police, and free elections. Recent political developments in Greece have only emphasised the danger. American intervention and the formation under American pressure of a Monarchist-Liberal Coalition have not succeeded in re-establishing peace and order. One reason is that the policy of persecution of all popular forces still continues, so that tension is growing. The fact that the Communist Parry has formed a government based on the partisans is, at least partly, the result of internal developments in Greece.</p><p>Faced with this situation, Greek Socialists maintain that an agreement between the two opposing camps is more necessary than ever as the only means of restoring democratic institutions. But it is clear that the Greek question is less and less a purely internal affair and more and more an international problem. This means unfortunately, that a democratic solution in Greece cannot be brought about by efforts within the country.</p><p>Because of the international interests at work in the country only a favourable evolution of the international situation will allow Greece to find the democratic path. In addition, the return of peaceful conditions inside Greece would bring about a slackening of international tension, since Greece at present, because of its strategic position and the bitterness of its internal struggle, has become one of the principal points of friction between the Great Powers.</p><p>The more the Greek question becomes an international one, the more Greek socialists look towards world socialism. World socialism should be the most important factor in an international movement for peace, working in the interest of workers everywhere. In Greece as in many other countries, a great deal of the present distress can be attributed directly or indirectly to what world socialism left undone in the past. We must hope that what was not done yesterday will be done to-morrow, for if the inadequacy of international socialist policy continues it will no longer be a question of trouble in single unfortunate countries, but of a new world catastrophe. In fact, the fate of socialism in Greece depends on the steps taken by the international socialist movement to bring progress and peace to the world.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>