<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Social revolution in Hungary</title>
         <author>Anonymous(Hungarian)</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Social revolution in Hungary</title>
            <author>Anonymous(Hungarian)</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>March-May 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.4</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Hungarian" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>In 1948 Hungary celebrates the hundredth anniversary of the struggle for national liberation. On 15th March, 1848, the battle for freedom of the press was won. The people forced the Hapsburgs to call an elected parliament with a responsible government chosen not by the king but by parliament. The peasants were at last freed from serfdom.</p><p>Hungary’s struggle for liberation was crushed in 1840 by the Hapsburgs with the help of Tsarist Russia. Serfdom remained a thing of the past, but landed feudalism returned to power. The peasants were no longer serfs, but they were still politically and economically oppressed by the landowners, just as they had been before 1848.</p><p>After the defeat in the First World War the October Revolution of 1918 made another attempt to destroy feudalism. This attempt also failed, because counter-revolution aided by the Entente powers was victorious. The Horthy regime was a period of even more savage oppression of peasants and workers.</p><div><head>Land reform </head><p>The Red Army’s victory in 1945 brought liberation and the opportunity of building democracy in Hungary, and so of completing the task begun in 1848, by bringing about the final liberation of the peasants.</p><p>Feudalism in Hungary has at last been destroyed. A thousand- year old system came to an end with the division of the great estates and the democratic distribution of land. Before land reform 302 big landowners owned 3.5 million hold (2 hold=slightly more than 1 hectare). More than 50 per cent, of the total cultivated land was occupied by large and medium estates of more than 100 hold. Since land reform the large estates have completely vanished. Owners of estates of over 100 hold to-day possess, not 50 per cent, of the total cultivated area as in 1945, but only 4 per cent. Owners of estates up to 20 hold of land possess 56 per cent, and up to 30 hold 83.5 per cent.      </p><p>Land reform completely revolutionised Hungary s social structure—for the first time in history. 642,342 peasants received 3.3 million hold of land, so that agriculture in Hungary to-day is mainly composed of small landowners. The big land-owning class of feudal magnates has been uprooted, and the country's chief problem, the peasant question, solved.</p></div><div><head>Nationalisation</head><p>The social revolution was not carried out in agriculture alone; it spread to other sectors of Hungary’s economy. Before 1945, industrial manufacture was exclusively controlled by large-scale capitalism. To-day, manufactures employ 390,000 workers, of whom about 50 per cent, are employed by the state, by local authorities, or in co-operative undertakings. In individual industries this percentage is engineering—state-owned undertakings employ 105,000 or 85 per cent, of the total workers, and private concerns only 12 per cent. In electricity supply the position is even better: 100 per cent, of the workers are employed in undertakings owned by the state or by local authorities. Food production industries have 75 per cent, or 33,000 of the total workers in state-owned concerns. Of course, there are still some industries where conditions are different: for example, in light industry, especially textiles, leather, rubber, and chemicals, the great majority of all undertakings are still in private hands.</p><p>In the mining industry, 3,500 workers are employed by private firms, while 63,500 are working in the state-owned coal mines.</p><p>Altogether, mining and industry employ 453,000 workers, of whom 253,000 are in publicly, owned concerns—that is, this sector of even more in favour of publicly owned enterprises. In the most highly developed industry—iron and steel and industry employs 56 per cent of workers. It must be added that according to official figures, 85 per cent of heavy industry is publicly owned, which is very favourable from the point of view of the Hungarian people. On the other hand, 72 per cent, of light industry remains in private hands, and this sector of industry is very important in the daily life of the people. This position means that the prices of consumer goods such as textiles and clothes, and shoes are very high in proportion to wages.</p><p>Transport, the third sector of industry, is entirely nationalised: railways, shipping, air-lines. In industry, mining and transport, 400000 of the total of 600,000 workers are employed by publicly-owned concerns, and only 200,000 by private enterprise.</p></div><div><head>Finance and trade </head><p>On January 1, 1947, financial credit also came under state control. The National Bank and the largest private banks were taken over by the state, and thus social reform in Hungary made a big step forward. Eighty per cent of capital issues are held by the banks belonging to the state or to other public authorities. Ninety-two per cent, of industrial accounts were taken over with these banks. Seventy-five per cent, of the capital of all banks is now in the hands of the nationalised banks.</p><p>In trade the position reveals many inconsistencies. Over 70 per cent, of foreign trade is in private hands, and at most 25—30 per cent, controlled by national authorities. Internal trade is almost exclusively carried out by private capital or by small traders. There are also tens of thousands of small shopkeepers who own and manage their own businesses.</p><p>In addition, since agriculture is now divided into small estates, hundreds of thousands of peasants now carry on business as small traders.</p></div><div><head>The co-operative movement </head><p>In trade and distribution as well as in agriculture there is a great campaign to strengthen weaker elements by forming co-operative organisations, which will ensure the economic and social betterment of the “little man.” Co-operatives ought only to be formed voluntarily, without any outside pressure. Hungarians, and especially Hungarian peasants, are above all individualists, and for this reason it has been laid down by law that voluntary association is the essential feature of co-operative undertakings. As a result of this freedom of choice the co-operative movement has made splendid progress in the last two years.</p></div><div><head>Financial stabilisation</head><p>What has so far been achieved in Hungary becomes even more noteworthy when one remembers that at the end of the war the country was despoiled, ravaged and destroyed. War raged in Hungary for almost five months. In the capital itself there were 54 days of bitter hand-to-hand fighting which destroyed a third of the town. Factories wore reduced to rubble: almost every bridge in the country was destroyed; raw materials, machines, millions of cattle, and uncounted other goods were looted by the Nazis or the Arrow-cross Fascists. The day the war ended, Budapest was without water, gas, electricity, and transport.</p><p>Yet in spite of these terrible conditions the Hungarian people— peasants, workers and intellectuals—set to work, though without adequate food and clothing, and in two and a half years accomplished a greater part of the necessary work of reconstruction. Production had to be increased in a period when inflation was rampant—the worst inflation in European history. Millions, then billions and more billions of bank-notes were printed and circulated. No one could buy even essentials out of wages. But still the work went on.</p><p>The Hungarian people understood that only increased production of goods could put an end to inflation. After a year and a half stabilisation became possible and was decided on, and on August 1, 1946, the new currency was introduced. In spite of the difficult international economic situation, stabilisation was successful, and by the end of 1947 it was clear that production was far beyond expectations. Prices of essential consumer goods had fallen; the national budget was balanced; foreign trade amounted to 2,400 million forint by the end of 1947. Great economies had been effected in administration: the number of civil servants had been reduced by 30 per cent, and in the financial year 1946-47 out of a total state expenditure of 4,200 million forint there was an estimated deficit of only 257 millions. In the year 1947-48 this deficit had disappeared; there is a surplus, in spite of the enormous investments called for in the first year of the Three-Year Plan.</p></div><div><head>The three-year plan</head><p>The Three-Year Plan covers the period from August 1, 1947, to August 1, 1950, and calls for a total of 6,585 million forint of capital investment. This enormous sum will be provided not by foreign aid, but out of the gradual increase in production achieved by the Hungarian people themselves. The target of the plan is to reach in all sectors of the national economy—agriculture, industry and mining - about 110 per cent of the level of 1938; similarly the people's standard of living is also to be 110 per cent, of the 1938 level.</p><p>In considering this target figure it must be remembered that when the currency was finally stabilised, those on whom the heaviest tasks of the plan will fall—workers, peasants, and intellectuals—were at a standard of living only about half that of before the war.</p><p>Of the total investment envisaged by the Three-Year Plan, 1,745 million forint are ear-marked for industry, with special weight given to machine tools and electric power.  </p><p>It should be noted that by the end of 1947, mining, iron and machinery production already surpassed the planned level.</p></div><div><head>The political situation </head><p>There is no doubt that the successes already gained would have been impossible without a coalition government. Co-operation of all parties and of all groups of workers was essential for success. Inside the coalition it was the two workers’ parties—Social Democrats and Communists—which provided the driving force.</p><p>It cannot be denied that conditions in Hungary, despite all the government's efforts are still far from the democratic ideal, but it should not be forgotten that the country has never had democratic rule, and that the people have no democratic traditions or education.  Only a small fraction of the population  - led by the Social-Democratic Party fought for democracy against the tyranny of the Horthy régime. Now democracy has to be built up, and for this one thing above all is necessary: people must be educated as democrats; and this in a country where there never has been any democracy, a country which during the war was nazified and oppressed, and after the war occupied for two and a half years, a country where has always been poverty and misery.       </p><p>The immense task of constructing democracy in Hungary can only succeed in a world at peace. If peace is preserved - and it must be preserved - Hungary will become a true democracy. It is no exaggeration to say that this gradual development towards democracy depends on the attitude and action of the Hungarian Social-Democratic Party. The responsibility is there; we must hope that the party will be equal to it.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>