<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
         <author>Editorial Staff</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
            <author>Editorial Staff</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>It was fitting that the fifth International Socialist Conference on 4-7 June should take place in Vienna. The Austrian Party has always been one of the most distinguished members of the international socialist movement. In the years between the wars, “Red Vienna” was an inspiration to socialists throughout the world—an example of what socialists could do if they were given the opportunity and the power. When the clerical fascism of Dollfuss attacked in 1934, the Austrian socialists did not submit, but went down fighting. The blocks of workers’ flats at the Karl-Marx-Hof still bear the marks of the shelling they suffered then.</p><p>To-day, three years after the end of the war, Austria is still occupied; the so-called Iron Curtain runs west of Vienna. But in spite of all the difficulties, Vienna is once more “Red Vienna,” and the Austrian Socialist Party the strongest party in the country. All who were at the Conference were impressed by the great demonstration, when thousands of Austrians assembled at the Rathaus-platz to hear speeches from representatives of the various socialist parties.</p><p>It was in this setting that the International Socialist Conference reaffirmed the principles of democratic socialism in the following declaration:</p><p>"The people of the world had expected that after the fall of fascism democracy would be established in Europe; this hope has been disappointed. In some countries fascism has persisted and in others it is about to be re-created. In other countries forms of government have been installed under Soviet political and economic pressure calling themselves ‘People’s Democracies,’ but being in fact dictatorships.</p><p> “Politically, these governments are the negation of all civic rights and of the fundamental freedoms. Economically, they are inclined to substitute state-capitalism for private capitalism. They betray both democracy and socialism which they claim to represent.</p><p> “The International Socialist Conference meeting in Vienna, declares that Socialism, being inseparable from political democracy, aims at completing the latter by economic democracy; this is its fundamental objective.</p><p> “Therefore:</p><p>I. The parties represented at this Conference will stand together in their fight for the preservation and extension of political democracy. They undertake to respect its principles in their own organisations and in all their activities. They also undertake to defend Human Rights and to insist on their observance, nationally and internationally.</p><p>"They are opposed to the one-party state and to any system of government based on it.</p><p>"They consider that political democracy implies recognition of the dignity of the human personality, which finds expression in: freedom of conscience opinion and speech; free access to all sources of information, freedom of association; legal security and protection against the arbitrary action of individuals or of society: equality before the law, free from any political interference; complete freedom and security of elections; the right of opposition; political and juridical equality of all citizens irrespective of class, race or sex.</p><p>"II. In order to complete political democracy by economic democracy the socialist parties maintain that legislative changes must be accompanied by a thorough reform of public administration which must be freed from all bureaucratic methods so as to evolve new forms of a truly democratic system.</p><p> “III. All people must be entitled to participate in the wealth of society by equal access to all economic, spiritual and cultural values of mankind.</p><p> “IV. The Conference is of opinion that economic security is one of the fundamental rights of mankind and that the spiritual and political emancipation of people is dependent on their economic liberation. Democratic socialism combines freedom of the individual with planned economy.”</p><div><head>The German question</head><p>Socialists—and indeed people of all political parties—are deeply concerned with the problem of Germany, especially the question of the Ruhr, the greatest industrial concentration in Europe. Recovery in Western Europe is impossible without the contribution which this enormous complex of economic power could make. On the other hand, the heavy industries of the Ruhr have been the key to Germany's war effort, the basis of two attempts to dominate Europe and the world. It is this dilemma—how to expand German production to help European recovery while preventing the industrial potential from threatening peace and security—which beset the recent six-power conversations on the German question. It also overshadowed the discussions at the meeting of European Socialist parties in Paris in April and the International Socialist Conference in Vienna.</p><p>The Vienna Conference met before the six-power recommendations were published. But it was able to reach unanimous agreement on the following resolution:	</p><p> “The reintegration of Germany into Europe's productive effort and into the world community from which Nazi barbarism had excluded her is one of the essential conditions for the effective reconstruction of our continent, for the re-establishment of the balance of forces in Europe, for raising the standard of life of the European peoples and for the recovery by Europe of a place in world economy worthy of her means and capacity.	</p><p>"The division of Germany into a number of small political entities would be incompatible with the unification of Europe at which we are aiming. Convinced that any attempt to use the "right of conquest” in order to prevent the German people from achieving the unity to which they aspire would inevitably encourage a dangerous spirit of nationalism, the International Socialist Conference believes that a Germany, which is unified and made democratic on the basis of a federal system freely accepted by the German people in which Prussia no longer plays a predominant part, will constitute a step towards peace.</p><p>"The Conference expresses the desire and the hope that the four occupying powers will find a basis of agreement capable of preventing the final division of Germany and with her of the whole Continent.</p><p>"Meanwhile, in the absence of such agreement, the International Socialist Conference, although it does not yet know the full official text of the six-power agreement reached in London concerning the Ruhr, welcomes with satisfaction the fact that agreement has been reached as a first practical step towards a united Europe.</p><p> “The Conference urges that the composition and functions of any International Commission for the Ruhr and the character of the control it exercises should be such as to ensure the security of all peoples and the fulfilment of the principles which inspire the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation, so that its work can provide an example of that constructive co-operation for the common good on which a European union must depend.</p><p> “The Conference declares its profound conviction that it would be greatly in the interests of European peace and prosperity if the German people decided for the social-democratic policy of putting the basic industries of the Ruhr under public ownership and a socialist control. Under no circumstances must these industries be allowed to return to private capitalists of any nation.</p><p> “Its examination of the Ruhr problem leaves the Conference more than ever convinced that it is necessary and urgent to put the major sources of economic power in Europe under international control. It therefore decided to set up a commission to continue studying the problem and to report its findings to a future meeting."</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>