<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The problem of the Ruhr</title>
         <author>Leon Blum</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The problem of the Ruhr</title>
            <author>Leon Blum</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="French" party="SFIO"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The recommendations reached in London by the representative of the six powers -USA, Great Britain, France and the Benelux countries —have been officially published. I am going to say, quite frankly, what I think about these recommendations, though I must admit that my point of view is quite different from that of many of my colleagues. Most of those who defend the agreement are disillusioned and resigned. “What can you expect?" they say. “In the end agreement has been reached in London, after weeks and weeks of discussions between nations which started from quite opposing viewpoints. Each contributed something. The agreement is a bargain, and a bargain is never entirely satisfactory to everyone. The others have given way to us on certain points; we have had to give way on others. The main point is to decide whether a correct balance has been achieved between profit and loss, between what we have agreed to and what others have agreed to.”</p><p>I do not like this kind of calculation, as if France had a special interest in the German question. France is of course interested, and interested to the highest degree, but it is not a selfish interest. It is not a question whether the London agreement represents profit or loss, defeat or victory for the French. The different facts of the problem and the proposed solution must be examined impartially as they affect the wider problems of Europe's economy and world peace.</p><p>I shall begin with the question dealt with in the appendix to the six-power declaration under the heading “International Control of the Ruhr," which I intend to examine, as I have said, without asking whether the proposed solution is the result of concessions by one side or the other, but in order to see what it is worth in itself. As socialists, we have always attached particular importance to this aspect of the German problem. As long ago as May, 1946, the International Socialist Conference at Clacton put it in first place on its agenda, and since then I have thought and written a great deal about the question. Instead of territorial separation of the Ruhr from the rest of Germany—an idea which is finally but definitely abandoned—I have repeatedly proposed “international nationalisation” of the industrial area of North Rhine-Westphalia. The Marshall Plan, one of whose inevitable consequences will be the gradual return of Germany’s former level of productivity strengthens my proposal, for as German industrial potential increases, a system of control designed to confine its use to purposes will obviously become more and more necessary.</p><div><head> “International nationalisation” </head><p>International nationalisation as I conceive it would consist three phases: first, expropriation of the former German owners who connived at Nazi aggression, who are mostly listed as war criminals, and to whom the Ruhr workers chiefly object, as recent strikes have shown; then socialisation, for there can be no question of eliminating the old owners in order to transfer ownership to other individuals: lastly, establishment of an international cooperative or of an international authority with effective control over all industries, though any profits would still go to the German people, except for whatever reparations might be due.</p><p>In the London declaration there is no mention of either expropriation or socialisation, but there should be no misapprehensions about that. Expropriation and socialisation were proposed by France; if they are not mentioned in the agreement, it should not therefore be concluded that the French representatives met opposition from the British and Americans on this point. The Anglo-American attitude is that measures like expropriation and socialisation should be the responsibility of the future German government and not of the allied authorities, and that they would be more effective if they were freely decided than if they seemed to be imposed from outside. The U.S.A. and Great Britain add that, far from being opposed to the idea, they would, if occasion arose, use their influence on the future German government or on the German federal state governments to advise in favour of it. Denis Healey, the International Secretary of the Labour Party, stated this at the Vienna Conference, and I may add that in a recent conversation with a friend who I know is well-informed about American official views, I learnt that the State Department in Washington holds similar views.</p><p>What does the Anglo-American plan mean? It is attractive, but is it the most effective? That can only be judged from results. I think it very probable that the German assemblies would vote for expropriation, which would in fact be all the better for being voted by the Germans themselves. Would they vote for socialisation? It is very possible—our German Social-Democratic comrades would certainly support it. But it seems to me very doubtful whether a German assembly would vote for socialisation under an international co-operative or an international authority. It would be much more likely to do so for the benefit of the Reich or the regional authorities.      </p><p>The plan adopted at London, therefore, implies a solution which is no "international nationalisation", but socialisation under the Reich or the Länder. I do not consider this kind of socialisation out of question, but there must be one safeguard - there must be real control by an international authority. The London agreement does provide for a system of international control. But what is it worth?      </p><p>The Allied representatives foresee two successive periods: the first, called the "control period" which covers the time during which sovereignty in Germany remains in the hands of the occupying powers, and a second period following the first. The international authority for the Ruhr is to be set up and start functioning immediately—-this is one of the points which the French are said to have gamed. During the control period,” therefore, there are to be two different authorities existing side by side: the allied military authorities and the international authority.</p></div><div><head>The question of control </head><p>How are their respective powers to be defined? The powers which the London agreement confers on the international authority are exclusively concerned with distribution, but it must be clearly understood that it is distribution between Germany and the receiving countries—Germany and the other countries of Western Europe. The authority is to fix quotas and allocations in accordance with existing agreements; it will supervise deliveries of coal, coke, and steel, so as to prevent stoppages and difficulties, and avoid discrimination between one power and another. It will have, in fact, control over exports.</p><p>This is, of course, most important, for Europe, above all France, needs Ruhr production. But from the point of view of security, which at present means French security, the control most needed is not over exports but over consumption inside Germany—to make sure production is used for peaceful purposes, to maintain disarmament. Such a control should supervise allocations to German consumers, making sure that no part of Ruhr production is ever used directly or indirectly for war purposes. In the London agreement, however, as I understand it, this control is not the function of the new international authority but of the Allied Military Governors during the control period. After that it will belong to an organisation to be established under the peace treaty. It is only in the absence of a peace treaty that control over security, with the powers it implies, will be transferred from the occupying powers to the international authority.</p><p>The fundamental error made in London in my opinion is the assumption that an enormous industrial complex like the Ruhr can be properly controlled from outside. Whether the authority dealing with exports or internal consumption, it is impossible to direct, to give orders, to prohibit, if the authority does not hold reins in its own hands. This must be obvious to anyone with I slightest idea of how large industries are run. That is why we have called for “international nationalisation,” and why we advocate the strongest possible controlling authority with real power over the whole scale of activities.</p><p>What powers does the London agreement give the international authority? They are simply supervisory powers which nowhere touch the essential. It is to receive and demand reports and full information, and make enquiries. Already, the existing military authorities have powers no more adequate than these. There is no need for me to point out the uselessness of this. The system recalls that set up by the Treaty of Versailles, with its military and civil missions, and with all its shortcomings. I am very much afraid that it will cause similar disappointment. The necessary step has not been taken—control within what is to be controlled.</p><p>I can guess what has influenced our American and British allies who are fully aware of the difficulties I have raised. There can be no responsibility without authority, and our allies want to have responsible German managers and technicians, whose hands they want to leave as free as possible. They fear that a “responsible” German who has an allied controller standing over him the whole time would tend to depend too much on the controller. But to set up a system of central control without hindering efficiency or limiting the responsibility of executives ought not to be a problem beyond solution. It is being faced and solved every day in private industry. This is the problem the London discussions should have dealt with. They did not do so, perhaps because of the pressure which the military governors apparently exercised.</p><p>Is it still possible to repair this fundamental mistake? Fortunately, it is possible, for in the London agreement, paragraph 12 of the appendix dealing with the Ruhr states that it should be considered only as a statement of principles, and that the contracting powers reserve the right to lay down ways and means of putting it into operation. The question therefore remains open. Everyone agrees about the aims of control of the Ruhr. It is indeed impossible to believe that there should be any disagreement about them between the allies, or even between the allies and Germany. If they can agree about ends, is it too optimistic to hope that governments, enlightened by the press and public opinion, will also come to agree about the means?</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>