<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Nationalisation in Holland</title>
         <author>G.M.Nederhorst</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Nationalisation in Holland</title>
            <author>G.M.Nederhorst</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Dutch" party="Dutch Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>In connection with nationalisation of the means of production in Holland it is interesting to note the proportion of the country’s total production contributed by public authorities. In 1941, a study published by the Dutch Labour Party examined this question on the basis of figures relating to the years before the war. This study estimated that at that time public authorities accounted for about 18 per cent of the national income, which amounted to 4,500 million florins; about 18 per cent of national production (4,300 millions); 25 per cent, of national capital (19,000 millions): and 37 per cent, of share capital (660 millions). Although the figures for the period since the war are not available, there is no reason to believe that participation by the state in Dutch economic life has diminished. On the contrary, it has probably increased. There is no doubt that the state exercises an important influence, if only through its own production and investments.</p><p>We shall examine the industries in which State influence is important, especially the following sectors: finance, transport and communications, fuel and power, and metal industries.</p><div><head>Banking and finance </head><p>The Dutch Parliament is at present discussing a draft bill for the complete nationalisation of the Dutch National Bank. The bill has already been passed by the Chamber and is now awaiting approval by the Senate. The Dutch National Bank is the bank of issue for Holland. In practice, the bill will make little difference, for State influence on the Bank is already very great. The bill, in fact, only legalises an accomplished fact.</p><p>The Bank’s tasks are denned in the bill as the regulation of the value of the florin, the assurance of note circulation, the control of credit, the issue of bank notes and the acceptance of deposit and current accounts. The question of control of credit is particularly important because it allows measures to be taken to control the activities of private banks. This control is at present carried out under a kind of “gentleman’s agreement.”</p><p>The Bank's Directors and Commissioners are appointed by the Crown at the proposal of the Directors and the Council of Commissioners, although some Directors may be appointed outside of this procedure. The Council of Commissioners has the duty of supervising the Bank's activities and of drawing up the balance sheet and the annual profit and loss account. The Royal Commissioners, nominated by the Crown, supervise the Bank's transactions made on behalf of the Government. In addition to the Council of Commissioners, there is the Banking Council, composed of the Royal Commissioner, four members of the Council of Commissioners nominated by their colleagues, and twelve members appointed by the Crown, of whom two are heads of commercial enterprises, two heads of industrial enterprises, two heads of agricultural enterprises three trade union representatives, and three experts in finance and banking. It is very important for the trade union movement that three workers' representatives are to sit on the Banking Council. This has not been the case up to the present.</p><p>The significance of the draft bill, which will probably also be adopted by the Senate, is that it constitutes the legal recognition of the fact that the functions of the bank of issue should be subordinate to the general economic and financial policy of the Government, while at the same time maintaining the independence of the Dutch National Bank, which will remain a limited company with the State as its only shareholder.</p></div><div><head>The national reconstruction bank</head><p>In order to facilitate the finance of national reconstruction after the war, a National Reconstruction Bank was created. The purpose of this Bank is to provide credit for enterprises in all sectors of business and also to act as intermediary for the placing of investments in these enterprises. Its capital is 300 million florins of which the greater part is in the hands of the State. Its board consists of four Directors, of whom one is Chairman and one Secretary. These are appointed by the Crown and the other two by the shareholders' meeting. A Control Committee supervises the activities of the board which must have the approval of the Committee before it can issue shares, borrow, or participate in the capital of other companies. In addition, the Board must report periodically on its activities to the Control Committee. Initially the members of the Control Committee were appointed in the order setting up the company. There are 18 members, including one trade union representative. In future, the shareholders’ meeting will fix the number of members, on condition this this number is always a multiple of three. One third will be elected by private shareholders, the others by the shareholders as a whole, among whom public authorities are in the majority. Private shareholders in the Reconstruction Bank are mainly insurance companies and private banks.</p><p>One of the Reconstruction Bank's tasks is to make advances on the amounts to be paid by the state for war damage. On 30 September, 1947, the Bank's transactions amounted to 250 million florins, of which 78 millions were for advances on war damage payments, 175 millions for other credits, and 75 millions for credits allotted but no yet made. The Reconstruction Bank can, in addition to making short-term loans, also make long-term investments. So far it has not done much in this direction. In general, short-term loans have been the practice. From the point of view of socialist policy it would obviously be necessary to extend the scope of long-term investments.</p><p>State Savings Banks are a branch of the Post Office. On 31 October, 1947, total deposits amounted to 1.459 million florins. During 1947 deposits averaged more than 20 million florins monthly and withdrawals between 25 and 30 million florins. These figures are much higher than the total for all private Savings Banks.</p><p>The State Insurance Company is concerned with administering accident and disablement insurance, sickness benefits, old age pensions, and family allowances. There is no need to deal with its activities in detail here. This company has three Directors, nominated by the Crown, who choose their own Chairman. The Crown also nominates the auditor. Supervision is exercised by a committee of eleven members, four nominated by the employers’ organisations and four by the trade unions. The Chairman is chosen by the Minister. </p><p>The State Insurance Company is very important because of the sums which it controls. In addition to the State Savings Bank and Civil Pension Fund, the state exercises through this company an indirect influence on investments by the large sums it at its disposal. It can be seen from the Annual Report of 1943 that total investments by the accident fund were 49 millions, by the sickness and old age pension funds 590 millions, by the voluntary old age pension fund 96 millions—a grand total of 733 million</p><p>The survey of all these activities proves conclusively what a great influence the community exercises in the field of finance.</p></div><div><head>Transport and communications </head><p>All the railways in Holland belong to the Dutch State Railways, the shares of which are held by the state except for two in the hands of individuals. The Railway Executive consists of a Chairman and three Directors appointed by the shareholders meeting in which public authorities have, of course, an overwhelming majority. The Council of Commissioners consists of 16 members appointed by the shareholders meeting and has the task of supervising the Executive’s activities. At present one trade union representative sits on the Council of Commissioners. The following figures give an idea of the size of the undertaking.</p><p>Share capital amounts to 10 million florins, but this figure gives no idea of the real extent of the railways’ activities. The Balance Sheet totals on 31 December, 1946, were 1,000 millions and this figure is much nearer the amount of real capital invested.</p><p>Dutch railways have many subsidiaries, the most important being the Algemene Transport Onderneming which controls a large proportion of goods transport on the roads. In addition there are many regional bus services and local tram services. In all, the railways employ more than 32,000 people.</p></div><div><head>State air lines </head><p>Relations between the Dutch Royal Airlines—K.L.M.—and the state are regulated by the law of 4 August, 1947. K.L.M. is a mixed company, the majority of whose shares are held by the Dutch state. The constitution of K.L.M. can only be modified with the consent of the Minister of Transport, who can impose conditions about the machines used, and who can also inspect the accounts. In proportion to the amount of capital invested, the state can also exercise an influence in appointments to the Board of K.L.M. The majority of the Board and of the Council of Commissioners are appointed by the shareholders’ meeting from candidates approved by the state. The Board directs the company's activities, although the Minister of Transport can at any time issue directives to the Board. The day-to-day running of the company is in the hands of a number of officials appointed by the Board and approved by a majority of the shareholders’ meeting. It will be seen from this description that the state has a great influence on the policy and activities of K.L.M. even though it remains a limited company with ordinary shareholders. The Council of Commissioners supervises the running of the company.</p><p>State investment in K.L.M. amounts at present to 40,500,000 florins, while K.L.M. has undertaken to reserve for the state 11 million florins worth of shares not yet issued, and so guarantee that the majority of shares will remain in the state's possession. In 1947 the total share capital of K.L.M. amounted to 94 million florins. The number of people employed was about 10,000. During 1947 the number of kilometres regularly flown rose from 62,784 to 104,300 while tonnage carried rose from 57,200,000 to about 100,000,000 ton/kms. The Annual Report for 1947 has not yet issued.</p></div><div><head>Fuel and power </head><p>In Holland, ownership of the land gives no right of exploitation of minerals under the surface. In theory, under the law concerning mining rights, minerals are the property of the state which can concede exploitation rights to individual enterprises. In this way, some Dutch mines are held in concession by individuals, while others are run by the state. After the liberation, an extraordinary decree of 26 April, 1945, put both privately exploited mines and state mines under the control of the Director of State Mines.</p><p>The present organisation of the mining industry is considered mainly temporary; a decision about the final system is still awaited. The first government after liberation declared in favour of eventual nationalisation of the mines and announced that it intended to nationalise the privately exploited mines in Limburg and to take preparatory steps for this purpose so that the next parliament could put this plan into operation. This point of the government’s programme never became a reality. The second government announced that nationalisation of the mines would be carried out as soon as a commission of enquiry had confirmed that public interest requires such a step. This commission was appointed in Autumn 1946, but up to the present has not yet issued its report. Socialists feel that privately exploited mines should also become the property of the state and are afraid that the Commission’s verdict will not be favourable.</p><p>The following table shows comparative production of state and privately exploited mines:</p><p>One important difference between state mines and private mines is that state-owned mines use a much higher proportion of their production on subsidiary undertakings, so that in mines used 45% of their production in this way and private mines only 18%. The state mines run coke ovens, a nitrate factory, and a gas and electricity undertaking. The nitrate factory is of very great importance for the whole of Dutch economy, for it provides a great part of Dutch needs in nitrate fertilisers, and when the expansion which is at present being carried out is complete there will be no further need for nitrate imports. Although other Dutch industries manufacture chemical fertilisers, the factory which belongs to the state mines is the most important.</p><p>The mines are run by a government department and not as a company. The Board is appointed by the Crown. The Mines Council constitutes the advisory body of the Ministry and at the same time supervises the Board’s activities. There are four state mines and nine private mines, most of the capital of which is held by French and Belgians. In all more than 130 million florins are invested in the state mines, and 28,029 people, including 3,215 administrative staff are employed by them.</p><p>Gasworks and electricity undertakings are generally run by provincial or municipal authorities—electricity usually by provincial and gas by municipal authorities. Only a very few gasworks belong to private companies.</p></div><div><head>Metallurgical and chemical industries </head><p>There is only one blast furnace undertaking in Holland—the Koninklijke Nederlandse Hoogovens en Staalfabrieken at Ijmuiden. This is a mixed company in which the municipality of Amsterdam as well as the state is a shareholder. The share capital has recently been increased to 32 million florins. The government investment amounted to 6,561,000 florins and that of Amsterdam to 3,795,000 florins. The members of the Board and the Council of Commissioners are appointed by the shareholders. According to the Annual Report for 1946-47, total invested capital amounted to 56 million florins. Total production of pig iron was 222,129 tons of which 120,105 were exported. The production of sheet steel was 38,516 and of castings 22,753 tons. As a by product about 26 million cubic metres of gas were produced and distributed to local authorities. The blast undertaking also has interests in other firms, especially in the Nederlandse Staalfabrieken v/h J.M. de Muinck Keizer at Zuilen and in the "MEKOG" at Ijmuiden which is an important manufacturer of chemical fertilisers.     </p><p>In the province of Overijssel in Eastern Holland some salt mines are exploited by the Koninklijke Nederlandse Zoulindustrie at Noekelo. The undertaking is very important in the chemical industries. It concluded an exploitation agreement with the state by which, in exchange for the concession, the state received 150,000 shares in the company. In addition, one clause in the agreement states that the state has the right to acquire all the remaining shares at any time after 1 January 1934. This agreement is valid until 31 December, 1978. Although there is no question of a direct influence by the community on the industry it is always possible for the state to play a more: active role. Because of its ownership of a proportion of the shares the state has an indirect influence on the undertaking. This is very important as the industry is a monopoly and is certainly ripe for nationalisation.      </p><p>We have confined ourselves to giving a survey of influence of public authorities over key positions in economy. A complete enumeration of all the state-owned industries and mixed enterprises would make this article too long. In conclusion, however, we must mention that by the transfer of enemy-owned assets to the Dutch state a number of shares in large Dutch industries, such as the Algemene Kunstzijde Unie and the Kon. Ned. Mij tot Exploitatie van Petroleumbronnen have fallen into the hands of the community. It is not known, however, what will happen to these shares in view of the small amount of publicity which has been given to the liquidation of enemy assets. There is here a means of influencing some strategic points in the national economy, but it is to be feared that the shares in question will be sold by the government to private individuals.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>