<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>European unity and European reconstruction</title>
         <author>Cerilo Spinelli</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>European unity and European reconstruction</title>
            <author>Cerilo Spinelli</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Italian" party="Italian Socialist Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The United States and the Soviet Union have reached the when they must either come to an agreement or go to war. With the elimination of the buffer states between the American and Soviet spheres of influence, any further political change in Europe would inevitably mean a substantial modification of the present strategic situation and would therefore constitute an act of war.</p><p>The situation is undoubtedly rendered more delicate by the fact that the boundary between Western and Eastern Europe runs across a Germany which has been plunged into misery by the war and poisoned by Nazism—a Germany whose population, artificially divided by the manoeuvres of the victorious great powers, is more than ever ready for extreme courses in the present complete collapse of moral and material values. The only obstacle to another war seems to lie in the material or moral inability of one or both of the opposing powers to face a new conflict.</p><p>It is certain, in any case, that Europe at present can do little or nothing towards removing the immediate dangers of war and there would be no point in examining the part which it could play in the event of a third world war. In fact, it is obvious that the peoples of Europe would not have a common attitude and every country would be internally divided between partisans of one or the other power, thus bringing about the break-up of the various European nations.</p><p>But if military considerations postpone the war, the possibility then arises for Europe to play—under certain conditions—a part of its own in promoting the organisation of world peace.</p><p>Any serious appreciation of the political situation in Europe must be based on recognition of the revolution which, has taken place in international relations in the last thirty years—a revolution whereby Europe has lost the power to determine the course of history. For centuries countries far greater in size and population than those of Europe have been subjected, entirely or in part, to the sovereignty of European governments and have recognised their moral and material supremacy. This supremacy has completely disappeared in the course of thirty years. Involved in internal wars, incapable of developing its own material and spiritual resources Europe has gradually seen the economic and political power it had accumulated diminish to the point where the recent tremendous military struggle not only destroyed its economic independence but made its day-to-day existence entirely dependent on the United States of America.</p><div><head>Political independence of Europe </head><p>The political independence of Europe was founded on a balance of power between the various European nations, arrive at by a complicated network of bilateral alliances between them. Since this equilibrium presupposed the existence of independent sovereign states, the old political system was liquidated beyond recall when national sovereignty was finally suppressed in the Balkan States which, in the past, had played a decisive part in the scheme of bilateral alliances. The problem of European equilibrium ceased to be a separate problem with its own traditions and solutions, and became merely one aspect of the problem of relations between the U.S.S.R. and the U.S.A.</p><p>It would, however, be a grave mistake to believe that Western Europe has completely lost its own power of initiative. At the end of the Second World War the natural function of Europe, which stands geographically, politically and economically between the two world powers. The disappearance of independent forces in Eastern Europe has, however, given this function a completely different form.</p><p>At present it is primarily a question of creating a political complex capable of gradually regaining its independence vis-a-vis the two great world powers and, secondly, of aiding the development within this new complex of political and social forces capable of pursuing a consistent policy of mediation. It is obvious that the political independence of Western Europe will be greater, the closer unity between the various nations, who will thus be better able to resist any unacceptable demands by Russia or America. But it is equally obvious that a common European policy does not in itself constitute a guarantee for the purposes of mediation. The mere formation of a federal state of Western Europe is insufficient for a policy of mediation, should those social and political forces which want a war with Russia gain the upper hand within the new federal state. It is clear that in such a case the very principles of peace and social progress which inspire the ideal of a United Europe would be totally frustrated.</p><p>Europe’s position as mediator appears, therefore, to be conditional on the constitution of a unified European state which does not, however, pursue an anti-Soviet policy. In certain circumstances it may be necessary to take an anti-Soviet line, but it must be clear from the start that Western Europe does not aim at threatening Russia but at facilitating relations between her and America.</p></div><div><head>Socialism and anti-socialism </head><p>Before examining the political situation in Europe it is necessary to make clear how naive it is to consider the political forces in Europe as Socialist or anti-Socialist according to the attitude which they adopt towards “Russian collectivism” or "American capitalism", and how completely mistaken it is to judge a policy as Socialist or not in relation to the support which it receives the USSR or from the USA.</p><p>The policy of these two countries is determined by economic, political and strategic factors of such importance that it is only very indirectly influenced by one group of social forces rather than another. Social structure in America and Russia is, moreover, so different from that in Western Europe that it is practically impossible to reduce United States and Russian policy to Socialist or anti-Socialist motives in the sense in which they are understood in Europe to-day.</p><p>Socialist theory and practice in Western Europe presupposes the existence on the one hand of a class possessing the means of production and, on the other, of a working class spurred on by poverty to modify the social structure by placing the means of production under public ownership. This double assumption of present-day Socialist policy in Europe has nothing corresponding to it in the Soviet Union, which has completely abolished private ownership of the means of production, nor in the United States, where the working class enjoys such a high standard of life that it does not feel the need for profound social changes. Any description of the two world powers and policies towards Europe in terms of Socialism and anti-Socialism is therefore mistaken.</p></div><div><head>The alignment of working class forces in Europe </head><p>Political forces in Western Europe tend at the present moment to fall into two groups: on the one side the forces under Communist control which aim more or less openly at the integration of the whole of Europe in the Soviet system; on the other, a conglomeration of forces which reject that solution and are apparently agreed in wishing to regain Europe’s lost economic independence and in promoting the political independence of Europe as a unified system. This alignment of political forces in Europe has necessarily placed Socialist parties in the painful situation of having to fight against Communist policy in so far as it is now clearly designed to destroy the Socialist movement, and therefore of finding themselves in danger of becoming the instrument of reactionary forces in a conflict initially directed against the Communist party, but which may in reality be turned against the working class as a whole. Although this is not the first time that the Socialist parties have been in conflict with the Communist parties, the danger of becoming instruments of reactionary forces has only recently arisen to any extent, since the Socialists in some countries are no longer in the privileged position of having behind them the majority of the working class movement and are weaker than either Communism and reaction. This dilemma may force some European Socialist parties to accept, in certain circumstances an alliance with the parties of the Right rather than with the Communists, but it is equally evident that in the event of the power in the working class movement and consequently regain freedom of action vis-à-vis the forces of the Right, their disappearance from the political scene would be only a question of time.</p></div><div><head>Socialists and communists </head><p>Since the end of the war Socialists on the Continent have been at disadvantage compared with the Communists as far as economic policy is concerned. Reacting against Russian collectivism Socialist Parties had, even before the war, become less dogmatic about the expropriation of the means of production and had formulated a gradual programme of planning, controls, nationalisation and social services better adapted to the economic and political conditions in which the Socialists had to work.</p><p>The economic collapse produced by the war, however, made the Socialist programme unreal, since its rational gradualism and the cost of structural reforms envisaged meant that it could only be put into practice in a balanced and healthy economic system. Instead, Europe's economy was in such a disastrous condition that all these projects were swamped by the fundamental and urgent problem of mere survival. In these conditions, the real problem which governments had to solve was to assure the continued functioning of the national economic systems by means of a supply of raw materials and by the creation of export markets. The Communists, therefore, found themselves able to offer a plausible solution to the problem - the economic integration of Western and Eastern Europe - and could therefore extend their influence to salaried workers and bourgeois whose existence seemed directly threatened by the economic collapse and who, exasperated by the intolerable speculative fortunes made by many individuals, were now much more responsive to the radical and far-reaching programmes of nationalisation preached by the Communists.</p><p>Of course, the Communist programme implied the adoption of a political system alien to the Western world; but thin appeared less hard in comparison with present difficulties and with the undeniable fact that an economic system which could exploit the natural and human resources in the region between the Pyrenees and the Urals would certainly constitute a permanent solution to the problem of Europe’s economic reorganisation.</p><p>In these circumstances, Socialists could not oppose an adequate counter-offensive to the spread of Communist influence— a counter-offensive which, in order to succeed, must provide an answer to the question of balance of payments with the Western hemisphere. Integration with the Soviet system having been ruled out, the Socialists had no alternative but to accept emergency aid from America, on condition that it was to be used in accordance a plan for national economic reconstruction; but since such a plan could be carried out only by means of economic controls and nationalisation, whose realisation had as its premise the adjustment of the balance of payments, the outcome was that the Socialists' were back where they started from—with no guarantee of the continuity and extent of American aid.</p></div><div><head>The problem of European unity </head><p>With the Socialists inability to hold up the Soviet advance by winning over the working classes from the national Communist parties, the initiative passed to other forces interested in preventing the establishment of a Soviet system in Western Europe. These forces are mainly under the control of two definite political groups: one Conservative and one Liberal-Democratic. Both these groups, which have been weakened by the development of the Socialist movement, had for some time been faced with the problem of gaining greater support from the popular masses, and were therefore particularly inclined to accept new ideas with a power of attraction greater than that which they generated by economic and social programmes which no longer had much relation to reality. Both these groups were therefore ready to accept the idea of a United Europe whose power of attraction was obvious, both because of its high emotional appeal and because it represented a real possibility of solving Europe’s political and economic problems.</p><p>By promoting European unity Conservatives and Democrats proposed very different aims. The Conservatives see European unity essentially as an aggressive or defensive military bloc against the Soviet Union, in the belief that war is in the long run inevitable. In that case United Europe is nothing more than a camouflage for the anti-Soviet foreign policy represented by Churchill and de Gaulle, and which is directly related to the reactionary policy which Conservatives advocate within the various countries—openly aiming at breaking the working-class movement under the pretext of anti-Communism. No one denies that a unified European state would at the same time constitute a military bloc, but if it should be its only bond and, in the last analysis, its essential aim, it is clear that the new European state would not be able either to carry out its function of mediation between the two world powers or to ensure social justice which the peoples of Europe so anxiously desire.</p><p>The liberal-democratic group, on the other hand, thought that economic dislocation caused by the war would facilitate European economic reorganisation on a completely new basis. They intended to exploit the exceptional situation produced by the collapse of the state apparatus in some countries in order to bring about a general redistribution of the productive, human and material resources in a Europe liberated from obsolete and cumbersome economic and political frontiers. They were aware that an upheaval on such a scale could take place only by a revolutionary process and consequently appealed to proletarian and intellectual forces to prepare for decisive action. Many Socialists, such as Silone in Italy and André Philip in France were attracted by this movement, although they knew that its aims, while progressive in themselves, might entail serious economic dislocation, and therefore unemployment and distress for the workers.      </p><p>Since-for a series of reasons which we cannot examine here - the expected revolutionary situation did not come about, United Europe has become more and more a problem of the progressive adaptation of the various national reconstruction programmes to the demands of general European recovery-that is, progressive integration of the various national economies by means of a co-ordinated policy of trade, tariffs and investments. Since the democratic federalists however, remained committed to their revolutionary idea and from many points of view even criticism of the Socialists’ position, they finished by splitting away from the working-class movement. </p></div><div><head>Socialists and United Europe </head><p>Between these two extremes - a reactionary European Union as a weapon of war and a democratic European Union indifferent to working-class needs - began to emerge a specifically Socialist policy for a United Europe. </p><p>We have already examined the main reasons for the weakening of the Socialist movement in Europe - reasons which explain the scant interest shown by Socialists in a United Europe whose establishments would do nothing to help the survival of the various national economies and of the populations whose livelihood depends on them. In addition, there was at the end of the war, the desire, for reasons of foreign and domestic policy, in the East not to break the links with the national Communist parties, in the West to maintain neutrality in the conflict between Russia and America. The Socialists, in fact, considered that Russia bad a definite interest in Europe’s role of mediator and therefore tried to make the easier for the Soviet Union in this direction. An important was to be played in this policy by the Polish, Czechoslovak, Hungarian and Rumanian Socialist Parties who were welcomed in the international Socialist organisation which was then being formed. Basically it was a continuation on a Socialist plane of the old European balance of power, to which the Socialist parties clung, not wishing to accept the only alternative at that time—integration in the Soviet system—and wishing on the other hand to break out of the vicious circle in which they were caught. This policy ceased to have any point from the moment when the political forces in Eastern Europe lost their freedom of action.</p></div><div><head>The Marshall Plan </head><p>The appearance on the political scene of the so-called Marshall Plan, however, offered the Socialists their long-sought solution. Their attitude towards United Europe was therefore to undergo a change. Having gradually come closer in the course of 1947, this change revealed itself openly in an abrupt switch by the Western Socialists in favour of European unity, at the same time as the Socialist parties of Eastern Europe were finally being submerged by the Communist deluge.</p><p>The most important political consequence of the European Recovery Programme was to re-create in Western Europe the condition for a genuine Socialist recovery. The guarantee of continued American aid allows Socialists to resume their programme of planning and gradual nationalisation which had been the basis of their appeal in the past. They were now able to offer a serious alternative to Communist economic policy, at the same time maintaining the democratic institutions created by the Western working-class movement and carrying on the struggle against the Conservative forces which had rapidly re-arisen after the reverse which the anti-Fascist war had inflicted on them. The Socialist parties have, in fact, come forward as the only forces capable of guaranteeing that American aid is applied to the real reconstruction of the European economic system and not used in the interests of private groups.</p><p>The essential prerequisite for a Socialist victory m Western Europe is that the Socialist movement must once again strike its roots deeply into the working class by defending the workers interests. Until that objective has been attained, the Socialist position will always be precarious, unstable, and exposed to inevitable defeats each time the political situation causes social conflicts of any magnitude. This objective can only be achieved by recapturing the trade unions and factory organisations, and by financial policy which ensures just redistribution of the national income.</p><p>It is clear that such a programme cannot easily be implemented in the present economic and political conditions of Western Europe, but its gradual attainment is undoubtedly possible and to that end Socialists - whether in the Government or in opposition - must adapt their political action as necessary.</p></div><div><head>Organisational control of the working class </head><p>Socialist Parties in Western Europe can be divided into two main categories: those which have the majority of the working class behind them, and those which have surrendered leadership to the Communist party. There is no doubt that Socialist parties in those countries with a more solid democratic structure and a higher standard of living—like Great Britain and the Scandinavian countries—have been more favourably placed to maintain their hold on the working class, but this does not explain the difference, for example, between Italy and Austria. Whereas in Italy the Communists are supported by the majority of the urban working class, in Austria the Socialist Party has succeeded in winning eighty-five per cent of the votes in the recent trade union elections in spite of the fact that the country is still under American and Soviet occupation.</p><p>The truth is that only those parties have kept control of the working class which remained independent and solidly based on the trade unions, in spite of all attempts at premature Socialist policies. This trade-unionist, reformist attitude was certainly responsible, at least in part, for the failure of Socialism before the war, but it did provide a base from which Socialists could reconquer the lost ground and come forward even more strongly after the war.</p><p>In Great Britain, the Labour victory of 1945 would never have taken place if the Labour Party in 1936 had adopted the Popular Front policy put forward by Cripps. It was the fact that the French Socialist Party stuck to the Front Populaire after it had ceased to represent working-class interests which opened the way for the Communist Party’s penetration of the trade unions.</p><p>It is now clear that a Socialist government has no hope of success if it is not permanently supported by the whole organised working class, though this close the between the Socialist party and the working class should not lead to a break with the middle classes.</p><p>When a popular movement is produced which thrusts Socialist parties into power, the latter must necessarily sometimes pursue a policy which, especially to begin with, disappoints the workers in many ways, and therefore no Socialist government can last long if it does not have the loyal and solid support of the organised and politically-conscious working class. For this reason a Socialist Party must always have close organisational ties with the workers. </p></div><div><head>Outlines of socialist planning </head><p>The success or otherwise of Socialist economic policy depends ultimately on whether unemployment is abolished or not. Workers will put up with controls and shortages so long as they prevent unemployment which they dread more than anything else. If unemployment were to spread in spite of controls, the masses of the people would rebel and internal conflicts would arise within the working class which would rapidly bring about the fall of any Socialist government and the return to power of the old ruling classes.</p><p>Full employment is possible only when the productive machine is kept technically capable of dealing with the demand of the international economic situation. That is particularly true of Western Europe whose economic system is based on the production of finished and semi-finished goods, which are exported in exchange for raw materials and foodstuffs necessary to keep the productive machine working. A full employment policy therefore demands both the re-organisation of European economy by eliminating uneconomic industries and productive processes based on the false idea of national self-sufficiency, and by raising output by means of the introduction of new and modern plant, and the employment of surplus European manpower in other continents.</p><p>The first of these points demands the planning of Europe’s economic reconstruction, the second, an agreement between the European nations on colonial policy. Both bring out strongly the absolute necessity for a common European policy, for no planning is possible without an effective central authority, and only the elimination of the old national state sovereignty can finally put an end to the old-fashioned colonial conflicts.</p><p>It is worth repeating that a Socialist plan for European economic re-organisation would not mean the immediate abolition of existing limitations on freedom of trade and movement of labour, but a gradual integration of the various national economics by means of a co-ordinated system of exchanges and tariffs which would bring about the gradual movement of capital and labour from uneconomic to economic tasks. This progressive integration also requires the re-organisation of different branches of industry, which would in turn make nationalisation necessary or, at least, controls over investments and the distribution of profits. The existence of a unified European state would make the struggle against monopolistic privileges easier, for the need to exploit Europe’s resources to the utmost would bring about a redistribution of productive forces which would leave very little place for monopoly capitalism.</p><p>The development of colonial resources in Africa and elsewhere constitutes the obvious solution to the problem of Europe's independence in the matter of food supplies. To transfer large numbers of white workers to Africa would be rather unpopular with those European states whose policy is to employ native labour and raise its social level, but once the dangers of colonial conflict eliminated, there is no reason why white labour cannot find employment alongside native labour when health and social conditions make that possible.</p><p>An equal sharing out of the total wealth is not only a guarantee against recurrent economic crises but also the application of the Socialist principle of fair distribution of income. Such sharing-out cannot, however, be fixed once and for all, since in order to be effective and fair it must always be adapted to the relative importance of the various economic functions and to the changing demands of society. A Socialist policy must therefore have as its objective the constant adjustment of financial policy to the needs of production, together with a universal system of social insurance.</p></div><div><head>Opportunity for socialists </head><p>This is not the place to examine to what extent the Socialist programme can be put into practice within the framework of the European Recovery Programme, although it is evident that any possible deficiency in American aid does not make the ERP useless, but should mean a corresponding increase in European co-operation.</p><p>We have merely tried to show that a United Europe and ERP far from making the Socialist movement the tool of American capitalism will instead make possible its rebirth, and that its rebirth, and that is only possible if the Socialist Party carries on the struggle against capitalism and maintains its ties with the workers. It is evident that Socialists will not have an easy life of it in the next few years but if they keep their faith and tenacity no power in the world will be able to prevent the great masses of the people from advancing along the road to democracy, peace and social justice.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>