<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Spanish socialists fight on</title>
         <author>Rodolfo Llopis</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Spanish socialists fight on</title>
            <author>Rodolfo Llopis</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Spanish" party="Spanish Socialist Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>It is hardly necessary to recall that on the 18th July, 1936, the day the military rising against the Spanish Republic began, the rebels ordered all political parties and trade union organisations in the areas under their control to be dissolved. From that moment to be a Socialist, or even to have been a member of the party became a crime subject to the harshest punishment. From that moment Socialists were imprisoned, assassinated, or executed Later, on the 29th March, 1939, when the Civil War came to an end, these laws against parties and trade unions were extended to the whole of Spain, and the punishments made more severe.</p><p>As the Civil War was drawing to its close, Spanish anti-fascists were promised that there would be ships at Alicante for them to escape from the Falangists, and party and union leaders assembled at the port. The ships never came to Alicante. Instead came the Italian Legions and Franco’s forces. Those who had hoped to escape—about 25,000 of them—were taken prisoner. All the prisons in the town were already full to overflowing; an enormous concentration camp was therefore improvised on the outskirts — the notorious Campo de los Almenaros. Some time later, in order to prevent escapes, the prisoners were transferred to the equally notorious Campo de Albatera, also in the province of Alicante. From there they were taken away, some to be shot, some to prisons in other parts of Spain to await trial.</p><p>These prisons and concentration camps at Alicante were a feature reproduced throughout the whole of the country. “It is no exaggeration to say,” reported our comrades in Madrid, “that more than two million people were in prison. In Madrid alone there were twenty-two prisons where more than 150,000 of our men were held.”</p><p>Almost all the Socialist Party leaders who had remained in Spain were prisoners, first at Alicante, then in the concentration camps. They included almost all the members of the provisional committees, many leaders of unions affiliated to the Union General de Trabajadores, members of the National Executive of the Socialist Youth Organisation, and almost all the members of the National Party Executive elected by the provisional committees which met in Madrid to withdraw recognition from the Executive led by Pena and Lamoneda which had fled to France.</p><p>In spite of daily murders by Franco's men, in spite of the shadow of the gallows, Socialists in the camps began to meet secretly and form underground groups, basing their own organisation on the prison system itself. This system divided the prisoners into prison "brigades": in each of these brigades was a socialist representative, who contacted representatives in the other brigades as occasion arose. It was a very rudimentary organisation, which tried to give as much help as possible, passed on news, and kept socialist faith alive. At that time, the party, the trade unions and the youth organisation were all merged together in the "Socialist Movement".</p><p>When it became possible to have news from outside prison and receive visitors, these visitors—wives, children, and socialists who were still at liberty because they were not thought dangerous or important —were entrusted with the task of making contact with prisoners in other gaols and camps. In addition, whenever there were transfers to prisons in other towns, any socialists who were transferred acted as messengers to their comrades in the new place. There was great joy when it became known that socialist groups were functioning in every prison, concentration camp and labour battalion and were functioning with the same spirit.</p><p>Everywhere the same loyalty to socialist principles was maintained, the same hatred of the Falange, the same distrust of the Communists. This distrust had grown out of the Communists’ conduct during the Civil War, when they murdered many of our comrades at the front, and especially during the rising in Madrid towards the end of the war, called “Communist Week,” which cost many socialist lives. It became stronger after the signing of the Soviet-German Pact, when the Communists, obeying orders, cheered Hitler’s victories—to the amusement of their Falangist gaolers and the anger of our comrades who firmly believed in the Allied victory.</p><div><head>Behind prison walls </head><p>In this way the Spanish Socialist Party was reorganised behind prison walls. Each prison committee was in contact with their comrades, and sometimes with socialists who by good luck were still at liberty. Socialist “cells” were gradually formed throughout the country, sometimes consisting of a single man, more often of a woman, a socialist prisoner’s wife in contact with a prison committee. These may be considered the origin of the “Socialist Movement". As might be expected, in places with strong socialist traditions, number of socialists at liberty. The younger ones among them began to work, at first individually, limiting their activity to the neighbourhood of their homes, but all the time in contact with the prison committees.</p><p>In 1942 when all the prison committees—about three hundred altogether—were in communication with one another and with others outside prison, carelessness caused a number of arrests which disorganised activity for a time.</p><p>By the end of 1943 there were sufficient socialists at liberty, though still under surveillance, who were known to the workers. It was decided to establish separate organisations for the party, the unions, and the Youth groups A provisional national executive committee came into being, and in April, 1944, when all the provincial federations and the national council had been re-established, the first Executive Committee of the Party was officially elected.</p><p>The Party was thus organically in action. It had local sections, provincial federations, a national council, an Executive Committee, with about 35,000 paying members. It had its own publications and was in periodical contact with socialists in exile. It formed part of the “National Alliance of Democratic Forces.” It was consulted by representatives of foreign powers, and negotiated with other political and social forces. In this connection it is only fair to emphasise how much the reorganisation of the Party owes to the tireless work of unknown members—who prefer to be nameless, to the women, and above all to the young people, who were for a time the heart and soul of the Socialist Movement.</p></div><div><head>Arrests and trials </head><p>In February, 1945, a large number of socialists were arrested including all the members of the executive committee. One of these managed to escape, and elude police searches. He lay hidden for several months, then succeeded in crossing the frontier and took refuge in France where he still lives.</p><p>A year later, in February, 1946, the trial of those arrested began before a Military Tribunal in the prison of Alcala de Henares. It was the first political trial held by Franco, and the Socialist Party had the honour of the leading part. The prosecution called for the death penalty for Gomez Egido, Vails, San Miguel, de Toso, Socrates Gomez, Mario Fernandez, Jose Diaz Mendez, and Enrique Melero, for a sentence of thirty years for fifteen of their comrades, and for fifteen years for four others.</p><p>Our comrades were accused of plotting against the security of the state by having secretly re-formed the Spanish Socialist Party. Our comrades did not deny this. They claimed the honour and responsibility of being leaders of the glorious Socialist Party, denounced the crimes of the Franco regime, and ended by saying: "if being a Socialist is a crime, then we Spanish Socialists are prepared to answer for that crime with our lives".</p><p>Thanks to international pressure aroused by us, there were no death sentences, and the accused were condemned to sentences of from four to twelve years imprisonment.</p><p>As may be expected, as soon as these comrades had been arrested in February, 1945, they were replaced by others. The new executive continued to work begun by its predecessor until May, 1946, when four of its members were arrested, along with many other Socialists.</p><p>Their case was tried in December, 1947, by a military tribunal in the prison of Ocana. They were accused of the same crimes as the previous Executive. The same harsh penalties were called for yet again. Our comrades did not deny the accusations, and maintained the same attitude as the others. Eduardo Villegas, Vicente Orche, and Leopoldo Mejorada were condemned to twenty-five, fifteen, and twelve years imprisonment respectively. The other accused received sentences of between two and twelve years.</p><p>When these comrades were arrested in May, 1946, they were replaced by others. The new Executive continued its activity until last December, when the Madrid police carried out a great round-up and imprisoned a large number of socialist leaders, trade unionists and young socialists. These comrades in Madrid are still suffering barbarous tortures at the hands of the police who are trying to force them to reveal the secrets of their organisation. It can be seen that the moment that international pressure diminishes, Franco feels his position safer and feels free to indulge in the worst excesses.</p><p>This is not the place to give a complete list of party members imprisoned for socialist activities, nor of those comrades who were murdered for the crime of being Socialists: both lists are endless. We have only given details of arrests and imprisonment which have affected the national leadership of the party.</p></div><div><head>The war against Franco </head><p>From the very beginning, it has been the party’s aim to keep alive the socialist ideal inside Spain. As we have said, former party members have been reorganised in a system of cadres, so that no more people are mobilised than is necessary for the tasks and missions which the party has set itself to carry out. As far as possible there is complete internal democracy inside the party at local, provincial and national levels so that at any time the real will of the party can express itself. Also from the very beginning the party has given as much help as possible to the innumerable prisoners. A special organisation has been set up to deal with the trials so as to organise the greatest possible support in favour of the accused. Written propaganda is intense, although always insufficient. Apart from pamphlets, manifestos and posters, there are periodical publications. With the Trade Union organisations and the Republican Alliance the party takes part in an organisation which co-ordinates the anti-Franco elements inside Spain, called the "National Alliance of Democratic Forces.” In the Basque country our comrades take part in the Consejo Delegado de Euzkadi and in the provincial resistance movement.</p><p>The party’s activity in Spain, it will be understood, is varied and is not just limited to the reorganisation of the party machine activity. Its activity arises our of circumstances and grasps every opportunity to continue the struggle and to express in the most effective way its hatred of the Franco regime and its devotion to the Republic and to Socialism. Its activity ranges from passive resistance to the most active resistance possible. There was the striking demonstration at the anniversary of the death of Pablo Iglesias and the splendid General Strike on 1st May, 1947, in Bilbao—a strike which aroused the admiration of the whole world and which was due to Socialist initiative.</p><p>In many parts of Spain the party has groups of guerrillas in the mountains. The federation of Valencia sends reports of their guerillas activities; so do Aragon and Andalucia, Castile and Asturias. Asturias has had its guerilla forces since the fall of Oveido that is for the last ten years. The party's policy concerning guerilla warfare is set out in the Memorandum which the Executive Committee presented to the meeting of the National Council somewhere in Spain on 16th September, 1945: "The Executive Committee is proud of the self-sacrifice and discipline of our guerillas. We ask them not to waste ammunition on sorties but to keep on the defensive, limiting their action to the minimum indispensable to assure their supplies. We hope that we shall soon be able to greet them and honour them for what they have done.”</p></div><div><head>The party in exile</head><p>Immediately after the liberation of France, the separate groups of Spanish Socialists which had functioned in secret under German occupation, met in a Congress in Toulouse. This was in September, 1944. At this Congress the idea was expressed that a number of socialists had emigrated from Spain, but that the Party itself had not emigrated from Spain, but had continued working there secretly with a legal Executive and a legal National Committee.</p><p>The Spanish Socialist Party in France was therefore founded. To this the important North African Socialist Federation and the sections in Belgium and Britain later adhered. Since then there has been a second Party Congress in France in May, 1946, at which were present representatives of sections from America, so that the whole of the exile socialist movement was re-united, except for the small groups of dissidents and people expelled from the party. The party in exile consists of 333 sections in France, Belgium, Britain, N.Africa and America, with a total of 12,000 members and joins in organisations created in exile by other parties and trade unions— except the Communists - to co-ordinate activity in defence of the Republic and the interests of the Spanish people. Our party was represented in the Republican Governments in exile, in one of which the Prime Minister was a Socialist.</p><p>The Party in exile functions quite normally with a constitution worked out by its members and approved by its Congress. It has local sections, a National Council which meets regularly and an Executive Committee elected by Congress. There have already been three congresses in France. The official weekly is El Sotialista. Some Federations publish their own papers: Adelante in Mexico, El Socialista in Algiers, Adelante in Marseilles. There is a review Cuadernos Socialistas and many theoretical pamphlets.</p><p>We have founded the “National Federation of Socialist Youth” which has been a great help to the party. This Youth Movement has arisen out of the confusion caused in Spain by the notorious “Juventudes Socialistas Unificadas,” dominated by the Communists. The Youth Movement has its own weekly, Renovation, and has had two Congresses in France.</p><p>In conformity with its traditional policy, the Party works in close collaboration with the trade union organisation, the Union General de Trabajadores, which has also been reorganised in exile. The Executives of both organisations meet together whenever events make it necessary. The Party and its Youth Movement, which are entirely dependent on membership fees, have formed a fund— Solidaridad Democratica Espanola—to assist needy socialists wherever possible. Our members, in spite of the hardships they have had to suffer since they first left their native land, in spite of unemployment, in spite of the high affiliation fees they have to pay to the party, to the Unions, and to the party’s press, still contribute a large proportion of their wages to help their comrades inside Spain. Small individual contributions, the result of great personal sacrifices, have already raised a sum of more than six million French francs for Socialists inside Spain.</p><p>In exile the Party has maintained at all times the ideological tradition, the irreproachable conduct, and the uncorruptable [sic] honesty which have always been the most precious virtues of the PSOE founded by our great leader Pablo Iglesias.</p></div><div><head>The Third Congress </head><p>From the 25th to 28, our Party celebrated its third Congress in exile in Toulouse. In spite of the grave employment crisis in France at present, and in spite of three years of Civil War and nine years of exile, in which they have known every kind of misery, hardship and oppression, Spanish Socialists have given a new proof of their fidelity, their idealism and their devotion to the Party.</p><p>At this Conference were present delegates from all the sections in France, Belgium, Britain, North Africa and America, as well as an “invisible” delegate from inside Spain, who was present at the debates, but was not seen by the delegates—or by Franco spies. Many friendly greetings from European Socialist parties were received. There were discussions of problems which have occupied all our attention since we began to work as a party in exile.</p><p>After reaffirming the decision not to ally with or have any tact with the Communist Party, questions affecting the Solidarity Fund and help for socialists were discussed, and then the problem of preventing young people from losing interest and of preparing them morally and ideologically to be what they ought to be— the reserve forces of the Party. Finally the Congress discussed international relations and the political problems of the liberation f Spain. The Spanish Socialist Party, which has among its achievements the overthrow of the monarchy in 1931, the social purpose which it gave to the Republic, and the defence of the legal régime which the Spanish people democratically chose for itself believed that the best way of finishing with the Franco regime which oppresses Spain and of bridging the gulf which the Civil War made in the Spanish people, is a free election—once Franco has been removed—by the whole nation, with full guarantees that it can express its wish. For this purpose the Congress unanimously voted a resolution entrusting the party with the task of taking the initiative to call a Conference of all anti-Franco forces, whether Republican or not, provided they sincerely desire to overthrow the present regime and guarantee democratic liberties to the Spanish people in order to form a government which would correspond to the conditions laid down in the Tripartite Note of 5th March, 1946, and repeated later in the United Nations Resolution of 12th December 1946.</p><p>The Congress finally declared that Spain-a democratic Spain- should be included in any Western European Union, in the hope that this would be the first step towards a United States of Europe the basis of a World Confederation which Socialism believes to be the only effective guarantee of peace and democracy for mankind.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>