<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The last months of social democracy in Hungary</title>
         <author>Antal Ban</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The last months of social democracy in Hungary</title>
            <author>Antal Ban</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>June-August 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.5</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Hungarian" party="Hungarian Social Democratic Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>The parliamentary elections in Hungary on 31 August, 1947, to be a decisive trial of strength between the Communist and Social Democratic parties. The Communist Party fought on the slogan of fusion of the two parties; the Social Democrats did not openly contradict this—a grave mistake—though they indicated that they wanted to maintain their party’s independence. Two days before the elections irregularities in electoral procedure were discovered—the famous blue voting slips- and the Party’s Executive met to discuss the situation. The faction led by Szakasits, the Party Secretary, either did not attend or left during the meeting. It was decided that the party would not be a partner to any irregularities, though it was not known exactly what was afoot, since Szakasits was not present. I must admit that I did not myself fully understand the situation until after the elections, when during a joint meeting the Communists reproached us with having given them away. In this they were right, since our crypto-communist “left-wing” told them only at the last minute that we refused to participate in any kind of electoral fraud. This proved to be too late for the Communists who could not call off their campaign. The Social Democratic Party’s left-wing promised that the party would not officially protest, but the Social Democratic rank and file were aroused and angry and thus made this deal impossible.</p><p>Communist officials in the Ministry of the Interior struck off the names of thousands of Social Democratic voters from the registers. The Communists’ report of imminent fusion with the Social Democrats cost the latter over 100,000 votes to parties of the Right. The blue voting slips gave the Communists many thousands of illegal votes. As a result the Social Democrats suffered defeat and the Communists gained an undeserved victory. We won 67 seats; the Communists 100.</p><p>Our party received a shock; there was a feeling of unjustified defeat and a revolt against Szakasits and his followers. Factory workers, local organisations, and civil servants called for the annulment of the election results, and demanded increased Social Democratic participation in police and army administration. At the same time they wanted to eliminate from the party leadership those who had proved unreliable and unlikely to resist Communist plans for fusion.</p><p>Though I did not myself endorse then desire for an open fight between the party’s "left" and “right" wings, the workers inside the party placed their confidence increasingly in myself. They asked me to lay down my ministerial functions and return as deputy-secretary of the party. The “left-wing" thought themselves defeated and the Communists also realised that 90 per cent of the party was behind us. Szakasits and the other pro-Communists resigned, hoping to put the party into an impossible position by implying that the party was becoming reactionary and anti-Soviet. Later, on the advice of the Russian Embassy, they returned to their posts. I continued at the Ministry of Industry on the understanding that a successor would soon be found so that I could begin my party work.</p><p>We may be accused of having left the leadership in the hands of those we knew to be unreliable. But it must be realised that the majority of the party officials were reliable, even though Szakasits was in charge. We were quite convinced of the need to maintain party unity and did not wish to appear anti-Soviet. During these weeks Szakasits told me repeatedly that he would not permit the exclusion of any of his adherents and would be prepared, if necessary, to split the party.</p><p>In the meantime international tension increased. The Cominform in Hungary decided to eliminate the “rightist" influence in the Social Democratic Party, in order to bring about a close working union between our left-wing and the Communists. It was given out that all social Democrats who opposed this close link were “dollar imperialists”, traitors to the working-class and anti- Russian.</p><p>Here I must emphasise that we, the great majority, are not opposed to a reasonable working arrangement with the Communists, that we are not anti-Soviet, and do not wish to make concessions to Hungarian reaction. On the contrary, we oppose reaction, wish to fight fascism and build a real democracy. But a constant stream of propaganda repeated that all Social Democrats (except the Szakasits wing) were enemies of the people, and the workers became confused and alarmed.</p><p>On 31 December, there was a meeting of the Budapest district’s Executive Committee—mainly composed of middle-class intellectuals. This passed a resolution which was in fact a declaration of war on the party majority. It called for unconditional support of a “left-wing” policy, and bitterly attacked Szelig, one of the main defenders of an independent policy and an outstanding working-class leader. Szakasits received this resolution and instead of submitting it to the Party Executive as he should have done constitutionally, published it in the party newspaper. From that moment there was open war within the party- a state of affairs which Moscow radio welcomed triumphantly.</p><p>At the same time a storm broke about the Ministry of Industry, which was a stronghold of Social Democracy, for the reason that its activity concerned the whole working class. While I was out of the country, investigations were started, people arrested and accused of crooked financial dealings and treason. I have never seen the material on which these trials were based. The Under-Secretary of my Ministry, Keleman, a member of the Party Executive and a leader of the so-called “right-wing.” was arrested and sentenced to hard labour for life.</p><p>This was the situation I found on my return after an absence of six weeks—trials, press attacks, denunciations of Social Democrats, pressure by the political police on our people, a gradual breaking down of all powers of resistance. It would have been impossible to call on the movement to resist, without such resistance being declared counter-revolutionary and so being broken up. I had to consider the task calmly and realistically; somehow the position had to be consolidated, the pressure lifted from the party, and time won to assure the continued existence of the party. I therefore made the following proposals.</p><p>The coming Congress would be prepared and everything agreed beforehand. The “left” would be given the leadership, but in return for two guarantees—the independence of the party and no persecution of our people. The price would be the retirement of those people regarded as an obstacle to the realisation of this measure.</p><p>The party leadership agreed that this conception was the only possibility, particularly as Szakasits, Marosan and other members of the “left” repeatedly declared that they wished the party to retain its independence. In short, they were to have taken over responsibility, and with our co-operation, continue to lead the party.</p><p>Then events took place which had nothing to do with this agreement, as the “left-wing” worked all the time under Communist orders, and brought the real independence of the party to an end. The party leadership and political committee were by-passed and the Szakasits wing led by Marosan overwhelmed the party with a carefully staged meeting in Budapest on 28 February. Here certain expulsions and the resignation of several comrades (Kethly, Ban, etc.) were announced. The battle had taken a new turn. Marosan spoke about fusion as if it were just about to happen. This had a profoundly demoralising influence on the party which had lived under tension for months. The fight was won for the Communist Party—the Social Democratic Party had fallen to pieces. In the days that followed thousands of our members applied to join the Communist Party. This was caused by fear for their personal safety, for it was decidedly unsafe to be classified as a "right-wing" Social Democrat. Entire party organisations went over bodily to the Communist Party. The Communists officially claimed 200,000 admissions of former Social Democratic Party members and mentioned a further 40,000 applicants. The left usurpers remained without a party. They were faced with the fact that the Social Democratic Party would be annihilated by the Szakasits group and the Communist Party before its Congress and thus would not be able to fuse of its own "free will. Marosan and his friends decided to cease all activities and to wait for the crash. When the Communists were told this, they stooped recruiting new members and thus saved the "Congress".  At the same time, they pressed for the expulsion of Szelig and others (Kethly, Ban. Szeder).</p><p>It was during these anxious days that I was given to understand that only special consideration had kept me from being involved as the chief defendant in the treason trials. I was no longer permitted to speak to the workers, my articles were not published, and I was prevented even from making contact with the Communist Party. I was also forbidden to take part in the Congress.</p><p>The Congress was arranged with the help of the Communist Party it excluded us from the party and declared for fusion. The necessary committees with the Communist Party were formed, and prepare the technical details for fusion by 1 July, 1948.</p><p>Now "purges” have begun, removing thousands of Social Democrats who do not belong to the “left”, from the police, the army, industry and the civil service. Specially appointed committees are carrying out this work of persecution.</p><p>The broad masses of Social Democrats have had nothing to do with all this; they have remained faithful to our traditions, and feel with us. Even if the party has been physically destroyed it continues to live in the spirit of the Hungarian workers. The reason why the working masses did not make a final heroic gesture, after more than two years of bitter struggle, to express their faith Democracy will be understood by all those who know the present hopeless position in Eastern Europe, and who understand what 25 of oppression under counter-revolution have meant for the workers.</p></body></text></TEI>