<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Berlin - City of decision</title>
         <author>Executive Committee of the SPD</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Berlin - City of decision</title>
            <author>Executive Committee of the SPD</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="German" party="German Social Democratic Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><div><head>Berlin—City of decision </head><p>Helmstedt, a small German country town, almost entirely unknown to the outside world, has become a suburb of Washington, and nearby Marienborn is now near Moscow—this is what was recently said in a German periodical. And one might add that Berlin has become the modern Babel in a world of unparalleled confusion. In this town the decision concerning the future of the world’s peoples is in the balance.</p><p>There has been no political event in Germany since the end of World War II, which has taught the Germans in the same way to think again politically, to show a firm, determined attitude, and which at the same time lets the world sec how strong the truly democratic forces in Germany really are. And something else has become evident: these democratic forces have their most effective representation in the German Social Democratic Party. The 10th October, 1946, was the day which revealed this fact in Berlin. On that day the Social Democratic Party gained a decisive success in the elections, and looking back to-day one can say conclusively that without this great demonstration of faith, and above all without a firm attitude afterwards, the situation of the Allies would have been hopelessly weakened from the outset.</p><p>Two weeks after the introduction of the new currency in the Western Zones the real fight for Berlin began. In this fight the Berlin Social Democrats were the only party which remained firm, with no hesitation born of thoughtlessness or shortsightedness, in an unconditional rejection of any dictatorship, whether it springs from a party which is only superficially German or from one of the occupying powers.</p><p>It is in the SPD that freedom-loving democracy and resistance against foreign interference and political totalitarianism can be most strictly observed. It is therefore logical that moral and human support in Western Germany in the fight for Berlin, as far as it is carried on by the Germans themselves, is led chiefly by the Social Democratic Party. It was as a result of the Hamburg meeting of the SPD Executive on 28-30 June, 1948, that the first strong feelings had an effect on the mind of the whole of Western Germany— that is, to organise with all possible means resistance against the attempt to conquer Berlin by means of the cold war. The population of all the large towns in the Western Zones proclaimed their unity with Berlin. Food is being collected and thousands of parcels find their way over the air-bridge to relations and friends in the besieged city, whose spirit, according to the will of the Russian occupying power, is to be broken. Willi Eichler, Fritz Heine and Franz Neumann of the SPD Executive Committee flew to London, where they had discussions about the Berlin situation with Foreign Minister Bevin and other important personalities of the Labour Party.</p><p>Erich Ollenhauer, deputising for Kurt Schumacher who is still ill, addressed a meeting on the Herthaplatz in Berlin, which will rank as one of the most impressive political events of post-war Germany. And everywhere at meetings or conferences where Berlin’s Mayor Luise Schroeder speaks or is present, this warm hearted, clever and modest woman encounters affectionate sympathy intended both for herself and to the city she represents.</p><p>All this has nothing to do with nationalist exuberance—at least not where Social Democrats take the lead. Behind each thought and act is the still very lively memory of the dictatorship which was only overcome by terrible sacrifices and the determination not to yield a second time to a still worse despotism. In the afternoon on 23rd June, 1948, a riotous mob of several hundred Socialist Unity Party demonstrators crowded before the Berlin Stadthaus. Soon they rushed into the building and occupied the galleries and part of the floor of the house, where they ranted and roared for two hours. In the evening, after the assembly meeting was over, they attacked several town councillors as they were leaving the building. Two of them, Jeanette Wolff and Otto Bach, members of the SPD, were struck down and severely injured. Reliable eye-witnesses report that there was no difference at all between these SED demonstrators and the raiding-squads of Nazi Storm Troopers in the ’thirties. It is against this that Berliners, led by the Social Democratic Party, are fighting.</p><p>The wonderful help and assistance which the Western Allies are giving to Berlin is generally appreciated. It is based on a feeling of responsibility for the lives of the people under their care, but also on a knowledge that Berlin is the point where it will be decided whether or not Germany and Western Europe can he saved for the ideals of liberal democracy. The continued success of the air lift and currency reform should not lead us to ignore the fact that the position is still very critical, but Berlin has become a convincing proof of the German’s choice of free democracy.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>