<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>International socialist planning</title>
         <author>G.M.Nederhorst</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>International socialist planning</title>
            <author>G.M.Nederhorst</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Dutch" party="Dutch Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Socialist economic planning is at present a subject of great political importance. In different countries economic planning is now accepted and forms part of government policy, and many kinds of authorities have been set up, charged with the administration and execution of economic plans.</p><p>Among important instances now operating may be mentioned far-reaching economic planning in Norway, the Monnet Plan in France, the plans for stabilising the trade cycle in Sweden, and the planning of production in Great Britain, Belgium and the Netherlands. Compared with the situation we knew before the war, much has changed, not only in government policy, but also in our conception of a socialist world.</p><p>Before the First World War planning was not generally accepted in the socialist movement. Marx and his followers wrote much about socialism, but you can find no mention, of planning in their works. After 1918, the socialist movement began to advocate socialisation of some of the more important industries, but these nationalisations were not part of a general plan for production and distribution. The idea of planning came much later.</p><p>On the other hand private industry began to develop planning. Starting in the United States, there was a great extension in the system of production based on a programme fixed in advance. Another form of planning concerns government finances. For a long time we have known about the budget for public finance: state income and expenditure took the form of a planned budget in the 17th century. These two forms of planning—in private industry and in public finance—can be considered as the origin of the present economic planning system.in the European countries.</p><p>It was the Soviet Union which started the great experiment, and by its successive Five-Year Plans began systematically to forecast its economic future. In these plans socialisation was combined with the planning which had been known for many years in private industry. Democratic socialism accepted this combination of planning and socialisation, and made it part of its own economic policy. And at .the present moment planning and socialism are so closely linked with each other that no socialist party would question the very great importance of planning. This does not mean, however, that planning and socialisation are the same. Planning is nothing more than a method for the realisation of socialism, although through planning other results can also be achieved.</p><div><head>From national to international planning </head><p>A second fact to which I would like to draw attention is that so far we have known only planning of national production. International planning has not yet begun. Moreover, when we talk about planning to-day, we mean the planning of a national economy which is not a completely socialist society. True, there has been development towards socialism, but there still exists an important private sector in industry. When we consider what possibilities there* are for international socialist planning, we must admit that at this moment, in the present political situation, we cannot always go as far as we would like. As democratic socialists we must accept that in most countries there is not yet a majority for socialisation on the scale we would like to sec. This is not only the situation in the countries where the socialist movement is in a minority and must join in coalitions with other parties, but in my opinion also in countries like Great Britain and Sweden, where democratic socialists have a majority in Parliament, but where nevertheless it is impossible to carry out far-reaching measures of socialisation, as there is great opposition in these countries against it. Just as in those countries where democratic socialists must accept coalition with other parties, we have to create in countries where a socialist government does exist a climate favourable to socialist developments before we can realise our policy. We must proceed steadily in this way, but we have to face the fact that progress often is not made as quickly as we should like. '</p><p>Where international co-operation of the socialist movement is concerned, it is an advantage that in most European countries we are developing towards the same political situation. Belgium, the Netherlands, France and Italy all have governments in which the democratic socialists and Christian Democrats are co-operating. That creates problems, because our partners are not inclined to go as far as we want in the direction of socialism.</p><p>On this subject each socialist party has different experiences and it would be of great interest to exchange information concerning the different political problems which arise during collaboration with other parties in the government. On the economic side this means, as 1 said earlier, that there remain some industries which in our opinion are ready for nationalisation, but which our partners in the government prefer to remain in private hands. If production front these industries is to form a real part of the overall economic plan, it is absolutely necessary that Governments should not leave them uncontrolled, but take measures to subordinate their production within the plan as a whole. To achieve this there are two alternatives. These industries can remain under private ownership and be placed under government control: this means that civil servants have the controlling voice. Or the government can take part in the administration of those branches of industry which are not yet ready for socialisation, by creating an organisation consisting of government representatives, trade unionists and employers, which will carry out the plan.</p><p>The first form—private industry under government control— has the disadvantage that the industrialists are usually opposed to government policy. The government then acts like a policeman, overruling the industrialists’ decisions on the subject of prices, wages, location of new factories, and so on, when they do not correspond with government policy.</p><p>Control by government also means that a great deal of administrative work must be done twice, first by private industry, and afterwards for a second time by civil servants.</p></div><div><head>The danger of bureaucracy </head><p>Another great disadvantage is that many civil servants are necessary to carry out the task of control. It is therefore always possible for private industry under government control to become inefficient, because of an inflated bureaucracy. This has a bad influence on public opinion, which is always prejudiced against the civil servants in charge of controls, and against the government, which is responsible for decisions which may affect the interest of certain groups of society.</p><p>For this reason it is better not to limit ourselves to control by civil servants, but to go a step further. This means that the government must not only control private industry, must also take part in management by forming boards, which are not only charged with control over private industry, but which can also give some direction to the management.</p><p>Those mixed committees will consist of three groups of representatives: one of trade unions, the second of the employers, and the third of representatives of the government, technical experts and, wherever possible, of representatives of the consumers. These semi-official administrators must have the right to give direction to private industry on all matters which concern the planning of private industry. Among these are price, policy, location of new factories, production methods, and so on.</p><p>It is hardly necessary to say that the ultimate decision must remain in the hands of the government, but in practice in most cases the civil servant who represents the government on the executive board will express the Minister's view in such a way that the government’s economic policy will be sufficiently respected.</p><p>By giving influence to representatives of the trade union and the government a form of management is created which is divided between the government and private industry, while on the other hand responsibility is also divided.</p><p>Only in this wav will it be possible to avoid the dangers of bureaucracy, while the presence of consumers and the government on the committee is a guarantee that there will he no restrictive practices or domination by private interests over economic policy.</p><p>A further important result is that in this way the labour movement acquires knowledge of what happens in private industry. There are no longer any secrets about profits and the incomes of industrialists. I know we do not all think the same of this subject. Our Belgian comrades are unwilling to take any responsibility for production in the private sector of industry. They leave management of production as a whole to government institutions and limit themselves to purely advisory councils.</p><p>The problem of socialisation and the organisation of the private sector in industry is one aspect of the problem of socialist economic planning. The other aspect, which is of equal importance, is the fact that for most countries planning on a national scale is no longer an adequate means of raising the people’s standard of living.</p></div><div><head>Towards a larger economic unit </head><p>When we consider the importance of Soviet Russia and the United States as economic units, it is an illusion to believe that it is possible for the small European countries to compete successfully with these great economic powers on the world market. If Europe means to have a place in the sun it will be absolutely necessary to make Europe an economic unit which can compare with the other two great economic powers.</p><p>From the point of view of socialist economic planning, it is possible that difficulties may arise at this point. All the countries have not advanced towards socialism to the same extent.</p><p>Close economic co-operation between the different states of Europe may mean that there will be danger that a country where the political situation is favourable for socialisation on a national scale must temporarily give up this decision, because in other countries there is so much opposition that it is impossible to carry it out. For some countries international planning may be an obstacle to far-reaching socialisation.</p><p>What is our policy to he in such a situation? Shall we give up our activity for international co-operation, and try to go as far as possible on a national scale? Or shall we take the risk that we may be hampered in our national socialist policy by co-operation on an international scale, which may not go as far as would be possible in our own country? I have no hesitation in answering that it is our duty to venture on international co-operation even when international co-operation means, for a short time, that we must give up some parts of our socialist policy in the national field.</p><p>In any case it is impossible, especially for the small countries of Europe, to find a solution for their economic problems by carrying on alone and trying to get out of their difficulties by national measures; I know that this is not generally accepted. I believe that this point was discussed at the Congress of the British Labour Party. The point of view that was defended there was that if the rest of Europe should hamper socialist development, Great Britain should put off European co-operation until the European countries has socialist governments. But Europe, and especially the small countries, can never become socialist as separate nations. They have not the economic foundation for a real socialist society. If we are to succeed, internationalisation is the first step.</p><p>I emphasise this because if Europe is to be constructed on a sound foundation, there must be planning and production of goods on a European scale. And I am convinced that experience will make it clear to people as a whole that socialist planning is the only way out of our difficulties.</p><p>Temporarily it seems as if we must take a step backward in our policy, but in the end international development will show that on this sounder basis we can go forward faster towards our socialist goal. If the socialist movement wants to have more influence on the international situation then it must know exactly what it wants and make its suggestions in the form of concrete proposals.</p></div><div><head>Principles of Economic Co-operation </head><p>If we are agreed that economic planning at the moment is only possible if all countries pool their economic resources, then we must examine the main principles of this co-operation. There are some resources which must be put under international management. With others it will be sufficient to co-ordinate policy, while for the time being they remain officially under national supervision. Finally there are some sectors of economic life in each country which will remain untouched by international co-operation.</p><p>It follows from what has just been stared that international control will be necessary for the production of raw materials: for example, coal and iron and steel. A second field for international management will include some public utilities. Consider, for instance, electricity and gas supply and the necessity to unify our railway and air-transport policy. In most countries these branches of the national economy belong to the government, or at least the various governments have great influence over their policy. It is therefore possible to join together their forces by bringing them under European management.</p></div><div><head>Control of credit policy </head><p>Of particular importance is credit policy in Europe. Short-term credit is mostly given by commercial banks, which are in private hands. Long-term credits, which are of great importance to investments in industry, are given partly by private banks and partly by special government institutions. On the other hand, the European Recovery Programme will make it possible for the different governments to receive money with which they can finance private industry, which is at the moment short of capital. If we want to prevent private banking from getting great influence on the economic life of Western Europe by means of large-scale credits, we must organise the credit systems and investments of the various governments. It will therefore be absolutely necessary to unite the different national efforts, and to decide on the foundation of an international financial institution to supply the credits which European industry needs for reconstruction. In such an institution the international socialist movement must have representation on the executive council; otherwise the European financial institution will become an instrument to further the expansion of private industry.</p><p>Another sector of economic life in which international control will be possible in the near future is international trade. European imports and exports must be seen as a whole. It is impossible for any country in Western Europe to act without taking into consideration the international trade policy of the other countries.</p><p>We must try to stimulate developments in the direction of common European selling agencies on foreign markets. This will not be achieved at once, but we must go step by step in this direction. If the Western European countries were represented on foreign markets as if they were one country, comparable with Russia and the United States, then their position would be stronger and would enable them to compete successfully with those countries.</p><p>Raw materials, credits for investment, public utilities and European imports and exports are already suitable for planning under international management. International management must be distinguished from international supervision. It may be that we must start on some points with international supervision, as a step towards international management, but the supervision itself is not sufficient to achieve the aims we want. By controls you can change decisions in private industry after they have been taken and after steps have been taken to carry out these decisions. When the decision is changed, it causes great loss of time and a good deal of trouble in private industry, which will complain about this international interference. Therefore it is much better to establish international committees, which must have the power to initiate policy and give directions to the industries under their control. This means that international socialisation of these industries would not be far off. </p></div><div><head>Co-ordination of national policies </head><p>This is not the case with that sector of private industry which it is not necessary to bring under direct international management, but where it is sufficient to take measures to co-ordinate different national policies. In this connection attention may be drawn to sea-ports. It ought to be possible to come to an agreement on the tariff-system in relation to sea-ports in such a way that inter- European competition is avoided.</p><p>Another point where co-ordination of economic policy will be of great advantage to economic well-being is an agreement on industrial policy. In the different countries the governments have their own ideas about the direction in which they seek a solution of the industrial problems. There are different economic programmes, but it would be disastrous if we should all take the same decisions, for instance, by the establishment of particular industries. In the industrialisation of Western Europe it will be necessary for the different countries to become complementary to one another.</p><p>By co-ordinating the national industrial plans and by taking into consideration the special interests which exist in each country on this subject, we must develop our policy in the direction of an industrial policy for Europe as a whole.</p><p>Co-ordination of policy is also of great importance with wages and prices and with taxation. In our countries wages and price levels are different, but we all face the same difficulty: how can we prevent wages and prices rising? How can we prevent inflation? The principle of planning must be applied not only to production problems, but to control wages and prices, too. It is not necessary that wages and prices in the different countries should be exactly the same. There might be some differences, because within each country- there are differences: for instance, between wages in the big towns and in the villages. But the principle of our policy for wages and prices must be the same in order to prevent dumping on the international market.</p><p>In this connection, the export drive which each country has opened is not without danger. Our comrade Cripps is very proud —as I can appreciate—of the export figures of Great Britain. We in Holland, too, do our best to stimulate exports, but what will be the situation in the country which receives these goods? Will this mean price competition within Europe on such a scale that unemployment will arise? This will be the case if we do not go beyond national planning, if we do not have the courage to see these problems from an international point of view.</p><p>We face the same difficulties with taxation policy. Taxes are very high in most countries. Capitalists may be inclined to flee with their money to other countries. It will therefore be necessary to co-ordinate our taxation policy to prevent this.</p><p>All this belongs to the section of economic life in which we have on the one hand a certain degree of freedom to follow a particular policy nationally, but where on the other hand we cannot succeed without co-ordination of our policies.</p><p>Finally there are some sections of national economic life which remain untouched by the international developments we aim at. For instance, the way each country tackles the housing problem, and their measures in relation to retail trade are of no importance to Western European collaboration as a whole. In these fields the different countries are free to follow their own policy, because they will not react on the other countries of Western Europe.</p></div><div><head>The task before us </head><p>To summarise: there are three different parts of economic life, each with its own policy. Firstly there is a sector of economic life which must be brought under international management. Whether it will be full international socialisation or a more moderate form of international management will be a matter of practical policy. In the second place there is a sector of economic life where a national policy remains in some form, but where co-ordination and mutual understanding will be necessary. And lastly there is a small sector where we can have a purely national policy, because that will have no consequences in international life.</p><p>The international socialist movement is at a decisive point in its historical development. If we want to succeed in solving these problems our international organisation can play a great part. We must set ourselves the task of making a serious study of these problems so that we have the economic foundation we need for our international policy. The working out of these ideas is for experts, but it must be supported by the political parties. In my opinion this will be our best contribution to a free, democratic, and socialist Europe.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>