<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Socialism and planning in Austria</title>
         <author>Karl Waldbrunner</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Socialism and planning in Austria</title>
            <author>Karl Waldbrunner</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Austrian" party="Socialist Party of Austria"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>It is many years since Austrian socialists won their first victories in the struggle to bring the means of production under public control and create a planned socialist economy.</p><p>A great step forward was made under the first Republic after the collapse of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy. The revolutionary situation and famine conditions gave the Social Democrats the opportunity to take the first practical measures. Otto Bauer and Karl Renner went over from theory to practice, and the successes they then gained could not be wiped out even under the bitter reaction which followed. Two conclusions were fully confirmed by this experience. Firstly, only planned economy under democratic control and serving the public interest can repair the disastrous consequences caused by capitalism with its wars and crises, and call for the fewest sacrifices from the people. Secondly, such a planned economy can only be successful if key industries are under public control. If transport, fuel and power, heavy industry and the Banks remain in private hands after they have reached the monopolistic stage, planned economy is impossible.</p><p>After 1918, therefore, the first step towards socialism in Austria was taken by nationalising a large number of undertakings: nearly all the railways, a large proportion of the electricity undertakings, and a number of individual factories. Heavy industry and the banks, however, were not affected. It was therefore not difficult for the attempts at planned economy to be liquidated afterwards. It was not long before the Austrian workers felt the consequences: banks collapsed, factories closed, unemployment increased. Nevertheless, all the progress made then was not liquidated. The railways remained nationalised, electricity, gas and water undertakings remained in the hands of local authorities. The section of publicly-owned industry—which had already included the state monopolies over salt and tobacco, as well as post and telegraph services—received considerable reinforcement.</p><p>In the years after 1918 “Red Vienna” played a prominent pan. For socialists Vienna was the testing ground for planning, a school in socialist economy and administration for younger generations of socialists.</p><p>Thanks to the practical achievements of our comrades of the first Republic, and thanks to their teachings, we were in a much better position in 1945 to carry on the work. And now looking back over the last three years, we can see what obstacles we have had to face in our efforts to establish a planned Socialist economy.</p><p>Of course the full weight of the bourgeois and peasant classes was opposed to us, for these classes are interested in preserving capitalism and its profit motive.</p><p>In addition, we have had to suffer military occupation by four great powers. Each of these powers has its own point of view on economic matters and has therefore pursued a separate policy in regard to Austrian affairs. Furthermore, the unfortunate definition of “German property" in the Potsdam agreement meant that the fate of a large number of the most important industrial undertakings in the country remains legally undetermined as long as there is no peace treaty.</p><p>The situation is made even more complicated by the communists who pursue a policy of demagogy and sabotage in the economic field under orders from a foreign power.</p><div><head>A desperate situation </head><p>While the People’s Party and the Communists, our partners in the provisional government, opposed any step in the direction of socialism and planned economy, we forced through the first measures. The situation we had to face was desperate enough. Industrial equipment was completely worn out; there was enormous war damage—in buildings alone it is estimated at five billion Schilling; factories were dismantled and stocks of new materials requisitioned by the occupying forces. We now reckon that machinery and equipment worth 1 1/2 billion Schilling have been looted since 1945.</p><p>It was quite clear to us that the difficulties facing us could only be solved by planning. But an essential prerequisite—as we had discovered from the experience of 1918—was nationalisation of the key industries, power plants, oil and coal reserves, and above all the banks. At the time we had no parliament which could pass the necessary legislation; the provisional government’s authority scarcely extended beyond Vienna and did not exist at all in the Russian Zone. We therefore had to improvise. In the most important factories, and in banks, insurance offices and so on, we installed officials appointed after consultation with the trade unions.</p><p>We were quite convinced that socialisation would give rise to quite new legal questions, as well as involving a new approach to management and organisation. But there was not enough time to work all these matters out in advance. For this reason we decided on straightforward nationalisation in the laws which we, though still a minority party, put through the freshly elected parliament in 1946 and 1947.</p></div><div><head>Nationalisation begins </head><p>Law 168 of 26 July, 1946, nationalised the three largest banks, all existing coal mines, oil wells and refineries, iron and steel works, heavy electrical industries (except Brown-Boveri), locomotive, wagon and shipbuilding plants, a large number of heavy engineering concerns, the Oesterrcichischen Stickstoffwerke (chemicals), and the Danube Steamship Company.</p><p>Under Law 81 of 26 March, 1947, the entire electric power industry was either nationalised or transferred to the ownership of the individual Bundesländer (federal regions). All installations serving the whole country became 100 per cent, state property. Other large installations serving more than one of the Bundesländer became public companies in which the State has at least 50 per cent, bf the shares, the rest being divided among the Bundesländer concerned. Shares in publicly-owned companies held by private individuals were taken over by the Bundesländer under the new law. As a result the entire electricity supply, except for that generated by individual factories for their own use, came under public ownership.</p><p>In choosing industries for nationalisation we took the view that all monopolies should become state property. Our decision was not governed by whether industries were making profits and would therefore make some contribution to the State or making losses and therefore in need of subsidies. Our experience under the first Republic was decisive. Monopolies can hold the entire national economy to ransom, and if they remain in the hands of capitalists too easily become the forerunners of fascism.</p><p>It is more than likely that what made the bourgeois politicians so ready to agree to nationalise many of these industries was the fact that many of them had suffered very great damage during the war, and that Austria had no capitalists in a position to reconstruct them and make them profitable again.</p><p>The nationalisation of key positions in industry strongly reinforced our far-reaching demands for economic planning. A special ministry was set up to deal with the administration or the nationalised industries and with economic planning for the country as a whole. To our chagrin we had to admit that we were not strong enough to put a Socialist in as minister. The present Minister for Economic Planning is a member of the Austrian People’s Party and a declared enemy of socialist planning. No wonder that Austria has no overall economic plan and so has lost a great many advantages. We have to be content with isolated regional plans for the various branches of industry, depending more or less on the voluntary co-operation of managers and technicians in these industries. Thanks to these men and the political influence of socialism it has been possible, in spite of difficulties, to make significant progress towards a planned economy. </p><p>By reason of our positive policy we have been able to win over to our point of view many technicians who are not Socialists but who appreciate that reconstruction and prosperity cannot be achieved without direction and planning of the most important sectors of our economy. This brings us to a question which is very important for all Socialists: the problem of staffing nationalised industries, especially in relation to central planning.</p></div><div><head>Management of nationalised industries </head><p>Our experience in this field confirms the confident predictions made concerning the transition from a privately to publicly owned economy. With the development from individual capitalism with its concerns owned and managed by one man to finance capitalism with its specialist directors there has been a far reaching change in management. Owner-managers have become highly paid officials. The functions of these men remain practically the same whether they are performed under private or public ownership. In the change from private to public ownership these men have to adapt themselves from serving the shareholders’ desire for profits to serving the interests of the community as a whole. We nave met many examples of enthusiastic change of this kind by many technicians and managers. This is not really surprising, for there is also full scope for outstanding ability in public service.</p><p>We have been able to observe this process while a number of important questions have been dealt with lately. In this connection I will only mention the currency reform which was inspired by us Socialists and carried through in collaboration with economists who were not Socialists. This reform, as we can sec to-day, greatly helped our economy, bringing more healthy conditions so that our economic life is now gradually returning to normal.</p><p>The work of the last three years has brought great progress. Economic developments appear to be proving that our policy was right. We socialists have laid the foundations for a great economic advance which cannot fail to have political consequences.</p><p>We have prevented the key positions in our economy from once again returning into the hands of our enemies. By doing this we have made a repetition of the developments between 1918 and 1934 impossible. The great iron and steel firms and the banks are now nationalised and so cannot again finance fascism.</p><p>We have made it possible for Austria to take its place within the European economic system, which, with the help of the Marshall Plan, must bring rapid improvements, and so create a base for resistance to the influence and demands of totalitarian Eastern Europe. The problem of incorporation in Western Europe’s economic system is not easy, for Austria has always been, even under the Hapsburg monarchy, closely linked with Last and South-East Europe. It is obvious, however, that developments in the last few years have already brought a fundamental change.</p><p>We Austrian Socialists can and will travel only the democratic road to Socialism. We do not believe it is longer or calls for more sacrifices than the road with no democracy and no regard for individual rights. We believe we have shown by our efforts that even under unfavourable conditions it is possible in a democracy to make progress towards a socialist economy. But reinforcement of public control by nationalising heavy industries and the banks is only progress if it goes hand in hand with reinforcement of democracy inside industry itself.</p><p>We do not intend to replace capitalist exploitation by exploitation by the State; we do not intend to replace the workers’ economic bondage under capitalism by economic pressure from the State. If we did these things we should be no different from the "people's democracies" and the Soviet Union.</p><p>Leadership in industry must not remain exclusively a matter for the government. Workers and technicians, as well as consumers, must be able to influence policy, so that a sense of responsibility for the national economy is spread as widely as possible. In this respect we have a long way to go, and a good deal of experimentation will be needed before we find the best form of organisation for the purpose. In the meantime we have passed a law which gives workers and technicians representation on the production councils, and allows them to take part in industrial management. In addition, the works council has a large voice in settling working conditions in the factory. In all nationalised industries production councils include, in addition to representatives of the State and of the workers, representatives of industrial consumers and the co-operative movement.</p><p>Without exaggeration, we Socialists in Austria believe that we have had great success with socialist planning. This belief is based on the knowledge that the majority of the people are with us, and that the people at last controls its own economic life. The keystones or our policy of building industrial democracy are the strengthening of the publicly-owned sector of industry, and the avoidance of state tyranny. By these means we are trying to build a completely planned economy, so that Austria can become a living socialist community.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>