<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Norway since liberation</title>
         <author>Haakon Lie</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Norway since liberation</title>
            <author>Haakon Lie</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Norwegian" party="Norwegian Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Since Norway’s liberation in May, 1945, the Norwegian people have been in the fortunate position of being able to concentrate on the task of reconstruction without serious interruption from political quarrels. This is due partly to the fact that in a country like Norway, where social and material differences are not very wide, the feelings of national unity were strengthened during the war years through common enmity towards the Germans; but the Labour Government is also partly responsible. It came to power after liberation and has since favoured a moderate policy, one of its most important points being a programme of reconstruction which is supported by all parties. Only on some minor points is there opposition against the Government, but even on these there is disunity amongst the other parties, which cannot agree among themselves on a programme of their own.</p><p>Shortly after the liberation a coalition government was formed in which all parties took part. This was a continuation of the coalition government which had existed in London during the war —but under a new Premier Minister, Einar Gerhardsen, one of the leaders of the Labour Party, who had been very active in the underground resistance movement and who was freed by the Allies at the end of the war from the concentration camp of Sachsenhausen, where he had been imprisoned for three years.</p><p>In the general election in the autumn of 1945 the Labour Party gained 76 out of 150 scats in the Storthing and thus had an absolute majority; the Conservatives won 25 seats, the Liberals 20, the Communists 11, the Peasants 10, and the Christian People’s Party 8. Although .the Labour Party was in favour of a high degree of control over industry and the whole economic life, its election programme stressed more the question of reconstruction than that of socialisation; all other parties consented to this for the time being, while the special circumstances created by the war were still in existence. It was necessary to replace a large part of the machinery necessary for production, and to build up food and raw material reserves; economic resources had to be further developed in order to enable the standard of living to be raised above the pre-war level.</p><p>The government which was formed after the general election consisted entirely of member» of the labour Party. The Prime Minister and some other members of the government had been political prisoners in Germany during the war; others had been active members of the resistance movement.</p><div><head>Priority for reconstruction</head><p>According to the government’s plan, economic reconstruction of the country was to be completed within five years, and there is hope that in most fields this aim will be achieved. Industrial production has increased from 65 per cent, of pre-war production at the time of the liberation, to about 120 per cent, at the end of 1947, and if no serious difficulties arise in connection with the import of raw materials, this high level of production will continue. The merchant navy, the largest single factor in Norway’s economic life, has already regained three-quarters of its pre-war tonnage— about 50 per cent, of the merchant navy had been lost during the war. Considerable progress has been made in the improvement of transport facilities and the reconstruction of industry. Housing is rather less satisfactory. Building stopped entirely during the war, and in addition a number of towns in the north and west of the country were destroyed by bombing. Thus Norway was confronted by a serious housing problem at the end of the war; it is estimated that 100,000 new dwellings will be needed. So far only 20,000 have been built, since it has been impossible to provide more building materials. Reconstruction in the far north of the country, which was destroyed by the Germans in 1944 during their retreat from the Russian armies, has been largely successful and the population which was then evacuated has been able to return home. Ports, iron ore mines and the fishing fleet were put in order, houses were built and a large number of temporary dwellings provided. These tasks were given priority; the next step is the rebuilding of the bombed towns. The Norwegian coal mines in Svalbard in the Arctic, badly damaged during the war, have been rebuilt and are now producing large quantities of coal. </p><p>A comprehensive system of economic planning and control has been worked out and reconstruction proceeds as a result of collaboration between the state and private industry. Every year the national income is assessed, the resources available for the production of capital and consumer goods are estimated, and the number of workers available in the different branches of industry is calculated. All these items are then balanced against each other in the various production plans. These plans allocate 20 per cent of the national income to investments, particularly in the export industry-—about 90 per cent, of pre-war investments.</p><p>The standard of living has considerably improved since the liberation. Food is more plentiful, though rationing has been maintained for some foodstuffs. Clothing too is still rationed, but available in sufficient quantities. The government has been successful in maintaining the cost of living index at the same level since liberation, but in view of rising prices of agricultural products large amounts have to he spent on food subsidies. Wages are not controlled, but there is a generally recognised agreement between the unions and the employees that wage movements should he kept in accordance with the cost of living index; the unions have also an agreement with the government that general wage claims will not be made during the period of reconstruction. All wages have now reached pre-war level and increases in the lower paid categories do, in fact, represent an increase of the average real wages. The government has also decided on an allowance for children between the ages of one and 16 at the rate of £13 per year. Thus the distribution of the national income has decidedly changed in favour of the workers. A law giving three weeks’ holidays with pay to all workers has also been passed. Unemployment is very low and there is a shortage of labour in most industries. Laws for the improvement and extension of social insurance are in preparation.</p><p>Prices of all goods are strictly controlled. Dividends may not be more than five per cent, per year, and goods whose price on the world market is considerably above the Norwegian price are subject to an export tax, so that the State and not the private producer benefits by this. New capital investments may only he made with government permission. . All these measures are, on the whole, accepted by all parties.</p></div><div><head>Growth of national enterprise </head><p>Although industry on the whole, has not been nationalised, public undertakings are considerably on the increase, and this naturally arouses opposition from the Conservatives. A steel plant with an electrical welding installation is being built by the State in the north of the country; a large aluminium factory which the Germans had begun to build has been taken over by the State and will be run as a publicly-owned undertaking. The State has also bought up the shares of the largest electro-chemical firm, which was formerly owned by the Germans, and control of this firm is thus now in the hands of the public. Furthermore, the government is buying shares in the Norges Bank, which means, in effect, the nationalisation of the most important bank. The numerous projected hydro-electrical plants which are part of the reconstruction plan will be owned either by the State or by local authorities.</p><p>A law to introduce production committees into industry has been passed. These committees are composed of representatives of the employers, the trade unions and the State. They can make proposals about amalgamations and combinations and about bulk-buying and selling, as well as take all other necessary steps to improve industrial efficiency; they also advise the government on industrial questions. They are the link between the government and industry the latter being often in need of greater rationalisation. The other parties opposed the idea of the State taking part in these committees, as they are of the opinion that industry should not he under the supervision of the State.</p><p>There is general agreement among all parties, concerning the law to introduce joint production committees in all industries. These committees consist of representatives of the employers and the trade unions in all firms which employ more than 20 workers, and are to deal with questions of working conditions and efficiency in the factories. Much improvement is expected from their work. Nine hundred and fifty such committees have been formed so far, 180 of them in forestry, which, as is generally known, is a very important branch of Norwegian economy. Relations between workers and employers since the liberation have been good, and there have, so far, been only very few small-scale unofficial strikes.</p><p>Although the Conservatives are strongly opposed to any permanent interference in industry on the part of the State, party struggles are not violent, and there are quite a number of questions on which all parties co-operate. It is likely that the Labour Party will succeed in retaining its leading role in the country: in the next general elections in the autumn of 1949 it will probably gain some of the votes which in 1945 went to the Communists; because of the admiration for Russia’s war record the communist vote was then disproportionately high. For several years before the war the Communists were not represented in the Storthing. International events in the recent past, as well as the fact that people have begun to realise that adherence to democratic methods by Norwegian Communists is rather doubtful, have considerably weakened their position. Inside the trade unions leadership is in the hands of the Labour Party. Membership of the unions since the end of the war has increased considerably, and is now at 450,000; this means that 75 per cent, of all workers are organised. The trade unions work in close co-operation with the Labour Party and the government and play an important part in Norway’s industrial life.</p><p>The success of the Norwegian reconstruction programme proves how much can be achieved by strong and active Social Democracy without curbing those fundamental human liberties, which the Norwegian Labour Party, and indeed all classes of the population except the Communists, have pledged themselves to maintain.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>