<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Denmark’s economic position</title>
         <author>Jorgen Paldam</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Denmark’s economic position</title>
            <author>Jorgen Paldam</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Danish" party="Danish Social Democratic Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Denmark is an agricultural country in the sense that butter, bacon and eggs represent the hulk of our exports. It is through our agricultural exports that we pay for a substantial part of the imports of raw materials and semi-manufactured goods which are essential to the whole of our economic life.</p><p>But Denmark is not an agricultural country in the sense that the majority of our population is associated with agriculture, as the following figures show:</p><p>The relatively important place which industry occupies in the Danish economy is not due to the fact that we have natural industrial resources. Denmark has neither iron, steel, coal, metals, oil, rubber or important chemicals. All these raw materials must be imported. The basis of Danish industry is our manpower alone and favourable geographical position.</p><p>Danish industry is chiefly based on production for the home market. Of the total industrial production before the war we exported only about 12 per cent, and although industrial exports have risen sharply since the war, our industry remains mainly a home-market industry. The bulk of our industrial exports consists of iron and steel products, chemico-technical products, and food and drink.</p><p>On the basis of the available official statistics it can be computed that Danish industry covers at least two-thirds of the internal Danish consumption of industrial goods. The percentage is the highest in the case of food, drink and tobacco, clothing and leather goods. On the other hand, there is still a considerable import requirement of, for example, certain iron and steel products and textile yarns and piece-goods.</p><p>Contrary to what might at first be thought, it is not only our industry which is based on supplies of raw materials and semi-manufactured goods from overseas; our agriculture is in the same position to a very large extent. Denmark is not in a position to produce the very considerable quantities of feeding-stuffs which are required in order to maintain large exports of high-class agricultural produce. On the contrary, our production of butter, bacon and eggs is based on the import of agricultural raw materials.</p><p>In the period 1935-40, for example, we annually imported about 500,000-600.000 tons of grain and 700,000—800,000 tons of oil cake including oil cake produced in Denmark from imported oil seed, in addition, there were imports of considerable quantities of nitrate, phosphate and potash fertilisers.</p><div><head>Decline in agricultural production </head><p>Since the war, unfortunately, it has not been possible to maintain these imports of grain and feeding-stuffs. These raw materials have been subject to international allocation, while prices have been such that only a very limited import has been commercially possible. Our imports of grain have lapsed altogether and the imports of feed cake have dropped to about 200,000 tons annually. The result, of course, has been a heavy decline in Danish agricultural production, and the reduction in 1948 is expected to be considerable owing to the poor harvest in 1947. The production of the leading Danish agricultural products is given below:</p><p>By heavy cuts in the home consumption of butter and bacon it has been possible, however, despite the rapidly declining production, to release quantities of high-class agricultural products for export. Great Britain has long been our principal market for agricultural goods. The next important market was Germany. Before the war Britain and Germany together took 76 per cent, of our export surplus, while 59 per cent, of all our imports came from these two countries. That our exports to Britain in particular were substantially larger than our imports was due to the fact that by exports to Britain we had to ensure a considerable surplus of sterling whi.ch we spent on imports of raw materials from overseas countries, including the Western hemisphere. Denmark’s economic structure, including our production of good quality agricultural produce, was, and still is, based on an export surplus with the highly industrialized countries of Europe and an import surplus from overseas countries.</p><p>In view of this it is obvious that the present restricted availability of sterling outside the so-called sterling area has been a heavy blow to Danish economy. When Britain suspended the convertibility of sterling into dollars in October, 1947, a part of traditional Anglo-Danish trade relations was suspended with it. The problem is not made easier by the fact that Britain herself finds it difficult to deliver many of the essential raw materials, including iron and steel.</p><p>The result of these difficulties in our traditional foreign trade has been to compel us to transfer an important part of our foreign trade dealings to new markets, in the first place to a number of European countries such as Belgium, the Scandinavian countries. Poland and Russia. It must he admitted, however, that this partial redistribution of our foreign trade has not enabled us to solve our dollar problem, although it has been possible by this means to secure important quantities of iron and steel, coal and grain.</p><p>In this connection it must be emphasized that it is especially Danish agriculture which is dependent on dollar imports, as our industry has the advantage of being mainly based on the consumption of raw materials which can be purchased in Europe. Furthermore, the moderate exports we have been able to develop to the Western hemisphere consist in large part of industrial products.</p></div><div><head>The Marshall Plan and after </head><p>The dollar problem sketched here is, of course, a problem common to the whole of Europe and it is now being relieved, at least temporarily, by the Marshall Plan. Yet it is natural to stress what has to be done. For if we fail, when Marshall aid ceases in 1952, to re-establish the possibility of converting European currencies and especially sterling into dollars, Denmark’s economic structure will have to be changed in important respects.</p><p>Up to now we have been a sort of “larder” for Europe, and especially for Great Britain; but the prerequisite has been an ability to obtain, in return, the necessary raw materials and semi-manufactured goods for both our industry and our agriculture. It is and will remain an untenable position if through more or less bilateral pacts we are obliged to try to pay our way by importing industrial goods which our own industry is able to produce quite competitively, or which because of our national reconstruction and the investment needs associated with it we are completely unable to afford.</p><p>In view of our entire economic situation, Denmark must follow with particular attention the discussions that are now taking place in the Committee of European Economic Co-operation in Paris on Europe’s economic position at the end of Marshall aid. If we are not successful first and foremost in making sterling convertible, it is difficult to see how Denmark’s agricultural production can be maintained at the same high level as before the war. So far, at any rate, it has not been possible to buy the necessary feeding-sniffs outside the Western hemisphere, and Great Britain seems likely to have difficulty, without convertibility, in offering us essential goods in adequate quantities.</p><p>Of decisive importance to our future foreign trade are also political and economic developments in Germany. Unfortunately, it has so far been extremely difficult to get trade started with Bizonia. As the Allied authorities have been very slow to allow Danish exports to the zone, we have not been able to maintain exports sufficient to pay for our imports of German coal; nor has the situation been rendered any easier by the Allied requirement that any balance outstanding has had to be settled in dollars. It is hoped, however, that on this point too the Marshall Plan will bring relief.</p><p>For a country like Denmark, which is more dependent on imported supplies than most other countries, it is clear that trade and currency problems must be foremost. It is through our foreign trade that the foundation is laid for an internal economic policy which can assure maximum production and the best possible distribution of the economic resources available to us.</p></div><div><head>Stable cost of living	</head><p>An examination of the price trend in the various countries shows that only a minority of countries, in the period since the beginning of the war, have escaped with a price increase of less than 100 per cent. The cost of living has risen least in Britain; but the Scandinavian countries, including Denmark, follow closely after. The Danish retail price level to date has risen by 68 per cent, beyond the consumption level. The importance of this relative price stability is evident, and the disasters brought about by inflation in countries like Greece, Hungary, Poland and France are well known.</p><p>That it has been possible to avoid uncontrolled price increases is due not least to the monetary deflation that has been carried out. By the end of 1948 it is estimated that 3,500 million Kr. will have been mopped up. This is nearly half of the credit expansion which took place during the war as a result of the demands of the German occupation powers. The absorption of surplus money ought now to be regarded as completed, as any further mopping up would probably have an unfortunate effect, especially on the rate of interest. The absorption has been carried out, inter alia, by means of taxation in the form of a once-for-all levy, tax fines and post- payment of taxes, and confiscation under measures taken against collaborators.</p><p>Other factors which may be mentioned as having contributed to the relative stability of prices are our price-control system and the responsible wage policy that has been pursued by our Trade Unions, which have generally refrained from pressing wage increases beyond the price increases that have taken place. In the latest wage negotiations, for example, despite a violent campaign of abuse by me the Communists, a peaceful conclusion was successfully achieved, whereby tranquillity was assured in the labour market for two year ahead. Unfortunately, other groups have not shown quite the same appreciation of the need for stable prices as the Labour Movement, and in this connection it can be mentioned that the income level of the Danish farmers has risen very considerably.</p><p>As the State, through intervention in economic affairs, assumes an increasing responsibility for seeing that the social mechanism functions satisfactorily, the people become more and more entitled to be kept fully informed of the general economic situation. This is the best guarantee that the necessary economic regulations will never conflict with political democracy.</p><p>Against this background the Labour Government of Hans Hedtoft which was formed in the autumn of 1947 considered it important to prepare a national economic survey—Denmark's first. It was published in June, 1948. In the economic survey (called in Danish the “national budget”) an attempt is made to co-ordinate and synchronize the available information about our economy to form a complete picture which reflects the essential features of our country’s economic life.</p><p>The Government's views on the main lines of Denmark’s economic policy find clear expression in the economic survey.</p><p>It is stated that the Government is of the opinion that it is highly desirable that a serious effort should be made to increase investment in Denmark by increasing efficiency and expanding Danish economic life. At the same time, an effort is being made, for example, through the various rationing schemes, to achieve the most equitable distribution among various social groups of the consumer goods which remain in short supply. Steps are being taken to increase exports by, for example, special allocations of raw materials to export undertakings, and to peg the price level both by a sound financial policy and by price controls.</p><p>Like the Governments of Britain and the other Scandinavian countries the Danish Labour Government is striving, during these years, to achieve Denmark’s economic reconstruction with the object of preparing the way for raising the general standard of living for the broad masses of the population. Reconstruction will follow present shortages as a result of the productive efforts that are now being exerted to build the future.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>