<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Labour’s Contribution to international understanding</title>
         <author>Mark Starr</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Labour’s Contribution to international understanding</title>
            <author>Mark Starr</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="American" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
    <text><body><div><p>One hundred years ago Karl Marx wrote the Communist Manifesto. Its climax sounded the clarion call: “Workers of the world, unite; you have nothing to lose but your chains. You have a world to win." This challenge was echoed down through the intervening century in many languages and in many lands. In the Red Square in Moscow, in the May Day demonstrations in Hyde Park in London, in monster meetings in Rome, Vienna, Berlin and Paris, that historic call for world-wide proletarian solidarity has been echoed.</p><p>But the exhortation was in vain. Nationalism proved stronger than class-consciousness. The workers of the world did not unite effectively. Nevertheless the Communist spectre, which Marx saw haunting Europe, is still present. His forecasts were, in large part, well founded—that big business would become bigger business and would spread into every land; that the sellers of labour-power would organise powerful unions; and that large masses of people would suffer increasing misery. World War II, like World War I, accelerated the trend towards concentration so that to-day in the United States 45 business concerns have each over one billion dollar assets.</p><p>The other grim social problems and contradictions whose economic origin Marx analysed so well, are still present with us and on a world-wide scale. The majority of our journalists and politicians too often externalise their feelings of fear toward every radical and progressive movement by openly expressed antagonism to Soviet Russia, where in one-sixth of the earth’s territory the Marxist maxims of revolution were first widely put into practice way back in 1917. However, Marx would hardly recognise the application of his theories in modern Soviet Russia where the State surely has not “withered away” and Soviet Russia has succeeded because she has exploited the nationalism which is present there as in other countries. A unique combination of Communism and nationalism functions under a single-party state which, in alleged fear of capitalist attack, suppresses civil liberties and political opposition at home and infiltrates and controls nearly every country contiguous to its borders.</p><p>The USSR has officially transformed Marxism into a new nationalistic religion which must he unquestioningly served by all. And currently the menacing polarisations of antagonisms between USA and USSR have increased the intensity of that religion and its further separation from the original Marxian class-consciousness as a basis for' world understanding and unity.</p><p>Meanwhile, the question remains: why did nationalism prove stronger than class-consciousness? Why have the ruling groups in the past century been able to rally the exploited workers of their own country to fight in the name of national defence the workers of other countries? Why have the various attempts to set up internationals by the trade unions and by Socialist and Communist groups proved to be ineffective? Why did the Third International—the Comintern founded in 1919 and continued in effect despite its formal abandonment in 1943—become the international agency of Soviet foreign policy? Its original purpose was to rally for international revolt all the workers of the five continents, as originally symbolised in the Soviet red star emblem. And now the Cominform, announced in September, 1947, by nine European Communist parties—why is it also generally recognised as a counteroffensive to the Marshall Plan in line with the same Soviet needs?</p><div><head>Miseducation of the past </head><p>There can be little doubt that education on nationalist lines was a factor which Marx overlooked or at least underestimated. Our schools have successfully helped to keep the nations of the world separate and isolated in their nationalist groups. Education has supported the status quo in national frontiers as in other things. Some twenty years ago I made a study of the textbooks, ceremonies and attitudes developed in the schools of Europe and when the facts were compiled, the natural title of the book was Lies and Hate in Education. A similar book could be compiled to-day here in these United States; glaring examples can still be found of unbridled nationalist egotism, the more effective because most often unconscious. Such examinations of our textbooks correct past mistakes and thereby advance international understanding.</p><p>The demobilisation of the mind is just as necessary as the demobilisation of the Nazi and the Japanese armed forces, if we are going to build a United Nations which is really effective. One fundamental reason why we are fumbling with world co-operation is because the present generation has been miseducated by its own nationalist textbooks. Each national group has written its own interpretation of past history which prevents a fair judgment of present and future developments. In its own history, every nation is the Herrrenvolk. Huxley and Haddon defined a nation as “a society united by a common error as to its origin and a common aversion to its neighbours.” Too often our textbooks perpetuate the error and aversion, for schoolbooks in many instances are the only books people have studied.</p><p>The Atlantic Charter emphasised that all peoples should have the right to choose the form of government under which they live and this usually involved the determination of national boundaries. But the economic realities of modern life undermine geographical frontiers and with the coming of the atomic energy age, national frontiers become lines on a map without a great deal of practical significance. The school textbooks should be rewritten with an eye upon the One World of the atomic energy age. The fighting instinct of man can be directed against the common cold, tuberculosis and poverty. The rocket bomb has made the two billion people of the earth into the “in-group’’ which the social psychologists write about.</p><p>We must prepare men and women to live in the twentieth century where the accidents of race and birth become less significant in the light of the impact upon our institutions of atomic energy in war and peace. More than ever before, civilisation must be seen as a collective achievement of the world’s peoples and its perpetuation their shared responsibility. The world awaits its political Copernicus to rescue us from the egocentric view of our own national group.</p></div><div><head>Labour and education </head><p>The members of the trade unions, of course, have been influenced by nationalist textbooks and their teaching and need an antidote as do other members of our community. However, workers’ education in this and other countries has pioneered in the field of international history. Its wide use of such books as Outline of Political Geography by J. F. Horrabin (translated into many languages and reprinted in many editions) can be cited .as tangible evidence that workers’ education escaped from the nationalist view of social development.</p><p>Labour has attempted to build international organisations based on political and industrial groupings. It was to the would-be International Communist League that Marx and Engels presented the declaration which was later expanded into the historic Communist Manifesto to which reference was made in the first paragraph of this article. More important was the First International (1864-1876), originally formed by the British trade unions to prevent the importation of strikebreakers. Its legendary strength was not adequate to overcome the setback of the downfall of the Paris Commune (1871) in which it had played a leading role. By that time its original purpose had been lost in the greater aims formulated by Karl Marx and his associates who finally, to frustrate the attempts of the Anarchists to capture it, located the International Office in New York to the a lingering death.</p><p>The Second International (1889-1914) was an affiliation of nation-wide socialist groups, some of which had great influence and political support. While revolutionary Marxist in word, its spirit became increasingly reformist. Plans were discussed to prevent war by general strikes, but the Second International provided little Resistance to the outbreak of World War I and was only able to hold sectional meetings toward the end of the war.</p></div><div><head>International trade unionism </head><p>In addition to these political organisations, the International Federation of Trade Unions, set up in 1903, linked together the national trade union centres and, while greatly weakened, survived the two World Wars to be now replaced by the World Federation of Trade Unions. The American Federation of Labour had belonged to the IFTU but, unlike the Congress of Industrial Organisations, did not join the WFTU. Previously the Communists had maintained their Red International of Labour Unions to oppose the IFTU as the political Third International had fought the Second.</p><p>The rivalry between the Eastern and Western worlds, prominent in the mutual criticism of the USA and USSR in the United Nations, finds its echo in the struggle inside the international labour movement. The secretariats of the various trades hesitate to lose their autonomy in the WFTU. The AFL remains outside because it believes the WFTU is dominated by the Soviet unions which are under government control. At present the CIO support for the Marshall Plan has put it in opposition to the Communist-controlled unions of the WFTU which parrot the denunciation of the Plan as a “Wall Street Plot.” Meanwhile the AFL actively supports the free trade unions of South America in their struggle against Communist control. A political International of the Social Democratic parties has now been formed to match the Cominform.</p><p>Even this cursory glance will show that Labour has had specific experience in building international agencies. The AFL Convention and the British Trades Union Congress have maintained an unbroken exchange of fraternal delegates. Much support has been given through labour unions to international relief.</p><p>In its most recent pamphlet, American Labour Looks at the World, the AFL records in detail its longtime record of international aid and service.</p><p>American labour’s participation in the writing of an International Bill of Rights by the United Nations Commission on Human Rights is significant. The draft of this document asserts:</p><p>1. that there can be no peace unless human rights and freedom are respected;	2. that man does not have rights only; he owes duties to the society of which he forms part;</p><p>3. that man is a citizen both of his State and of the world;</p><p>4. that there can be no human freedom or dignity unless war and the threat of war are abolished.</p></div><div><head>      The AFL and Germany </head><p>In contrast with the Morgenthau “pastoralisation” of Germany and the suggestion by Harold Stassen that no aid should he given to countries operating schemes of nationalisation, the AFL leaves such aims to the democratic will of the people concerned. To quote the official pamphlet;</p><p> “Nor need there be any dispute among the Allied Powers as to whether the German coal and steel industries should be socialised or run on a private basis. Let us decisively help to make Germany democratic by restoring to her the first basic democratic right—the right to national independence. Since German industry can and must be rebuilt by the Germans, let the German people—the moment their full sovereignty is restored—decide for themselves, through genuinely democratic procedure, whether they want these or any other industries to be under public or private ownership. No economic or political system can or should be forced on Germany or any other country by any power or combination of powers. That would be the very undoing of democracy.”</p><p>The AFL supports the Marshall Plan and proposed the conference of unions from all the 16 countries participating in order to show that it is not a deep-laid plot of “American imperialists.” In midsummer 1948 both AFL and CIO were active in sending CARE packages to European workers in line with their wartime contributions.</p><p>Both CIO and AFL are represented, in the U.S. National Commission of UNESCO, and Labour generally has warmly supported this organisation which hopes to create the defence of peace in the minds of men.</p><p>Labour has a natural affinity with the forces which are now making for international peace and understanding. If we could get miners, teachers, doctors, railroad workers, farmers, and so forth to unite with one another on the basis of their work, we should be able, as Archibald MacLeish puts it, “to improve the mutual understanding of peoples by substituting for the artificial image of the state the human and living image of the people themselves.”</p><p>Exchanges of visits between individuals and organisations on every level of culture should he provided. Let the labour unions of America exchange visits with union workers of other countries. Let the doctors, the barbers, the teachers and every other group in society consciously develop contacts with their opposite numbers in other countries. We can cite the successful operation of the Universal Postal Union, the International Telegraph Union, the International bureau of Weights and Measures, the International Copyright Union, the Iceberg Patrol in the North Atlantic, the co-operation of doctors and scientists for specific projects. And we can remember the work of the labour unions in international co-operation described above.</p><p>Some 18,000 students from other lands studied in American colleges last year. Difficulties of getting American dollars reduced this year’s foreign student body. But the State Department has announced that sales of war materials abroad has produced over 137 million dollars which under the Fulbright Act should make possible student exchanges and scholarships for study in other countries on a more ambitious plan. Labour should participate in such exchanges. The labour unions should run international summer schools to overcome dangerous hangovers of ancient ignorance.</p><p>It is significant that the only part of the League of Nations which survived was the International Labour Office (in which the AFL played a prominent role), and there is little doubt that peace can be continued only if it is based upon social justice—an assertion which is the motto of the International Labour Office.</p><p>There is a current urgency for international understanding which cannot be exaggerated. The atom bomb ticks closer to the zero hour. If we were aware of a threatened invasion from Mars, we should unite the two billion inhabitants of our planet for defence. If we could only make the constituent parts of humanity realise that internal conflict will prove as disastrous as external attack, we should be able to accomplish the same unity. But here imagination and education are needed, and Labour, particularly in its educational activities, must be prepared to continue and extend its co-operation with other like-minded groups.</p><p>Unity did not come to the workers of the world as Marx anticipated but, with international understanding and resulting unity among its members, the human race can win a world at peace and this in the atomic age is its only chance of survival.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>