<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The high cost of occupation</title>
         <author>Erich Labunde</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The high cost of occupation</title>
            <author>Erich Labunde</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="German" party="Social Democratic Party of Germany"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The Occupation Statute as a constitutional question, and its economic counterpart, occupation costs, are now in the forefront of German politics.</p><p>It is clearly recognised on the German side that the occupation of Germany is the logical outcome of Hitler’s lost war. There is also no questioning the fact that the German people must bear the cost of occupation. But there is considerable criticism of the amount of these costs. In the British and American Zones, and especially in the French Zone, they have reached an extraordinarily high level. And there has been no noticeable reduction since the currency reform. They cannot be reduced as long as the occupying powers do not considerably restrict their activities in Germany.</p><p>In view of the increasing inflation of German currency circulation from 1945 to 20 June, 1948, many people, including British and Americans, believed that occupation expenses were just paper Marks, and would therefore constitute no real burden on the population of Western Germany. The Social Democratic Party, however, pointed out again and again that occupation costs are part of the peace time economic system. For the German system of controlled prices, introduced in 1936, meant that wages, rents and the official prices of goods remained more or less unchanged. The occupation authorities paid at these official rates and prices, without using the black market. Since currency reform the Social Democratic thesis has been most powerfully confirmed by the facts. For the Occupying Powers claim approximately the same amount in Deutsche Marks as they previously did in Reichsmarks. Some of the Länder have registered a reduction of only 10 per cent. The German view that this causes an extremely critical situation is shared in political and economic quarters of Military Government. Nevertheless, there seems to be no way of reconciling the different views, since occupation costs would have to be reduced by about 70 or 80 per cent, to make them bearable for German budgets.</p><p>German criticism is being levelled not only against the total occupation costs, but also against individual items, as far as they have become known. The words “as far as they have become known" must be emphasized. Quite recently, British Military Government prohibited the Budgetary office of the British Zone from communicating details of costs to the German Peace Office in Stuttgart, a semi-official institute engaged in collecting material on problems connected with, the occupation and with the preparation of the peace treaty. Nevertheless, reliable figures can be given in this article, because German politicians were able to collect them in spite of the news black-out by Military Government and analyse them more closely than would have been possible even from the hooks of the Finance Division. This required considerable time, so that international publicity could only he given to this question much later than had been wished. Full publicity in this matter remains a hope for the future. Social Democrat speakers have repeatedly pointed out that, in history, democratisation has always begun with the reorganisation of finance. The democratisation of Germany can only begin to be effective when Military Government, pursuing this aim, makes a start on this reorganisation itself.</p><p>During the first months of occupation none of the Military Government authorities had a properly functioning administration to deal with occupation costs. Requisition of billets, warehouses, factories, and stocks of materials was carried out arbitrarily. There was no regular procedure and no clear responsibility, for at first the authority of any individual soldier of the occupying armies was so great that no German could insist on the observance of orderly procedure. Little by little a set of rules was built up—but even so they only gradually came to have any measure of authority. To-day, violations of these rules have become comparatively rare, at least in the British and American Zones.</p><div><head>The American and British Zones </head><p>In the American Zone costs of occupation were charged from the beginning against the four Länder of Bavaria, Württemberg, Baden, Hesse, and Bremen. So at least the sum total of occupation expenses could be established. Not so in the British Zone. Here Military Government set up a Zonal Budgetary Office for the whole zone which had to enter occupation costs secretly. This Zonal Budgetary Office, dissolved on 31 March, 1948, was under the supervision of British finance officers during the whole period of its existence. German authorities were never allowed to inspect its books or papers. When the Zonal Advisory Council submitted questions which I had proposed in the name of the Social-Democratic Party, the replies were insufficient. But from figures already known to me I was able to analyse the data given by the Military Government representative. The members of the Zonal Advisory Council found that on the part of the Military Government there was not as much information about its own budget as would have been required under normal parliamentary procedure from a Finance Minister and his officials. Social Democrats therefore directed their efforts towards drawing the British and American Public's attention to the present state or occupation finances. Success in these efforts has so far been very gratifying.</p><p>Occupation costs were as follows for the last two years:</p><p>These amounts show a substantial increase from 1946 to 1947. In fact, the increase is greater than is evident from the figures, for numerous bills dating from 1945 were paid in 1946, while such overlapping was not so noticeable in 1947. It must be assumed that the real increase amounts to approximately one billion Marks. This is partly due to the fact that Military Government dismissed their own staff of office workers, drivers, and other auxiliary employees, employing Germans in their place. According to the latest statistics, both Military Governments together employ more than 650,000 Germans, a figure certainly much larger than that of British and Americans in the Army, Navy and Air Force or in civilian posts in Military Government. A possible estimation is that the number is twice as high. German experts think a reduction in the number - of German employees is imperative and believe that it can be reduced to—not by—20 to 30 per cent, of its present level. It has been proved that only a small proportion of the German employees are continuously and intensively at work, while most of them are permanently paid but not fully employed. Military Government offices have a regrettable habit of employing highly qualified German technicians—urgently needed by the German administration— whose work could be done by unskilled workers without prejudice to the efficiency of the job. A very large proportion of these employees took up Military Government work against their will; German labour exchanges were simply requested to provide such employees regardless of all German requirements. Most of them are being paid at German rates. But in 1945 and 1946, Military Government gave jobs to numerous highly-qualified specialists paid far better than is customary in Germany—an additional load on the occupation account.</p><p>Expenditure for German personnel amount to more than 30 per cent, of the total occupation costs in Hamburg. This figure may be reckoned as representative for Western Germany. Dismissals on the scale recommended would cause additional unemployment on the German labour market—the German programme provides for the dismissal of no less than 500.000 people. But in the German view, this is no reason for deferring or turning down this possible and necessary step. A high percentage of those dismissed would soon find new jobs in German undertakings. Unemployment pay for the remainder would mean a much smaller load for the German budget than occupation pay.</p></div><div><head>The Cost of DP camps</head><p>Staff reduction would, however, only decrease the problem as a whole without fundamentally solving it. A further big item is the cost of DP camps. In 1947 this amounted to about half a billion Marks in the British and US Zones, also a substantial increase over the preceding year. In the German view, these expenses should be fully borne by British and American Military Government. Many of the inmates of DP camps came to Germany after the surrender: that is, they fled from their own countries not to the Germans, but to the British and Americans, looking for protection. As political refugees, they should be financially provided for by the countries to which they look for protection. Those who were living in Germany at the time of the surrender were brought here by force under Hitler. But since then all of them have had the chance to return to their home countries. For understandable reasons, they did not do so, having the same aversion to the Communist governments of Poland, Latvia and the other Eastern countries as the German people have to Communism. Their continued stay in Germany is therefore equivalent to a flight for political reasons—but a flight again not to the Germans, out to the British and Americans. The Germans are of the opinion that they ought to be liable for costs for political refugees only if they themselves were responsible for the decision to offer them asylum. But this was done exclusively by Military Government.</p><p>Expenditure by Military Government on building, maintenance and repair is likewise extremely high. It amounts to about one- eighth of the total expenses, and so reaches amounts far surpassing in various Länder what could have been spent there on housing. This financial side reflects the position in the supply of building materials. Housing could not make progress in the first three years of occupation in Germany because Military Government claimed priority in all supplies of building materials and labour. Many investments in this respect miscarried. This applies not only to the well-known Hamburg project for British Headquarters, which under a plan of 1946 was to move to Hamburg; such wrong investments were made also in numerous other big and small building projects. Modification of buildings for occupational purposes took place not once only, as would have been absolutely understandable; numerous instances have been known where alterations just completed had to be further modified on the orders of a new officer. Of course there have been a number of threefold changes. </p><p>An analysis of almost all other items in the occupation account shows similar results. </p><p>The Hamburg statistics are exceptional only in the fact that shipping expenses for the British Zone are centrally hooked in Hamburg and that the provision of food for DP camps is likewise largely accounted for in Hamburg.</p><p>For 1948, British Military Government calculated that occupation costs would decrease materially, but this goal has not been attained. The Hamburg costs of occupation were to have decreased front 45 to 32.4 million Marks a month. In fact, 40 millions of the new D-Marks were required in July, 1948. This shows that adequate measures have not been taken to keep within budgetary limits.</p><p>Even with the old paper Reichsmark currency, the German budgets of the British occupied zone were unable to balance the extremely high costs of occupation, amounting to 6 billion Marks since the beginning of occupation. Credits had to be used for financing them. The main burden of credits was put on the Reichsbank, which contributed 3.1 billions. A further billion—to he exact, 976 millions—was provided by funds called among experts “cigarette funds”; that is monies whose origin is not yet clear to German politicians. In this way the occupation costs problem had reached a dangerous pitch before currency reform. Currency reform meant a temporary relief since it simply annulled the Reichsbank credits on the occupation act omit, but this relief is Ito real solution »if the problem. The crisis continue« to develop day by clay. It is very likely now that I.KI’ funds, the Deutsche Mark payments for raw materials and food supplies, «ill he only partly available for investments in the (German economy because a very high percentage must he reserved for the extremely high occupation costs.</p><p>There is less information about the costs of occupation in the French Zone. It is known that the items included in the budgets are only part of the real expenses, by order of the French Military Government occupation costs of nearly 800 million Marks in 1946 have been theoretically reduced by about a half. But on the other hand, other budgetary funds of the Länder in the French Zone have been used, so the sum total of expenses seems to have been reduced. The problems of the British and US Zones are found herein an even more acute form.</p><p>All in all, occupation costs in the three Western Zones of Germany amount to 5.5 billion Marks. This is, at present exchange values, 1.65 billion dollars or more than 400 million pounds sterling, of which 200 million are accounted for by the British Zone. In 1946, the British home budget included an item of 80 million pounds sterling for the zone; since then these expenses have obviously been much reduced. This comparison shows to what extent the German taxpayer has to pay occupation costs for Hitler’s lost war. The decisive factor is, however, not the actual sum, but its unbearable relation to the German economy, a fact about which German, British and American experts are in agreement. It must be realised that the problem of occupation costs is a key problem not only for the budget, but likewise for the future fate or a German currency just starting on a new basis.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>