<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The suppression of the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party</title>
         <author>Vilém Bernard</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The suppression of the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party</title>
            <author>Vilém Bernard</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>September-November 1948</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.6</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Czechoslovak" party="Czechoslovak Social Democracy"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>On Sunday, 27th June, 1948, the fusion of the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party with the Communist Patty was solemnly proclaimed in Prague. The self-appointed leaders of the Social Democratic Party had thus fulfilled to the letter the last task entrusted to them by the Communists and had carried out in a in a few weeks all preparations for this final act of self-annihilation. The local and divisional organisations, robbed of their freely elected and reliable officials by a thorough purge, simply handed over their membership lists to the regional offices of the Communist Party; nobody thought of consulting the opinions of the rank and file. No Party Congress was convened to approve or disapprove of the momentous decision to dissolve the Party. The new united Party bears the name of Communist Party and has adopted its programme. Though official propaganda speaks of voluntary fusion, the tact is that the Communists have swallowed up hundreds of thousands of organised Social Democrats who thus, without having had any opportunity to express their own will, have become members of the Communist Party. Their influence on the policy of the united Party will be negligible, because in this new body there will be no scope at all for democratic expression.</p><p>While political freedom in Czechoslovakia still existed the Social Democratic Party jealousy guarded its own independence; this was stressed by the last Congress of the Party held in November 1947 in Brno which in its decision and resolutions insisted upon full ideological, political and organisational independence.</p><p>The debate inside the Party preceding the Congress did not even touch the subject of fusion with the Communist Party, and nobody even dared to suggest such a motion at the Congress itself, since it was generally known that the slightest hint of such a move would have been spontaneously and vigorously repudiated by the membership. The February coup dՎtat was needed to break by force the Social Democratic Party's resistance and determination to remain independent. Without police action against the Social Democratic Party offices in February there would have been no fusion. The Act proclaimed on 27th June in Prague does not mean the final healing of the breach in the working class movement dating from 1920, as its instigators assert, and it is in sharp contradiction to the ideal of Socialist unity which can be only the expression of free will and not the result of blackmail and brute force.</p><p>The final stage of the unequal struggle of Czechoslovak Social Democracy tor independence took place when in all other states of Central and Eastern Europe the fate of Social Democracy had already been sealed. The plan of the Cominform to liquidate Social Democracy within the Soviet sphere of influence was carried through gradually in each country, and though methods were similar, the speed applied varied. In Czechoslovakia during the first weeks after the February crisis it was assumed that the fusion would be effected after the Parliamentary elections. Even the spokesmen of the Communists seemed to support this view, and the new leaders of the Social Democratic Party went on trying to deceive their membership by spreading of illusions about the significant and important tasks allotted to Social Democracy under the new order, naturally in closest co-operation with the Communist Party. The final decision to speed up liquidation of Social Democracy was taken at the beginning of April while the existence of the other political parties, of course under controlled leadership, was not affected. The Communist leaders well realise that there was no mass defection of Social Democrats to the Communist Party; measures taken to control the Social Democratic Party as a body by Communists proved insufficient. Thus it was suddenly decided to effect the fusion much sooner and more quickly than originally intended. A party appealing by its programme and its living traditions to large sections of the working class remains a potential threat to the dominance of the Communist Party, even if led by personalities more than loyal to the Communists and prepared to deny completely all the principles of democratic socialism. This danger for the Communist Party would tend to increase with the increasing oppression which the working class was bound to suffer after the February coup. As for the right wing political parties, the Communists are not unduly concerned since they assume that these parties which based their strength on support from private enterprise will lose their social and economic oasis through progressive nationalisation.</p><p>Only a democratic conception of Socialism, joining economic planning with the principles of freedom, gives any hope to the working class now longing for the rebirth of lost political freedom, but not prepared to give up the achievements gained in the political and social held. The end of the legal activity of the Czechoslovak Social Democracy does not mean the wreck of its ideals. The vitality of these ideals is confirmed over and over again by the experience of everyday life.</p></body></text></TEI>