<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
         <author>Editorial Staff</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Notes of the quarter</title>
            <author>Editorial Staff</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="None"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><div><head>Comisco at Clacton </head><p>On 3 December 1948 the Committee of International Socialist Conferences (COMlSCO) met at Clacton-on-Sea under the chairmanship of Morgan Phillips, Secretary of the British labour Party. This was the first meeting of the Committee since the International Socialist Conference in Vienna in June, and a number of important questions were on the agenda, including the problem of Socialist refugees from the countries of Eastern Europe now under Soviet domination, the problem of Italian Socialism, and the question of Spain. Delegates from Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Great Britain, Holland, Iceland, Italy, Spain, Sweden, Trieste, and the International Jewish Bund attended the meeting.</p></div><div><head>Eastern European Socialist parties in exile </head><p>The problem of socialist refugees from Eastern Europe has become very urgent in recent months. At the end of the war Socialist Parties sprang up in the countries of Eastern Europe, and a number of these were members of the International Socialist Conference: the Czechoslovak, Hungarian, Polish and Rumanian parties. Each of these parties tried to maintain its independence while at the same time collaborating in a coalition government with the Communists. But loyal collaboration was not enough for the Communists; they were satisfied with nothing less than complete domination. One by one the socialist parties in Eastern Europe were destroyed and absorbed into so-called "Unity Parties" —against the wishes of the majority of their members. Fusion was forced through by political pressure, terrorism, the threat of Russian power, and the treachery of certain socialist leaders.</p><p>Of the great number of Socialists who opposed fusion, the majority have had to remain in their homeland under the shadow of political reprisal. A few have managed to escape and make their way to Western Europe, where they have again begun the fight for national independence and Socialism. It was the problem of helping these socialist parties in exile which COMlSCO discussed at Clacton and which it decided to tackle in the way set out in the following resolution: —</p><p>1. The Committee of International Socialist Conferences believes that the Socialist Parties from Eastern Europe in exile should be linked to be linked to the International Socialist Conference by some form of organisation which would include the parties of Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Rumania, Bulgaria and Yugoslavia.</p><p>2. Socialist Parties in exile from territories now administered as a Part of the Soviet Union should not be directly associated with COMISCO; but the East European organisation should be free to associate with them.</p><p>3. COMISCO will establish a Sub-Committee with three functions: —</p><p> (a) To attempt reconciliation of the rival groups of Hungary and Rumania, or failing reconciliation, to choose between them;</p><p> (b) To assist the six parties of Eastern Europe in forming a joint organisation;</p><p> (c) To draw up proposals governing the relationship between COMISCO and the East European Parties in exile.</p><p>4. The next full Conference shall take a final decision on the basis of the report submitted by the Sub-Committee.</p></div><div><head>The Spanish question </head><p>The following resolution on Spain was also unanimously passed by COMISCO at its meeting on 3 December: —</p><p>The problem of Franco Spain is now entering a new phase. It has long been agreed that the Franco regime can play no part in the development of a European Union which must be a stronghold of democracy against all forms of totalitarianism. But as European unity gathers strength, the Franco regime has dearly become a positive menace to its success. More and more the forces of reaction and division in Europe base their hopes on the survival of fascism in Spain. More and more the forces of progress and unity find their plans frustrated by the fact that Franco excludes the Spanish people from their company. Recent events make it clear that so long as the Franco regime exists, Spain will remain a source of differences among the outside world which may threaten the very basis of European union.</p><p>For this reason COMISCO considers that opposition to the Franco regime must pass to a more active phase. It urges all governments to treat the removal of the Franco regime as a matter of major urgency for the progress of unity in Europe. It further declares, while stressing its solidarity with the PSOE, that no change in the Spanish regime will be acceptable which does nor allow all democratic parties to function in full liberty so that the Spanish people can freely express its will.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>