<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Labour’s Colonial Policy</title>
         <author>H.D.Hughes</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Labour’s Colonial Policy</title>
            <author>H.D.Hughes</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="British" party="British Labour Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>October, 1948 wan a memorable month in the history of the British Commonwealth. Seventy delegates, over half of them Africans, representing the legislatures of the African Colonies, met in London for the first African Conference of its kind to discuss the political, social and economic development of their territories with the British Government. At the Conference of Commonwealth Prime Ministers which opened at No. 10 Downing St. on October it, Pandit Nehru, Liaquat Ali Khan and Mr D.S. Senanayakc came on equal terms with the Premiers of the older Dominions to represent three self-governing countries which in 1945 were dependent colonies. At the United Nations, Mr Grantley Adams, West Indian leader of the Barbados House of Assembly, made a powerful defence of British colonial policy.</p><p>These happenings mark the tremendous changes that are taking place. There is still an enormous way to go, and great difficulties to be overcome, as recent events in Malaya, the Gold Coast, British Guiana and elsewhere, make dear. But under the present Government the old record of exploitation and oppression is being steadily brought to an end. As the official Colonial Office Report for 1947/48 makes clear (Cmd. 7443 The Colonial Empire 1947/8):</p><p> “The central purpose of British Colonial policy is simple.</p><p>It is to guide the colonial territories to responsible self-government within the Commonwealth in conditions that ensure to the people concerned both a fair standard of living, and freedom from oppression from any Quarter."</p><p>"Responsible self-government” implies a great deal. It involves the establishment of a free and democratic system of local and central representation, and the setting up of an administrative machine which can with efficiency and honesty control the affairs of great territories. The task of making these conditions possible varies enormously in different colonies, from Nigeria, which held the first meeting of its new legislative Council with an unofficial African majority in March, 1947; to Ceylon, which attained its full independence in December of the same year. But even a mere list of the constitutional changes of the last year is impressive - revisions in the Legislative Councils of the Gambia, Kenya, Uganda, Tanganyika and N. Rhodesia, all giving greater representation to African interests, discussions of similar reforms in Sierra Leone and Nyasaland; the establishment of a new Federation and States constitutions in Malaya, an unofficial majority in the reconstructed Council of Singapore; a Caribbean Conference preparing the way for federation, discussions on constitutional revision in the Bahamas, Bermuda, British Honduras, Jamaica, Trinidad and Tobago in the West Indies; a new constitution in Malta, constitutional reform in the Seychelles and Mauritius and so on. Jamaica and Trinidad now possess full adult suffrage and there have been extensions of the franchise in British Guiana and Mauritius. The various stages are clear – from a Legislative Council with a majority of official representatives indirectly or directly elected, the entry of non-official members into the Executive Council, the reduction of reserve powers, and so to full self-government. The problem is to time development in accordance with the wishes and experience and ability of the local population, bearing in mind not only the interests of the educated minority but also of the masses who must be protected from exploitation and misgovernment.</p><p>Local government is perhaps the easiest and most direct means of training administrators and legislators, and an essential basis of democracy. In 1947 the Colonial Office organised a special Conference on Local Government in Africa and its conclusions were approved at a subsequent Governors’ Conference. A special Local Government Advisory Panel of British experts has been established to assist in applying British experience to the problem in the colonies. In Kenya and Uganda popularly elected African majorities on local councils are now the rule. Younger and more educated members are being increasingly brought iii on Native Authorities in N. Rhodesia, Tanganyika, Nyasaland, the Gold Coast and parts of Nigeria, to supplement the traditional chiefs.</p><p>One of the great needs is for a vast increase in qualified colonial civil servants and local government officials, and here also much is being done. The experience of Nigeria, long regarded as a backward area, may be specially quoted. In May, 1948, the new Governor, Sir John MacPhcrson, appointed a special Commission with an unofficial African majority, including men of the calibre of Dr Azikiwe and Mr Onyeama of the Legislative Council, to make recommendations on the steps needed to execute the policy of "Nigerianisation" of the Government Service. A unanimous report, accepted by the Governor, provided for a three-year training plan estimated to cost over £250,000 (the annual revenue of Nigeria is only £18,000,000), with 385 scholarships and grants, and laid down the principle that "no non-Nigerian should be recruited for any Government post except when no suitable and qualified Nigerian is available." In the whole of West Africa, the principle of equal salaries for European and African officials is now in operation, the Europeans receiving special allowances to enable them to maintain their homes and responsibilities outside the country in which they work.</p><div><head>The economic background </head><p>But political development can only succeed if it is based upon a sound social and economic framework. Social reforms and services, essential if the health and welfare of the colonial peoples are to be improved, are dependent on the development of the economic and financial resources of the colonics to enable them to bear the cost. Many of the colonics are desperately poor and backward—Nigeria and Tanganyika for example each have an annual revenue of less than £1 per head (In 1938 Nigeria, with a population of over 22 million, had an annual revenues of £5.8 m., or about 5/3 per head—since then it has almost quadrupled).</p><p>To-day great efforts are being made to raise tire economic standards of these territories. Under the Colonial Development and Welfare Act of 1945 a sum of £ 120,000,000 is being provided from the British Exchequer towards the cost of ten-year development plans, and double this sum is being added from colonial resources. In 1947, under the Overseas Resources Act, two new public corporations, the Overseas Food Corporation and the Colonial Development Corporation, with borrowing powers up to £ 165,000,000 were set up. The first of these, under the Ministry of Food, can undertake development schemes in the colonies at the request of the Colonial Secretary, and is already responsible for the large-scale groundnuts scheme in E. Africa; the second, under the Colonial Office, is wholly confined to projects of colonial development. No longer, then, is the colonial role of the British Government confined to the preservation of law and order, while private enterprise exploits the resources of the territories. Britain is now committed to a positive policy of development in partnership with the colonial peoples, in the hope that both may benefit.</p><p>This new approach has been stimulated by the post-war economic situation. To the needs of the colonial peoples themselves have been added the pressure of the world food shortage and the dollar crisis. Faced with an increase of 125 millions in world population since 1939, and the likelihood of this continuing, it is reliably estimated that world food production must be doubled in the next 25 years. Taking vegetable oils as an example, with India exporting only one-fifth of her pre-war level, and Manchurian supplies non-existent there is a world shortage of 4 million tons. Many of these deficiencies can only, or most easily, be made up by the rapid development of agricultural production in the colonial territories.</p><p>The dollar deficit of the sterling area can also he most easily remedied by stimulating colonial development. In 1947 the United States imported only 1250,000,000 manufactured goods as against £1,150,000,000 worth of food and raw materials. American emphasis on stockpiling of strategic raw materials in connection with the European Recovery Programme has also shown that here is the most hopeful solution to the restoration of a reasonable equilibrium in world trade.</p><p>It would be unrealistic and dishonest to deny the importance of these factors in assessing the increased interest in colonial development. But that does not mean that all that is involved is a renewed and intensified exploitation of the colonies in the interests of Europe. Properly handled, the present situation provides an unrivalled opportunity to strengthen the economic and financial position of the colonial territories themselves and to enable them for the first time to carry an improved standard of living for their peoples. The problem is to see that the colonial producer gets a fair return for his crops and labour, that the proceeds of mineral exploitation go back into the economies of the territories concerned, and above all, that the colonial peoples are fully brought in as partners in the development schemes.</p></div><div><head>Expansion of production</head><p>The first of these two conditions is being increasingly fulfilled by the establishment of marketing boards under public control disposing of colonial produce at the full world price. This now applies to the cocoa crop of the Gold Coast and Nigeria with a balance of £25,000,000 accumulated in the period 1939-47 which is to be used to regulate the effect of falling world prices, for research, eradication of disease, and other purposes benefiting the cocoa producers such as the development of co-operatives. The West African Produce Control Board is now performing the same function for oilseeds.</p><p>Mineral exploitation in the colonies is still in the hands of private enterprise, which also benefits from royalties under agreements concluded in an era when views on colonial development were very different. In 1946 the Colonial Office issued a Memorandum on Mining Policy which recommended the vesting of all new mineral rights in the Crown, and where possible the purchase of those already in private hands. It also favoured the public operation of mines, and the arrangement of royalties and export duties to ensure that a fair proportion of the financial proceeds of private mining were reserved for the community. This Memorandum has not yet been followed by sufficiently energetic action on the part of Colonial Governments. In Nigeria for example, negotiations have been going on without result since 1943 between the Government and the United Africa Company, which under an agreement of 1899 is entitled to receive 50% of royalties on all minerals mined in N. Nigeria. That agreement was concluded by a Chancellor who regarded £ 1,000,000 as a wildly exaggerated estimate of the value of the royalties concerned. Since then nearly £3,000,000 has been taken out and still no settlement has been reached. Such relics of the old Imperialism must be eliminated in the shortest possible time.</p></div><div><head>Development plans </head><p>Seventeen ten-year development plans under the Colonial Development and Welfare Act have now been approved. The aim is to balance social and economic projects, hospitals and schools, roads and bridges, and so provide the essential prerequisites for expanding industry and agriculture and raising the standard of life. The limiting factor in this type of development is no longer money but rather the scarcity of skilled administrators and technicians and the shortage of capital goods and raw materials. In 1947 and 1948, of nearly £ 17,000,000 approved expenditure, less than £9,000,000 was actually spent. Mistakes were made in the early stages in not doing enough to enlist the active co-operation of the colonial people, in pitching standards far higher than was practicable, and in insufficient planning of priorities and supplies. These defects are now being rectified. In many cases they were due to the very desire to encourage colonial self-reliance and not to impose too centralised control from London. But development planning and constitutional progress are not really contradictory— the former is necessary to bring the colonies to a stage in which it is possible for them to stand on their own feet.</p><p>Let us examine the development plan of Nigeria, the largest colony, as an example of what can and cannot be achieved under these ten-year plans. Here is a population of some 25 million people spread over an area four times the size of the United Kingdom, living mainly a primitive agricultural life, suffering from widespread malnutrition and disease. There is one doctor for every 133,000 people and one hospital bed for every 3,700. Out of about 8 million children under 16,660,000 are receiving some form of primary education. 10,000 are in secondary schools, and there are three technical trade training centres. Some 2,000 government officers in all departments carry the whole burden of administration. The ten-year development plan provides £55,000,000, 5/- per head of the population per annum. £9.000,000 will be spent on building, £8,000,400 on rural and urban water supplies (in some cases women have an 18-milc journey 10 fetch fresh water for their homes), £7,000,000 for roans, £6,000.000 for medical services, £5,000,000 for education, £3,250,000 for agriculture, forestry and veterinary services, and so on. When the plan is completed, there will be a University, a few more schools, hospitals, agricultural research stations, water points and so on, all desperately required.</p><p>To be effective such a plan must be supplemented in at least three ways—by the new public corporations, by the development of agriculture and secondary industries, and by rousing the people themselves through mass education or communal development to assist in the solution of their problems.</p><p>Here and there in the colonial territories exciting things are happening. Administrative officers with knowledge and insight are rousing hidden springs of enthusiasm and energy amongst the most backward peoples. Without waiting for development plans from above, they are stirring from their age-old apathy and setting to work on roadways through the bush to link their villages with the outside world, to build maternity centres, dispensaries, co-operative stores, etc., from materials locally available. Whole villages are turning out to learn the elements of reading and writing under the guidance of schoolchildren. Faced with the enormous problems of mass poverty and illiteracy, it is better for hundreds to get their schooling under trees and in primitive huts rather than to wait until a few score receive their education in elaborate buildings under fully qualified teachers. This movement is still in its infancy and comparatively localised—if it can be encouraged and spread it will carry the flame of progress throughout the colonics.</p></div><div><head>Increased production </head><p>But the spread of literacy and improved social services must be supported by increased production. Improved agricultural technique and equipment can lead to an enormous increase in output. Over vast colonial areas the peasant still maintains himself with the hoc and mattock. Ten acres of Nigerian palm trees, uncultivated, and with native extraction methods, produce only 16 ? cwts of oil and 21 cwts of kernels annually. With scientific cultivation and simple mechanical extraction, the rate of production can be quadrupled. Peasant co-operatives provide the most hopeful means of spreading improved methods and equipment in large areas, and they are being stimulated by experienced Government officers.</p><p>The development of secondary industry is also of great importance. Far too high a proportion of colonial produce has been exported in its natural state for processing abroad. Both private and public enterprise is required to survey the possibilities of increased industrial development in the colonial territories themselves But if private industry is to develop, precautions must be taken to see that the people of the colonies themselves have a chance to participate and to rise to the highest managerial and technical levels as well as form the bulk of the skilled and unskilled labour. In very few colonies to-day are there as vet adequate opportunities for technical training. The domination of trade and commerce by a few powerful businesses, often located outside the colony, as for example the trade and commerce of W. Africa is dominated by the United Africa Company, is unhealthy. To restore a proper balance, Colonial Governments will have to pursue a number of different policies simultaneously. Legislation on the lines of the new Monopolies Act in Britain might be introduced to make possible inquiries into restrictive practices and their termination. Transport and other interests of big companies might be acquired by the Colonial Governments, e.g., the Niger flotilla. The development of co-operatives and trade unions must be increasingly encouraged.</p></div><div><head>Public enterprise </head><p>But one of the main problems of colonial development at the present time is that private enterprise is unable to handle industrial and agricultural development on the scale required. Here the two new public corporations referred to above must fill the gap. Starting from scratch in 1947, they have had to build up their administration, determine their techniques and survey the whole enormous field. The Overseas Food Corporation has now taken over the E. African groundnuts scheme from the United Africa Company, who acted as original agents for the British Government. In spite of enormous difficulties in obtaining suitable equipment and labour, some 40,000 acres of bush have been cleared and 7,500 acres were planted in the first year. A new deep-water port and over 130 miles of railway are being constructed, water, housing and schools provided. The aim is to settle the working population on the land and ultimately to hand over control of the scheme to those employed in it. Though the first, this is only one of hundreds of schemes now being examined by the Corporations. The Colonial Corporation has set up subsidiary' boards in each of the main regions, including some representatives of local opinion. There will no doubt be serious teething troubles, suspicions and difficulties to overcome. But in a comparatively short time schemes of enormous potential value to the colonial peoples should be under way.</p><p>This brief article cannot do more than indicate the main lines of British colonial policy as it is being developed under the Labour Government, with Arthur Creech Jones, a true friend of the colonial peoples, as Secretary of State. The intention is to press on as rapidly as resources permit with the economic development as the foundation of improved social standards and political self-government. The British colonies tend to make world headline news only when there is trouble – riots on the Gold Coast and disturbance’s in Malaya. None are more aware than the Labour Government of the difficulties to the overcome and the immense strides that have to he made. But we are determined to achieve real partnership with the colonial peoples and ensure that as British control is released it is replaced by genuine self-government of free peoples accustomed to work their own democratic institutions and control their own destinies. New constitutions and economic development will not succeed if they are imposed from above-the greatest problem facing the British Government is to find the best means of working with the peoples of the colonies and assisting them to realise their own desires. Where a few years hack constitutional reforms were imposed from above with only formal consultation, now in Nigeria, the Gold Coast and elsewhere far more effective preliminary discussions are taking place. The African Conference in London pointed the way. If the key to real co-operation can he found, the present discontents will vanish and we can move steadily forward to the establishment of a self-governing Commonwealth of free and equal peoples, a true example to the world.</p><p>Let me close with an extract from an African paper, which can be left to speak for itself:</p><p> “Sir John (Macpherson, the new Governor) has come to us, not from the Colonial Office of eternal subjection of backward peoples and weaker races. He has come to us from a new Colonial Office—the Colonial Office of rebirth, the Colonial Office that has revolted against the old ways of leopards and wolves, of strong devouring the weak. He has come from the Colonial Office that has rigorously set its face to liquidate those ‘old ways’ and set up the new and better ways of providing education for all, employment for the unemployed, health for the sick, freedom for the oppressed in India, in Burma, in Ceylon, in lands inhabited not only by white persons, but also by coloured races. That Colonial Office is new. It is something that never was. It has come because Britain herself is re-born. For the first time in history Britain is being ruled, not by kings and princes and ‘natural rulers’ and not for the glory of ‘sceptre and crown’ but by the ‘labouring man’ for the good of all the people.’’</p><p> (Nigerian Eastern Mail, July 3, 1948.)</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>