<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>French policy in Indo-China</title>
         <author>Georges Brutelle</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>French policy in Indo-China</title>
            <author>Georges Brutelle</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="French" party="SFIO"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>In order to understand the situation in which France has got herself in Indo-China, we must recall what has happened there since the French Collapse in 1940. Mistakes by French colonists on the spot, or mistakes in French colonial policy as a whole would not in themselves have brought war to Indo-China so soon. It was the collapse and the disappearance of France as a power, followed by a series of occupations, which gave the nationalist movement its chance to win over the peoples of Vietnam. But even so I am convinced that if it had not been for the enormous mistakes committed by most of our Government since liberation, and above all their criminal weakness in dealing with French representatives in Indo-China, we should not now be in our present dilemma—a dilemma which is insoluble unless there is a radical change in French policy. This change must occur within the framework of the Constitution of the Fourth Republic which is an attempt to make the French Union a community of free, self-governing peoples.</p><p>On 21st June, 1940, the Governor General of Indo-China, General Catroux (who was later to support Free France and join General de Gaulle in London), was forced to yield to an ultimatum from the Japanese who invaded Tonking in the face of French resistance. General Catroux’s successor, Admiral Decoux, was appointed Governor General of Indo-China by Vichy, and collaborated with the Japanese, maintaining only nominal French sovereignty until 9th March. 1945, when the Japanese seized control of the whole country by force and disarmed the French troops.</p><p>The first French troops to come from France after the war did not land in Indo-China until 25th October, 1945. The Emperor Bao-Dai had abdicated and the Republic of Viet-Nam had been proclaimed on 25th August, 1945.</p><p>France had shown herself incapable of defending the people of Indo-China against foreign aggression. She had lost face, and some of her representatives had disgraced her. The Japanese had proclaimed the independence of Indo-China. But this independence existed only in words: they would never have granted real independence in fact, and after a few weeks had passed the people began to realise it. But the idea of independence took root. With liberation, the Chinese in the north, and the American missions in the south both encouraged the growth of nationalist tendencies.</p><p>What conclusions should the governments of the Fourth Republic have drawn from all this? First of all they should have realised that a people's national unity and will to independence ought not to be under-estimated or despised. Secondly, they should have realised that, in a country with such strong traditions, where French power had been inexistent for so long, and where national feelings had been so powerfully stimulated, there were only two possible courses to be followed: either to recognise the independence of the states of Indo-China or to repeat the former colonial policy of domination.</p><p>The first alternative had in its favour the firm friendship which still existed, and the hopes raised by post-liberation France, where the idea of the French Union seemed to have triumphed over the old idea of the Colonial Empire. These, as well as the magnanimity of such a gesture, would have ensured that the Indo-Chinese states, which still looked to France for support, would remain within the French union after being granted self-government. On the other hand, a return to the old colonial policy inevitably involved reconquering Indo-China against people ready to take up arms to defend themselves. This meant a long and difficult war, with all the horrors which would result from conflict between fanatic nationalists and French troops unused to colonial conditions. Nothing could be more dishonouring to a French Republic dedicated to liberty and to fraternal collaboration with all the peoples of the former Empire.</p><p>But no clear choice between these alternatives was possible in a Parliament whose government is always a coalition supported by a majority composed of a number of different parties. In addition, French representatives in Indo-China, having decided on a policy of force, sometimes created situations in which it was impossible for a Government, even with the best intentions, to have its policy carried out as it wanted.</p><p>Neither of these alternatives—neither the policy of reconquest which we Socialists have always opposed, nor the policy of free association for which we have always worked—has been followed clearly and unambiguously.</p><p>On the 17th or 18th August, 1945, the Emperor Bao-Dai addressed a message to General de Gaulle and the French people in which he wrote, as he said, as a “friend” and not as “Head of the State.” He warned the French Government against the dangers of a policy of reconquest. It is interesting to quote passages from his appeal, which now seems prophetic.</p><p> “If you understand the present situation in our country and the strength and depth of patriotic feeling which inspires all Annamites who refuse to be unjustly oppressed, you will know this. Even if you could take over the entire administration in the country, your authority would not be respected. Every village would become an island of resistance; every Annamite would become your deadly enemy. And in the end you would have to withdraw, for you would not be able to carry on in such an atmosphere.”</p><p>He went on: “The best method by which the French can remain in Indo-China is to recognise Annamese independence and not to attempt to regain power in the country by any means.”</p><p>The head of the French provisional Government at that time was General dc Gaulle. He made no reply to Bao-Dai’s appeal. Ho-Chi-Minh took power in Indo-China. And now to-day, when President Ho has become the symbol of Viet-Nam resistance, and when no agreement with the ex-emperor could have any effect on hostilities, it is with Bao-Dai, whom de Gaulle ignored, that French representatives are negotiating.</p><div><head>Agreement by negotiation </head><p>Between Bao-Dai's appeal and the opening of negotiations with him efforts were made to reach agreement with President Ho-Chi- Minh. A convention was signed on 6th March, 1946, by Admiral d’Argenlieu and the head of the Viet-Nam government. This preliminary convention recognised the Viet-Nam Republic “as a free country with its own government, parliament, armed forces, and finances, forming part of the Indo-Chinese Federation and of the French Union.”</p><p>The problem of uniting Tonking, Annam, and Cochin China was to be dealt with later, the French Government having undertaken to accept the decision expressed by the Cochin-Chinese people in a referendum. Negotiations were also to take place later concerning the future status of Indo-China, French economic and cultural interests in Viet-Nam, and the difficult problem of Viet-Nam’s diplomatic relations with foreign countries.</p><p>On 14th September, 1946, a modus vivendi was signed with Ho-Chi-Minh’s government. This completed negotiations which had taken place at Fontainebleau. The French Minister for Overseas Territories, Marius Moutet, a Socialist, accepted the Viet-Nam point of view concerning the Indo-Chinese Federation—the Viet-Nam representatives wanted this to be merely a regional organisation for economic co-ordination and co-operation between the states of Indo-China. Viet-Nam wished to become a partner in the French Union, but directly, and not through its membership of the Indo-Chinese Federation. The convention of 6th March had thus been confirmed and completed, and final agreement was in sight.</p><p>The search for agreement which the Socialist Party continuously defended was a policy of peace and honour. Neither Viet-Nam reluctance nor the demands by some Viet-Nam extremists could have prevented this policy from being effective if it had been loyally put into practice by French representatives in Indo-China. Certain economic interests" and military circles which favoured force and the attitude of Admiral Thierry-d’Argenlieu made all attempts at conciliation vain.</p></div><div><head>Agreement Sabotage </head><p>In effect, the convention of 6th March made it possible for General Leclere’s forces peacefully to occupy a number of strategic positions in a country which had declared itself independent after France’s defeat. Although General Leclerc took the convention seriously and considered it the only way to preserve France’s position in Indo-China, the colonials, the administration and the High Commissioner, Admiral d’Argenlieu, looked on it as a stratagem of war. Quite unpardonable actions were taken. It was maintained that the convention applied only to the territory north of the 16th parallel, and fighting was begun in the South after leaflets bad been dropped to Viet-Nam forces in the south calling on them to surrender to the French. The convention was, in fact, valid for the whole of Viet-Nam. Nothing in the convention obliged the Viet-Nam forces to surrender or lay down their arms or allow themselves to be imprisoned.</p><p>Moreover, Admiral d’Argenlieu on loth June, 1946, recognised the government of Cochin-China, and proclaimed its independence. This was while the only true representatives of Viet-Nam were on the way to Fontainebleau to discuss the unity of Viet-Nam—including Cochin-China—and their independence with the French Government.</p><p>On 1st August, 1946, while Ho-Chi-Minh was at Fontainebleau, the Admiral called a Conference at Dalat of all the Indo-Chinese States, including Cochin-China, to establish the Indo-Chinese Federation as an economic and political entity. The Viet-Nam government was not invited to this conference.</p><p>The High Commissioner’s attitude and the sabotage of the agreements by all those who wanted war, led to an increase in agitation by extreme nationalists who already disapproved of the concessions made by Ho-Chi-Minh at Fontainebleau. In the words of a report by the French Socialist Party’s Executive, it was the acts of adventurers on both sides which made war inevitable.</p><p>It is useless to dwell on the efforts made by d’Argenlieu’s successor. Some of these efforts were praiseworthy. But the policy which he pursued, or which he was forced to pursue, was incapable of bringing the conflict to a satisfactory end.</p><p>To stop the war we must come to an agreement with the leader of those who are fighting. Negotiations and agreements with anyone else in Indo-China cannot possibly lead to a final solution. Even if Bao-Dai is granted much more than Ho-Chi-Minh ever asked for the problem remains unsolved.</p><p>On the other hand, it is sometimes asserted that this policy admittedly the only one which could put an end to the conflict’ might offer a chance of success if it were not for the fear that Ho-Chi-Minh is the Indo-Chinese representative of the Cominform for the Far East. No one has been able to prove that Ho-Chi-Minh is a member of the Cominform; it is also impossible to prove that he is not. In 1913 he became a member of the French Socialist Party, but from 1920 onwards he was undeniably a very active Communist. Does he still maintain strict obedience to Moscow’s orders? It is a possibility not to he overlooked, though it cannot be asserted definitely.</p><p>What can be definitely asserted, however, is that Viet-Nam resistance is not a monopoly of the Communist Party. Viet-Minh is a coalition including a variety of nationalist and democratic movements, with the Socialists playing an important part. And what can also be strongly asserted is that the longer hostilities go on the stronger Communist influence will become. There is also the fear that a check to Communism in Europe would cause Moscow to reinforce Cominform in the East, so that Communists inside the Viet-Nam resistance movement would gain a strong position and upset the balance of forces within the resistance itself.</p><p>Meanwhile, Indo-China is being ruined. A war to reconquer the country would need an army of 600,000 men and much special equipment. Reconquest, to which Socialists are firmly opposed,</p><p>I not necessarily mean the end of resistance. A country with 22 million inhabitants cannot be subdued indefinitely by suppressing all expressions of nationalist feelings by force.</p></div><div><head>The Socialist Party’s Policy </head><p>The French Socialist Party has considered the conflict in Indo-China at all its Congresses and has continually re-affirmed its belief that only a policy based on agreement and a respect for the convention of 6th March and the modus vivendi of 14th September can be effective. Our Party demands that Viet-Nam be recognised as a free state with its own government, parliament, armed forces, and finances. Within the French Union Viet-Nam should be represented on the Council and, if it wishes, in the Union Assembly. The Socialist Party Executive has already stated that Viet-Nam should be authorised to have consuls and diplomatic representatives in neighbouring countries, with France, as representative of the French Union as a whole, representing Viet-Nam in other countries. As far as uniting the three Ky is concerned (Tongking, Annam. Cochin-China), Viet-Nam and Cochin-China should be left to settle this problem together by democratic procedure in accordance with the people’s wishes. It has always been understood that the Indo-Chinese Federation would be an organisation for economic co-operation and would form a customs union, but that it would not be an intermediate political organisation and that Viet-Nam would he a member of the French Union in its own right. Defence of the French Union in the area should be the joint responsibility of Viet-Nam and France, and Viet-Nam should guarantee military and naval bases for French forces. Once collaboration had been achieved between the general staffs, the Viet-Nam national army would receive French material and French instructors. Finally, French property and interests in Viet-Nam should be protected in accordance with article 2 of the modus vivendi. Economic and cultural agreements should be concluded under articles 3 and 4.</p><p>French Socialists are convinced that the only wise course is for the Government to approach Ho-Chi-Minh to open negotiations, at the same time making clear that it has decided the policy just outlined. As soon as Ho-Chi-Minh’s reply is received—and we are convinced that it would be favourable—an armistice could be concluded. One of the armistice clauses should fix the date of the Peace Conference, and this being settled, the French Government should take steps to deal with anyone who, as has so often happened in the past, might upset French policy.</p><p>The problem is far too complex for all difficulties to be solved at once. There are still far too many reasons for suspicion between the two sides. In addition, an agreement between France and Viet-Nam would not necessarily mean the end of trouble in Indo-China: there are differences between the Indo-Chinese states, there is the struggle between the different political forces, and personal rivalry among political leaders. But whatever conflicts may arise inside Viet-Nam, they should not be the concern of France. It may be that the Fourth Republic, by furthering democratic development in the other countries of the French Union and by helping them with technicians and administrators, will be able to create a new fraternal peace-loving organisation extending across Africa and Asia. This is not just a hope held by French Socialists, it is a great opportunity for France of which the Government should be aware. Will the French Government grasp this opportunity and bring about a rapid, peaceful settlement?</p><p> (Recent appointments of officials give rise to doubt. The new High Commissioner will only continue the present policy. His past record causes us to believe that our policy can only be brought to success if he is replaced at once).</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>