<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Berlin fights for freedom</title>
         <author>Kurt Mattick</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Berlin fights for freedom</title>
            <author>Kurt Mattick</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Germany" party="Social Democratic Party of Germany"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><p>It was in Berlin that communist theory was turned upside down. It all began with the first mistake, made when Soviet forces captured Berlin in May 1945. In the wake of the Red Army came the trained Bolshevist commissars, charged with the task of supporting the allied campaign against Central Germany, and at the same time of preparing a springboard for the conquest of Europe. It is certain that many Russian officers, when they arrived, were convinced that all Germans were fascists who could easily be bolshevised. According to communist theory it would be enough to have control over the administration, press, radio and propaganda.</p><p>First of all, therefore, communist cadres were organised, and really democratic parties permitted, since the Bolshevists were confident that these could be controlled without difficulty later on. The fusion of the so-called workers’ parties was to follow. But when the Berlin Social Democrats refused to fall in with what had been worked out and did not act as theory laid down, the Communists consoled themselves with the thought that the Social Democrats would not be able to hold out very long, for they were only a small minority and the Communists were in power. This was the first mistake.</p><p>As a result, it was chiefly because of the insistence of the Russian occupation authorities that elections were quickly organised in Berlin and took place on 20th October 1946. Leninist theory took it for granted that the enormous power and propaganda machine which the Russians had built up for their German stooges would be enough to win the elections. The way would then be dear for depriving the Western Allies of all basis in Berlin and holding the other parties up to ridicule as agents of foreign powers.</p><p>The second defeat came on 20th October 1946. Contrary to all Leninist forecasts the desired election result did not happen; it was not even possible to fix the elections in the Eastern Sector which is in Soviet hands. After this grandiose election campaign only 20 per cent, of the votes went to the Communists; 80 per cent, of the population had already understood that a hard struggle would have to be fought for freedom.</p><p>The rest of the world took notice. The Berliners were delighted by their victory and still maintained the hope that this democratic election result would also be recognised by the Russians. In the eastern zone the people, oppressed and silenced, welcomed this manifestation of freedom from the heart of their zone.</p><p>But the Communists, both German and Russian, swore revenge. Their illusions had been destroyed, and their great plan had to be reorganised. Neither the Berlin democrats nor the distant Allied peoples, nor even the Allied representatives in Germany, realised the true seriousness of the situation. Just as Stalin had signed an agreement at Potsdam whose main provisions he had already broken before signing, so the Communists decided that this democratic success had to be brought to nothing by their usual tactics.</p><p>All this was hardly noticeable in the beginning, for up to a certain point the constitution of Berlin was accepted by the Russians as well as the other occupation powers. But by the summer of 1947, when a mayor for Berlin was elected who had once been a Communist and so was too well acquainted with communist tactics, the Russians ceased to recognise the provisional constitution. The city assembly, which had been elected on 20th October 1946 in a really free and secret ballot under control of all four allies, by June 1947 no longer had the right to elect the mayor.</p><p>From then on the democratic mask was dropped, and Berlin became a battlefield in the struggle between democracy and terror. There is no need to recount all the stages of this conflict. Step by step, the Russians have destroyed all democratic basis for the provisional constitution and have carried through the political and economic division of Germany’s former capital. Berlin thus became a battlefield between the allies. After the Kommandatura had ceased to function the allies adopted their own individual policies in their sectors.</p><p>The elections which took place on 5th December 1948 were the final stage in a development which could have no other outcome. In 1932 the Communists believed that a world war was inevitable, and that this would result in the victory of Bolshevism on a world scale. Already in 1930 the Comintern had ordered the German Communist Party to organise a common strike with the Nazis against the Berlin Transport Authority—a communal undertaking. The men in the Kremlin knew that the democratic Weimar Republic would never start a second world war. The Communists were hoping for a world conflict; an essential condition for this was the triumph of reaction in Germany. Everything followed logically from this. The war on two fronts, against Bolshevism and Nazism, which the Weimar Republic had to fight led to its collapse.</p><p>Fascism triumphed. The Second World War followed, once Hitler had made an alliance with Russia—an alliance which fitted well into this framework. The Communists did not foresee that Hitler, already at war with the rest of the world, might also destroy Russia.</p><p>Shut in for 25 years in the Kremlin, still thinking rigidly in terms of 1917, and having liquidated all opposition, the Russian leaders have reached such a degree of political stagnation that they amid learn no lessons from their defeats up to 1945. Once again the Communists worked out a European policy based on the hope that the Second World War had fundamentally shaken world capitalism.</p><p>After the Communists’ failure to win ground in France, Italy, the Ruhr, and other areas of Europe where they were not supported by Russian bayonets, the isolation of the territory' beyond the Elbe is essential for the continuation of Soviet domination; Berlin is the only obstacle in this process. As long as democratic forces can show the Western Powers on the spot that Berlin is the microcosm of the European conflict, the complete Sovietisation of Eastern Europe is impossible. Russia since the war is still devoting a large proportion of its production to armaments, and so cannot raise the standard of living of its people. Thus the presence of a normal European standard of living behind the Iron Curtain would be a constant peril; for no power can in the long run allow its people to occupy a territory whose standards are far higher than those of its own country.</p><p>Berlin's freedom must be ensured, if Europe is to survive. The people of Berlin know this. They are facing a winter which will perhaps dwarf the sufferings of previous winters. The air-lift of the Western Powers has eased the food situation. But if the winter is hard, the people of Berlin will be exposed to cold as never before. There are no stocks of coal; there is no wood left to use; there is no chance of the people supplying themselves. In spite of this the Berliners will patiently bear the cold, in the consciousness that they will be passing through the last but most difficult stage of their struggle. They know that by accepting the three hundredweights of coal which the Russians are offering them they would betray not only their own existence but also the fate of Europe.</p><p>If Berlin’s freedom can be maintained the Communists will be forced to try a new policy in the new year. They will be forced to recognise that it is better to live peacefully with a Europe capable of defending itself; otherwise they will not be able to prevent their own regime from collapse. Berlin is fighting for freedom in order to make it possible to win back the Eastern Zone and to force the Communists to live at peace with the world. To help in this task should be the duty of everyone who believes in liberty and progress.</p></body></text></TEI>