<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Some aspects of Western Union</title>
         <author>Jean Weiller</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Some aspects of Western Union</title>
            <author>Jean Weiller</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="French" party="SFIO"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The purely economic arguments in favour of a Western Union are well known. Nevertheless, the problem remains essentially political. In the economic field it is obvious that sooner or later there must be an expansion of trade on a European scale. National markets are no longer sufficient to ensure the full use of mass-production methods and economic resources, or to raise the standard of living. Potential overseas markets have their own protected, rapidly developing industries. One might therefore expect economic necessity to lead inevitably to one result, whatever our own intentions might be. But the political factors affecting union cannot be ignored, while from the point of view of economics, an inevitable result does not necessarily help us to choose between the various means of arriving at that result, for these means are all affected by the imponderables of the European situation.</p><p>Much that we read on the subject reveals an eagerness to succeed which is touching but which may defeat its own purpose. We need, it is said, immediate political action to settle all the outstanding problems; otherwise economic union would be a delusion. In this article we shall try to show that it is possible to avoid the impasse to which too rigid theorising of this kind leads, and which is not justified by present political conditions.</p><p>It is correct to say that the problem is primarily political, if by that is meant that just any kind of union would not necessarily be successful. Even if economic union were achieved it would still be possible for political union to fail disastrously. Hitler’s New Order arose from the need for a larger economic unit and from the urge to maintain the supremacy of one of the most highly industrialised areas in the world; in order to expand, it demanded Lebensraum. After the Second World War there is no need to stress this example.</p><p>The problem is also political in the sense that it arises out of the need to construct a framework for the peaceful development of international trade, and union would fail in its task if its result were only to increase tension between the rival “blocs.” Those who violently opposed the creation of a “Western bloc” failed to notice a greater danger—that of the gradual incorporation of European countries into either an American or a Russian sphere of influence. Western Union, even if it is not completely successful in the economic field, can still be a safeguard of peace. </p><p>But there is a third sense in which the problem is essentially political, and it is economic analysis which leads to this conclusion. It is haul to imagine how federation would be worthwhile to the participating countries, if it did not lead to a rationalisation of Europe's production. A pooling of natural resources, labour and capital should lead to a reorganisation of productive resources and so increase output and raise living standards, at the same time removing the need for outside aid and dependence on foreign capital. On this point Liberals and Socialists seem to be in agreement, but a choice must be made between the means of achieving economic union. In effect it is a choice, on a European scale, between planning and a return to laissez-faire: no compromise between these two alternatives is possible.</p><div><head>The theory of Western Union </head><p>There is no need here to list all the necessary conditions for complete economic union. If, like those economists who support Western Union, we look at the problem purely from the standpoint of the internal stability of the projected union, the conclusion seems inescapable. What would be the good of a union if it did not destroy the barriers hindering the development of trade, and therefore increased production? Moreover, once these barriers had disappeared, how could the member states carry on their own conflicting monetary and financial policies—for example, by putting a heavy purchase tax in one country on an article which is sold at a low price in another? Similarly, how could they maintain their separate social insurance systems? The projected union —so runs the argument—would inevitably lead to the formation of a very strong economic authority, similar to that of a State, with control over currency, exchange, customs, and so on, as well as control over financial policy and taxation.</p><p>If only strictly economic problems are taken into account, there seems to be no escaping the fundamental choice between a return to 19th century liberal capitalism and the establishment of a federal authority with full powers of control. In the first alternative there would be a return to the time when the State’s authority was limited to the bank of issue which maintained the gold standard, and any attempt to interfere in economic or social affairs was resisted. The second alternative would involve a federation of states with common socialist principles, or at least prepared to carry out a common policy on a European scale. But, with the best will in the world, is there any hope of achieving either of these alternatives in the foreseeable 'future? We cannot ignore the perils which would arise from an artificial economic union bearing no relation to the social and political realities of contemporary Europe. There are too many unknown quantities—for example, the position of Germany. As long as one concentrates exclusively on the internal problems of federation there seems no way out of the impasse. Liberals emphasise the value of a large free trade area of the traditional kind. But do they realise how great are the obstacles they face when they talk of reducing the amount of central planning in finance alone, not to mention economic affairs in general? Evolution towards a planned economy seems to be irreversible. It is generally agreed that considerable powers ought to be placed in the hands of the federal authority, though the amount of sovereignty to be surrendered by the participating countries would be greater under the kind of federation advocated by Socialists. No doubt everyone, whether Liberal or Socialist, is internationally- minded enough to agree that their long-standing quarrel could be transferred to the federal plane. Is not this an additional reason, it may be asked, for immediate federation?</p><p>Nevertheless, we cannot wait for agreement to come from amalgamation of the various utopias which have been produced. In addition, we must also take account of factors which may at any time affect these plans. For example, a sincere Liberal may decide in his programme for federation that international industrial agreements should be ruled out or at least limited, and a Socialist would, of course, agree. But we have reached a stage in economic development in which international cartels tend to reappear and use every opportunity to extend their influence. Economic union is such an opportunity—not the only one, naturally. Is there not therefore a danger, if cartel agreements are not taken into consideration, in a too rapid surrender of national sovereignty in economic affairs before the real powers of the projected union have been defined?</p></div><div><head>The problem of foreign relations </head><p>Nobody underestimates the great difficulties confronting any attempt to realise an economic union which functions perfectly. Nevertheless, some people talk as if there would be no point in having a union if it did not function perfectly. All or nothing— that seems to be the motto. This is why economists of this school have concentrated on the advantages which the participating countries would gain from one another inside the union. But this is only one aspect of the problem. In estimating the value of a gradual approach to union — even an incomplete union — other aspects are perhaps of more importance. At present, relations with the powers outside the union are the most significant of these —especially relations with the USA on the one hand and the USSR on the other. How could federation affect these relations?</p><p>Of course, there can be no question of a Western Union becoming a self-sufficient bloc. But how will federation help to develop trade with the rest of the world? That is the essential problem, and it seems to have been hardly touched on up to now.</p></div><div><head>Western Union and International trade charter </head><p>There is one question which is always raised when discussing expansion of trade by lowering customs barriers: would it not he possible to extend the free trade area to be created by European union to other parts of the world, and so make a reality of the dream world of the 191I1 century Liberals and Socialists. At this point it becomes absolutely necessary to understand the reasons why a gradual approach to union is not only desirable but essential. In fact, we have already been presented with a perfectly clear proposal to create a large area of freer trade, if not of free trade—the International Trade Charter adopted by the Havana Conference. This charter is an attempt to go as far as possible in the direction of lowering tariff barriers and removing quantitative restrictions. It will be argued that we could go even further in this direction inside a European union. But in met the charter does not overcome some difficulties, both in the United States, whose continued protectionism will make it more difficult to re-balance world trade, and in the debtor countries, which are less developed industrially or badly damaged by the war. As far as Europe is concerned nobody doubts that it will be desirable, for a transitional period at least, to maintain protective customs barriers and limit non-essential imports. There is still an enormous deficit in Europe’s balance of payments. The problem is to ensure that aid and loans designed to bridge the gap are not wasted. In spite of all the criticisms of austerity and planned economy, it is unlikely that anyone would recommend allowing imports of luxuries instead of necessities. As long as the deficit with the USA exists each country is bound to make every effort to avoid increasing it.</p><p>It would be an exaggeration to say that this situation is always fully understood, especially when discussions are theoretical. Theories do not always yield easily to the evidence of facts. But in the end we must come to this conclusion: whatever weight may be attached to the principle of non-discrimination, almost every country in Europe must follow' two distinct policies. Among themselves the balance of payments is more or less steady and they could fairly easily expand their trade with one another; vis-à-vis the United States they must restrict imports, many of which are bought on credit, and make great efforts to increase exports to the maximum. Article 23 of the International Trade Charter signed in Havana is a subtle attempt to make certain discriminatory policies possible while at the same time categorically affirming the inflexible principle of non-discrimination. Yet it is difficult to measure the effect a clause authorising bilateralism to increase trade between two countries which each have a deficit on their balance of payments, and forbidding it in ordinary trading or more expressly when the countries concerned attempt to reduce their shortage of hard currency. But, leaving details on one side, it can be seen how dubious are the concessions made to European countries by a simple clause in the Havana Charter.</p></div><div><head>The paradox of the Marshall plan</head><p>The Charter was amended to include this escape clause because to apply a policy of non-discrimination now would obviously lead to disastrous consequences. But what was permitted only as an afterthought in the Charter can be done openly by an economic union—and still serve the same principle of increased international trade. This is a strange paradox, for the exceptions admitted in the Charter could only rarely happen. But from now on the European nations are free to go even further. All that was needed was a way of legalising an exceptional but nevertheless urgent situation— and this was done by the Marshall Plan. I should not be surprised if a number of American economists were relieved to hear the US Secretary of State, in his speech of 5 June 1947, call on the European countries to do just what the International Trade Charter, then under discussion at Geneva, seemed utterly to rule out. It is true that other difficulties may still arise—the problems are complex and their solution may not agree with abstract theories. Nevertheless economic union will permit commercial relations between Western European countries to return to normal in the long run, without increasing dependence on the United States. The union should be able to reduce the deficit in the balance of payments, reduce its indebtedness and perhaps even reverse the present balance of trade with America, and so be able later to co-operate, on a sound and permanent basis, in the development of multilateral trade with the other nations which signed the Havana Charter.</p><p>European union can also help to simplify and extend trade relations with the Soviet Union. The formation of a federation with large economic resources would certainly stimulate trade between East and West. While the USSR might continue to ignore small, isolated countries, it would be more easily attracted by the overall possibilities of the new union.</p><p>But in dealing with this problem we quickly come up against the political problems we emphasised earlier. We need only recall the fact that the Soviet Union’s suspicion of all plans to form a Western Union is due in large measure to the part which the United States seems to play in it. But present plans only reflect economic realities. We agree that the European Recovery Programme is the direct and inescapable result of Western Europe’s economic situation; we must also agree that, in the long run, Western Union offers the only chance of reducing Europe’s trade deficit and her economic dependence. The results of our plans depend above all on political conditions in Europe. If a united effort is made to realise the possibilities of a simple economic policy inside the union, it will inevitably help to restore economic prosperity and to maintain peace.</p><p>This article has devoted much less attention than most writings on the subject to working out plans for a perfect economic union. What seems more important is the question of relations between the union and the great powers outside it. On the other hand, while I maintain that political considerations must take precedence, this does not mean that any kind of political federation will lead inevitably to a stable economic union. Economic union demands the surrender of a large part of the sovereignty of the participating powers all the more reason why a gradual approach to union is preferable to a too rapid abandonment of national sovereignty. In any ease the national state will for some time continue to be a living reality. It should therefore be regarded as an essential part of the new economic organisation. In fact it would be best to define what powers should remain with the individual states in the union. For example, at a time when there is considerable international movement of capital it seems essential to maintain strict controls in order to use this capital to the best advantage. As long as investment plans remain a national responsibility (like the Monnet Plan in France) it would be dangerous to do otherwise. There should also be national control over international cartel agreements, as is laid down in the Havana Charter. Similarly, there would probably be differences in regard to social security legislation, though in this respect uniformity could almost certainly be achieved quite rapidly on a federal scale—the trade union movement’s international traditions ought to smooth the process. Later on also it should be possible to develop uniformity in monetary and financial policy.</p><p>It is not so much for economic as for political reasons that we must beware of a too rapid surrender of national sovereignty. A gradual approach to economic union does not raise the same difficulties from this point of view as the immediate federation proposed by economic theorists.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>