<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Austria’s Economic Future</title>
         <author>Karl Waldbrunner</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Austria’s Economic Future</title>
            <author>Karl Waldbrunner</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Austrian" party="Socialist Party of Austria"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>The economic problems facing Austria in the period since the end of the war in April 1945 go far beyond the tasks of reconstruction alone. We cannot possibly remain satisfied with bringing back the economic conditions of 1937—the year before the Anschluss, or 1929—the year before the world economic crisis. To-day political and economic conditions have changed so much that an attempt merely to reproduce a past economic structure is doomed to failure.</p><p>In comparison with the appalling conditions following the Second World War the economic situation in the years before 1937 now appears almost favourable, though of course it was in fact bad enough. Mismanagement of our industry led to a collapse of the banking system, which contributed to the world economic crisis which followed. This crisis brought untold restrictions and hardships whose main burden fell upon the industrial workers. An attempt was made to protect the farmers by means of high customs duties, with the result that the sale of industrial products was made still more difficult. There was an army of about 600,000 unemployed. The national income declined; consumption declined still further.</p><p>During this period Socialists had very little influence on economic affairs. By 1934 the gains we had made towards socialism in 1918—extension of public ownership, appointment of Socialists to influential positions in the country’s economic life—had been almost entirely lost. In 1934 Socialists were expelled from local government councils and from the Co-operative Movement. By 1937 the entire economic system was in the hands of our opponents.</p><p>From this point of view we can scarcely regard the year 1937 as a basis of comparison. We refuse to be satisfied with regaining the standards of that year.</p><p>In discussing the problems of economic reconstruction, the question of manpower must take first place. We cannot again tolerate a pool of several hundred thousands of unemployed, especially as our chief concern is the people’s well-being and the maintenance of political stability. Full employment—so much spoken of nowadays—does not mean conscription of various categories of workers for particular jobs according to economic needs. On the other hand, neither private nor publicly-owned enterprises should be burdened with superfluous workers.</p><p>A ban on dismissals, such as has been tried in Italy, is in the long run a handicap for industry and also brings no final advantage to the workers. The same argument applies to the swollen civil service which has arisen because of the extension of State control over the economy and the wider activities of the government during and since the war. As conditions return to normal a large number of these civil servants will become redundant and their continued employment will be an unnecessary burden on the taxpayer.</p><p>State control of industry will mean that great changes in employment will be necessary, for workers cannot be just thrown out into the streets. It may be that better results can be achieved by keeping the workers fully informed about the needs of the situation than by a programme of re-training for new and more essential jobs. But in any case special attention must be given to technical training of young people. This campaign of redeployment of workers opens under favourable conditions, for Austrian participation in the Marshall Plan means that full employment is assured, at least for the next few years, in spite of the fact that our industrial potential has been lessened as a result of the war. It is high time that ministries, employers’ organisations and trade unions joined forces to work out a long term plan for the future</p><p>      .</p><div><head>Austria’s great losses </head><p>This question is bound up with that of re-equipping and rationalising the most important branches of industry so as to increase output to the greatest possible extent. Within the short period during which the Marshall Plan will be in force, we must successfully organise our resources in material and manpower so that both overall production and output per worker is greatly increased. It is only by this means that the national income can be increased and so bring the workers’ standard of living into line with that of other countries. Indexes of production, proving that we have reached or surpassed the 1937 level, do not alter the fact that Austria’s real national income has fallen in comparison with other countries. Recent estimates show that it is not much more than 50 per cent, of the national income for 1935 which was about 6,500 million Schilling.</p><p>The reason for this is chiefly the damage caused by the war, though mismanagement of our industry before 1937 is' partly to blame. Very few reliable figures of war damage are available. Where it has been possible to make adequate estimates, they have been confined to the physical damage suffered up to the end of the war. When the reconstruction law came into force it was reckoned that damage to dwellings amounted to about 8,000 million Schilling losses due to seizure of property as war booty since the war will cost an estimated 2,000 million Schilling 10 replace. Occupation costs amount so far to about 4.000 million Schilling. The United States is the only one of the occupying powers to pay its own occupation costs. A continuous drain on Austrian resources are the Soviet-controlled industries (USIA) which comprises mitre than 200 enterprises, many of them very important. Many millions of dollars are lost annually in the form of exports from these extraterritorial undertakings.</p><p>The war seriously damaged agriculture, industry, trade and communications, and almost completely destroyed the financial system. Without help from the West we should have been quite lost. Up to the start of the Marshall Plan in the spring of 1948 more than 300 million dollars worth of relief goods had been received in Austria. The Marshall Plan greatly increases this help. In the first year of the Plan Austria has been granted a sum of 280 million dollars.</p></div><div><head>Aid for reconstruction </head><p>Marshall aid gives us the opportunity systematically to repair the damage the war has caused to all branches of our economy, and to construct a much more favourable basis for our industry than existed before 1937. Including Marshall Plan deliveries, Austrian imports will amount to 480 million dollars in the year 1948-9. Calculating the dollar as equivalent to 3 Schilling at 1937 values, our total imports are about the same as in 1937. But our exports are far below the level of that year.</p><p>In addition, the Marshall Plan makes it possible for Austria to become a part of a great economic region. Austria is still dependent on the outside world. In fact, until 1937 our foreign trade relations were among the most extensive in the world. But since the war it has been extraordinarily difficult to extend our foreign trade. Since 1945 there has been an ever more marked tendency for Eastern and South-Eastern Europe to become a closed trading area. All the commercial agreements and economic plans which these countries have made reveal this clearly. Even though their policy may bring no immediate benefits to the states concerned, the fact remains that in its former markets Austria is to-day only a stop-gap.</p><p>To us Socialists it is unthinkable that Austria’s economy can be developed without further public ownership and a planned economy that can avoid the regimentation which the war-time system brought. This is our conception of the democratic road towards a socialist economy. But we are living in a society whose economy is still mostly capitalist in structure, although the changes brought by the war were very great. Since the war we have been able to make great progress in nationalisation—the first step towards socialism. Transport and the fuel and power industries, together with the main banks and the key industries, are now state property.</p><p>Our influence over the economic affairs is incomparably greater and more solid than it was in the years following the First World War. And this means that we have a proportionally greater responsibility for Austria's economic development. We can safely say that so far we have played our part to the full. But we should not have any illusions—the most difficult task lies ahead: for instance, the problems of the nationalised industries will need a good deal of careful thought.</p><p>In particular, we cannot indefinitely preserve the war-time economic system with its forms and controls which are a greater and greater burden on the people the longer they are maintained. These controls were imposed during the war, and were a great help in overcoming the difficult conditions since the war, but it must be remembered that as conditions improve so it becomes necessary systematically to remove the controls which impede progress. To keep restrictions on consumer goods and food tor longer than is absolutely necessary can never be part of socialist policy'. Any such mistake would do great harm to the ideal of planned economy, for we must not forget that it is the overall plan, and not restrictions for their own sake, which constitutes the basis for rapid methodical progress.</p><p>In this respect, too, the Marshall Plan comes to our aid. This great co-operative effort at European economic reconstruction makes planning in the individual states the primary consideration. So the struggle to establish a planned economy in Austria has become more than a battle against profit-seeking private enterprise in certain branches of industry: it is a campaign to use American aid in the most useful way, so that Austria’s economy develops as rapidly as possible towards independence of outside assistance. We Socialists are therefore the trustees of Austrian economy.</p><p>Although we may be unable to control the whole political and social development, yet it will mainly depend on us how Austria's economic future is shaped. In present circumstances we have more chance than ever before making reconstruction take the course we wish. We must not allow ourselves to be driven from the positions we have won; we must work out long-term plans for the future. The basis of these plans will be the principles we have stated.</p><p>The essential conditions for healthy economic development, and therefore for a rising standard of living for the people, are the maintenance of financial stability, rising production, and the co-ordination of Austria’s economy into a European planned economy. Hand in hand with reconstruction must go consolidation and extension of public ownership, for this is the only means by which a stable economic future can be achieved.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>