<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>Economic Development in Iceland</title>
         <author>Gylfi Gislason</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblFull default="false">
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Economic Development in Iceland</title>
            <author>Gylfi Gislason</author>
          </titleStmt>
          <extent />
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>International Socialist Conference</publisher>
            <pubPlace />
            <date>December 1948-February 1949</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist World</title>
            <idno>No.7</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note nation="Icelandic" party="Icelandic Socialist Party"/>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text><body><div><p>Since the turn of the century, such great changes have taken place within Iceland’s economic structure that they can without exaggeration be termed a revolution. Iceland obtained its own financial system, with legislative powers of control, in 1874, but for the first twenty-five years afterwards this did not amount to much. The Alting, the Icelandic Parliament, was cautious about spending money, and the citizens were not very enterprising, owing to the country’s poverty and lack of capital.</p><p>After the turn of the century, a joint-stock bank was set up, with the right of note issue. Up till then, there had only been the Iceland National Bank, which had been opened 19 years earlier. The new bank provided the country’s economy with a considerable amount of capital, and, moreover, the idea now arose in the Alting of taking action to install industrial equipment.</p><p>The first trawler came into Icelandic ownership in 1904; at that time 95 per cent, of the fishing was made up of sail. During the next twenty years, tonnage rose very considerably, but what was more important was the complete change in its composition. Sail practically disappeared, and the number of trawlers rose to 47, or 61 per cent, of the tonnage.</p><p>Great progress was also made in agriculture and trade. At the start of the century, there were 208 commercial undertakings in the country, of which one-fifth were foreign-owned. During the first decade of this century, practically the whole of the country’s trade came into Icelandic ownership, largely on a co-operative basis, particularly in the rural districts.</p><p>During the First World War, the country’s economy was affected by outside events. Inflation arose, mainly owing to the loan policy of the bank of issue. This bank was a private undertaking and only lost its note-issuing rights a few years after the war, when they were transferred to the National Bank. Prices quadrupled but wages did not rise to the same extent. At the beginning of the war, the bank was absolved from its gold-redemption obligations, and since then Iceland has had a paper currency.</p><p>Although the first two war years were favourable for Iceland’s economy, it suffered during the last years. In 1917, the Icelanders were forced to sell ten of their trawlers to the Allies. This was half of their ships and the biggest ones at that. It became difficult to obtain supplies, the conditions for foreign trade were very bad, the banks incurred foreign indebtedness, and the value of the Icelandic krone fell to only 47 per cent of the 1924 gold parity.</p><p>In 1922 the Danish and Icelandic currencies were separated with the latter becoming an independent currency. In 1924 things took a turn for the better, and several good years followed. Catches were particularly heavy, and the price for fish was high, so that the country benefited from the great expansion of the fishing fleet which followed on the war. The banks again accumulated credits abroad, and the currency rose to 81 per cent, of gold parity. The price level had fallen since 1920, and this fall continued till 1927. Wages rose to some extent, and the standard of living went ahead.</p><div><head>The Great Depression </head><p>The good years lasted till 1929, when the great world depression set in. This brought down the price of Iceland’s exports, and the decline continued till 1932, when they reached the lowest level, lower than that at the end of the war. At this time, the balance of trade was particularly unfavourable and foreign indebtedness increased. When England went off the gold standard in 1931, the Icelandic krone, like the other Scandinavian currencies, followed sterling. In spite of the very bad currency situation, the krone did not fall in relation to sterling, but import regulations and currency control had been introduced by 1931, although they only became effective after 1934.</p><p>Export difficulties and the weak currency situation lasted longer than the depression itself. When prices again rose in 1934, it was the catches, which were missing, as 1935-1939 were very bad years in the cod fisheries. At the same time, the import restrictions adopted during this period by a number of countries materially affected exports. In 1930 58 per cent, of Iceland’s fish exports had gone to Spain, Italy and Portugal, but the corresponding figure was 18 per cent, in 1938. Iceland’s best market—Spain—virtually closed down for several years.</p><p>The decade preceding the last World War was therefore extremely difficult from the economic point of view, despite the different measures adopted to overcome the obstacles, especially in the year when a Progressive Party and Social-Democratic coalition government was in power. But it was just this year that saw the loss of the Spanish market and the subsequent difficulties. Action was taken to promote the development of the herring fishery, which had been started during the depression. Quick-freezing plant was built, and new processes for the preparation of fishery products were initiated. Output from the herring factories was particularly high, since the herring catch was exceptionally heavy in several of these years. In the cod fisheries, the processing of the catch was changed, so that it was now sold as frozen fish to Great Britain and Germany, instead of being processed as dried cod for Southern Europe. Moreover, a start was made with expanding agricultural exports by balancing prices on the home market with export prices.</p><p>Wages remained practically unchanged during this period, but the workers' income dropped because there was some unemployment and prices had risen, partly owing to import regulations. Price control was introduced in 1938, but even then it was not far-reaching enough.</p><p>The action taken to bring equilibrium into the field of foreign trade proved inadequate, and foreign indebtedness increased. In the early part of 1939, all the parties, except the Communists, therefore agreed to an 18 per cent, devaluation of the krone. It was also decided that, if the cost of living rose by more than five per cent, part of this should be compensated by a wages increase.</p></div><div><head>The Second World War </head><p>A few months after the start of the war, the economic circumstances of the country were very much changed. The market in Continental Europe was closed, but fish prices in Great Britain rose substantially, as well as the marketing possibilities. Iceland’s fish production increased considerably during the war, and went almost entirely to Britain. The exports of frozen fish went up tenfold, a great deal of modern quick-freezing plant was installed, and great importance was attached to processing frozen and quick-frozen fish, herring oil, and herring meal. But the production of salt herring fell, and the processing of dried cod came to a complete standstill. The value of exports was quadrupled during the war; in the last war year nine-tenth’s of Iceland’s exports went to England. Commerce with the European continent and with the Scandinavian countries came to an end, although prior to the war they had taken about two-thirds of Iceland’s exports and supplied much of its imports.</p><p>Even with most of the exports going to Great Britain, it soon became difficult to obtain goods from there, and recourse had to be had to America. During the last year of the war, two-thirds of Iceland’s imports came from the United States. The British Lend-Lease Agreement laid down that the United States should pay in dollars for the frozen fish Great Britain received from Iceland; this allowed of increased imports from the USA. The value of imports quintupled during the war, even though the price of imported goods only rose by 170 per cent. The greatest increase occurred in consumption goods.</p><p>Iceland was occupied by the British in 1940, and in 1941 the country's protection was taken over by the USA, in accordance with an agreement with the Icelandic Government. The military needed many workers for all kinds of work. Unemployment soon gave way to a labour shortage. The cost of living rose steeply, not so much on account of the increased price of imported goods, but because of the rise in agricultural prices. The prices were fixed by a public Price Control Board, which thought that an increased income for the farmers was justified, since the wages of seamen and other workers had risen owing to the higher export prices and the high level of employment.</p></div><div><head>Inflation during the war </head><p>By the end of 1940, agreements had been concluded covering the complete regulation of wage rates. This means that the rise in the price of agricultural products led to a parallel increase in wages. Then agricultural prices went up again, and so on. This senseless method of regulating wages and prices produced a pendulum process, which was bound to lead to cumulative inflation. Even by the end of 1941, the cost of living index had risen to 172 (Jan-March 1939=100), one year later it stood at 250, and towards the end of 1946 it was over 300, and would have gone even higher if subsidies had not been introduced to keep down the price of the most essential agricultural products. In addition to the payment of cost of living supplements on wages, basic rates were raised considerably.</p><p>In 1942 the Independent and Progressive Parties introduced legislation to stop any further rise in wages and domestic agricultural prices; but the Social-Democrats then withdrew from the government, in which they had taken part since 1939 with the other parties, and, together with the Communists, fought this legislation. This was a great year of expansion, and the Parties which proposed the price ceiling were not prepared to put forward a really complete solution of the inflation problem, which might possibly have reconciled the Labour Movement to having wages frozen. The great increase in export prices at the beginning of the war had brought a tidy profit to the ship-owners, while tremendous profits were also being made in the import trade out of the high domestic prices.</p><p>It was impossible to reach agreement on reasonable and adequate measures to reduce radically the enormous profits being made in import and export trade, in order to combat inflation. But this was a fundamental condition for the co-operation of the working-class parties and the labour movement in a more moderate wages policy. The legislation on a wage and price ceiling came quickly to grief, and was soon repealed, with the result that basic wages were substantially raised. In 1943, it was decided to peg agricultural prices in such a way that farmers’ incomes would be in line with the incomes of urban workers and fluctuate in proportion to them. Generally speaking, this rule has been adhered to since then.</p><p>The Icelanders had considerable foreign debts at the start of the war, but foreign trade conditions were specially favourable during the war. Between 1940 and 1944, the foreign credits of the banks rose by an average of 115 million kroner per annum, reaching their peak in November 1944, when they amounted to 586 million kroner.</p><p>This great improvement in the foreign currency situation, in spite of heavy importing during the war, was of course due both to good trading conditions and to the high receipts of foreign currency through the military garrison’s use of labour.</p></div><div><head>Expansion of shipping </head><p>When the Independent, Social-Democratic and Communist Parties formed the government towards the end of 1944, it was agreed to reserve 300 million kroner in foreign currency, for the purpose of post-war economic reconstruction. Increased investment in the fishery industry was regarded as particularly important. The government signed contracts for the construction of 33 trawlers in Great Britain and 50 motor ships in Sweden; in addition, 30 motor ships were to be constructed at home, and private firms ordered more than 50 motor ships abroad.</p><p>A large increase in merchant tonnage was also agreed to, and this tonnage was tripled after the war. The fishery industry was to be substantially extended, especially the herring industry.</p><p>These investments naturally took a great deal of foreign currency, and in 1945 there was a change on the foreign currency market. During this year, foreign credits fell by over 100 million kroner, and this decline continued until they were exhausted by the middle of 1947.</p><p>Although the new industrial investments had taken a lot of foreign currency, it is impossible to explain the rapid disappearance of the country's currency reserves by this alone. At the end of the war, there was a great optimism in the field both of public activities and private enterprise, and much initiative was manifest, especially in the building trade. People were better off, economically speaking, than before; they felt they could afford better and bigger houses. Many people also wanted to put their money into property, so that there was a great increase in building, especial in Reykjavik, where the population had increased from about 37,000 at the beginning of the war to about 52,000 at the end of 1947-</p><p>All this building naturally made heavy demands on the foreign currency balance. And it must be remembered that, although prices during the war had probably risen four-fold or five-fold, wages had been quintupled or sextupled, and the national income was about eight times higher than before the war, rates of exchange had remained the same, so that all foreign goods and services were very cheap, reckoned in Icelandic currency. It is therefore not surprising that the rush for foreign currency was very great, with everyone eager to import both consumption goods and all kinds of capital goods, which would provide the basis for increased consumption.</p></div><div><head>Economic reorganisation after the war </head><p>The Communists withdrew from the government towards the end of 1946 as they did not agree with granting the United States rights over the Keflavik airfield. When the new government came in, in February 1947 (this government consisted of Conservatives, Progressives and Social-Democrats, with a Social-Democrat as Prime Minister), its first task was to try to improve the foreign currency situation and to stop inflation getting any worse.</p><p>The government increased import duties considerably, laid down import restrictions, initiated strict rationing and the tight supervision of investments. A census of financial holdings was undertaken at the same time as the registration of securities and the calling in of note issue. A tax was laid on increased fortunes, and a sales tax put on most goods, so that prices rose correspondingly. The permitted profit margin was reduced, and parallel action was taken with wages. The wages index was only to be 300, although the cost of living index was 328. At the same time, prices for agricultural products were proportionately reduced, so that the drop in real wages amounted to five or six per cent.</p><p>As there was a good deal of difference of opinion on this matter between the various government Parties, it was difficult to reach agreement on such far-going measures. The task was to reconcile the aims of the different groups. The Social-Democrats urged that the position of the urban population be brought up to that of the economically strongest section of the people, and that economic planning and rationalisation be introduced into industrial life, not least into trade; the Progressives demanded that no restriction be placed on agriculture and that the consumers’ co-operatives should have the largest share in the import trade; while the Independent Party was hostile to all the economic planning, including the reorganisation of the import trade, which was being pressed for, and was also opposed to radical taxation measures.</p><p>But it was possible to continue the economic reconstruction which had already begun, without deterioration of the foreign currency situation, or, in other words, without incurring foreign indebtedness.</p><p>The situation was greatly aided by the unexpectedly large catch of herring last winter in Hvalfjord, north of Reykjavik, which brought in a large amount of foreign currency.</p></div><div><head>Great shortage of foreign exchange </head><p>There are still great difficulties in Iceland with reference to the foreign exchange situation. The new production capacity has certainly improved the situation, especially the new trawlers, which sell their catch to Great Britain at a price 50 per cent, above the price obtained by the old trawlers. But the standard of living rose so much during the war that it is difficult to maintain the level. With the income level as high as it is, coinciding with relatively low prices in those countries with which trade is carried on, reckoned at the current exchange rates, there is strong pressure on the foreign currency market. Stringent regulation is necessary to maintain a balance.</p><p>But this is not the whole story. In addition to the all-round foreign currency difficulties, there is a shortage of the dollars which are essential for the purchase of various necessities from the United States, to which country exports have never been extensive. It is now hoped that the Marshall Plan will help to solve this problem, but it is clear that it alone will not be enough. In the near future, therefore, it will certainly be necessary to take extreme measures to remedy the foreign currency situation.</p><p>When this is done, the Social Democrats will continue as in the past, to regard as their main task the protection of the higher standard of living which workers and wage-earners have obtained during the war. The means to this end are a more equal distribution of income, a greater measure of economic planning, and the rationalisation of economic life.</p></div></div></body></text></TEI>