<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in France</title>
         <author>Jean Texcier</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>14 January, 1956</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.VI, No.2</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
   <p>If one is to study the history of the development of Socialist ideas in France during the last thirty or forty years, one must start from the 1914-18 War or, to be exact, from the year 1917.</p><p>For the First World War, fought in the name of “internationalism” by France, Britain and their allies against the Germany of Wilhelm II (which was totally involved in spite of the courageous protests and revolts of certain Socialists) - this war had dramatically posed the problem of national solidarity and of the way in which, when matters came to a head during an armed conflict, it got the better of working-class solidarity and that “class action” whose international revolutionary importance had been stressed by Marx.</p><p>The last pre-war international Socialist congresses had discussed - in a rather theoretical way - the attitude of the proletariat and the working-class parties in the event of a conflict provoked by the insatiability and the crises of capitalism. It was the French delegation, with Jaurès and Vaillant, which presented the motion recommending the general strike as an effective weapon against military adventures in those countries threatened by armed conflict. They were opposed by Guesde and the federation of the North, who pointed out the dangers of a method which could be turned against the democratic countries, where class consciousness was naturally most developed. The majority motion of Jaurès and Vaillant expressed the same idea as Aristide Briand had put forward, but applied it to a situation where war and peace were in the balance - namely, the idea of the revolutionary general strike.</p><p>War was declared, and although Jaurès had just been assassinated by a fanatic the French Socialists did not hesitate. Their duty as Socialists and their whole conception of internationalism went hand in hand with their duty as French patriots. The situation was fairly clear since British and French democracy, united in the <hi rend="underline">Entente Cordiale</hi>, found themselves faced with the aggressive imperialism of Germany and Austria, whose political structure was entirely feudal. The situation was, therefore, that this war, although it was capitalist since it was the result of a world which was correctly considered to he capitalist, was, from the political and social point of view, in line with the type of political struggle traditionally waged by the working classes in all countries.</p><p>The attitude of the French Socialists, amongst whom it was possible to discern the natural bitterness which goes with profound disillusionment, was, however, unanimous; both the anti-militarists and the formerly “unpatriotic” elements associated with Gustav Hervé as well as the revolutionary syndicalists who had formerly been anarcho-syndicalists of the CGT, if they did anything at all, responded to the appeal to mobilise. That this attitude was unanimous was demonstrated at the public meeting organised in Paris the day after Jaurès’ death. Men like Sembat, Renaudel, Cachin and Vaillant could be heard explaining to the applause of Socialists the overwhelming reasons why the French people should defend the rule of law and liberty. Yet the speakers pointed out that they must refrain from hatred or from any action which might falsify the aims of the conflict because, as they said, the working class had adopted a cause which was its own, since it was the cause of liberty. They must, therefore, while playing their full part in national defence, keep it on the right lines - i.e. on the lines of a just defence and not of conquest.</p><p>The decadence of Tsarism, together with its clear intention of profiting from the war - not only by settling accounts with the Socialist enemies of the regime but by ensuring for Russia those outlets and spheres of influence which were the constant dream of the Tsars before they were taken over by the Soviets - led to two things: to the first Russian Revolution and to the separate peace treaty of Brest Litovsk which heralded the October coup d’etat and the seizure of power by Lenin and the Bolshevik Party.</p><p>To begin with the Russian Revolution had been greeted enthusiastically by Socialists throughout the world. Soon, however, the way in which it developed and its persecution not only of Liberals and revolutionary Socialists, but of Menshevik Social Democrats, caused uneasiness in the French Socialist Party. This, moreover, coincided with the formation of a group which, although it was still a minority in 1917 when the pacifist conferences at Kienthal and Zimmerwald were reaching their decisions, was later to become a majority group including among its members a large number of new adherents. They were attracted not only by the example of Soviet Russia, but by the creation of the Third International which denounced the failure of the Second International and the collection of “petit bourgeois reactionaries” and “social patriots” (they were soon to be called “social traitors”) still to be found in the SFIO.</p><p>It was at this point that - owing to active propaganda based on a revolutionary romanticism with an anarchist or “blanquist” tinge - a big shuffle took place in the various French provincial sections which had been swollen by hot-headed members who did not know where to draw the line.</p><p>L.O. Frossard, who was at this time General Secretary of the Party, went off to Moscow, accompanied by Cachin, to “discuss” the possibility of the SFIO's adhesion to the Third International, which everyone knew was international only in name and entirely Bolshevik in character.</p><p>The two emissaries brought back with them the famous twenty-one conditions. They themselves had already resolved to accept these conditions in their entirety and intended to ask the party to accept them, too. Moreover, everything had been so well arranged and the atmosphere was so heated that there was no doubt as to the outcome. Consultations with the local parties did the rest. The congress of Tours was to be the congress which agreed to join the Third International. The minority, faithful not so much to an International which had stood up badly to the so-called Great War as to the doctrine, tactics and spirit of democratic Socialism and international democracy, knew that it would be unable to withstand the attack.</p><p>But at least it wanted to save the honour of Socialism by preserving its spirit and sheltering from the mad whirlwind what Leon Blum called the “Old House”, which one day would welcome back its adventurous prodigal sons.</p><p>The Congress of Tours and the discussion of the incredible conditions which were defined and made more severe on the one hand by Zinoviev’s telegram denouncing the Left-wing group, represented at this time by Jean Longuet, and on the other by the theatrically-staged intervention of Clara Zetkin, faced the Socialists not only with the question of freedom to express and therefore also to publish their opinions, but with the whole question of doctrine and tactics. The latter included the question of the very nature of Socialism as opposed to Bolshevism which, in order to deceive everyone, had adopted the honoured name of Communism.</p><p>It was Leon Blum who, amidst the unheard-of and almost savage uproar at the Congress of Tours, opened the great debate. It was not only a question of preserving purity of terminology but of that purity of ideas which had been so terribly sullied by the use of a dialectic, which is no longer comprehensible since in the land of Bolshevism they gravely talk about "dialectical materialism" as if the combination of these two words could mean anything at all.</p><p>* * *</p><p>What was Leon Blum's position ? He spoke in the name of the Socialist Resistance Committee, whose motion, signed by Leon Blum, Bracke and Mayéras Paoli, was withdrawn in the course of the debate and replaced by the motion of Mistral and Longuet which was also supported by the group represented by Renaudel called Vie socialiste. This genuinely Socialist motion obtained 1,022 votes as against 3,208 for the resolution put forward by the Committee of the Third International which had won the support of the group led by Cachin and Frossard.</p><p>“You are freed”, said Lion Blum, “with a whole body of doctrine. If you accept it, then you accept it in all its aspects - it means you accept it determined to conform strictly to the new doctrine in thought and deed.</p><p>“It is not a question merely of revision and re-adaptation. This is a new kind of Socialism in all its essential points - in its views on organisation, in its views on relations between the political organisation and the economic organisation, in its conception of revolution and its conception of the dictatorship of the proletariat.</p><p>“This new kind of Socialism, in our opinion, is based on essentially false ideas which are contrary to the basic and unalterable principles of Marxist Socialism. It is based, moreover, on a kind of vast false assumption which consists in generalising and applying to the whole of international Socialism a certain number of ideas drawn from local and specialised lessons - the lessons of the Russian Revolution itself. It consists in setting up as a universal and obligatory model for international Socialism the lessons and they are debatable ones - which have been slowly drawn by the men who carried out and gave life to the Russian Revolution.”</p><p>Having thus presented the problem Leon Blum, of whom Bracke said that his speech at Tours was a miracle of penetration and today still has the force of prophecy, examined the changes which would necessarily be made in the democratic constitution of the Party if the twenty-one conditions were accepted.</p><p>“Our Party”, he said, “is based on the widest possible recruitment. As such, it is a party of freedom of thought; the two concepts belong together and the one necessarily derives from the other. Within the framework of acceptance of Socialism all shades of thought are tolerated. Some of us think that our goal can be reached by certain means and within a certain time; others by other means and within a different time. All these divergences are allowed and we cannot forbid them without renouncing our aim, which is the rallying of all the workers of all countries.</p><p>“Thus, when the Party wrote into its statute that there was complete freedom of discussion, that the press was free, these were not vague democratic ideas introduced into our Socialist constitution - it was a rule which derived from the very nature of what a Socialist party must be.”</p><p>After stressing the difference in the constitution of the Communist Party, where the central authority is in the hands of a committee appointed under the control of the Executive Committee of the Third International, Leon Blum pointed out that the most important steps taken by the Party would be subject to the wishes of leaders whom no one knew. He was surprised, therefore, that even within the SFIO people should speak of tyranny - of tyranny of the leaders, tyranny of people who had been <hi rend="underline">elected</hi>. “I do not know”, he exclaimed “how those who have been elected exercise their tyrannical powers - but at least you know who they are and you can have things out with them. But tomorrow? With whom will you have to deal then? With anonymous persons, with unknown men, with masks.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Turning to the supporters of adhesion to the Third International, he pointed out that so far unity in the Party had been symbolical, harmonious unity. “It was, as it were, the product of all the forces and all the currents which came into play in deciding the common basis of action. What you want to have in your party only men who will not only act but think as one. Your doctrine has been laid down once and for all.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">If in 1920 Leon Blum did not yet use the word “totalitarian” which suits so well not only the structure of the Communist Party but also the Soviet system of government, it was because at that time the world had not yet experienced the terror of Hitlerism and National Socialism and did not know the real threat of totalitarianism in action. But Blun was even then prophetically explaining the need of that system for incessant, large-scale purges. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Coming to the heart of his thesis, Léon Blum then protested against the type of polemic and discussion which consisted in depicting the opponents of the Third International as “counter-revolutionaries” and in maintaining that the debate for and against adhesion, was, in reality, a clash between the idea of revolution and the idea of reform. He demonstrated that the debate was between two conceptions of revolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Having defined what to a Socialist revolution meant in terms of the doctrine which still holds good today, he stressed the fact that Socialism is, by its very nature and function, revolutionary and that Socialism and revolution are two inseparable concepts. Having pointed out that revolution could no more be opposed to reforms than reforms to revolution – which is the transition from one order of things to another – he affirmed that in the eyes of traditional Socialism the revolutionary transformation of property (which is a basic condition of social revolution) could not be carried out except by the conquest of political power and (to Guesde’s formula) “by all possible means including legal ones”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">He stressed the essentially anarchist error “which consists in thinking that the conquest of public power is an end in itself when it is only a means to an end; that it is a goal when it is only an incident; that it is the play when it is only the prologue”. “In fact” he went on, “if you are not certain of achieving a social transformation by this means, the only positive result of your work is the destruction of what is known as the bourgeois government machine.” And he asked : “How has Bolshevism come to embrace an idea so opposed to that of all the parties which belong to the Second International?” His answer was: “By laying down purely Russian conditions for the methods of revolution.”</p><p>“Lenin thinks”, he went on, “that so long as the domination of the capitalist class over the working class has not been broken by violence, any effort to rally, educate and organise the working class must he unsuccessful. Hence his imperious order that power must be seized at once, as quickly as possible, since on that conquest depend not only your final aims but your initial efforts; for even the first steps in your Socialist task will only begin when you have taken power.”</p><p>At this point in his speech, Leon Blun left his examination of the twenty-one conditions to consider the point of view of historical materialism itself, which is too often presented as a blind fatalism whereas it is explanatory - a method which is valueless unless it has the effect of making the working class conscious of its historic role. “Consciousness presupposes an examination of the situation, education, organisation, whereas the Russian Revolution, having broken down the external forms of Russian capitalist society, has found itself faced by a vacuum which can be filled with no other resource than the mystique of opposition; its architects and leaders are the cadres and prophets of a party which, itself a splinter, has eliminated at one blow the rival groups whose ideas and representatives it refused to entertain.”</p><p>Such an error was doubtless inevitable in a country like Tsarist Russia which passed from one day to another from a feudal state and a kind of theocracy to the Bolshevik dictatorship without ever having known true democracy.</p><p>“I can understand that”, Leon Blum continued, “when one is faced with a proletariat like the Russian proletariat and a country like Russia, where no really effective propaganda had been carried out before the seizing of power. Then you can imagine that first and foremost the power of the bourgeois: has to be broken before that propaganda becomes possible. But is the situation the same in our Western countries?”</p><p>Coming back to the two opposing conceptions of revolution that which sees social change as the aim and the seizure of power as the means, and that which sees the aim in the conquest of power - he stressed that this was not a question of Socialist hair-splitting. “This distinction is of the first importance”, he said, “in the sense that it leads to two completely different conceptions of organisation and propaganda”.</p><p>Here is his proof.</p><p>“If you are of the opinion that the end is social transformation, if you believe that it is this transformation which is the revolution, then everything which leads up to this transformation - even within the framework of bourgeois society - becomes revolutionary work. If that is the revolution, the daily task of propaganda carried out by the militant is the revolution advancing a little day by day.</p><p>“Reforms themselves, if they tend to increase and consolidate the gains which the working class has won from capitalist society; if they increase its militant spirit, even reforms, interpreted in this way, are revolutionary. But if, on the contrary, the only object is the seizure of power as quickly as possible, then all such activity becomes useless.”</p><p>Turning to the dictatorship exercised by the Bolshevik Party over the Russian working class and to the totalitarian nature of that Party, Léon Blum then gave a definition of how a Socialist regarded the possibility or necessity of an impersonal dictatorship of the proletariat at the moment of revolutionary “break”. He recalled that it could not be other than temporary and provisional, whereas under the system where the conquest of power in the immediate aim “dictatorship” becomes almost a regular system of government and all the tasks must be carried out under it. Addressing himself directly to those members who were about to vote for membership of the Third International, that is, for the doctrine of Moscow, Leon Blum exclaimed : “This is true to the point that, for the first time in Socialist history, you think of terrorism not merely as something which is used at the twelfth hour, not as the ultimate measure of public safety, not as a matter of life and death for the Republic, but as a means of government.”</p><p>I ask your forgiveness for having written at some length of Leon Blum’s speech at the Congress which saw the split, that is to say, the weakening not of Socialist thinking but, on the contrary, of Socialist activities, take place as a result of a working-class division prepared and imposed by Moscow, This fratricidal split still makes difficult the daily task of a party such as the SFIO; since the SFIO is continually preparing for the advent of a form of social democracy such as will allow the establishment of a Socialism compatible with justice and liberty, yet is obliged to reckon with the demagogic manoeuvres and the disastrous temptations of a Communist Party, which is less anxious to defend the real interests of the French working class than blindly to follow orders from Moscow.</p><p>But the birth of a Communist party in France and Blum’s statement at Tours had the effect of making French Socialists think about questions of doctrine and tactics which, since the death of Jaurès, they had ceased to examine. The great, blind and disastrous rush towards Communism since 1920 had at least this to be said for it - that it allowed Socialists to put Socialist thought to the test by confronting it with Communism and pondering the differences. We can be certain that if Jaurès had been present at Tours he would have spoken in the sane terms as Leon Blum. By so doing he would merely have continued his work, which was always one of clarification and thorough examination. For his main preoccupation was with syntheses and cogent arguments based on the history of events and ideas.</p><p>Therefore, when one listened to Leon Blum's speech at Tours, one heard an echo of that courageous and noble mind which was always at once exact and generous. And if, here, I associate the names of these two men so closely, it is because it is not possible to examine the history of Socialist thought in France since unification without referring to one for the pro-1914 period and to the other for the later period. The latter continued the work of the former with a loyalty born in equal part of fervour and intelligence - of courage, too, physical, moral and intellectual courage, which kept alive the flame, scorned the dross and made Socialism a living thing, not a dry doctrine.</p><p>I repeat, that if any good can come from evil, the appearance of a French Communist Party allowed the Socialists to understand better what Socialism was and was not. On orders from Moscow certain people had left the “Old House” to establish a base which was to become one of the outposts of Bolshevism. And all because they maintained that Russia would build Socialism.</p><p>For the first time we had an example of a revolution “realised” and of “victorious” Socialism. We looked and we listened. We saw a revolution, but we did not see Socialism.</p><p>Meanwhile, we were urged on. “We must do the same”, was the cry, and the great demonstrations chanted: “Soviets everywhere”. We let the frenzy and the crowds pass. Far from being dazzled by what was presented to us as a victory, we were shocked to discover an imposture. No, this was not Socialism; it could not be. The revolution which we wanted, about which we sang, was not the setting up of a totalitarian, dictatorial police state which was also imperialist; which, if it had abolished capitalist property, not only had not done away with the wage-earning classes but had organised a dictatorship of the state over a proletariat more enslaved than in any other land.</p><p>It was when considering the tragic experience which was held up to it as an example that the SFIO was led to reflect on the nature and form of Socialism. It was in the speech Leon Blum made at Tours that the French Socialists rediscovered the true face of Socialism and its real ends.</p><p>All the point's dealt with by Leon Blum in this speech, denouncing the deliberate equivocation and the distortion of Socialist doctrine and action were later cleared up within the SFIO - which certainly possessed all the necessary knowledge and which the severe shock had stimulated to make an effort to define and settle these points.</p><p>* * *</p><p>In spite of its organic unity and the internal discipline without which no party can exist, the SFIO, which replaced the large number of pre-1905 Socialist organisations, has never taken on authoritarian or totalitarian forms. It is not a question of advanced thoughts forcibly unified, but of tactical discipline freely agreed between men who, since they belong to one party, know what they are doing and what they want. Free citizens meet on a common basis, to act together for the victory of a cause which would be a victory for all. If they “do not think together”, they agree on common action after long and free discussion. It is thus that a real living unity compels respect for democracy over issues, whether large or small, concerning its orientation and course. So there can be no blind obedience, no political sleep-walking, no formulae laid down once and for all; instead, there is a constant need to face up to reality while preserving vigour of thought which respects both tradition and facts.</p><p>So there must be a critical examination of those doctrines and those new forms which borrow the vocabulary of Socialism but in the end, by using false terms, deliberately create confusion in the interest of false revolutions.</p><p>***</p><p>This is why between 1922 and 1924, i.e. two years after the split at Tours had led to the creation of the French Communist Party, it was possible to witness the rise and victory of Fascism, which came to power in Italy after the march on Rome, and which doubtlessly appeared to the masses as a revolution at once “anti-capitalist” and “anti-democratic”.</p><p>It was doubly clear from two revolutions which were no mere than coups d’état that there could be no real Socialism without democracy; democracy in the Party for its day-to-day activity, democracy in the nation to allow the realisation of that social democracy which is the true end of Socialism in action and which brings with it both collective and individual liberty. That is to say that Socialism is, as it were, the highest expression of the motto of the Swiss Confederation : “One for all and all for one” - a formula which has still to be translated into reality in social and political terms.</p><p>While it pondered, on the one hand, Russian totalitarian Communism, where freedom of thought and democracy were lacking, and, on the other, totalitarian Fascism, whose leader, a former Socialist, bragged of wishing to create a national, anti-capitalist Socialism (as, later, Hitler made Nazism into a national Socialism) - while it pondered those forces, these doctrines and these regimes, the SFIO remembered the excellent advice of Jaurès on the difficulties of a democratic regime vis-à-vis tyranny. Liberty is a virtue which is at all times on the defensive. It is a delicate thing, since everyone is tempted to claim it for himself to the detriment of the liberty which must be granted to others - and does so in the name of that same liberty.</p><p>So that, as the writer Albert Camus said, just as there are various degrees of revolt, since absolute revolt is merely a concept of the mind, so it is essential to consider the conditions of freedom, i.e. its various degrees.</p><p>Thus the Communist; case, like the later cases of Fascism and Hitlerism, dramatically drew the attention of the French Socialists to the fact that Socialism, if it wishes to conserve its true spirit and human value, can only be democratic and that, in order to obtain the maximum possible justice in the new society, it must allow man, considered as an individual and a citizen, to enjoy the maximum amount of freedom. It is thus that, during the German occupation, the clandestine central organ of the Socialist Party in the occupied zone chose as its title <hi rend="underline">Socialism and Liberty</hi>.</p><p>Thus Socialism, after a period which, if not easy, was at least hopeful, since it believed the way had been cleared for victorious action, had the unpleasant task of studying the difference between the sacred word and the debased reality. Socialists could, thanks to the performance of the drunken Helot, observe the inhuman form in which certain people presented their proposals for “revolutionary progress”. Since the triumph of Bolshevism and the setting up of the totalitarian Stalinist state, French Socialists, like the rest, have thought a great deal not only about the problems of realising Socialise but also about its essential nature.</p><p>To follow the developments of this process it is essential, in the case of France over the last thirty or forty years, to return to the thought of Leon Blum who, following in the steps of Jaurès, gave life to Socialist thinking - that is, not to something dead but to a living doctrine which is in line with the evolution of things. Neither pragmatism nor empiricism, nor opportunism; his task was an unswerving examination of the realities of the day and continuous comparison between thought and those realities.</p><p>One must have no preconceived ideas and yet at the same time have a mind which is furnished with a knowledge of the past and of the difficult conditions under which mankind and society go forward towards that future of which our imagination catches a glimpse by the aid of images drawn from past and present and which, as Anatole France said, will be the dream of the sages become reality. It was in this spirit that Jaurès had offered his party the formula which is both courageous and wise : “Ain at the ideal and understand reality.”</p><p>By giving modern Socialism its scientific form Marx, without neglecting the permanent appeal to justice made by his forerunners, furnished both guiding lights and tools. The French Socialists, whom Marx had not allowed to forget what they owe to men like Babeuf, Cabet, Constantin Pecqueur, Saint Simon, Fourier, Victor Considérant, Auguste Comte and Proudhon (forerunners whom Jaurès did not fail to salute for he was always anxious to establish his relationship to them and to appeal to tradition) - the French Socialists today know better than ever that the main point is not to be first and foremost doctrinaire. Socialist doctrine - which is not a revealed religion - is at one and the same time the expression of human aspirations and a realisation of the conditions imposed on the working class by industrial development. The French Socialists, using Marx’s tools and respecting a method which is still valid, spend their time in our day carrying out “confrontations” and studies made necessary by phenomena unknown in Marx's time - phenomena which have modified certain aspects of the problem, while leaving intact a method of analysis which has proved its worth.</p><p>I use the word “confrontations” since it is the word chosen by our comrade Jules Moch for a recent and very important work of which I shall have occasion to speak later. </p><p>But let us return to the examination of <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">the</seg></hi> political and economic factors which have determined, <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">if</seg></hi> not the evolution, at least some aspects of Socialist thinking in our time.</p><p>The fall of the franc in 1924 faced all workers in France not only with the question of how to earn <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">a living</seg> </hi>but with that of a<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> general</seg></hi> state <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">of poverty which</seg></hi>, after swamping the working class, reached that considerable group of genteel paupers which in France consists of the small “rentiers”, who are on a level below the middle class, and of old people living miserably on scanty pensions. Thus, not only the proletariat, in the narrow sense of the word, but also a portion of the so-called bourgeoisie was revealed to be suffering grievously from the consequences of both inflation and deflation.</p><p>The difficulties of the Treasury, the financial crises, the fall in the value of money, the state of disequilibrium, from which some people naturally cams out much better than ethers and oven found a chance of building <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">a</seg></hi> fortune on the misery of others, made easier the task of recruiting and finding volunteers among a conscious working class, which was finding life harder and harder.</p><p>But problems of a political character were also to face the SFIO as a result of the success of the Popular Front in the 1936 elections. A hard battle had been fought by the parties of the Left, including the Communist Party, which seemed to have learned that it was no longer possible for it to remain outside the democratic community. When the Popular Front had crushed the so-called National Bloc and the Socialist Party turned out to have the strongest parliamentary representation, Leon Blum claimed power in the name of the SFIO. The Prime Minister of the day gave way all the more readily since working-class agitation was widespread and since, especially in Paris, strikes had taken the form of occupation of the factories.</p><p>Until then Leon Blum had vigorously and persistently opposed any Socialist participation in the government; this had led - as a result of measures taken in 1932 - to the splitting off of a certain number of Socialists, like Pierre Renaudel, who strongly favoured “participation”. Having set up his government on the lines of the victorious Popular Front, and having decided without hesitation to carry out forthwith the programme on which its propaganda had been based, Leon Blum explained to his party the nature of an event which was without precedent in the history of the SFIO.</p><p>***</p><p>This brought new light to bear on the fundamental differences between the seizure of power and the exercise of such power. This important distinction and the clarifying statements made at the time are an important contribution towards clear Socialist thinking in general.</p><p>The SFIO was faced for the first time with the question of the me exercise of power, and that in a striking manner. This was something quite different from Socialist participation or, rather, of the participation of a single Socialist in a bourgeois government which, before the unification of 1900, had given rise to so much emotion and discussion in the French Socialist organisations and had only been settled by the resolution on the Millerand case adopted by the Amsterdam Congress of the Socialist International.</p><p>To tell the truth Jaurès was not, properly speaking, either a “participationist” or a “ministerialist” (as was the expression) and took care not to present the Millerand case as a question of doctrine. He carefully weighed the disadvantages of the entry of <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">a</seg></hi> Socialist into the government of the day. He considered the presence of a Socialist in the councils of the government as an experience which should neither commit the Party nor modify its parliamentary tactics. The Party doctrine, in any case, was not in question. It was a case only of authorising one man to gain experience as an individual. Having defended this position along with his friends, and having on this occasion developed his views on the value of controlled reforms – “revolutionary reforms” as he was to call them later - he gave way out of respect for party discipline and Socialist law to Amsterdam resolution presented by Bebel and supported by Jules Guesde. Nevertheless, he had had the opportunity, in the course of lively discussions, to indicate the difference between a Socialist minister and a minister who was also a Socialist. In fact, although he personally defended Millerand and believed that there was an experience worth gaining without compromising the Socialist Party and Socialism, he himself was not an active participationist. It was not a “revisionist” or “bourgeois” thesis against which the Socialist International had expressed itself. The International had wanted to <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">make</seg> <seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> a general rule </seg></hi>for all its sections in face of a given situation by stressing the oppositional character of Socialism within the framework of the bourgeois state.</p><p>Since then time has marched on, and the famous “exceptional circumstance” whereby the SFIO was guided during the 1914-18 War (when Guesde himself, Sembat and Albert Thomas became ministers in the wartime cabinets), have come into play without it being possible to oppose the Amsterdam notion to tactical necessities. We are, in fact, living in a time of “exceptional circumstances”, because times themselves are no longer ordinary and also, as Léon Blum said in 1947, “because in a democracy the modern state becomes progressively more detached from capitalism, and it is possible for Socialist parties to manage it without becoming enslaved by it and, more important still, without becoming enslaved by capitalism. They take power as an instrument in the battle against capitalism, i.e. by using the authority of the state in order to create conditions which will be favourable for the coming of Socialism.”.</p><p>It is true that when making this observation Léon Blum envisaged not Socialist participation in a “bourgeois” government but the exercise of power by a government under Socialist leadership, if not by a complete Socialist government. In fact, Leon Blum always regarded such participation with considerable dislike and for long, with the support of a large majority of the SFIO, did everything to remove any temptation the Party might have in this direction. He said that he saw the inconveniences entailed by this position but could not see the possible compensatory advantages. From 1924 to 1936, in spite of many opportunities, many summons and appeals both from outside the Party and from the “participationist” group of the SFIO led by Pierre Renaudel, Leon Blum in agreement with Alexandre Bracke, and supported by the majority of the Party, kept the Party out of the government. So following his advice the Party refused to participate in the government (in 1924, 1925, 1926 and 1932). It was not until 1936 that, believing circumstances to be ripe and the need for parliamentary action sufficiently decisive, Leon Blum would not only accept participation but claim the leadership of the government in the name of the party which had obtained the largest number of seats.</p><p>Thus the hour of what Leon Blum had for long called “the exercise of power”, as opposed to the “conquest” of power, arrived. It was on this occasion that Bracke, in his joy, uttered the famous words : “At last, the difficulties begin.”</p><p>***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As far back as 1920 at Tours, when the question of joining the Third International came up, Leon Blum had expressed a theory which both defined and developed Socialist thinking on the revolutionary problem of power. He was often to return to this idea to which he had always attached extreme importance, since he feared the effect on Socialists of the dangerous illusions which arise not only from the abuse of words but from their heedless use. As he explained again : “The conquest of power is the complete capture of political power, a possible prelude to and an essential condition of the transformation of property relations, i.e. of the revolution. The idea of the conquest of power is thus above all a revolutionary idea. Against this ‘conquest’ of power must be set the ‘exercise’ of power in a capitalist regime. It has no revolutionary character. It is only the consequence of parliamentary action itself which Socialists may be obliged to accept, to demand, to submit to by virtue of the fact that they carry on parliamentary activities.”</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">There is no subtlety here, merely a statement of fact and a restatement of doctrine.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">We know how, in 1936, at the instance of the Blum Government, the electoral programme of the Popular Front was fully realised and how the Government achieved improvements, not only material but moral, in working-class conditions and even in the constitution. But the threat of Hitlerism, which had become increasingly acute in the international field, and the disastrous Munich Pact, heralding a world war, posed other problems and taught other lessons. Social achievements and economic reforms, an improved organisation of production and a more equitable distribution of the national income <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Spaziatura_4_pt">–</hi>all these had to take second place in a period when danger threatened from abroad. The most important question was that of assuring peace while resisting the blackmail of war. It was thus essential to be ready for war. And any action to prevent war was the same time national and international, but the League of Nations no longer existed. It had died from lack of confidence in itself. It had died because it had abandoned Albania and Ethiopia to the belligerent imperialism of Fascist Italy, which scoffed at feeble sanctions; it had died of its own timidity and had even gone to the length of abdication. Aggression, despite the League, proved a paying proposition; the consequences of this failure were Hitler, the trouble over the Sudeten Germans the attack on Poland and the Second World War.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The subjection and finally the occupation of Frauen by Hitler's armies, the collaboration of a section of the French bourgeoisie, was a new and terrible lesson for the SFIO. It realised that there was 1) a certain degree of bourgeois complicity with German militarism; 2) a feeling of solidarity, which was both necessary and natural , with various "degrees" of democracy which <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_10.5_pt" xml:space="preserve">extended </hi>from the idea - or the form - to true democracy itself.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This solidarity between Socialism and democracy, or rather the necessity of democracy for the establishment of true Socialism, an idea which had been momentarily obscured, constituted one of the themes which had always been developed by French Socialism, especially by Jaurès, and continued by Blum. I do not wish to look back to speeches of the former for the texts in which he laid down his in this intimate and indispensable union. 1 shall cite only the words of Leon Blum:</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"Political democracy was the beginning of and remains the condition for the emancipation of the workers,<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_14_pt;Grassetto;Proporzioni_75%" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>and it must be noted that to the extent to which they developed class consciousness it has been increasingly subject to pressure from social democracy and consequently from Socialism, which is its direct expression." Again: "There is nobody in the proletarian world now who claims that capitalist evolution or the evolution of the proletarian parties are independent of the political forms of the society in which we act. We all know now<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_14_pt;Grassetto;Proporzioni_75%" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>that there is <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">an </seg></hi>insoluble link between Socialism and democracy, that without Socialism democracy is imperfect, but that without democracy Socialism is powerless."</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">If today, when faced by the attempts of so-called Socialist construction which, by <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt">a</hi> solemn fraud, have stolen from tradition and history the name of "Communism", one can oppose democratic Socialism to the doctrines, policies and tactics of totalitarianism, it is, I think I may claim, to French Socialist thought that the world owes this - to that thought common to the Party but expressed most forcibly by Jaurès and Leon Blum. Going beyond mere critical doctrine, Jaurès and Blum always made a point of studying that "further step" of which Nietzsche speaks in order to assert that over and above man's lot considered socially and economically, it was essential not to forget that the supreme aim was the flowering of man himself.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It was in 1945 at the first post-war Congress of the SFIO when he put forward the new party statute that Leon Blum explained the supreme aim of Socialism to the delegates of the federations : "Social transformation in itself is not the final aim. It is the means. It is the essential condition of the transformation of man's lot. I mean that the aim of revolution is not only to free man from economic and social exploitation as from all other secondary forms of slavery which arise from such exploitation; but it is also essential to assure him, in a collective society, of the full exercise of his fundamental rights and the full exercise of his personal inclinations. I believe that the aim of revolution is to establish harmony between the individual as a social unit and the social whole of the collective society of the future."</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This idea is a heritage, not only from the century of the French "encyclopaedists", but from that revolution of which Jaurès wrote the Socialist history, finding there ideas which, through our "Utopian Socialists", led to the admirable work of Marx, of which only the semi-literate can believe that it was nothing but cold science. After all, when Marx defines capitalist "profit", he does not confine himself just to registering the fact, but judges it by condemning it as unpaid labour - that is to say - "stolen" labour. This idea of justice which may be said to be the French contribution to Marxism - itself more concerned with the study of facts and the conclusions to be drawn from them than with mere moral speculation - passed into the tradition of British Socialism and has increasingly impressed its stamp on international democratic Socialism. It is thus that Leon Blum, having studied the experiences of the British Labour Party, could write in Populaire of 5 March, 1950: "The evolution of the British society under the direction of a Labour government has re-affirmed a truth which the Socialists, described as reformists, formulated fifty years ago and to which all international Socialism rallied on the eve of the First World War. That truth is that to a certain degree it is possible to improve in terns of justice, equality and freedom not only the condition of the workers but also the lot of mankind before the legal system of capitalist ownership is due for a revolutionary transformation."</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Thus the events of 1940, by focusing the attention of the French Socialists on national and international solidarity, made them feel - painfully yet with pride - the bond between Socialism, of which free citizens who care for social justice can be proud, and democracy, which is the indispensable condition of the free development of Socialism without fetters.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But what has been called - and what will always remain in history as - the French Resistance Movement has taught French Socialism another lesson.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It is common knowledge how, having lost all contact at the start owing not only to the dispersal of groups and families, but to the existence of a demarcation line cutting France in two, isolated but determined men acting in their own interest and in the name of those who, wherever they might be, represented the stifled voice of Franco, undertook a task which was both obscure and glorious, difficult and ennobling. They ended up by forming groups here and there until the whole of France was covered by a clandestine network formed by fighters who became the men of the secret army, allies of those who were to disembark one day on the shores of France.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The Resistance was the conscience of a France which everything conspired to mislead. Their task was a triple one. They had to gather the fragments of the broken sword, to reforge it, and meanwhile to fight without uniforms and with what weapons they had against an enemy which had occupied and conquered a country betrayed both by military disaster and the spirit of despair. It was essential, too, to fight against the false Vichy Government which, by declaring itself legal and legitimate, began to take on monarchist airs and had at its head a man who traded on the legend surrounding his name - a government whose members played the part of wiseacres and claimed to give lessons in virtue to Frenchmen. Finally, it was essential to give back to the French not so much confidence in a miraculous destiny as courage to look events in the face, to weigh their chances and, above all, to realise the shame into which they might be plunged and not only by German propaganda - which was quite natural - but by the terrible advice of men who, even before the disaster, had already dreamed of a France given over to Hitler's dreams.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Certain Socialists, certain terrified parliamentarians, and some representatives of other political parties - both of the Right and of the Left - had shown themselves for what they were. Faced by the misfortunes of their country only eighty representatives of the people could be found who opposed the giving of lull powers to Pétain and to say "no" to what was put forward as a national revolution. No party could claim to have remained untarnished in this shameful hour.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This all had to be made good ; and in the great wilderness of the nation was enclosed the wilderness of the Republic. Yes, everything had to be begun again and here and there, just as they had for resistance against the enemy, Socialists fastened on renewing the broken links of social democracy. It was essential at any price to hold fast. To keep France in the fight and safeguard its raison d’être, its hopes, its moral and political force for the morrow, to keep the Party going by purging it. It was thus after long patient and courageous individual action that that the best men came together to form what was called the “Socialist Action Committee” in the two zones of occupation. One day these men - patriotic resisters who <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Times_New_Roman;13_pt;Grassetto"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve">were </seg></hi>always anxious not to draw a line between their status as combatants and their civil conscience - were able to publish the Party paper clandestinely, in miniature form like all other clandestine publications. In it there were no partisan politics. Everything was subordinated to the fight against the enemy and his French supporters. Nevertheless, by saving the honour of France along with other members of the Resistance, the Socialists claimed to have saved the honour of the Party for its future tasks. For those who had betrayed France had at one and the same time thrown overboard both democracy and the Republic. The fight was straightforward, and that explains why in nearly all articles published by the clandestine press - ’’Liberation" , "Franc-Tirour" , "Resistance” , "Combat" , "Defense de la France", "Valmy" - there was to be found a patriotic as well as a Socialist note.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Thus the Resistance united in its various movements, which were themselves linked by a National Council, all those who fought against the invader, against acceptance of the invader, against Hitlerism and totalitarianism; who fought for democratic Socialism which, with all its tradition and its passion for justice and freedom, opposed all the caricatures the Fascists dared to set up against social democracy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">From this arose a kind of community of action and feeling which, at the liberation, led to an obligation to exercise power together. It is impossible to compare the Chamber of the Popular Front of 1936 after the great electoral victory either to the Provisional Consultative Assembly or to the first National Assembly elected as an expression of the Resistance. There were then no losers except the collaborators. Nevertheless, the enormous programme drawn up by the National Council of the Resistance which was, in fact, less a programme for a government than a general statute of the Resistance, was unable to find, either within the Government or within the Assembly, that driving force, that coherent majority which allowed such important and rapid achievements in 1936. It is true that this Assembly met amidst the terrible ruins of the nation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Of course, it would all be rebuilt, but divergences of interest and the clash of social forces arose more rapidly than the houses, bridges, railways and factories. The result was that, soon, the links forged in the battle against a common enemy disintegrated and the old antagonisms and the old misunderstandings returned.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Nevertheless, before returning to the old custom whereby a French Left-wing majority, which is full of zeal at the beginning of a new legislature, deteriorates and almost inevitably becomes rotten, giving way after less than four years (without the people concerned being at all changed) to a reactionary or almost reactionary majority – before reverting to such sad tendencies, those who were deputies of the Resistance and who soon found themselves side by side with men who were anything but, did much good work, and the Socialists gave an example of daring and loyalty. Thus, the all-Socialist ministry, over which Leon Blum presided after the victory, will remain in the history of Socialism and democracy an event of note. The old question of participation - I mean the question which was supposed to have been settled by the Amsterdam resolution - no longer arose.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">As I have pointed out above, Leon Blum had put the problem perfectly in context not only for the SFIO but for the whole Socialist movement in countries where there is a parliamentary democracy. Thus the question of Socialist participation in a government proved more and more to be a question of tactics where advantages and disadvantages were weighed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">*[The following must be noted - Socialist participation in office or the exercise of power on their part must not have the effect of weakening or lulling to sleep their demand for Socialism. This explains the advice given by Leon Blum to the Party when he became Prime Minister. : "Stay as you are as I shall stay as I am." The Socialist Party and the former Socialist ministers must not - outside the government - let themselves be tempted to transform a Socialist frame of mind into a governmental frame of mind because of contingent circumstances. There is such a thing as governmental tactics but there is also, and that permanently, the great aim of Socialism, the Socialist calling.]</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The subject of this paper is not to be any sort of French "revisionism". Historically, among the parties belonging to the Socialist International, that word has had a certain suggestion of aggressive heterodoxy. But the question for a Socialist is not whether he is orthodox or heterodox. Socialist doctrine, which is born of a critical examination of economic and social facts, is no longer a sort of blind submission to things nor does it consist in a hard and fast position of which, because it came into being at a certain point in an evolutionary process, theory can make nothing. Socialist doctrine examines the past not only to understand the present better, but to try to understand the meaning of history, which is the work of the living who salute the contribution of their predecessors but continue to move with the times, and a combination of critical examination (i.e. the passing of judgments) and of propositions based on the observation of certain tendencies and themselves judgments, sometimes daring ones. Its main achievements are, firstly, the Marxist method and dialectic founded on the recognised principle of historical materialism, understood in the wide sense of the word and, secondly, the considerable contribution of Marxism towards explaining an industrial and social system (the so-called capitalist one) which is founded, on the one hand, on that profit or surplus value – incidentally, the latter is not a Marxist discovery for Marx borrowed it from Ricardo – and on the other, on the existence of a dispossessed proletariat, tragical and historical proof of the class struggle. So such remains; to it must be added all that goes with great prophetic visions, which one would be wrong to consider defined once and for all, for they are founded on the examination of actual facts – which are, however, partly out of date – and on the probable course of their evolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The important thing is therefore constant examination. The evolution of things does not stop when a doctrine has been laid down and no Socialist can today dispute that "scientific" Socialist, which in its day replaced the old Utopias, must now apply to the contemporary scene the same methods of scientific observation which allowed Marx to analyse, understand and so mark out the road to revolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">When dealing with the application of the doctrine of Marx and Engels to the evolution of modern society, one must always come back to Jaurès for the period up to 1914 and, after his death, to Léon Blum whose penetrating, universal intelligence was able to combine profound legal knowledge with a vast and penetrating observation of the economic and social phenomena of our time.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But he was not only zealous in his examination of present-day realities; he studied in Marxism a form of Socialist thought which, to say the least, is often distorted by people who have a scanty knowledge of Marx although they quote him with fervour.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It was Leon Blum who drew the attention of the SFIO to the fact that, according to Marx himself, the destruction of capitalism did not imply the destruction of all forms of property. It was possible - he pointed out - to destroy capitalist property without destroying capitalism itself. The example of Soviet Russia, which claimed to have carried out a Socialist revolution, in his view gave food for thought. It was undeniable, he said, that in the USSR the system of capitalist property had been completely destroyed. But there was still a class of wage-earners ; the material conditions of the proletariat were still miserable and the workers were denied the elementary liberties. The social revolution, that is to say Socialism, was something entirely different from the destruction of capitalist property. Then he went on :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"A society where capitalist property has been abolished but where the wage-earning class still exists, where the task of running society is wholly in the hands of a privileged oligarchy in whose selection the mass of the workers has no say - an oligarchy which, in order to maintain its rule by artificial means, is led to suspend indefinitely the exercise of all personal and civic liberties: such a society is not a true and exact version of the Socialist state."</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Blum pointed out, on the other hand, that certain developments had taken place in capitalist society since Marx had made his analysis. The system under which ownership had been the privilege of a certain number of individuals had been replaced by one under which ownership was exercised by groups or associated groups. He therefore urged that the following important fact should not be overlooked - that there is nowadays a form of capitalist ownership which is in the nature of "collective" ownership but which enjoys, as before, the advantages of surplus value.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But his Marxist analysis applied to modern situations and changing forms of capitalism led Leon Blum to extend his examination to other subjects. Thus at the first Congress of the SFIO after the liberation he presented the new Party programme which he considered should not so much revise the former as give it new life by means of a more exact interpretation of doctrine, of terms and facts.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It was at Leon Blum's suggestion that the 1945 Congress decided to replace the expression "class struggle" by "class action" in the Party's declaration. Certain members at the time were alarmed by this, thinking that it was some sort of retreat from the revolutionary character of the Party. But Leon Blum had previously had occasion to say that the expression "party of the class struggle" seemed to him a bad translation of what Marx had written and a bad interpretation of his thought.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">To make his point of view clearer, Leon Blum felt impelled to publish his thoughts on the subject in the "Revue socialiste" of July 1946 under the title of "Notes on Doctrine".</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">He points out, first of all, that in Marx and in the "Communist Manifesto" in particular the term "class struggle" stands for different notions, which he analyses as follows :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">1.The class struggle is a phenomenon which is decisive for the interpretation of history; it is the complement, or rather the key to historical materialism. However, the theory of class struggle adds something which is not necessarily included in the theory of historical materialism - namely, the idea that according to the nature of the means of production and the way in which they are used, humanity is always divided into two varying but homogeneous groups. Roughly speaking, they are the exploiters and the exploited. Those are what are known as "classes" and history is composed of their inevitable struggle as the one tries to take the place of the other. This is the class struggle in the historical sense of the word.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">2.The historical idea of the class struggle, which is out of date as an epistemological instrument, becomes a means of foreseeing the future. In this case his direct analysis of the capitalist method of production - which, Blum stresses, has no necessary connection with historical materialism or the class struggle - led Marx to the conclusion that there could be an end to a struggle which seemed to result in the recurring replacement of an exploiting class by an exploited one, which in its turn becomes the exploiter, The history of the class struggle will not permit any further exploitation of one class by another. That will be the end of class antagonism. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Leon Blum points out that, in order to arrive at this denouement, Marx had to transform the "historical” idea of the class struggle into an economic concept based on the growing antagonism of the classes. This is what he calls not the fatalism but the revolutionary optimism of Karl Marx. So it is the growing antagonism of the classes and not the class struggle in the primary sense of the word which leads, according to Marx, to the coming of a classless society.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Passing then to questions of tactics after an examination of historical and economic relationships, Leon Blum recalls the following teaching of Marx: that for the final expropriation of capitalism, the organised working class can count only upon itself. The revolution - although it is a logical necessity of history - cannot take place except by an act of human volition. According to Marx, this act is the class action of the proletariat which has organised itself into <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_-2_pt"><seg rend="italic">a</seg></hi> working-class party in order to conquer political power.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">At this point Leon Blum points out that all the tactical difficulties which continually arise for a Socialist party in the pre-revolutionary period spring from the fact that class action is directed towards a political objective and is carried out within the framework of capitalist society. Hence the false position of the Socialist parties.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Leon Blum notes, however, that they could not escape from this difficulty except by abandoning the political forms of class action in the same way as did the revolutionary syndicalists on the lines of the French Trades Union Congress and the Anarchists, who were excluded from the Socialist International at its London Congress.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Here is his conclusion :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"Thus in the complex group of ideas which current usage gathers together under the term 'class struggle', I can distinguish three related, closely-knit ideas which naturally interpenetrate each other, reflect each other, but are distinct and autonomous in the sense that the accuracy or inaccuracy of the one does not no necessarily imply the accuracy or inaccuracy of the other two. They are :</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"Class struggle in the strict sense of the word - a retrospective law whereby history is explained.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">“Growing class antagonism - the law of the development cl' capitalist society which is itself hastening towards revolutionary destruction.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"Class action - a tactical law which is therefore part of the make-up of the proletarian parties. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"When we say ‘a Socialist party is necessarily a class party' or 'let us be careful that our party stops being a class party', etc., etc., to which of these three ideas are we referring ?</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"To the first ? Certainly not. You cannot base a party on a retrospective law for the interpretation of history.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"To the second ? Perhaps. That is not impossible. The idea of 'growing class antagonism' is not by nature retrospective. It contains an analysis of the present and a forecast of the future. But for my part, I think - and it seems to me to be difficult to contest this that, after a century's experience, the idea of continuous growing class antagonism is one of the points of least resistance in the whole Marxist structure.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"The continuous growth of class antagonism implies continuity in the growth of capitalist concentration, it implies the continual proletarisation of the middle classes, the pauperisation of the snail property-owners<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Grassetto" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>and peasants - and Marx's forecast has not been verified on any of these points. The process of capitalist decomposition is more complex than that and less regular.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"On the other hand, it is impossible not to reckon, when dealing with the political tactics of the Socialist parties, with the compensatory effect of an inverse phenomenon. By that I mean the cases of class solidarity which give rise - with more or less lasting effect - to internal crises in the various States, an illusory solidarity when it is a question of cyclical crises of the economy, but real solidarity when it is a question of crises which are really national in character and such as to endanger the existence, the independence or the liberty of the country. My doubts on this score are of long standing. I expressed them at the Lyon Congress twenty years ago and reflection has only confirmed them.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"To the third ? Certainly.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"By defining a Socialist party as a class party one means, in fact, that that party carries out class action. That means that its aim is the conquest of political power in the name of and by means of the organised working class which it represents; that the conquest of power for it is a means and a condition of the revolutionary transformation of the system of ownership ; that, whatever changing and complex permutations work within the framework of capitalist society may oblige it to accent (parliamentary coalitions, sharing of power, assumption of power, etc.), whatever the competition with other parties, its sympathy for them and their common aims which may at certain points facilitate its work, it expects final victory only from its own action or rather from the specific action of the organised working class. ‘The emancipation of the workers will be the work of the work of the workers themselves,’ </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">"That is the only possible meaning of the 1905 Statute. Both the context and the historical circumstances prove it. When they speak of class struggle, what they really mean is class action. And by substituting the words 'class action' for the words ’class struggle’ in the Declaration preceding the new statute, that is what I meant too."</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">From this last example of thinking by Blum, who was following in the steps of Jaurès, one can form an idea of the effort at clarification made by the SFIO. The man who, in this way, by his articles and speeches at the Congress, showed how necessary it was not to regard historical texts as an immutable law when they are, from certain points of view, merely an attempt at interpretation, showed himself to be both intelligent and faithful to Socialist principles.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Socialist thought cannot be either dry or uninspiring, for it is at once action and living thought. Being based <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Times_New_Roman;Spaziatura_1_pt" xml:space="preserve">on </hi>a rigorous examination of <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Times_New_Roman;Spaziatura_1_pt" xml:space="preserve">social and economical facts, </hi>it cannot suspend that examination <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Times_New_Roman;Spaziatura_1_pt" xml:space="preserve">on </hi>the pretext that, since laws have been derived from past experience and <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Times_New_Roman;Spaziatura_1_pt" xml:space="preserve">since </hi>the direction in which evolution is moving has been discovered, there is nothing more to be said and nothing more to be done except push on along a historical course whose secret has been discovered. B</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">But Socialism is not more mechanical. than history. It is as alive as the latter, for it is based on it and because, if history weighs upon mankind, it is still men who make it. That is why it is indispensable to put everything in doubt and to answer the questions incessantly posed by a society that has not finished evolving. Hence the necessity for "confrontations” of contemporary facts with certain aspects, if not of the doctrine, at least of the forecasts it was possible to make ninety years ago.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p>"Confrontations" is the title which Jules Moch gave to <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_13_pt;Grassetto"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve">an </seg></hi>important work in which he studies certain new forms of capitalist society, certain aspects of which Marx could not foresee; the latter, which arise during the continuous process of decay of capitalism (whose disappearance had been forecast by the author of "The Capital") are doubtless shifts and tricks and ways <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Spaziatura_2_pt" xml:space="preserve">out, </hi>but they must nevertheless be looked at because the Socialists can see "intermediary stages" coming in to being before their eyes - situations which it seemed could not exist in the days when the situation was clear-cut.</p><p>Little caring whether by writing his most important study he was going to show himself to be orthodox <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">or</seg> </hi>heterodox, Jules Moch, while studying the economic and social phenomena at the time, was particularly not to betray the Marxist method and to consider facts carefully. It was by applying the Marxist method to the study of contemporary economic phenomena that the Socialist, Jules Moch, attempted to make a useful contribution to the history of Socialist ideology, <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">which</seg> </hi>must never be diverted from realities under the pretext that it has nothing further to teach the custodians of the true doctrine.</p><p>Jules Moch's book is the result of the meditations of a Socialist and cannot be considered the expression of the official thought of a party which has not yet had the opportunity of discussing thoughts which link up <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">in</seg> </hi>an unusual manner with those of <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">Léo</seg></hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi> Blum.</p><p>I wish here to give an outline of this study, which refuses to put forward a new brand of Socialism but which is an attempt to put in a correct light certain things which are often wrongly considered to be the fundamentals of our doctrine.</p><p>I should mention that, when he spoke of his project to Leon Blum in 1950, Jules Moch was strongly encouraged by the latter to carry out the work and received the advice to read "The Great Hope of the 20th Century" and "Machinery and Welfare" by Fourastie. "Read Fourastie", Blum told him, "and you will come to the same conclusions as he does on more than one point - he will start <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">from </seg></hi>observation and you from doctrine."</p><p>Jules Moch's great work is, in short, a confrontation in the year 1952 of the "proved and glorious doctrine” with a humble but strict observation of contemporary reality.</p><p>"Confrontations" is in four parts .</p><p>The first - "Doctrines" - adapts to the 20th century the conclusions which Marx deduced from his pitiless analysis of nineteenth century civilisation. Here is how Moch sums up his conclusions : "The differences are profound. Accelerated technical progress, bringing in its train an immense increase in productivity, has put an economic force at the disposal of the small enterprises and multiplied production, which is now widely distributed and consumed by increasing layers of society; it has allowed men to set aside increasing amounts of money for the purchase of other things than food and thus created needs more and more remote from the industrialised countries. How could the capitalist market fail to be profoundly transformed by such a development?"</p><p>Hence the reappearance or the consolidation of a human "fringe" intermediary between capitalism and the wage-earners, whose total disappearance Marx had prophesied. Hence access to the ownership of certain means of production has become possible for a certain category of workers who, for lack of another word, can be called “artisans” whose reappearance had already been noted by Vanderveld in his book “Collectivism and Industrial Evolution”.</p><p>This category of workers, owners of small-scale enterprises or free workers, have not the same class reaction as the mass of workers concentrated in the factories. It may even be said of this fringe that it lives in the shelter of capitalism whose disappearance would present it with a difficult problem of adaptation.</p><p>At the same time as capital becomes less valuable in comparison with wages and incomes, property ownership changes; profit and power are no longer identical with its juridical forms. The crises of capitalism no longer present the same characteristics of inevitability as before and may come to mean over-equipment of industry, which creates new dangers different from those which arose from the old sources. Meanwhile, the internal contradictions of the regime develop and increase. </p><p>The differences of technical development in the modern national States create antagonisms between working classes; for the working classes of the <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">most</seg> </hi>industrialised countries try to defend the material advantages they have won against the working class <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Grassetto"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve">of </seg></hi>more primitive societies.</p><p>Hence there comes the disappearance, not be say the collapse, of that international class solidarity which, in Marxist thought, ought to permit in industrially developed countries, quite apart from any consideration of the national situation, victorious class action, the only instrument capable of transforming capital<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Grassetto"><seg rend="normalweight">i</seg></hi>st society into a collectivist or communist society - "<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Grassetto"><seg rend="normalweight">co</seg></hi>mmunist" being understood in the historical sense of the word sanctioned by Marx and not in the <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_10.5_pt" xml:space="preserve">sense </hi>which has been given to it by the Soviet imposture.</p><p>Thus, in whatever direction we look, the theses taught by the nineteenth-century masters no longer correspond exactly to the situation created by modern science. Their analytical method remains valid. But in certain fields it leads to different <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt" xml:space="preserve">conclusions. </hi>To be more exact, it reveals that yesterday's theories have the value of a first approximation which the advances made since then force us to make <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo"><seg rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">more </seg></hi>accurate and more complete, rather in the way that, in physics, Einstein had carried on the work of Newton without disowning him.</p><p>The second part of the study - “Deviations" - defines old-fashioned Communism and modern Stalinism - which it is wrong to confuse - and examines the methods which allowed Stalin to subjugate a third of humanity and dominate a quarter of the earth's surface. Jules Moch points out that, if the French had not such short memories politically, they would remember that, from 1944 to 1948, the French followers of Stalin tried to <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">win power by using most of the methods which brought them success in Eastern and Central Europe.</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">In the third part - "Experiments" - Jules Moch compares the attempts at breaking away from the capitalist system carried out in various countries: in the parliamentary democracies such as France and Britain; in the United States and Israel; in Russia and her satellites in Europe and Asia and in her occupation zones in Germany and Austria. The author attempts to define the intermediary regime - which is sui generis - represented by fully developed nationalisation, which is not State capitalism and yet is not Socialism or anything like it.</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">The fourth and last part - "Hopes" - deals with the conditions which must precede any attempt to set up Socialism. At the height of its technical development the capitalist regime disintegrates into insurmountable moral and material contradictions. What human organisation will take its place ? A choice must be made between the dictatorship which Bolshevism imposes on the proletariat and which has lasted for a third of a century without establishing Socialism, and evolution towards a regime where the individual can develop fully in economic freedom and political democracy. How can the present intermediary forms - nationalisation experiments, cooperative systems or solutions which are neither one nor the other - develop towards Socialism without constraint ? That is the theme of Jules Moch in the last pages of his remarkable contribution -towards the knowledge of Socialist ideas as measured against present-day realities.</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">***</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">At this point, however, it is necessary to stop relating the intellectual efforts made within the SFIO since Jaurès' time to come to grips with realities - not in order to set them aside out of respect for Socialist doctrine, but to examine them rigorously in accordance with Socialist method. This effort is the same as Jaurès himself suggested should be made by every Socialist conscience and which he summed up in the motto : "Seek the ideal and understand reality."</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">The ideal is no longer the particular domain of the "revolutionaries" any more than reality is the property of the reformists. Leon Blum often recalled that, since Socialism is, in essence, revolutionary, Socialists cannot be anything else than revolutionaries. But revolutions are not made in the clouds, nor do they draw their energy from wild imaginings or from dry-as-dust doctrines which have no contact with life.</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">The power of Socialism lies in the fact that it is at one and the same time an explanation and a goal, a science, a political theory and a moral law.</hi></p><p><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">***</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The picture of <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">th</seg></hi>e development of Socialist ideas <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">in</seg></hi> France would be incomplete if I did not give some ideas of the evolution of ideas on the problems of peace.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">In this connection it may be said that after two world wars there is no purely French attitude to the <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_13_pt;Spaziatura_0_pt" xml:space="preserve">subject. </hi>The position taken up by the SFIO in 1952 is the same a<hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_Grassetto"><seg rend="normalweight">s</seg></hi> that of all Parties affiliated to the <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_13_pt;Spaziatura_0_pt" xml:space="preserve">Socialist </hi>International. However, it is tempting to survey the road which the SFIO has followed from the idea of the general strike in the event of war to the idea of collective security.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Let us not forget, however, the idea which Jaurès had worked out, even when he supported the idea of the general strike in the event of the situation becoming desperate. I refer to the definition which he gave of an "aggressor" - a definition which was linked to the setting up of compulsory arbitration. The aggressor country was one which, whatever the reasons produced to justify its warlike attitude, refused to submit the conflict to international arbitration. A refusal was an act of self-accusation. From that point it was the aggressor who imperilled international peace and it was the international comity of nations which had to prevent him from harming the rest of the world.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This was, indeed, the principle of collective security. Here we have also the idea of a supreme tribunal and an international force at the service of organised peace.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">After the failure of the League of Nations, we witnessed the birth of the United Nations Organisation which, at the present time, is hampered by difficulties and too often paralysed not only by the right of veto but by the fact that it is made in the image of the divided world of the cold war.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">However, we know - and because we are Socialists we feel it more deeply than others - that the United Nations Organisation, whatever its defects and its present difficulties given the absence of a Socialist International of all the nations, is both a fact to be welcomed and a source of great hope.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Some people say that UNO is, in fact, powerless, whilst others seem disposed to mock at its work. But let us suppose for a moment that it ceased to be. I leave you to imagine the dramatic vacuum which would replace UNO and its short-comings - short-comings which are merely due to the difficulties in which it is placed by those powers who are afraid of having to submit to an international body because (so they say) it lacks respect for the sovereignty of individual nations. But the raison d 'être of the United Nations is precisely to oppose abuses of sovereign power and attempts to justify the use of force while making a mockery of the rule of law.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">However, the SFIO which is aware that peace, like democracy, is necessary for Socialism does not think of <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">collective security as the only means to peace. Leon Blum always took care to link three ideas - simultaneous, controlled disarmament, international arbitration and collective security guaranteed by an international armed force. World peace can be guaranteed by setting to work this inseparable group of ideas.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">This brings us back to the idea of true democracy, which extends from the individual to his town, from the town to the nation, from nations to continents and from continents to the whole world; in this connection one should read and re-read what Leon Blum wrote on the subject in prison. There as a witness of a disaster without precedent in the history of France, as a prisoner in his own country condemned without proper trial by a government which dared to call itself French when it had not only capitulated to but was collaborating with the enemy and had delivered him into their hands, Leon Blum, by examining the errors, the illusions and the sufferings of his generation, attempted to arrive at a lesson for coming generations.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">In the course of many years entirely dedicated to meditation and reflection, he asked himself if, during the years before the war, Socialists had fully understood their mission and fulfilled their duty.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">"Did we", he wrote, "sufficiently understand the meaning of the effort whereby Jaurès had transformed the deductions of Marx? Marx had provided the working class with the most invigorating and powerful of aids - namely, the conviction that historical destiny was on their side. But what is destined is not necessarily just, does not necessarily satisfy critical reason or the moral conscience. Jaurès then pointed out that the social revolution is not only the inevitable consequence of economic development, but that it would fulfil at the same time an eternal demand of man's reason and conscience.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">"It is through Socialism that the democratic heroism of the French Revolution, whose struggles have filled Europe and the world for a whole century, could be brought to the pinnacle of victory. The materialist conception of history is also impregnated with all forms of human and republican idealism."</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">Leon Blum went on with his self-interrogation. If he recognised that the usual argument that "it is useless changing social institutions without changing the individual's mentality" is too easy a way of putting off the necessary changes, he nevertheless asked himself:</hi><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)_+_Times_New_Roman;Grassetto;Corsivo;Spaziatura_1_pt" xml:space="preserve"> </hi><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">"Have we done as much as we could to make man bettor as an individual, at the same time as we were trying to change society? Have we faced the two tasks squarely, as we should have done, made the one penetrate the other, made the one depend on the other?".</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)_+_11.5_pt;Grassetto;Proporzioni_75%"><seg rend="normalweight" xml:space="preserve">But </seg></hi><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">true democracy and that fully-developed human being which should be the masterpiece of Socialism harmoniously combining justice and liberty, are only possible if the world succeeds in ridding itself of the scourge of war and of the great fear which besets it. Just as democracy is the environment necessary for Socialism, so peace is the environment necessary for democracy.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">"Democracy", wrote Leon Blum, "implies social democracy. Social democracy implies internationalism in a highest sense of the word. So we must work towards that human order which can only be based on an international structure. If that solid organisation is lacking we must look for another way of removing permanently the reality or even the threat of war."</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">Examining the reasons which reduced the League of Nations to impotence and finally to failure, Leon Blum began to imagine what kind of international body would be set up as a sovereign authority, limiting individual sovereignties and capable of imposing its judgments on refractory nations - if necessary by an armed force at the service of international law. He stated that "instead of being run by conferences, where each delegate la subject to the interests and instructions of the State which he represents, this super-state should possess its own institutions and its own directorate", for, he emphasised, "a true international community is quite different from a court of arbitration or a diplomatic meeting".</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">Leon Blum, who never doubted victory, foresaw in the distant future the foundations of the new world arise as follows: "Within the nation political democracy is justified and consolidated by social democracy while the national democracies support an international order, which crowns them and maintains their equilibrium."</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">After the Liberation, Leon Blum was able to be present at the birth of UNO ; up to his death his one aim was to support and give strength to this institution which - in spite of the difficulties which arose from the splitting into two blocs of the wartime alliance - seemed to him still to be the great hope of the nations.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)">He was also able to see collective security being organised - still on too narrow a basis but nevertheless effective and capable of countering threats of force with real strength. He was able to hail the first labours and the first achievements of the European Community which must be tomorrow's firm guarantee against the renewal of an international conflict whose terrible consequences no one can measure.</hi></p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)"><hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(4)" xml:space="preserve">We know the place which has been taken in the work of building Europe by the French Socialists - first and foremost by the General Secretary of the SFIO, Guy Mollet, together with Gerard Jaquet, Andre Philip, Jean le Bail and Marceau Pivert. In the same way, Leon Blum could </hi>hail in the setting-up of the Franco-German Coal and Steel Pool the first practical attempt - although still too limited a one - at establishing a model worthy the old dream of a truly supra-national authority, independent of governments, would be realised.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">However, in this great question of the defines and organisation of peace, Leon Blum - in agreement with his Party - did not stop short at collective security based on national armaments. From 1931 on he pointed out that the military conception of security, lust as it may lead one to the idea of the inevitability of war, may imply the equally terrible idea of a preventive war.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">If, however, the setting-up of compulsory arbitration is a method of prevention which must never cease to be foreseen and prepared for, it must - if it is to be effective - be universal in the sense that all states submit to it, general in the sense that no category of dispute must be exempt from it. Moreover, the obligation of having recourse to it must be guaranteed. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This guarantee Leon Blum saw in general, simultaneous and controlled disarmament, the supreme authority or the supreme court having at its disposal the arms - the atomic power - necessary to threaten or, <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_13_pt;Grassetto;Proporzioni_75%" xml:space="preserve">if </hi>necessary, to punish.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Thus, of the three concepts - disarmament, arbitration and security - Leon Blum and the SFIO put disarmament first without, however, detaching it from the others.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">We know the forms the question of disarmament totes today and how, faced by certain Soviet proposals, the democracies which adhere to the Atlantic Pact are always obliged to clarify the thought which lies hidden behind mere propaganda.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">This is doubtless a matter of loyalty, but it is also a question of method; for if disarmament, even limited disarmament, demands checks, it also demands as a starting point exact knowledge of existing armaments and of the facilities for making them - that is to say, not only arms factories or factories which are easily convertible into arms factories, but also laboratories and natural resources.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">***</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">It is not without point, I believe, to end this examination of the development of ideas within the <hi rend="Corpo_del_testo_(2)_+_12_pt;Corsivo;Spaziatura_0_pt"><seg rend="italic">SFIO</seg></hi> in the last thirty or forty years with these remarks on action for the defence of peace ; for that action is closely bound up with the defence of civil liberties and the establishment of social democracy which, in turn, leads to a Socialist civilisation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">Just as, after the 1914-18 War, the French Socialist were the most ardent defenders of the League Of Nations and strove to give it confidence, to make it bold and to claim for it the means to achieve its aim, so after the Second World War it is the French Socialists who, in spite of difficulties and disappointments, remain the most ardent supporters in France of the European idea which is today taking shape.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">The French Socialists are also the most determined to ensure that the United Nations Organisation, in spite of its internal weaknesses, does not produce a record of failure. They are well aware - and say so - that if the United Nations Organisation did not exist we would be faced with armed coalitions and unrestrained instincts.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">People tell us that UNO has no authority. That it is only a talking-shop.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (2)">No authority ? That is not exactly true. The answer to aggression in Korea remains a decision of the utmost value. But even if UNO were merely an international talking-shop it would still be important for the peace of the world.</p></body></text></TEI>