<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
         <title>The Ideological Development of Democratic Socialism in Italy</title>
         <author>Leo Valiani</author>
      </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Socialist International</publisher>
            <date>18 June 1955</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <seriesStmt>
            <title>Socialist International Information</title>
            <idno>Vol.V, No.25</idno>
          </seriesStmt>
              <sourceDesc>
              </sourceDesc>
              </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
                <appInfo>
                  <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <listChange><change><date>2015-07-30T02:23:15Z</date><name>e w</name></change></listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
<text>
  <body>
   <p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is no denying that Socialist ideas – whether in their original form or in one of the many many metamorphoses they have undergone in the course of more than a century - came to Italy for the most part from abroad. The writing of Saint Simon and Fourier and their disciples, and later on these of Pierre Leroux, Louis Blanc and Proudhon, were read in Italy long before the formation or the Italian Socialist Movement. That movement, which first saw the light of day at the time of the First International and the Paris Commune, was influenced in turn by Bakunin, Malon, Kropotkin, Marx, Engels, Sorel, Jaurès, Lenin and Léon Blum – to mention only the greatest. The spokesmen of the ruling classes have never let slip any opportunity of violently reproaching the Italian Socialists for their ties with foreign ideology. The reproof has obviously no serious grounds. In the Western world, which is a world of mutual contact, between nations, ideas have been constantly in circulation for hundreds, indeed for thousands of years - if we go back to that Greek culture brought to Rome along the roads the legions made. Like other intellectual upheavals which preceded it, international Socialism adapted itself to the intellectual, ethical and economic conditions of Italy and has ended by becoming a profoundly important element in the life of the nation today.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">That section of the Italian people which welcomed Socialist ideas at the outset were the romantics (potty bourgeois by social origin but with a considerable admixture of proletarian elements) who had taken part with the utmost zeal and spirit of sacrifice in the conspiracies and battles of the Risorgimento and had been left disillusioned by its outcome in favour of the House of Savoy - a solution which was admittedly anti-clerical and constitutional but; was at the same time conservative rather than democratic or liberal. Having chosen as their aim a people’s republic, no being at once the guarantee and crowning achievement of notional unity and notional liberty, the extreme left wing of Italian youth wanted to continue the fight for revolutionary ideas.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But even the ideal of a democratic republic had risen through contact with abroad. The trees of liberty were brought to Italy and planted there by the emissaries of the French Revolution among whom there figured, moreover, the Italian Filippo Buonarotti, companion of Baboeuf and historian of conspiracy of the Equals. In the French, the great mass of the people had seen invaders, an oppressive occupying power, but the more radical youth in the cities were deeply moved by the new visions and from them derived the dreams of a united republican Italy. Disillusionment followed, and there were still further disappointments in 1830-1831, with the revolutionary attempts of the carbonari, inspired once again by France. Then In 1832-1834, Giuseppe Mazzini succeeded in separating the struggle for a democratic Italian republic from that which was still being waged concurrently, in France, and gave it an anti-Jacobin twist. Forty years later, on the morrow of the Commune, the first Italian Socialist movement was founded - also with an anti-Jacobin ideology.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Of course more than one of the main currents of Western Socialism - English, French or German - had taken shape in polemics against Jacobinism and its various re-incarnations. Men such as Saint-Simon, Enfantin, Bazard, Fourier, Proudhon, Owen, had disavowed the Jacobin ideology for the good reason that they were much more advanced than the neo-Jacobins in their conception of social economy. For the same reason they had also stood aloof from revolutionary violence. The latter’s most clear-sighted exponents in the Socialist camp – namely Blanqui, E. Jones and the great founders of the Communist league - while hostile in social matters to petit-bourgeois neo-Jacobinism and brought up on advanced, modem economic ideas, were nevertheless, to varying degrees, under the spell of 1793. Mazzini the anti-Jacobin, and his disciples, were paradoxically no lees insurrectionary than the most extreme and violent of the republicans, Socialists or foreign communists. According to the conspirators around Mazzini - among whom we can number a genuine Socialist theorist Carlo Pisacane, - the idea of an independent Italy meant that the national republic had to be the result of a people’s revolution stirred up on the initiative of a fearless minority; but the victorious revolution was not intended to take the form of dictatorship by a committee of public safety but of an entirely democratic constituent assembly, which was to be convened immediately. On this point both the orthodox followers of Mazzini - who favoured a central government - and the numerous federalists were in agreement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The first Italian Socialists to join the International were disappointed followers of Mazzini who had been converted to the extreme form of federalism advocated by Bakunin. The famous Russian revolutionary stayed in Italy from 1864 to 1867 and later in an Italian newspaper defended the Paris Commune against an attack by Mazzini, praising its federalist and socialist aspects; but it must be pointed out that, during the period when he was proselytising in Italy, Bakunin himself had massed from being an advocate of radical political revolutionary activity with no clearly defined aims to a form of libertarian anarchism on a collective basis. Bakunin and his Italian followers, while rejecting Mazzini<hi rend="superscript">’</hi>s purely political concept of the revolution - and, indeed, any political concept of the revolution – and, indeed, any political ideology, any struggle for the conquest or reform of the State - nevertheless adopted Mazzini's idea of an insurrection initiated by an advanced group, which would not aim at a Jacobin dictatorship but summon the people to democratic self-governement during the revolution; a revolution which Bakunin, as opposed to Mazzini, conceived as a social and proletarian movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Naturally not all the Italian revolutionaries believed equally firmly in the democratic ability of the people in revolt. Garibaldi was strongly in favour of dictatorship through a committee of public safety - but taking Washington rather than Robespierre for his model - and said so without mincing words in a letter to the Paris Commune. But the majority of Garibaldians who joined the Socialist movement - and under their influence Garibaldi himself applauded the International - had declared for the principles of liberty. In these circumstances, even though no less person than Engels was corresponding secretary with Italy for the Workingmen<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>s International in the years 1871-1872 , it was inevitable that political Marxism could not expect to be welcomed by the Italian internationalists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Besides, divisions of opinion were not lacking among the libertarians in Italy. Some of them seriously believed that a victorious insurrection was at hand and therefore wished to ally themselves with the numerous republicans who had remained revolutionaries without adhering to the principle of Socialism. Others, more intransigent because more pessimistic, conceived the insurrectionary movement - in these years there were several of them, all easily put down - purely as "propaganda by deeds" and therefore wanted it to take place only under the red and black banner of international anarchism. Others were chiefly concerned with direct working-class action, with the spontaneous strikes which gave the Socialists an opportunity to organise the first trade unions. And still others, although members of the Anarchist International, came out for the formation of a democratic Socialist party. In spite of persecutions, the International survived in Italy until 1880.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The enlargement of the franchise in 1882, which gave the vote to great masses of manual workers, found the proletarian movement in Italy divided into three distinct groups: anarchists; the militant members of a workers’ party which flourished only in Lombardy and which only manual workers could join - they were for the class struggle in politics and the trade union field, but did not adhere to any definite Socialist ideology; and political Socialists, who professed themselves ardent revolutionaries and in the Romagna had mass support, thanks to Andrea Costa, the ex-secretary of the Italian Federation of the International, who had vociferously welcomed the political struggle and got himself elected Member of Parliament. They were much more evolutionary, if much less numerous, in Milan, however, where the young lawyer and man of letters, Filippo Turati, belonged to their group. Only the anarchists had remained faithful to the idea of insurrection in theory and practice. The Socialists in the Romagna called themselves revolutionaries, but were so only in theory; they were in fact a party which believed in electoral methods although they used most violent language in their agitation. In Milan, the workers’ party organised strikes for trade union aims and wage claims but shrank from violence. Nearly all of then, however, had remained libertarians in the sense that they rejected the possibility that the emancipation of the proletariat might come about through the political and administrative action of the State. They therefore did not aim at taking over the State - not even those of them who took part in political elections - but took for granted or dreamt of its revolutionary dissolution. It is true that in the programme of Andrea Costa’s party in the Romagna there was a reference to the possibility of the dictatorship of the proletariat - but the term was interpreted according to Lavrov, whom Costa had read, and not according to Marx. Among the evolutionist intellectuals - and Turati was in their van - there were some who had already grasped how to carry cut social reform through the State; but Turati himself, when replying to Mai on’s criticisms in 18S7&gt; defended the classical libertarianism of the working class party, which he held to be an expression of working-class independence (what the English would call ’self-help’) and as such a useful brake on State authoritarianism, which in other countries had already made breaches in the working-class movement.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Not many years passed before, in 1892, all the trends in the Italian working-class movement - with the exception of the Anarchists - fused into a Socialist party, which adopted a Marxist programme on the contemporary German model, Cafiero and Gori among the anarchists had been the first to translate Capital and The Communist Manifesto into Italian. A Hegelian philosopher, Antonio Labriola, was the first interpreter of the materialist concept of history in Italy. The practical introduction of Marxism into politics – and into the political ideology of Italian Socialism - was due to Filippo Turati, gallantly aided by his Russian wife, Anna Kulishov, and by a group of young people who, like Turati himself, had their philosophical roots in the theory of positivist, experimental evolutionism. I have already said that Turati rejected the anti-State theories which belonged to the Italian tradition of social libertarianism. He had come to Marxism by reading the texts of Marx and Engels themselves and by studying closely the intelligent, constructive political and trade union activity of German Social Democracy. He differed from the latter, however, because on the one hand - parliamentary government being considerably more established in Italy than in imperial Germany - he held that one should aim at not only the future conquest of the State but also at obtaining a coherent social policy from the existing State; on the other, because he wished, then and in future, to keep intervention by the State - even the Socialist State - in economy and production within strict limits. He was convinced that the national economy – whether bourgeois or Socialist - was subject to its own laws which the State did well to observe scrupulously and not break them by too frequent interventions. Moreover, he wanted Socialist ideology, that is to say, Marxism, to be interpreted in the widest, most liberal sense possible - he wished there to be no sects, dogmas, excommunications in Socialism, and wished all philosophical, economic, literary opinions compatible with faith in political Socialism, understood in the widest sense, to find common ground there. If he was not, and never was, a libertarian like most of his early companions, Turati was a most liberal and individual Marxist.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">From Marxism, Turati, who was in correspondence with Engels had taken part in the international Socialist congresses of Brussels (1891) and of Zurich (1893), took the essentials of his programme - socialisation of the means of production, to be achieved by the conquest of political power through the class struggle of the proletariat in the political and trade union field. It was not easy to get this programme accepted by militants who were influenced on the one hand by a libertarian, collective but anti-State tradition, and on the other by the feeling that, in order to preserve the unity of the working-class, no other ultimate, more specific aim should be adopted than that of the emancipation of the working class. However, not without hesitations and concessions to the various trends - the appeal to the peasants, small proprietors, tenant farmers, share-croppers, to join the party of the working class in the defence of their own interests – Turati’s theses carried the day at the congress which gave birth to the party in 1892.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It could be pointed out - and more than one person did so - that in Turati’s Marxist programme there was no firm declaration of the necessity of the proletarian revolution - no appeal to the “midwife of history”, the violence of a class losing its chains. In fact Turati, convinced as he was of the superiority of peaceful evolution, never believed in the usefulness of violence. In this he differed not only from Marx but from the revolutionary tradition of early Italian Socialism, dating from the Risorgimento, which still lived on in many of his adversaries. On the other hand, Turati realised more profoundly than the majority of his critics what the essence of the Risorgimento had been - namely, the passion for liberty; out he belonged, by intellectual temperament, to that trend among statesmen which had consolidated the unity of Italy in a parliamentary, constitutional regime and renounced the idea of attempting to attain by force of arms and under unfavourable circumstances those national and democratic aims which were still unsatisfied and which must now be won by the pressure of maturing public opinion. His enemies on the extreme left deduced from this that, in Socialism, Turati represented a liberal trend of bourgeois origin. And certainly he could not be expected to believe blindly in the Marxist or pseudo-Marxist theories of the inevitable collapse of capitalist economy and the inevitable proletarisation of the middle classes.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">What then did his Marxism consist of? First and foremost, of his faith in the independent action of the working-class, which not only had no need of Messiahs, saviours, dictators, but must rather shun any tendency to believe in miracles - just as it must avoid any guidance from without, from above, since it both can and must count on its own strength and its own power of action, which inevitably develop with the progress of industry and freedom to carry on the class struggle. As a Marxist, Turati had faith in the objective development of modern economy on which, in the final analysis, the outcome of the struggle between the social classes depended. He was sometimes accused of interpreting Marxism as economic determinism. But from his conviction that ultimate political solutions depended on economic circumstances - a concept which undoubtedly had a streak of determinism in it, somewhere between Marxism and evolutionary positivism - Turati did not deduce a kind of fatalism about the future but the proof that the Socialist party could carry out a programme of political reform. That is to say, that if the passage from capitalism to Socialism depended on a complete determinable phase of economic development which the Socialist party could not hasten to any appreciable extent, nor the bourgeois parties prevent from running its course - and given the technical backwardness of Italy, the time could not be very near - it followed that there was nothing to prevent political collaboration for limited but immediate aims, between those bourgeoisie who were both sincerely democratic and sincerely desirous of reform, and the Socialist workers who, turn, were conscious that within the old society the techniques organisational methods of the new society were irresistibly - but not necessarily rapidly - coming to maturity.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the fight against authoritarian, conservative reaction (always a threat in Italy) and for the introduction and consolidation of democracy and for impartiality on the part of the State in trade union disputes - in this hard battle which marks the first twelve years of life of the Socialist party (1892 - 1904 ) and led to the coming of power, under Giolitti, of a government desirous of winning the parliamentary support of the Socialists, what we may call the Turati line (the line, too, of his collaborators, such as Kulishov, Bissolati, Prampolini and Claudio Treves) won its greatest victories. In the following ten years democratic Socialism obtained further important results - particularly in the field of social legislation to safeguard workers of either sex and in the organisation of the first national industrial unions which, together with the great organisations of the land workers (the most typical form of Italian trade union movement) succeeded in infusing life and increasing power into the reformist Confederation of Labour (CGL) which won the upper hand and stood out strongly against the revolutionary syndicalists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is no place here for an examination of revolutionary syndicalism, to which Turati was all the more bitterly opposed since the Italian revolutionary syndicalists for years claimed the right to fight in the ranks of the Socialist party, more than once won over whole local sections of the party and - however contradictory it might be - had themselves elected parliamentary deputies. Suffice it to say that, in Italy and in France, revolutionary syndicalism took up certain threads of the anarchist tradition, modernising it with the Marxist concept that even strictly economic and partial strikes - as apart from the general strike of the entire working class - served the cause of the workers. Yet in Italy, where it was nourished by the spontaneous brutality of numerous class struggles against owners (particularly the landowners), still blindly selfish in mentality and given to violent measures, it found its theoreticians in a large number of young intellectuals from the South; that is to say, from the most backward and economically retarded part of the country, but that part which was psychologically most alive. These young men had embraced the theories of Georges Sorel. In these they saw a thorough-going revision of Marxist economic doctrine and unlimited stress on hostility towards the bourgeois state, whether conservative or reformist - a sentiment which, from being at first anti-militarist, later became nationalistic.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">To be brief, Turati won his battle against revolutionary syndicalism in the Socialist movement. He lost it against the maximalists, who appealed to Marxist orthodoxy. The origins of Italian maximalism once more go back to the militants of the First International. These libertarians who at the time of the extension of the franchise became converted to the participation in the elections (which was already accepted by Marxists in the most advanced countries in Europe) continually stressed that their presence in parliament and</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">municipal councils had purely agitational and propagandist aims, just as they stressed their invincible hostility to the bourgeois State, their complete disbelief that the proletariat could free itself from the capitalist yoke by means of legislative and bureaucratic reforms, and, conversely, their unbounded faith in the mass action of the proletariat, including demonstrations as well as normal industrial struggles. As long as the government was reactionary, this agitational intransigence was entirely natural, its exponents abroad being, in the early days, the best known of the Marxists, Wilhelm Liebknecht and Jules Guesde.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It ceased to have any real justification, however, as governments became more liberal and democratic and began to set about improving the living conditions of the working class. In fact, in Romagna itself - the cradle of those intransigent ex-anarchist agitators who later with the greatest success fought elections as Marxists - an excellent system of agricultural and other co-operatives developed, at first tolerated and later actually supported by the liberal government; their aim being to reduce unemployment among the agricultural labourers. In other words, it meant to carry out to all intents and purposes the task of reformism while preserving a romantic revolutionary ideology.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The possibility of enduring reform depended on the government having a continuous tradition of democracy. This was possible only if, on these occasions when the representatives of authoritarian ideologies and vested interests joined battle with the government, the Socialist deputies, whose number was growing with each election, voted in support of the ministry. It did not seem a very big stop to pass from occasional but frequently repeated support to entering the government itself. This possibility provoked a rebellion among the die-hard members of the party - at first in alliance with the revolutionary syndicalists and then in rivalry with them - who considered it the abandonment of Marxist principles, and a grave threat of betrayal to the ultimate aim of the Socialist revolution and the class struggle. There was a certain logic in their argument that Italian capitalism had given way to legislative and wage concessions only under the pressure of electoral and trade union activity by the masses who, it was feared, might give way to revolutionary outbursts. It was not easy to contradict the revolutionaries before an audience of workers who knew from their own experience the rancour of the employers at every concession forced from them, and the way the police were biased in favour of the bosses.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The reformists should have pointed out that even frequent and active support of a democratic bourgeois government in order to avoid having a conservative one was not incompatible with that particular brand of Marxism which was the real ideology of Italian working class Socialism. Jaurès was able to do it m France at the same period - that is to say, after Socialist unity had been reconstituted. But in Italy the great Jacobin, republican and democratic tradition was lacking – the tradition of which Jaurès was both historian and spokesman and which not even the French Marxists could for long entirely reject if they did not wish to condemn themselves to political isolation. The libertarian tradition in the Italian working-class movement was on the whole against Turati, as was the frequency of conflicts between strikers and police. Very significant efforts were, of course, made in Italy to re-examine, elucidate and re-formulate critically the bases of Marxist doctrine. I have already mentioned Antonio Labriola. In his learned and acute essays on the materialist conception of history (1895-1898) he had rejected not only the positivist and determinist interpretations – these were to be attributed less to Turati than to the celebrated criminologist, Enrico Ferri, a follower of Spencer and Darwin, who was for Enrico Ferico Ferri, a follower of Spencer and Darwin, who was for many years leader of the die-hard wing of party and later became a political opportunist – but also the opposing theory of free will. His interpretation of historical materialism as pragmatic philosophy – reality being conceived of as the independent activity of history – meant an inquiry into the origins and nature of the actual conditions in which Socialism was called upon to work from time to time; that is to say, concrete social history with no <hi rend="underline">a priori</hi> assumptions. From this a long-term policy was to be deduced which would be in conformity with the objective tendencies of historical and social development and would take the place of the policy of improvisation. But so long as this method, which was certainly on a high cultural level, was confined to the sphere of philosophy and sociology it permitted two kinds of conclusions to be drawn: revolutionary democracy like that of Marx and Engels in 1848, or reformism in the grand style of Jaurés. Antonio Labriola, who is not to be confused with the revolutionary syndicalist, Arturo Labriola, died in 1904 – too soon to allow him to make a choice or reach definite political conclusions in the debate between revolution and reform.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Antonio Labriola’s philosophy of activity was taken up again by Rodolfo Mondolfo, who made a name for himself by his studies of the gnoseological and ethical aspects of the thought of Feuerbach, Marx, Engels and Lassalle. In politics the sympathies of Mondolfo – who, together with his brother, Ugo Guido, was a valued collaborator of <hi rend="underline">Critica Sociale</hi>, the review edited by Turati and Anna Kulishow – were in favour of a policy of great structural reforms; but he remained a scholar and only rarely descended into the day-to-day political struggle. His interpretation of Marxist philosophy may, however, he described as close to the neo-Kantian interpretation of the Austrian Marxists, although he arrived at it independently from them. The publication of the unedited philosophical writings of Marx and Engels confirmed some of the theses he had put forward fifteen or twenty years before – theses which did away with rigid materialism, substituting a realistic and flexible historical methodology and a political philosophy in keeping with the spirit of human liberty.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Gaetano Salvemini – another great teacher of social history – maintained at the Socialist party congresses with the aid of G. E. Modigliani and Ugo Guido Mondolfo that the struggle for basic political reforms should supersede a reformist policy concerned with partial measures – measures which were frequently of limited, not of general interest. Salvemini could not win the support of the Socialist working-class, which had developed in the North, for his hostility to the protectionist industrial policy of northern Italy - a policy which he considered artificial and which hindered the proper development of the South. He had more success with his denunciation of the practice of Giolitti's government, which, in order to win the support of the semi-feudal cliques of the South, denied to the working masses their full enjoyment of the democratic liberties which had been won elsewhere in Italy. But while on Giolitti's right there were large social and political forces, on his left the radicals and republicans ware unable to exert sufficient pressure. Only the Socialists could have given a lead, and they would have required the support of the masses. Salvemini was of the opinion that the budgetary situation would very soon prevent the expansion of expenditure necessary to finance particular measures which would benefit the various categories of workers, e.g. social legislation on working conditions, public works, subsidies to co-operatives, increased pay for civil servants. But the far-reaching reforms of the system of taxation, of tariff policy, of the educational system, which would change the face or Italy and set free the working-class of the South presupposed a parliamentary majority which was determined to strike at the great vested interests. According to Salvemini , only the introduction of universal suffrage could open the way to great structural reforms.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Unfortunately, Salvemini’s diagnosis was more successful than the treatment he proposed. This was seen when Giolitti introduced universal suffrage in 1913. The Socialists gained a large number of votes and seats, but for the first time since 1870, the great mass of faithful Catholics openly and systematically sided with the monarchist government forces, who came forward under liberal labels. At this period Salvemini himself had withdrawn from the Socialist party in order to devote himself to a moral revival in public life, but even if he had remained within the party, his passionate temper would not have made him particularly suitable for on objective discussion of the relationship between Socialism and State.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">About the same time, the French and German Socialists as well as the English Radicals and Labourites were attempting to moot the growing demands for social expenditure - and it was hoped to increase them - by the introduction of direct progressive taxes on income, and of death duties. Progressive fiscal reform also figured in the minimum programme of the Italian Socialist party, but the Italian Socialists, whoso leaders came from professions unpractised in modem administration, were sceptical of taxation as an instrument for social progress. The diehards of Marxism maintained that, in the final analysis, it was the workers who paid all the taxes by increasing surplus value, while Turati and his friends thought it inadvisable to hamper capitalism with heavy taxation, since it was responsible for the development of production. When, in 1909, Giolitti proposed what was admittedly a very modest but progressive fiscal reform, the Socialist parliamentary group did not defend it against the attacks of the right and allowed it to be dropped. In Turati’s opinion, the money for social services should be procured not by increased taxation but by reduction - or at least, by strict limitation - of military expenditure.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">At this point a split took place within the ranks of the reformist Socialists. Their strength derived from the fact that they concentrated on the realities, on the actual conditions obtaining. In Europe the arms race was about to become a reality and Italy, which was nominally allied to the Central European powers of the Triple Alliance while visibly in sympathy with the West, could not escape it. The orthodox diehards were at least consistent in refusing to accept the situation. The reformist could not do so without cutting themselves off from the remaining democratic forces in the government in Parliament. They could have asked that the money for arms be found by a progressive fiscal policy, but their refusal to increase the military budget meant that they could no longer exercise a reforming influence. So they fell back on the sane position as the diehards. Bissolati realised this and said so in Avanti, which he edited on behalf of the party majority which was still reformist. Turati answered him. Since he did not believe that in a bourgeois society a progressive fiscal policy would bear fruit, Turati was convinced that the growth of military expenditure would make expenditure on social services impossible and he was too devoted to the working-class to resign himself to the prospect or approve it. Moreover, since he hated violence and had faith only in peaceful progress, he maintained that war could not solve any modern problem, and meant instead a return to barbarism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">That re-armament - as Turati, Treves, and Modigliani - foresaw - would lead to war was only too true, and it was the Italian government which set things ablaze with the war in Libya against the Turks. But it was not only the nationalists, the natural enemies of Socialism, who wanted Italy to take Tripoli. It was also the wish of those same democratic bourgeois forces with whom the reformist Socialists had up to now managed to co-operate on all really important occasions, and whose most radical elements would have liked to force  armed intervention for Trento and Trieste when the time came. If only not to be cut off from these patriotic and democratic forces, Bissolati and Bonomi and a few other parliamentary reformists declared, once the Libyan war had begun, that - apart from the question of the usefulness or otherwise of colonial adventures - one must hope that Italy would energy victorious from the war in which she was involved.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Turati and Treves opposed the war in Libya. The great majority of Socialists, including almost all the leader- even the reformist ones - of the Confederation of Labour and trade unions were against the colonial adventure, against which the direction both of the party and of the Confederation had protested under pressure from the anti-militarist working-class by a twenty-four hour strike. Throughout huge areas of Italy the conditions in which the workers lived were still extremely primitive; elsewhere the standard of living reached- by the well-organised workers was higher, but was always threatened by unemployment, which was to increase rapidly because of the economic dis-equilibrium brought on by the cost of the war, expected. One anti-war influence was naturally the traditional hostility of the Italian proletariat to the State, whose hand became increasingly heavy with the growth of colonialism. The violent repression of demonstrations against one despatch troops to Libya stirred up bitter feeling. Between 1904 and 1906 Turati and Bissolati had on other occasions found themselves in the minority at party congresses, because the police had killed demonstrators and so forced the militant  socialists to extremes. At the 1912 congress, the anti-militarist delegates voted for the expulsion of Bissolati, Bonomi and Cabrini, who had had an audience with the King to congratulate him on the failure of an attempt at assassination by an anarchist - and handed over the leadership of the party to the uncompromisingly revolutionary wing. Its leaders were: the elderly Lazzari, who had been a popular figure ever since the days of the workers’ party (1882-1887) of which he had been a leader; Serrati, a rigid doctrinaire, devoted heart and soul to the idea of the proletarian revolution; and Mussolini, stirring orator and a tactician of exceptional ability, a man of unbounded ambition and great talents.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Turati and almost all the reformist organisers split with Bissolati over the question of war, and remained in the Socialist party. Bissolati, Bonomi and Cabrini resigned themselves readily to expulsion and founded a reformist party. But, as Turati had warned, although they won some seats in Southern Italy at the expense of the bourgeois democrats, they had never any organised mass following. Their numerous friends in the more advanced unions did net follow them, but remained attached to Socialism on a class basis - their only guarantee that they would maintain contact with the broad masses.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The European conflict produced even graver consequences within the Socialist party. This time the revolutionaries split. Italy’s initial neutrality - which meant the end of the Triple Alliance - soon gave place to the simultaneous pressure of radical democratic sympathy with France, or anti-Austrian irredentist and militarist nationalism. An atmosphere was created in the country which made war with the Habsburg Empire inevitable. Almost all the revolutionary syndicalists declared themselves in favour of intervention in the war, and they were followed by the young editor of Avanti, Benito Mussolini. The Socialist party did not hesitate to expel him from its ranks.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Faced with Italian intervention in the European war - an intervention which was at first extremely popular with the middle classes but, with a few local exception, generally unpopular with the working class - Italian Socialism took a further step towards the left, being the only one of the Western Socialist parties to adopt an attitude of determined opposition not only to the conduct of the war but to the grounds for fighting it. This intransigence was dictated by the extreme wing of the party under the leadership of Lazzari of the secretariat, and above all of Serrati, who had taken over the editorship of Avanti. In Parliament, however, its spokesmen - partly from pacifist convictions, partly in obedience to party discipline - were the Social-Democrat leaders: Turati, Treves, Modigliani. Turati defended the vote against military credits, Treves and Modigliani on various occasions proposed that Italy - which, incidentally, had come into the war to liberate these Italian territories included in the Austro-Hungarian Entire – should take the initiative for a peace without annexations. Modigliani -as one of the leading organisers of the conference of the anti-war Socialists held at Zimmerwald in the Autumn of 1915.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Italian reformist Socialism led the international pacifist movement and the opposition to imperialism of any sort all through the war with great spirit and lofty aims; but against the purity of its ideals had to be put the fact that it antagonised the middle classes - even the most democratic of them - who saw in its policy only a doctrinaire lack of solidarity with the fatherland in its moment of danger and indeed with Western civilisation itself. Nor did the pacifist reformers win back the complete faith of the working classes, who from 1917 on looked above all to the Russian revolution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the four years between the end of the conflict and Mussolini’s coming to power, events developed more disconcertingly and more rapidly than during the war years. At first it seemed as if the Italian working class was about to take the State by storm and unleash a revolution on the Soviet model. The vast majority of the Italian Socialist party, whose organised forces and votes has swollen enormously, declared itself maximalist and voted for adherence to the Third International. Then the revolutionary wave subsided without having provoked any serious clash. In September 1920, the metalworkers had, it is true, occupied the factories throughout the country and had run them for the three weeks’ occupation under the hastily recruited “red guards” - but it soon became apparent that this was only a wage struggle. As soon as the maximalist leaders themselves had dismissed the possibility of an insurrection, the aged Giolitti on the one hand, and on the other the reformist Socialist secretary of the Metalworkers’ Union, Buozzi - he was to be shot by the Nazis in 1944 - were able to negotiate a compromise over wage increases and legislation providing for the setting up of factory councils; the latter was to have been the prelude - according to the Government - to social control of production. But public opinion interpreted the solution as a defeat of the Socialist working class and reaction passed to the counter-offensive.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Meanwhile Zinoviev had contrived to split the Socialist parties which were already torn by divergent currents. The twenty-one points made the expulsion of Turati and Treves inevitable if the party intended to continue to belong to the Third International. The majority of the Italian Maximalists refused to obey and the revolutionary minority, which had been demanding their expulsion ever since the end of the war, split off and turned itself into the Communist party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the winter of 1920-1921, the terror organised by the armed squads formed by Mussolini was unleashed with unheard of violence against working class organisations of all shades. The Fascists drew their recruits from young men back from the war, chiefly petty bourgeois in origin, whom the country’s economic crisis could not absorb and who believed that the Socialist and pacifist opposition had weakened Italy in the international negotiations. But the most dangerous squadristi were adventurers with criminal inclinations in the pay of the big landowners and the most reactionary industrialists. The liberal government, terrified by the Maximalist Socialists, whose sympathies lay with Bolshevik Russia, and wracked by the conflict between the anti-clerical democrats and the new mass Catholic party - the Popular Prty - who between then had to fill the ministerial posts, committed the fatal error of allowing the military authorities to supply large quantities of arms to the Fascists, who at the elecetions formed part of the national liberal-conservative block. And the police not only did not interfere with the squadristi; in general it protected them when they attached the local premises of the Communists and Socialists and of the trace unions.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Although he expressed his solidarity with the Russian revolution for having brought peace, equality and Socialism, Turati from the first was firm in his opposition to Bolshevism and Maximalism which - as he dramatically put it in his speech to the Socialist congress in 1919 - would have provoked in Italy a ferocious anti-working class reaction on the part of the bourgeoisie such as would have put civilisation back many decades. As soon as the Third International’s plan of action became known, Turati, Treves and Rodolfo Mondolfo pointed out that Social Democracy must clearly deny any responsibility for the methods of the Communist dictatorship, whilst at the sane time opposing intervention against Soviet Russia.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">But if it was sufficient to denounce the incompatibility between reformist Socialism and Communism on the ideological field, ideological opposition was certainly not enough against the violence of Fascism. It was necessary to defend oneself, to defend the working class organisations, the offices of the party press, of the trade unions and co-operatives, which the Fascists periodically burned or destroyed - to defend parliamentary democracy. Apart from the Communists who were still few in number - except in certain centres like Turin where in Gramsci (he later died in prison under Fascism) they had an outstanding leader in both theory and politics - the situation may be summed up as follows: - The Maximalists should have challenged the Fascists with revolutionary violence, but they were incapable of it. The reformists should have Joined the government, where the Liberal democrats would have welcomed them with pleasure in 1920-21, since first Giolitti and later the ex-Socialist Bonomi were then Prime Ministers; but only Treves publicly insisted on the absolute necessity of doing it quickly - in fact, at once. The bulk of the reformist Members of Parliament did not wish to leave the party since the Maximalists, who were still in the majority, had preferred to split with the Communists rather than expel the reformists when Zinoviev condemned them. It was only in 1922 after the defeat of a great anti-Fascist general strike, that the maximalists and reformists realised that they had paralysed each other, and the latter left the party, which had formally expelled them for considering ministerial appointments, and formed a new Unitarian Socialist Party. Turati, Treves and Modigliani were the acknowledged political leaders and Matteotti the secretary. It was already too late. The Liberals no longer dared to include the Socialists in the government. After some days of acute crisis, due to Fascist threats to cause an insurrection, the King entrusted the government to Mussolini. The elections of 1924, although held under the Fascist terror, showed that the Unitarian Socialist Party had a considerable following in the middle and working classes, and that the Maximalists and the Communists still had a proletarian mass following. But the government had at its disposal the repressive forces of the State.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The revision of Socialist thought in Italy began under the Fascist dictatorship. First and foremost, it was necessary to get back faith in a spontaneous upsurge of the people. In his speech to the Marseilles congress of the Socialist International in 1925, Turati raised the fundamental question. We have not come to complain of the persecutions we have undergone – he said – nor to ask for help from our comrades abroad. The martyrdom of Matteotti has confirmed what he always maintained in the face of Fascism terrorism – that each nation must win its own liberty and if it has lost it, win it back again. So it is not a case – as the Communists maintain – of choosing between the dictatorship of one class or another, but of demanding liberty which cannot triumph without the conviction that liberty itself is not a mere tactical weapon, but a permanent and universal ideal.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In 1926 – the last year in which, in spite of sequestrations and suppressions, opposition paper could still be printed – a young intellectual, Carlo Rosselli, a pupil of Salvemini, who a few months later was to organise the dramatic flight of Turati from Italy, published <hi rend="underline">The Fourth State</hi>, a political and cultural review, “Dogma”, he wrote in the first number “is the last thing Socialism is; it refuses to be rigidly formulated. It is a problem more of faith than of science. While it raises the most fundamental economic problems, and the most fundamental moral ones, socialisation remains only a means, a most powerful means – it is not and cannot be an end. The end is different. The end is the perfecting of the human personality, and the creation of a new order which will procure for the largest possible number of human beings the concrete possibility of raising themselves to the highest level of material and spiritual life”.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It could certainly be pointed out to Rosselli – and the Marxist Claudio Treves did not fail to do so – that he was taking a step backwards and that his liberal Socialism was a return to the theories of Proudhon or John Stuart Mill. But Rosselli replied that one had to draw from the past something in which the present had been found lacking when faced by the onslaught of Fascism – namely, the passionate desire of the Socialist pioneers for liberty, through which alone the Italian working-class in its defeat and isolation would be able to find allies among those of the middle class intellectuals who – having recovered from their intoxication with nationalism – would discover once more the value of the liberty they had lost. If one considered complete socialisation of the means of production as the final goal, from which everything else followed, then one would have to agree – in theory, at least, with the Communists, and in practice the working class would be left isolated. It was only by an alliance between the most militant members of the working class and the idealists of middle class origin that the material and moral weapons for the fight between liberty and dictatorship could be found. The victory of Socialism was possible only if it adopted as its programme the socialisation of only part of the economy – the great industrial and financial monopolies and the big estates – and stated that in other sectors it wished to leave untouched the healthy free enterprise; it must also declare solemnly that the ultimate aim was not mere economic transformation but a society of free men. </p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">As his later activity showed, however, Rosselli had not so much the gifts needed to lay down a party doctrine and expound systematically, as intuitions which transcended party politics - thus he was among the earliest to foresee the Second World War and to champion European federation. Above all, he was a great conspirator and fighter; a man ready to sacrifice his own life. He founded and led the anti-Fascist movement, “Justice and Liberty”, fought in Spain and in 1937 was murdered by the Fascists, along with his brother, Nello Rosselli, the historian of the working class movement in Italy.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The illegal struggle, which remained clandestine until 1943 and took the form of partisan warfare in the two following years, was certainly indispensable to give the opponents of the regime confidence in themselves once more. But once the dictatorship was over, the question of working class organisation and of systematic propaganda for Socialism was bound to present itself. And for that the daring conspiracies of "Justice and Liberty” were insufficient.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">From the time of the publication of The Fourth State, Pietro Nenni and Giuseppe Saragat - the former joint editor and the latter a valued contributor of the review - had distinguished themselves by their thorough political approach to the problem of re-stating Socialism. Nenni came from the Maximalist section of the party but was not pro-Communist; indeed at the end of 1922, after the split with the reformists, Serrati tried to force the fusion of the Maximalist party with the Communists, Nenni prevented it and removed <hi rend="underline">Avanti</hi> from Serrati’s control. He was to remain editor throughout the following extremely difficult years. In 1926, Nenni left Avanti to be able to campaign for Socialist re-unification — that is to say, the fusion of the reformists with those maximalists who had refused to follow Serrati into the Third International. On the reformist side Saragat, who was considered the rising hope of the young united Socialists, supported the same line for the re-constitution of a single, democratic, proletarian Socialist party which would be able to surmount the difficulties of the past. Nenni, who was more an empiricist and man of action than a theorist - he had been a revolutionary republican in his youth and still had a vein of romantic oratory - now accepted Marxism in its traditional form. Saragat, who was a political theorist rather than a politician, favoured a Marxist humanism - he had published a philosophical study with this title in exile - which would take up and develop, on the political plane, Rodolfo Mondolfo’s philosophy of action. At this time, both Nenni and Saragat had in common a realistic attitude, a belief in free will, which led them to criticise the fatalistic passivity shown by all the Socialist groups in the face of the advance of Fascism. They urged them to adopt an active policy, a policy full of initiative, which would bring about the alliance of the working class and the petty bourgeoisie in opposition to Fascism and the monarchy itself, and, once some grave crisis had overthrown the dictatorship, would establish their collaboration in the future democratic republican government.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Filippo Turati, having met them again in exile, took the part of the young leaders of the Socialist revival.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Turati had at one time been sceptical of the opposition between Republic and Monarchy and tended to rely on the automatic resolution of such problems by economic evolution – after the assassination of Matteotti he had even hoped for an intervention by the King – but now he accepted the need for the anti-Fascist struggle to be given a republican, that is to say, a revolutionary turn. He thus satisfied Nenni’s requirements. But he also restated the theses of Saragat. At the Brussels congress of the Socialist International in 1928 Turati declared that the problem of Socialism was more than ever the problem of liberty, that is to say, spiritual, political, economic liberty, liberty for the nations and for individuals, the independence of the working class movement. While he therefore refused any rapprochement with the Communists – although in Italy theirs was the most highly organised clandestine working class movement fighting Fascism – Turati pointed out the course of a friendly debate with Vandervelde that fascist totalitarian pressure was not confined to the economically backward countries, but that it threatened to spread over all Europe, engulfing it in a new war. Fascism, Turati insisted, was the product of moral rather than economic backwardness. The property-owning classes and the middle classes who have been displaced by the economic crisis, react with violence against the existence of a great working class Socialist movement which puts forward claims too advanced for the intellectual, moral and social development of its own nation. German Nazism was to prove the tragic correctness of this analysis a few years later. It follows that the socialist movement of the working class cannot hope for an uninterrupted development, free from terrible reactions, except in so far as it no longer develops as a State within the State, as one class against the other social classes, but makes itself felt by its ability to develop not only the administration of the State and the social economy but also the habits and spiritual climate of the nation.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Thus in 1930, at the Paris congress, fusion was achieved between the reformists and maximalists in the new Italian Socialist Party. The programme adopted re-stated the old theories of orthodox Marxism but also affirmed the new principles of liberty and of activity for concrete political ones. Turati died in 1932. Hitler's coming to power made it a matter of immediate importance to prevent the spread of Nazism and Fascism throughout the world. So, in 1934 - like the SFIO - the exiled Italian Socialists in France made a pact for unity of action with the Communist party. In spite of frequent dissensions, the pact worked fairly efficiently during the period when the Italian anti-Fascists were engaged in the Spanish war. As was logical, the approach of the Second World Tar and the Soviet-German pact in particular split the united front. The Communists went their own way. The Socialists split. Some of them, like Modigliani, who was old by now, and Angelo Tasca (Rossi), the erudite historian of contemporary politics, had certain hankerings after the old pacifism. Others, like Faravelli and Silone, who took a particular interest in contacts with the clandestine organisation which had been set up in Italy, favoured energetic support of the democratic war, but wished to keep contacts with the Communists to a minimum, even after the German attack on Russia. They were especially Ignazio Silone - preoccupied with the fate of Socialism and democracy after the war. The defeat of Hitlerism, Silone prophesied in an article on the necessity of organising a third front – what one might call the social front – would not by itself prevent Fascism from arising again in another guise. It would have to be fought on its own ground – in terms of the economic, political and moral crisis of the modern world. Only a Socialist movement larger than before, based on European federalism and inspired with religious fervour, could win the enthusiastic support of the youth and the most advanced workers while at the same time resisting Communist pressure, which the triumphs of the Soviet army would increase enormously. Pietro Nenni, who refused to be convinced that the Soviet-German Pact would last long, maintained from 1941 on that the German attack on Russia obliged Socialists to return to closer and more strict unity of action with the Communists. The way in which the anti-Fascist opposition arose in Italy in 1942-1943 – that is, by the formation underground of a Committee of National Liberation of all the anti-Fascist parties from the Liberals and Christian Democrats to the Communists – favoured his arguments for a single front with the Communists; with the liberation of Rome in June 1944, his line prevailed.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The contradictions inherent in the pact between Socialists and Communists became apparent after the partisan rising of April 1945 had opened the road to the setting up of the democratic Republic, which took place through the popular referendum of 1946.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The elections of 1946 showed that the alliance between the Socialists and Communists could count on the working class, but that once more the petty, middle and upper bourgeoisie were solidly against it. To go on like this would have meant a return to the situation in 1921. On the other hand, if the close bonds between the Socialists and Communists meant a political stalemate even when the two left-wing parties were collaborating in the government headed by the Christian Democrats, it would be even more serious when the international situation led, as it did in 1947, to the exclusion of the Communists from the government. Public opinion hoped that the Socialists would take an independent line and break away from the Communist party.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">Saragat, Faravelli, Ugo Guido Mondolfo, Zagari and others had been for a break with the Communists since 1945. Since they could not convince Nenni, who was still the most determined advocate of the united front, they left the Italian Workers’ Socialist Party. Eventually, in 1951, after a period of rather unproductive collaboration in the Christian Democrat government which led to violent dissensions, internal splits and disillusionment, this party, having won the support of leaders such as Romita and Silone, set up the Italian Democratic Socialist party, the Italian section of the Socialist International. By then, Nenni’s Socialist party had been able to win back a substantial part of its mass following, making things even more difficult for democratic Socialists.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">For the last forty years Italian Socialism has been living under such adverse conditions that its theoreticians continually had to take part in the actual political struggle. It is therefore impossible to outline the development of the ideology of Italian Socialism other than through the history of the political movement; and this is what has been done in this essay. It is preferable to pass over in silence (though always bearing in mind) certain theoretical works by non-Socialist philosophers and economists - including some great ones - like Benedetto Croce, Vilfredo Pareto and others who have examined Marxism and related doctrines, in order to preserve more space to record what the Italian Socialists themselves thought in the course of their hard struggle.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">When attempting to sum up the progress made by Socialist ideology in Italy, one can point more frequently to problems posed than to clear-cut solutions - but they are real problems, problems which are apparent to an ever-increasing number of people and which are inherently capable of solution.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It was inevitable that the problem of relations between Socialism and Christian faith should arise in Italy, a Catholic country governed by a Christian Democratic party which not only has links with the hierarchy of the Church and the ruling class of Italian capitalist economy, but also organises millions of genuine workers and must therefore take their interests and aspirations into consideration.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">This problem was neglected in the past, when the Socialist party only represented an advanced guard and could easily be anti-clerical, like the liberal bourgeoisie of the time. The great mass of the people still stood aside from political life and the Catholic Church, unyielding in its protest against the entry of the Italian army into Rome in 1870, continued to be not only hostile to the State, but something apart from it. Things changed with the Second World War and in 1948 Christian Democracy not only won an absolute parliamentary majority, but also created a strong trade union organisation, including workers, black-coated workers and, of course, peasants. Today the spiritual climate of Italy is marked by the revival of Catholic religious education, which has once more won control of the schools. From time to time the Democratic Socialist Party may find itself either collaborating in the government with the Christian Democrats, or in parliamentary opposition to them; but just as it cannot ignore Christian Democracy in terms of political tactics, so it cannot deny the strength of Catholicism in Italian society. The old-fashioned propagandist speeches on the primitive Christian origins of Socialism are no longer any use. The problem now does not consist in examining how equalitarian the contents of the New Testament are, but in the compatibility of the Catholic religion as it is today with modem democratic Socialism.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">From different points of view, both Saragat and Silone have declared it to be their opinion as political theorists that it is possible for a Socialist to be a Catholic and for a Catholic to be a Socialist. It is well known that the Vatican does not share this view, but it is also common knowledge that a century ago the Vatican declared Catholicism and parliamentary democracy to be incompatible, and that it now admits the opposite. Certainly, militant materialism cannot be reconciled with any religion, but Italian Socialism, even when anti-clerical, has never been truly materialist. It was positivist when almost all students of the physical sciences were so too. In general, science has now progressed beyond positivism. In Italy, the social sciences are mainly historical in their approach and the historical approach, far from keeping up an <hi rend="underline">a priori</hi> debate with revealed religion, confines itself to tracing its history calmly and objectively.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The question of the Socialist attitude to the State seems simpler than that of its attitude to the Church. No Democratic socialist today doubts that he should regard the democratic parliamentary State as his State and therefore defend it against enemies, internal or external, and that it is permissible to enter the ranks of the Government even if the Socialist Party is in the minority. But the State does not consist solely of Parliament and the Cabinet, it is not only concerned with drawls up and voting laws, but also with their effective application and increasingly, as the State’s economic functions grow, with administration and bureaucracy. The position in Italy is that administration and bureaucracy are antiquated, authoritarian and conservative. After the fall of Fascism, the Christian Democrat party, having inherited the State, was neither able nor willing to carry out a radical reform of the administration and confined itself to a few experiments in regional devolution. It will be the task of democratic Socialism to raise in a decisive manner the question of the modem State, a State capable of functioning in conformity with social justice. It cannot be said that much progress has yet been made. In this direction, not even in the field of detailed study, but the Democratic Socialist party should be determined to face the problem.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">On the question of the planned change-over from a capitalist economy to a Socialist one, Italian Socialism is today generally agreed. It has been stated - chiefly by Tremelloni, the party’s most authoritative economist - that the passage to Socialism presupposed the planning of investments and State control of the national economy with the aim, firstly, of absorbing the large number of unemployment by a full employment policy, and secondly, the redistribution of wealth and income by a severe fiscal policy which would replace the system of tax evasion by the rich. Measures are proposed for the nationalisation of some of the largest private monopolies. Progress towards Socialism is therefore conceived of in terms of systematic organic intervention by the government, the aim being the Welfare State.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In the field of land reform in which the government is at present experimenting, there is less agreement among Socialists. Those Socialist theoreticians who are experts on the subject, consider that the reform at present being carried out - it splits up the big estates into little peasant holdings - is on the wrong lines and that only large-scale cooperative management can solve the problem of industrialising Italian agriculture. The political spokesmen of the party, on the other hand, are of the opinion that, whatever its shortcomings, the present scheme was the most that could be achieved, given the present composition of Parliament, and that they had to vote for it because it is a democratic experiment; in fact, its opponents come from landowning and capitalist circles.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">The role of the trade unions in a modern economy and in social reform is still an open question. The traditional trade union of the Socialists, the CGL. (Confederation of Labour) was captured by the Communists in 1944. A trade union organisation with a position close to Social Democracy, the UIL (Italian Union of workers), has been in existence for only a short time and has had to face innumerable difficulties.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">There is no doubt that the greatest and most difficult problem is how to win back a great part, at least, of the workers who today are Communist-led; it is not only a problem of propaganda, organisation and tactics, but also of ideology.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">In international politics, Italian democratic Socialism after having broken with its old pacifism, found itself faced with a world split into two blocks. On Saragat’s initiative, the party has adopted the foreign policy of the Socialist International - the policy of defending the Western world.</p><p rend="Corpo del testo (87)">It remains to be seen to what extent the party realises that all the far-reaching economic and social problems of our time have inescapably an international character. At all events, the party has pledged itself in principle to support the movement for a European federation, for the creation of a federal democratic State in a free continent as a force for peace, social progress and liberty.</p></body></text></TEI>